go back over to Rinkeby ether
scan, paste our address and and
we can see that we now have 0.1
ether as a balance. We can also
see that we have a transaction
with all this information going
into our wallet. That's what
this green is for. If you click
that transaction link, you'd get
something like this, but If you
didn't, don't worry, because on
the ether scan, if you click the
transaction hash in the
transaction list, you can also
see all the details like that.
So now in our meta mask, we have
0.1 eath. Again, this is fake
Aetherium. And we have a
transaction associated with our
wallet now, which is awesome.
Again, though, if we switch
networks, if we switch networks
back to Etherium main net, you
can see that we have nothing on
a theory main net. Or if we go
to ropsten, we also have
nothing, we only have this 0.1
eath. On the Rinkeby test
network, if you want to practice
working with another test net,
and the faucet that we're using,
has multiple test nets. Let's go
ahead and try it during this
section right now is completely
optional, you can watch or you
can follow along. But for
example, I can see in my wallet
that we already have COVID
supported, so maybe I'll switch
to COVID. Maybe we'll switch to
COVID. In the drop down here,
we'll remove test 10 Link,
because we only need test eath.
We'll hit I'm not a robot, and
we'll send request and the same
things will pop up this time,
this is going to be for the
COVID test net. And once our
transaction finishes going
through. Now, same thing on
COVID. Here, like what we did
with rink B, once our
transaction finishes going
through, we'll see 0.1 test eath
on the COVID network, if you
want to go ahead and try working
with another one of the test
nets. Like maybe, for example
COVID recommend you go ahead and
giving it a try. But it's
completely optional. And I would
always refer back to the GitHub
repo to make sure you're working
with the most up to date faucet
and test net. And if we look
back at ether scan, we can
actually see more details on
what actually just took place.
What actually just happened, how
did our Metamask get a balance
of 0.1 eath. All of a sudden?
Well, if we looked down in the
transaction section, we can see
that there's a transaction here,
some address sent us 0.1 ether.
And if we click the transaction
hash, we can see more details
about what actually went down
with this transaction. Now
understanding what's going on in
this transaction is essential to
learning and being a smart
contract developer or just
engaging with the ecosystem. So
let's learn the first bit at the
top is this transaction hash.
This is a unique identifier for
this blockchain or this test net
that identifies this exact
transaction. This transaction
hash identifies sending 0.1 eath
to our address, we can see that
the status of this transaction
was successful, it didn't break.
In any case, we can see the
block number that this
transaction was included in and
we'll get to blocks in a little
bit, we can see the timestamp
which of course is when this
transaction occurred, we can see
which account it was from which
if we go ahead and open in a new
tab, we can see that this is the
account that this transaction
came from. And it's got 3
million ether. Of course, this
is fake Rinckey ether. So it
doesn't really matter, we can
all see who it was to, which
again, is just us. This is our
wallet address 0x 106 X blah,
blah, blah, cero x 1066, blah,
blah, blah, right, the value of
this transaction, of course, is
0.1 ether. Now what's all this
that we see as the value so
obviously, the value is 0.1,
because that's a mode which we
sent. But we see this
transaction fee. In this gas
price, we hover over the
tooltip, we can see if you zoom
in on your ether scan, you see
amount paid to the miner for
processing the transaction. And
we see a gas price which is cost
per unit of gas specified for
the transaction and ether and
gray. The higher the gas price,
the higher the chance of getting
included in the block. Now if we
scroll down even more, and we
click See more, we can also see
a ton of other information here.
For now we're just going to
click to see less and just focus
on these two. I'll explain all
of these in a later session.
Let's talk about just
the concept of transaction fees
and gas for a second. Remember
how I said the blockchain is run
by all these different nodes
will all those different nodes
are running this blockchain
because they actually get paid
for all the transactions that
happen on these blockchains
whenever you make a transaction,
there's a node or a miner or or
a validator somebody running the
blockchain software is gonna get
paid a tiny bit of Aetherium or
polygon or whatever blockchain
that you're running on, they're
gonna get paid a tiny bit of
that native blockchain currency.
This payment is obviously to
incentivize people to continue
to run nodes and they calculate
how much you pay and how much
the node operators get paid
based off of how much gas you
use. So there's this concept of
gas. Gas is a unit of
computational measure. The more
computation a transaction uses,
the more gas you'd have to pay
for. For example, we do hit
click More just really quickly.
We can see this section say A
gas limit and gas usage by
transaction, there was a limit
of 60,000 units of gas on this
transaction, and 21,000 or
actually use. So this
transaction use 21 units of gas.
Now for very simple things like
sending ether, the units of gas
are usually pretty cheap. But
maybe for more complex things
like like minting NFT,
depositing to some defy
contract, etc, maybe those will
cost more gas because they'll be
more computationally expensive.
And this is a little confusing
right now, don't worry too much
about it. But just know that we
use 21,000 gas here. And if we
pull out the calculator 21,000
gas times this gas price right
here, times the gas price, we
get the exact same as we see for
the transaction fee. So gas
price, times how much gas you
used, is the transaction fee. So
whoever sent us this 0.1 ether,
also paid 0.0000525, etc Rinkeby
ether to make this transaction.
Now, each blockchain has a
different way of actually
calculating how this gas stuff
works. So that's basically going
to be the high level of it. So
we're going to focus just here
for now there's a total
transaction fee. And then
there's obviously the gas price.
After we cover how blockchain
works, I'll explain what this
burn stuff is these gas fees and
all these other stuff. For now,
just know that anytime you make
a transaction on chain, you have
to pay a little bit of what I
call transaction gas. So for
example, if we go to our
Metamask, we have two accounts
right here, we have account one
was 0.1, Rinckey eath, and
account two was zero. Rigby. If
I were to send 0.05 Rinckey
eath. From this account to my
other account, how much rinky
eath Do you think I'd have left?
Well, let's go ahead and try it,
this will be the first
transaction that you're actually
creating that you are going to
spend the gas for. So if we go
ahead and hit send, we'll hit
transfer between my accounts.
count two, we'll do 0.05.
Next, we can see
some information here about
what's actually going on
Metamask has some new advanced
gas for UI and settings, we're
also going to turn the song, so
go ahead and click that enable
enhanced gas UI, turn that on,
and then go back. And again,
this is going to be the
experimental tab. But it could
also just be in the General
Settings tab. Depending on when
you actually run this, we can
see a little notification here.
Again, this depends on what
version of Metamask we're using.
And we get this little drop down
that says Here are some of the
different type of gas fees that
you can actually pay. The reason
that gas fees might change, as
you can see here is that
depending on how busy the
blockchain is, you have to pay
more gas. If a lot of people are
sending transactions, that means
there's not going to be enough
space for everyone's transaction
to get through. That's a bit of
an oversimplification of what's
happening. But don't worry too
much about it for now. Now, if
we want to send the 0.05 ether
to our second account, we can
see this gas estimated section,
which is saying it's estimating,
we're going to pay 0.00004792
gas in addition to sending the
0.5 eath. So at the bottom, we
have amount plus gas fee. And
this is going to be the total
amount that we're going to be
spending on this transaction
0.05 is what we're sending. And
we also have this gas piece. So
we go ahead and confirm, we now
see we have a transaction
pending in our Rigby ether scan.
And if we click on it, we can
even hit View on block Explorer.
And a Rigby transaction hash
will pop up and depending on
when you click it, it might say
indexing, this means that ether
scan has received your
transaction and is trying to
place it. If you don't see
anything here, it means that
maybe the transaction hasn't
gone through yet. Maybe you need
to wait a little bit more. Or
maybe you need to go back to the
GitHub repo and pick the
recommended testament and
faucet. So you might have to
wait a minute or so for this to
actually finish indexing. After
a minute or so we can see that
this transaction has indeed
passed. And we can see a lot of
the same information that we saw
on our last one, this time with
0.05 ether. And now if we look
in our meta mask, we'll see we
can see account one has 0.05
It's rounding up a little bit,
we click on the big button, we
can see it actually has
0.049953, etc. And our other
account account two does have
exactly 0.05. This is because we
spent a little bit of Aetherium
on gas to send this transaction.
And now with just this little
bit of information, you know how
to actually interact with
applications that use the
blockchain, how to send
transactions and a lot of the
non technical details. Now
here's something that's
incredibly exciting with just
this little bit of information.
You now know how to interact
with blockchains and interact
with the Etherion protocol. So
if you don't want to learn how
to code anything, you can go If
you can start interacting with
Aetherium and interact with
protocols with just as much
information. However, I know
most of you guys are here to
learn how to code. So let's look
under the hood of Aetherium. And
what is actually going on with
these transactions, and what
these gas and what these
blockchains. And what's really
going on, let's learn all the
fundamentals of a blockchain.
Now, if you want to just go
ahead and jump into the coding,
go ahead and grab a timestamp
from the description. However,
learning exactly how the
blockchain works is going to
make you an incredibly powerful
developer.
So let's take a look at that
first. So we're going to
be going through this blockchain
demo on this site right here.
Now, the creator of the site has
a fantastic video and a
fantastic walk through
blockchain one on one, it is
right on their site. So if
you're looking for another
explanation, definitely check
out his video, it is absolutely
fantastic. But the first thing
that we really need to do in
order to understand blockchain
or just on really anything, and
everything that's going on here
working first really need to
understand this Sha 256, hash,
or hashing just kind of in
general, let's first understand
what a hash is. A hash is a
unique fixed length string,
meant to identify any piece of
data, they are created by
putting some piece of data into
a hash function. In this
example, the hashing algorithm
used is Sha 256. Now Etherium
actually uses this, this right
here for its hashing algorithm,
which isn't quite Sha 256, but
as in kind of this SHA family.
But it's really just another way
to hash things. And the specific
hash algorithm doesn't matter so
much. So this example, you just
shot up to six, but you can
imagine it's the same as the
Etherium. Hash, they're just
going to result in a different
hash. So what's going to happen
in this application here is
whatever data or whatever
information we put into this
data section here, as you can
see below this hash changes. So
what's happening is this data is
running through the Sha 256 hash
algorithm. And it's outputting,
this unique hash. So this hash
is a unique fixed length string,
that's going to identify like a
blank data piece here, right. So
if I put in, you know, my name
like Patrick Collins, this is
the hash that's going to
represent Patrick Collins,
right. And you can see, even
when I put, you know, tons and
tons of data in here, the length
of the string doesn't change,
right. So it's always gonna be
the same, we can put almost any
amount of data in here, there is
an upper limit on the max size
of the data. But for all intents
purposes, we can pretty much put
any length in here. And you'll
see to that every time I type in
Patrick Collins, this hash is
always gonna be this seven e
five D, right? I'm gonna delete
I'm gonna do Patrick Collins,
again, you're 75 B is always
this, this unique hash is always
going to be unique, right, it's
always gonna be this fixed
length string here. So now we
can take this idea while putting
this data in here, we can move
on to this concept of a block.
So with this block concept,
we're going to take the exact
same thing with this hash this
this data section, right, but
instead of having everything
just being in this, this
singular data area right here,
we're going to split this data
up into block, nuns, and data.
So all so what we're going to do
is we're actually going to hash
all three of these to get to get
this hash, right, we're gonna
put all three of these, we're
gonna say all three of these are
combined. Together, we're gonna
put every all three of them into
this hashing algorithm to figure
it out. So if I type a bunch of
stuff here, we can see that
block one with nonce, you know,
this nonce, and this data, we're
going to get this hash. And as
you can see, actually, the
screen turns red, this block
turned red. Now, what happens
when I hit this mind button?
When I hit this mind button,
it's actually gonna take some
time, it's gonna think for a
little bit. And we can see that
the nonce here actually changed,
right? The nonce is different
from what it was before. And
this hash now starts with four
zeros. Okay, and then the back
turn green. When we're talking
about mining, we're talking
about miners solving some type
of very difficult problem that
takes a lot of time to do now in
this example, here, the problem
that the miners had to solve was
they had to find a nonce, or or
a value in this nonce section
that when hashed with at block
number one with this data, it
would start with four zeros. So
the problem here the miners had
to solve was to start with four
zeros and the only way for them
to really do that is kind of
this brute force, you know,
trying stuff so they tried one
okay, one didn't work. Okay,
two, nope, two didn't work. 3456
Okay, five, well, that started
with one zero, but it's not
four. And they have to keep
trying all these numbers until
they get to this one where you
know, let's hit mine again.
Where it has four zeros at the
top at the start. Now, this
specific problem changes
blockchain to blockchain right
yet. Aetherium has a different
problem for miners to solve A
bitcoin is different problems
from yourself, but this concept
is going to be the same. So they
have to take it, one block is
going to be this, this, this
concept is going to be all this
data, it's going to be the block
number. And it's going to be
this nonce, right. And so this
nonce is the solution is going
to be the the number that they
use to get like the solution to
the problem, right? So if I go
to one here, you know, I do this
again,
hit mine. And the nonces
changed, right? And went from
one to 33,128. Because this is
the nonce that allowed this hash
to start with four zeros. And so
that's what's happening. When
blockchain miners are mining
they're going through this
process is very computationally
intensive process of trying to
find a nonce that fulfills
whatever the problem is. So
that's really it, actually. So
that's a block. And that's
really what's happening when
miners are mining. They're just
looking, there's trial and
error, brute force trying to
find this nut so so now that we
know what a block is, let's go
to the next step and figure out
okay, well, what's a block
chain. So here we have an
example of what a blockchain is
going to look like. Right, we
have a combination, you know, we
have back here in the block
section, we have one what one
block looks like. Now here, we
have multiple different blocks,
right, each one of these
represents a different block,
but we have an additional column
here, we have additional
variable here. So like before,
you know, we have block nonce
and data, right, we have blocked
nonce data, we also have this
thing called previous right, and
so this is actually gonna be
pointing to the previous hash of
the last block. So for example,
if we go to the last block in
this blockchain, it says
previous 008. And if we look at
the hash of block number four,
is 00008. And then we look at
its previous it's four zeros, B
nine, we have four zeros, B,
nine, and so on, all the way
back to our first block, which
has previous of just all zeros,
right. And so the block with the
previous of all zeros, is going
to be known as the Genesis
block. So you've probably heard
that before the Genesis block,
it's the first block in the
blockchain were the previous
hash points to a hash that
doesn't actually exist. Now, as
you can imagine, kind of the
same as how this block worked,
how the block nuts and dated all
go through the hashing algorithm
in the blockchain, the block
nonce data, and previous hash
all go through this hashing
algorithm to figure out what the
hashes okay? So if we go to over
here, you know, for example, if
I type in Patrick, obviously,
this is now no longer valid,
right? Because this nuns
combined with the block the data
in the previous hash, aren't
going to solve our problem of
having four zeros at the at the
start, right. So I'm gonna go
and fix that. And that's, that's
kind of an easy way to see it
being broken. But, but let's
take a look, if I break this
block, right here, what happens
if I, if I break the data in
here, if I do like Patrick in
here, you can see that both of
these are now read, both of
these are now invalid, right?
Because the block hash with the
nonce hash with the new data,
which is my name, Patrick has
hashed with the previous block
is now a brand new hash, right,
and this block is still pointing
to this previous hash right
here, right is pointing to this
previous block. And now it is
wrong, and it is messed up and
now, and now it's nuts with this
previous hash is also wrong.
Right? And this is where when we
talk about blockchains, being
immutable, this is exactly how
it's immutable, right? Because I
go back and I change anything,
you know, if I've just typed a
right here, the entire
blockchain is now invalidated.
Because none of these are going
to have nonces that solve this
equation anymore. So this is why
blockchains are immutable is
because anytime you change one
thing, you ruin the rest of the
blockchain, okay? So however,
though, you know, if it was
here, originally, we can go
ahead and mine these, mine all
these but as you can see, you
know, this is going to start
getting very computationally
expensive, because I have to go
redo basically the entire
blockchain. And the farther and
farther down the line you get,
the harder and harder it becomes
to, you know, rehash and redo
all these different block chains
here. Now, this makes a lot of
sense, right? So we have this
blockchain, it's really hard to
change something in the past,
but if we do, we can just go
ahead and remind it. Now if I'm
the one who controls the
blockchain, right, if I'm the
one who controls this, you know,
and I want to change something,
the past will, okay, great. All
I got to do is change the state
of here. And then you know,
mine, each one of these, you
know, obviously, it's going to
be very computationally
expensive, but it's something
that I can do right if I'm the
one who owns the blockchain.
Now, here's where the
decentralized nature or the
distributed nature really makes
it incredibly powerful. So we're
gonna go to the distributed tab
here, which is also referred to
as the decentralized tab here,
and it's going to show us what a
blockchain looks like in a
decentralized manner. So we have
this exact same initial setup
here we have to Shoot a
blockchain, we have our first
blockchain, which is kind of
exactly as the one from here.
But we also have more than once
we have peer, a peer beam, and
PRC and when people are talking
about Peer to Peer, peer to peer
transactions through the
talking, this is kind of that
concept that they're talking
about, right. So we have a
number of different peers who
are running this blockchain
technology, they're all weighted
equally, right, each one of
these peers or each one of these
nodes, each one of these
entities running a blockchain
has the exact same power as
anybody else, right. So the way
that we can tell very easily
which blockchain is correct, or
which ones are correct, or by
looking at this end, hash here,
right, or by looking at where we
are in the blockchain, because
again, remember, because again,
remember this, this hash that
this this in this last block
here, is going to encompass all
of the blocks from before,
right, because this last hash is
going to have the previous hash
here, which includes the
previous hash here, which this
hash includes the previous hash
here. And so this last hash is
encompasses everything in here,
right? And we can look, we can
look at the hash of Piercey,
which is four zeros, and then E
four B, we can look at the
latest hash appear B, which is
four zeros, E for B, and then
pure A, which is four zeros, E
for b. So all of these peers,
all of these nodes, all of these
decentralized, you know these
independent, all these
independent users running this
blockchain software, they're all
matched up, it's very easy for
their nodes to look at each
other and say, hey, great, we
are all matched up. Now, what
let's say that a decides that,
you know, something happened on
the blockchain that they didn't
like, and they wanted to go back
and change something, right. So
let's say they change here, you
know, obviously, the rest of
their blockchain is invalidated.
And they have to spend a lot of
computational power to catch up
to speed. So let's go ahead and
humor it. Let's say that they
did, they ended up catching up.
They ended up catching up, you
know, they ended up mining
everything. And now they have a
valid blockchain. Right? It
solves the equation. Awesome.
However, in block number three,
there's something new, right?
This is here, and it shouldn't
have been here, this is some
that Peer A put in by
themselves. All that happens now
is we look at all the
blockchains that are running the
software, and we're looking at
all the hashes and hash at block
number five. So pure A has this
new hash. Now, there's a 09 BC.
But pure B has a different hash
00, e for B, right? So who's
right? Is it disappear a with
their new stuff? Or is it pure
B? Well, that's where the
decentralized data comes in.
Because then we can look at
Piercey Piercey, also as E
forby. So if you're being
Piercey will say, Hey, you're a,
you're wrong, get out, right.
And pure A will stop being able
to participate in the mining
rewards because they have
essentially forked the
blockchain and started their own
little blockchain right with
their own history, because
they're the only ones with this,
this piece of data in block
three, whereas pure B, and pure
C have nothing in there. So that
really shows why in these
blockchain worlds in this
decentralized world, there
really is no centralized entity,
you know, pure A, you know,
might have been maliciously
motivated to change. You know,
there's this block number three,
however, democracy rules, right,
the majority rules in the
blockchain, pure vmpfc will say,
hey, you know, the, that's cute
and all puree. But you're wrong,
right? That's not right. Now, it
might be a little abstract, that
you just look at data and you
know, as typing kind of random
stuff in here and think, okay,
yeah, that's, that's data,
right? That makes sense, you
know, just kind of random
strings in here doesn't really
do anything for us. So if we
actually go over to the token
section here, this is where
everything really starts to make
a lot of sense. So we have the
exact same setup here with pure
a pure B Piercey. Except and the
difference is, instead of having
kind of this, this data section,
we have this TX This transaction
section, right? And this
represents all the transactions
that are happening in this
block, right? So we're sending
$25, from Darcy to Bingle, or to
Bingley force toward dollars and
27 cents here. 1922, right. And
it's the exact same thing. So
this, all these transactions are
gonna get hashed in the exact
same way that the data is going
to get hashed. And, and this is
why it's so powerful, because
again, you know, if I want to be
malicious, right, if, if I want
to say, hey, I really wanted to
give Jane a lot more money from
Elizabeth, so I'm puree and I go
back and I change it to 100.
Well, now, you know not only do
I does my whole blockchain get
invalidated because that was so
so long ago, but I'm not going
to match any of these other
chains. Right? And so my
blockchain is going to be
excluded from the overall
blockchain. So and let's let's
go ahead and fix this. And it's
the same thing if down here if I
become malicious, and I want to
send you know, I want
Miss Audrey to have less money.
Maybe I want to send $1 And they
go had in mind it the same thing
here, this hash now this two a
one is not going to match the
rubies rubies hash of BBA. And
it's not going to match Pierce's
hash of BBA as well. So the two
of them are gonna say, hey,
this, your blockchain is
invalid, it's not matching the
majority, you know, you're out,
right. So that's really how
these blockchains work at a low
level. And it all goes back to
this, this understanding this
hash idea, and using it in this
very sophisticated manner, to
kind of cryptographically prove,
you know, where, where stuff
lies. Now, the way the
blockchain works is, instead of
random stuff, put in the Status
section, it's actually going to
be solidity code in here to
finding ways to interact with
different blocks and different
protocols that are on chain, or,
as we've said before, different
smart contracts. Now, the next
question that you might be
asking is, okay, well, how do I
know how can I be sure that I'm
the one? You know, let's say
this is, let's say, I'm Darcy
right? How can I be sure that I
was that Darcy was the one to
actually send us money here. How
do we know that Darcy sent $25.
To Bingley? Well, this is where
we get into private keys and
public keys. And that's what
we're going to go into. Now.
Let's just do a quick recap of
what we've learned in this
section. So far, right? We've
learned that Aetherium actually
runs on this hit check 256. But
we use Sha 256. For this demo,
it doesn't really matter. We're
just talking about hashing
algorithms. So again, hash is a
unique fixed length string meant
to identify any piece of data. A
hash algorithm or a hash
function is a function or
algorithm that computes any type
of data into a unique hash.
Mining is going to be the
process of finding the solution
to the blockchain problem. In
our example, the problem was
finding a hash that starts with
four zeros. nodes get paid for
mining different blocks. And the
problem is going to be different
blockchain to blockchain a block
and a blockchain is basically a
combination of a block, nonce
transaction and previous hash to
create this unique hash for this
block. And again, depending on
the blockchain implementation,
this might have a couple other
fields or might have different
fields. But this is essentially
what's going on blockchains are
decentralized and distributed
because many independent users
are going to run this blockchain
software. And they will check
and then we'll compare against
each other to see which
blockchains are acting honestly,
and which ones are acting
maliciously, in the blockchain
world majority rules. The nonce
here is the answer used or the
number used to get this hash.
Now nonce is kind of an
overloaded term, it's actually
used for a number of different
reasons. In this case, we're
using it to solve this problem
of getting four or five zeros at
the stop or the hash. However,
in Aetherium, it will also be
often used as the number of
transactions from a given
address.
So now we're going to talk a
little bit about signing these
transactions and private keys
and some other cryptography
pieces, right? Because in this
blockchain demo here, we can see
we have all these these
fantastic transactions, right?
All these things went through,
but how do we know that it was
Darcy? Who was the one to send
$25? To bangli? Right? How do we
know that actually happened. And
this is where all those pieces
that we just learned about in
our test net, in our meta mask
account are really going to
start to, to come to life here a
little bit here. So here we have
an example of public and private
keys, okay, at the top, we have
this private key, right that was
that was randomly generated. A
private key is you know, as it
kind of states is a key that you
really want to keep secret,
because you're going to be using
this as kind of your your secret
password for all your
transactions where I can really
pick, you know, any, any, any
private key, anything that I
want. And with it, this
algorithm, or they're going to
use an algorithm for Aetherium.
Bitcoin, they both use this
elliptic curve, digital
signature algorithm, it's a
variant of just a digital
signature algorithm. And it's
going to create this this public
key, right, I'm really not going
to go at all into kind of this
digital signature algorithm. But
just know it does use some of
these, some of the hash
knowledge that we just learned
combined with some other pieces
to kind of get this this public
here. So I'm not gonna go too
deep into it. But we have this
private key that we create. And
we get this public key. Now this
public key we want everybody to
have access to right this is
yeah, whole world can see this,
this private key, we really want
it to be private, we don't want
people to see this, we're going
to use this private key as like
a password to quote unquote,
digitally sign transactions, and
then people can verify them with
this public key. So let's, let's
see what this actually looks
like. Let's pick a random key, a
more secure key, right? Because
the longer it is, the more
secure it's going to be. And if
we go to signatures now, right?
Let's say we have this, this
message that we want, right?
We'll say hi world, right? We
want this To be the message,
what's gonna happen is this
private key that we've created,
we can use to sign this data,
right? Remember how in the
blockchain demo, you know, we
were kind of we were hashing
stuff, right? We were using this
Shea 256 hash to get this hash.
Well, we're doing something
similar. But instead of hashing,
we're, we're using this digital
signature algorithm to create
this message signature. Now,
what's really powerful about how
this this algorithm works, is
that you can create this message
signature with your private key,
but somebody else can't derive
your private key from the
message signature. And that's
what makes this really, really
powerful. However, if we go to
verify using this public key,
right, and so this is the this
is that, Oh, 403. This is that
same public key, using this,
using this public key, anybody
can verify, let's go ahead and
sign again, anybody can verify
that the signature is yours,
right? So you have a public a
private key, just for you. So
you can sign things and a public
key that anybody can verify
something, right. So anybody can
verify this, and let's say
somebody tries to fake a
transaction from you, they say,
Hey, you know, this is this is
this is their transaction, all
they have to do is verify that
this signature against your
public key and very easily, this
whole thing turns red, because
it isn't verified, right, that
the algorithm says, hey, that's
wrong. So we can go ahead and
take that into transactions in
this exact same way. So if I
want to send money, you know, if
I want to send $400, from, you
know, my address to another
address, using my private key, I
can sign that transaction. And
anybody else in the world can
then verify this transaction,
right. And this is why when
people say Hydra keys, you know,
protect your keys, this is what
we're talking about in our
accounts here. Right? If we go
to settings, and again, the only
reason that I'm showing you
guys, my pneumonic, and my
private key is because this is
a, this is a dumpster account,
I'm going to throw this away at
the end of this video, or I'm
just not gonna put any real
money in it. But when we look at
our Metamask, here, we have this
pneumonic phrase, which allows
us to easily get these different
private keys, right? So
pneumonic phrase combined with,
you know, whatever account
number will get us a private
key. So mnemonic phrase combined
with one, we're gonna get this
private key. And this is when we
look at account details, export
private key.
That's where it confirm, this is
going to be the private key that
we're going to use to sign our
transactions, right, this, if
anybody else gets access to this
private key, they then can sign
transactions for us, and they
can send transactions for us.
And that's why we want to keep
these private, so that it works
the exact same way, right. And
so this is why it's so important
to hide your private keys and
hide your mnemonics now, your
Aetherium address is actually a
piece is actually a piece of
your public key. Now, to get our
address in Aetherium, all we
have to do is take this public
key that we've created with our
private key, hash it using that
same Aetherium hashing
algorithm, and then take the
last 20 bytes. And that's how
we'll actually derive to our to
our address here. Now, knowing
the exact methodology of how to
get the address doesn't really
matter, because it could change
blockchain to blockchain and
could even change it too. But
just know that that is
essentially how kind of these
addresses are derived or there's
some derivative of the public
key, right, because the public
key is public. And you know,
using the public key and kind of
any public way is totally fine,
but not the private key. So that
is how we sign our transactions.
Note though, this isn't how we
send the transaction. So so this
is just going to assign it
create a transaction for us to
send, we'll learn later on how
to send these transactions.
Cool. So that was a lot of
information there too. Let's do
a quick recap, your public key
is derived by using a digital
signature algorithm on your
private key, right, and you want
to keep your private key private
at all times, because you're
going to use your private key to
sign transactions. Signing
transactions with your private
key, you are the only one who
can actually do this because you
can't get the private key from a
message signature. However,
using your public key, you can
anybody can very easily verify
that a signature that signed by
you is in fact signed by you in
our meta mask. Our private keys
are located in this account
details section you just hit
show private keys and type in
your password. And you'll get
your your private key here. A
quick note here is oftentimes
when using your private keys
somewhere, they want it in
hexadecimal form. So if we're
going to use our private key for
something like brownie, which
we'll go into later, we need to
actually append a 0x to the
front but We'll get into that
later. And the address of your
account is derived from this. So
if you think about your private
key creates your public key,
which then can create your
address. And there's a little
barrier or a big barrier here.
Because your private key, you
want to keep private and your
public key and your address can
all be public information.
Now that we know a little
bit more about what's going on
underneath the hood of these
blockchains, let's go back at
our transactions and look at
this gas thing again, and we'll
look to see what's actually
happening here, gas in
particular can be a little bit
tricky to wrap your head around.
So if you don't get it right
away, don't worry. As we go
through examples, it'll start to
make more sense. So before I was
saying, let's just look at this
transaction fee bid, which is
the costs associated with
running this transaction. If I
scroll over this on ether scan,
I can see this thing that says
block base fee per gas plus max
party fee per gas times the gas
use, which might be a little bit
confusing here, let's actually
break down what's going on on
Aetherium with ERP 15, five nine
in place. And again, this is
going to be specific to
Aetherium, as every blockchain
might do it a little bit
differently. But if we click to
see more, we can see a number of
useful values here, we can see
gas limit is 21,000. And usage
is 21,000. So this transaction
used 21,000 gas, and we sent
21,000 gas along with it.
Sometimes when sending a
transaction, depending on when
it's sent. And depending on what
the specific instructions are,
it might actually use way more
gas than what you want it to
use. So with your transactions,
you can actually set a limit,
hey, I don't want to use more
than x amount of gas, I don't
want to do more than x
computational units. And in
fact, we go to our Metamask. And
we click Send to transfer
between accounts again, and we
pick you know, 0.01 eath, or
something next can actually hit
this little button here, go to
Advanced, and we can actually
edit some specifics of this
transaction, one of them is
going to be the gas limit, we
can change this gas limit to
maybe 2200 2300, or more or even
less, since sending Aetherium
takes exactly 21,000 Gas
Metamask just defaults to
setting into that. Well, we also
see these other interesting
things, we see a priority fee,
and a max base fee. Let's reject
this transaction. And let's look
back at ether scan to talk about
these. So currently in
Aetherium, according to EE IP
1559, every transaction on
Aetherium comes with something
called the base fee. This is the
minimum gas price you need to
set to include your transaction.
And you'll notice that these are
priced in something called
gateway. So what is a gateway?
If we come to the site eath
converter.com. And again,
there's a link to this in the
GitHub repository, we scroll
down we can see way gateway and
ether five put one ether in
here, I can see how much one
ether is in terms of way. And in
terms of way, one ether is equal
to 1-234-567-8990. So that's
that's 1 billion way is going to
be one ether. And then
1-234-567-8910 1112 1314 Did 16
Seven, eight team and then 18
zeros is away. These are just
easier ways of referring to
really, really small amounts of
Aetherium. So if we look at our
gas fees, we see that the base
fee is 0.00000004 Go away. And
this obviously would be an even
smaller number if this was in
units of weigh. So if we take
this number, and we put it into
our calculator, we can see that
this is equal to 40 weigh or
0.0000 a whole bunch of zeros
for ether. The max fee here
refers to the maximum gas fee
that we're willing to pay for
this transaction. And you can
actually see that our max fee is
a little bit higher than what we
actually ended up paying. Our
maximum was 2.2132 something
something and the gas price we
actually paid was up here. Now
your transaction might of course
be a little bit different than
Additionally we have a max
priority fee. This is going to
be the max gas fee that we're
willing to pay plus the max tip
that we're willing to give to
miners. Now currently in
Aetherium, this base fee ends up
getting burnt and we can see on
ether scan exactly how much is
getting burnt here. And if we
pull up our calculator again, we
can grab this gas fee, multiply
it by the amount of gas we used,
and we can see that this is
indeed how much Aetherium we
actually ended up burning. We go
back to Ethereum converter,
paste it in we can see that
these two numbers are indeed
equal. This means whenever you
send a transaction, a little bit
of Aetherium is removed from
circulation forever, or it's
considered burnt. So currently,
in theory As part of your
Aetherium part of your
transaction fee actually gets
burnt. And then the other part
goes directly to miners. So to
figure out exactly how much went
to miners, we could do this
number minus the burnt amount.
And this is how much Etherium
was paid to Aetherium miner for
this transaction, you'll see
down here your transaction type
to ERP 15, five, nine, this is
the eip 15 five nine version of
these transactions. Like I said,
every blockchain is going to
have a different fee burning and
fee and gas process. And they're
all going to be a little bit
different, but the some of it is
blockchains have limited block
space for transactions, the gas
price that costs for your
transaction to be included in
one of these blocks changes
based off how much demand there
is the base gas fee for
Aetherium will go up and down
depending on how many people are
sending transactions and how
many people want to be included
in a block. If a ton of people
want to be included in a block.
That means a ton of gas is
obviously going to get burnt.
We've left a link to a video in
the GitHub repository with this
section from this YouTuber who
does an amazing job breaking
down this EIP 15, five, nine and
more about how this gas model
actually works. I highly
recommend you pause this video
and watch that video. To
understand more, the base fee
gets programmatically
algorithmically adjusted to try
to target for all the blocks to
be 50% full. If they're more
than 50% full, this base fee
automatically goes up. If
they're less than 50% full, this
base fee goes down. Now this is
a lot of the basics of how this
transaction works. And it can be
a little confusing. So let's do
a quick refresher of everything
in here. There's a unique
transaction hash that uniquely
identifies this transaction. On
this blockchain, we can see the
status, we can see the block
number that it's confirmed on.
One other thing we want to look
at. If we scroll up, we see
block number and block
confirmations. This is how many
blocks have been mined. Since
this block was included. Like we
saw with our blockchain demo,
the longer the blockchain gets,
the harder it is to tamper with
and the more secure it is
typically, you'll see some
processes say they'll only do
something after 20 Block
confirmations, 30 Block
confirmations or etc. The reason
that they wait for these block
confirmations is because they
want to make sure that that
transaction is actually
included. And we can actually
see the block that our
transaction was included in and
all the other transactions with
it, different details about how
much gas was used, the gas
limit, etc. timestamp is when
the transaction happened, we can
see from and to we can see the
value. And then we can see the
transaction fee, which we see
right here is blocked base fee
per gas plus the max priority
fee per gas times the gas used.
And we see all the details of
the gas down here gas price is
the cost of one unit of gas gas
limit is the max amount of units
of gas that we're willing to pay
in this transaction, the usage
is how many actually got us the
base fee is going to be the base
network fee per gas. So 40 way
per one gas used, the max gas is
the max gas price we're willing
to pay. And Max priority is
gonna be the max gas price, plus
the tip that we give to miners,
and then we can see how much is
burnt. And then we see
transaction savings which which
is the difference between how
much was actually used or paid
for and then returned. So for
example, in this transaction,
the gas price we ended up
picking was a little less than
our max gas price here. So the
gas price we ended up using was
a little less than our max
priority fee here. So we had
some savings compared to that,
we can also see that this was an
ERP 15 five nine transaction, we
can see our nonce here, which
was not zero because the
transaction that I'm showing is
our first nones. And then of
course, we can see the input
data for transactions that are
just sending Aetherium, the
input data is going to be blank.
But you'll see that when we get
to smart contracts, the input
data is not going to be blank.
And it's going to be one of the
most important features of these
transactions. You'll also notice
that there's a state tab. This
is an advanced tab, and it shows
the different states that are
changed based off of this
transaction. We're going to
ignore this one for now. Now
that we know how the blockchain
itself works under the hood,
let's talk about some blockchain
fundamentals. And we actually
covered all these topics in a
previous Freako camp video. So
let's go to that.
If the first time
you listen to this, some of
these concepts seem a little bit
hard to grasp. Don't worry about
it. As we continue and as we
move on with this course,
they'll start to make more sense
when you see them used in real
examples. I definitely would
recommend going back and
rewatching and re listening to
the parts that you don't quite
get an asking questions in the
discussions tab of the GitHub
repository. Awesome. So now that
we know all the cryptography
pieces and all the little nitty
gritties of how the blockchain
actually works, and how our
signatures work and how
everything sticks together.
Let's talk a little bit about
how this works, in actuality,
and what's really going on. Now
for a lot of this, each
different blockchain has
slightly different algorithms
and slightly different metrics
and criteria for doing a lot of
this stuff. So when we're
talking about these specific
implementations, keep in mind,
the exact algorithm might be a
little bit different, but the
concepts are all still going to
be exactly the same. Hashing and
hash function is going to be the
same. No matter where you look
at decentralized blockchain,
it's going to be the same no
matter where you look, how it's
actually implemented, is going
to be a little bit different.
Now traditionally, when you run
an application, you will be
website or something that
connects to some server, you are
interacting with a centralized
entity. And unlike how we saw
with the blockchain with
multiple different peers, it's
going to be run by a single
centralized group. Now, it still
could be run on many different
servers, but all those servers
are still going to be controlled
by the same centralized group
blockchains, as we saw run on a
network of different independent
nodes. When we saw a peer, a
peer, B Piercey. Those were
different examples of different
independent users running the
blockchain technology on their
own node. Now, when I use the
term node, I'm usually referring
to a single instance of a
decentralized system. So when I
say a single node, when I'm
talking about a blockchain, I'm
talking about one of those pure
A's pure BS pure C's running
that blockchain software, I'm
talking about one server running
this technology. And again, it's
this network. It's this
combination of these nodes
interacting with each other,
that creates this entire
blockchain. What makes these so
potent too, is that anybody can
join the network. And that's why
there's decentralized the
barrier to entry is a little bit
of hardware requirements for
getting the correct materials to
run the software. And then you
running the software, anybody
can join these networks and
participate. And that's what
makes it truly decentralized. In
fact, you can go to GitHub right
now, and run your own Aetherium
node in a few seconds. Now in
the traditional world,
applications are run by
centralized entities. And if
that entity goes down, or is
maliciously bribed, or decides
that they want to shut off, they
just can't, because they are the
ones that control everything.
blockchains, by contrast, don't
have this problem. If one node
or one entity that runs several
nodes goes down, since there are
so many other independent nodes
running that it doesn't matter,
the blockchain and the system
will persist so long as there is
at least one node always
running. And luckily for us,
most of the most popular chains
like Bitcoin and Aetherium, have
1000s and 1000s of nodes. And as
we showed in our demo, if one
node acts maliciously, all the
other nodes will ignore that
node and kick that out or even
punish it in some systems,
because they can easily check
everybody else's node and see,
okay, this one is out of sync
with the majority. And yes,
majority rules when it comes to
the blockchain. Each blockchain
keeps a full list of every
transaction and interaction
that's happened on that
blockchain and we saw if a node
tries to act maliciously, then
all their hashes are going to be
way out of whack and they're not
going to match everybody else.
This gives blockchains this
incredibly potent immutability
trait where nothing can be
changed or corrupted. So in
essence, we can think of a
blockchain as a decentralized
database. And with Aetherium, it
has an extra additional feature
where it also can do computation
in a decentralized manner. Now
let's talk consensus, proof of
work and proof of stake because
you've probably heard these
before. And they're really
important to how these
blockchains actually work. We
went through that blockchain
example, and we did that mining
feature. This is what's known as
proof of work. Proof of Work and
proof of steak fall under this
umbrella of consensus and
consensus is a really important
topic when it comes to
blockchains. Consensus is
defined as the mechanism used to
reach an agreement on the state
or a single value on the
blockchain, especially in a
decentralized system. I briefly
alluded to this consensus
mechanism in our blockchain
example, when I said if one
change is something and the
other two, don't, then majority
will rule and kick that one out.
This is part of that consensus
mechanism. Now very roughly a
consensus protocol in a
blockchain or decentralized
system can be broken down into
two pieces, a chain selection
algorithm, and a civil
resistance mechanism, that
mining piece that we were doing,
or where the proof of work
algorithm is what's known as a
civil resistance mechanism. And
this is what Aetherium and
Bitcoin currently use. Please
note that depending on when
you're watching this, if eath
two is out, then it's no longer
proof of work. Now, proof of
work is known as a civil
resistance mechanism, because it
defines a way to figure out who
is the block author, which node
is going to be the node who did
the work to find that mine and
be the author of that block so
all the other nodes can verify
that it's accurate civil
resistance is a blockchains
ability to defend against users
creating a large number of
pseudo anonymous identities to
gain a disproportionately
advantageous influence is over
set system. And in layman's
terms, it's basically a way for
a blockchain to defend against
somebody making a bunch of fake
blockchains so that they can get
more and more rewards. Now,
there are two types of civil
resistance mechanisms that we're
going to talk about here. Namely
proof of work and proof of
stake. Let's talk about proof of
work a little bit more in depth
first, in proof of work. This is
civil resistant, because a
single node has to go through a
very computationally expensive
process called mining, which we
demonstrated earlier to figure
out the answer to the
blockchains Riddle of finding
that correct nonce, or, or
whatever the
blockchain system has in place.
And proof of work. This works
because no matter how many
pseudo anonymous accounts you
make, each one still has to
undergo this very
computationally expensive
activity of finding the answer
to the proof of work problem, or
the proof of work riddle, which
again, in our demonstration, it
was finding a nonce with that
first four zeros. But again,
each blockchain might change the
riddle work or change the
problem to be a little bit
different. In fact, some of
these blockchains make this
riddle intentionally hard or
intentionally easy to change
what's called the block time,
the block time is how long it
takes between blocks being
published. And it's proportional
to how hard these algorithms
are. So these problems actually
can change. Depending on how
long they want the blockchain to
be. If a system wants to block
time to be very, very long, they
just make the problem very, very
hard. If they wanted to be very
short, they make the problem a
lot easier. We'll talk about
civil attacks in a little bit
and how they can affect the
system. But with proof of work,
it's a verifiable way to figure
out who the block author is and
be civil resistant. Now, you
need to combine this with a
chain selection rule create this
consensus. Now, there's some
consensus protocols that have
more features, but very, very
roughly, these are the two
pieces that we're going to look
at. The second piece is going to
be a chain selection rule. How
do we know which blockchain is
actually the real blockchain and
the true blockchain now on
Bitcoin and Aetherium, they both
use a form of consensus called
Nakamoto consensus. And this is
a combination of proof of work
and longest chain rule, the
decentralized network side that
whichever blockchain has the
longest chain, or the most
number of blocks on it is going
to be the chain that they use.
This makes a lot of sense,
because every additional block
that a chain is behind, it's
going to take more and more
computation for it to come up.
That's why when we saw in our
transaction, we actually saw
confirmations. The number of
confirmations is the number of
additional blocks added on after
our transaction went through in
a block. So if we see
confirmations as to it means
that the block that our
transaction was in has two
blocks ahead of it in the
longest chain. Now, I do want to
point out that a lot of people
use proof of work as a consensus
protocol. And I do want to say
that this is a little bit
inaccurate, but sometimes people
use it interchangeably. Proof of
Work is a piece of the overall
consensus protocol, which in
Bitcoin and Aetherium. One
current case is Nakamoto
consensus, Nakamoto consensus is
a combination of proof of work,
and this longest chain rule,
both equally and very, very
important. Now, proof of work
also tells us where these
transaction fees and these block
rewards go to remember how when
we made this transaction, we had
to talk about gas and a
transaction fee. So who's
getting paid who was getting
this transaction, and this
transaction fee is going to the
miners or the validators in a
proof of work network? They're
called miners and in the proof
of stake network, they're called
validators there are a little
bit different. And we'll get
into that when we talk about
proof of stake in this proof of
work system. All these nodes are
competing against each other to
find the answer to the
blockchain riddle. Remember, in
our example, it was to find a
hash that has four zeros at the
start. And again, depending on
the blockchain implementation,
that riddle is going to be a
little bit different. But all
the nodes are trying as many as
possible to try to get this
answer first. Why? Because the
first node to figure out the
answer to the blockchain real is
gonna get that transaction fee,
they're gonna get paid from
that. Now, when a node gets
paid, they actually get paid in
two different ways. One is going
to be with a transaction fee.
And another piece is going to be
the block reward. Remember how
we talked about alternating the
gas price or the gray on our
transaction? Well, that's the
transaction fee that we're going
to pay to these blockchain nodes
for including our transaction,
the block reward is given to
these nodes from the protocol
from the blockchain itself.
You've probably heard of the
Bitcoin halving before the
halving is referring to this
block reward getting cut in half
and it's supposed to be cut in
half, roughly every four years.
This block reward increases the
circulating amount of whatever
cryptocurrency that is being
rewarded. For example, on
Aetherium the block reward is
giving out Aetherium and a
Bitcoin the block reward is
giving out Bitcoin. So these
nodes are competing against each
other to be the first one to
find this transaction to be the
first one to find the answer to
this problem, so that they can
be the ones to win both this
block reward and your
transaction fee. Some block
chains like Bitcoin, for
example, have a set time when
they're no longer going to give
out block rewards and the miners
or the nodes are only going to
get paid from trends. Action
fees. Now this gas fee, again is
paid by whoever initialize the
transaction. When we got our
funds from the faucet, there was
some server and somebody else
was paying the transaction fee
for us. However, when we sent
ether from one account to
another, our first account
actually paid some transaction
fee to send that ether. In proof
of steak. There's also a gas
fee, but it's paid out to
validators instead of miners.
And we'll talk about that in a
little bit. Now let's talk about
two types of attacks that can
happen in these blockchain
worlds. Let's talk about the
first one being the Sybil
attack. The Sybil attack is when
a user creates a whole bunch of
pseudo anonymous accounts to try
to influence a network. Now,
obviously, on Bitcoin and
Aetherium, this is really,
really difficult because user
needs to do all this work in
proof of work or have a ton of
collateral and proof of stake,
which again, we'll talk about in
a bit. The other more prevalent
attack is what's known as a 51%
attack. Now, as we saw as part
of our consensus protocol, these
block chains are going to agree
that the longest chain is the
one that they're going to go
with, so long as it matches up
with 51% of the rest of the
network. This means that if you
have the longest chain, and you
have more than 51% of the rest
of the network, you can do
what's called a fork in the
network, and bring the network
onto your now longest chain. Now
Sybil attacks, obviously, are
when a single node or a single
entity tries to affect the
decent reality of the network by
pretending to be multiple
different people, although
they're just the same person or
entity. And like I said, it's
really difficult to do in proof
of work and proof of steak. So
you can see now that blockchains
are very democratic, whichever
blockchain has the most buy in
and is the longest is the
blockchain that the whole system
is going to corroborate. When
nodes produce a new block and
add to the longest chain, the
other nodes will follow this
longest chain that the rest of
the network is agreeing with,
add those blocks to their chain
and follow up. So very small
reorganizations are actually
pretty common when a blockchain
picks a block from a different
longest chain puts it on and
then has to swap it out for
another block and continue with
a different blockchain. However,
if a group of nodes had enough
nodes or enough power, they
could essentially be 51% of the
network and influence the
network in whatever direction
that they want it. This is
what's known as a 51% attack.
And it's happened on blockchains
like Ethereum classic, which is
not Aetherium. This is why the
bigger a blockchain is, the more
decentralized and the more
secure it becomes.
So after you watch this video,
and you become a blockchain
engineering expert, I definitely
recommend you run a node as
well, because you are going to
increase the security of the
network as a whole by running a
node. So proof of work is