fantastic because it allows us
to very easily protect against
the Sybil attacks and keep our
blockchain is decentralized and
secure. However, it has some
drawbacks as well. Proof of Work
costs a lot of electricity,
because every single node is
running as fast as they can to
win this race to get the
rewards. This leads to obviously
an environmental impact. Now
since proof of work and Nakamoto
consensus, a lot of other
protocols have taken this idea
and gone in a different
direction with a different civil
resistance protocol, a lot of
them with the intention to be a
lot more environmentally
friendly. And the most popular
one right now is proof of stake.
There are some chains that are
already using this proof of
stake protocol, and that are
live and thriving. Some of them
are like avalanche, LaLana,
Polygon, polka dot and Terra and
additionally Aetherium is
decided to upgrade to eath. Two,
which will have this proof of
stake algorithm as well, it will
also have some other features,
which we'll talk about in a bit.
Now as a quick aside, all the
tools that we're going to learn
here are still going to work in
eath. Two, so depending on when
you watch this, everything here
is still valid. So let's talk
about proof of stake. Now,
again, this is a different civil
resistance mechanism. Instead of
solving this difficult problem,
proof of stake nodes put up some
collateral that they're going to
behave honestly, aka, they stake
in the example of Aetherium. two
nodes put up some Aetherium as a
stake that they're going to
behave honestly in the network,
if they misbehave to the
network, they are going to be
slashed or remove some of their
steak. Obviously, this is a very
good civil resistance mechanism.
Because if you try to create a
whole bunch of anonymous
accounts, then each one of those
accounts, you have to put up
some stake. And if you
misbehave, you're going to run
the risk of losing all the money
that you put up as collateral.
In this system, miners are
actually called validators
because they're no longer
binding anything, they're
actually just validating other
nodes. Now, unlike proof of
work, which every node is racing
to be the first one to find the
block, and proof of stake nodes
are actually randomly chosen to
propose the new block and then
the rest of the validators will
validate if that node has
proposed the block. Honestly, as
we saw with our cryptography
lesson, it's usually very easy
for other nodes to verify if a
proposal or a transaction is
honest. Now randomness is a
really important topic when
we're talking about blockchains.
Because keep in mind, these
blockchains are deterministic
systems. They're walled gardens
from the rest of the world. And
as you know, a deterministic
system by definition can't have
random numbers. So how do we
choose the random validators in
the system? While it changes
from blockchain to blockchain,
and actually choosing the node
will change blockchain to
blockchain, but eath two,
they're using what's called Rand
doubt, at least for the original
implementation. This is a
decentralized autonomous
organization that collectively
chooses the random number and
collectively chooses which node
is going to run. Next, we aren't
going to dive too deep into this
because there's a good chance
that this might change in the
future. But we will go into
randomness solutions and
blockchain later on in this
course. Now, proof of stake
obviously has some pros and cons
as well, pros are that again, it
is a great civil resistance
mechanism. And a great way to
figure out who the author of a
block should be. The other pros
are that it's way less
computationally expensive to
figure out the new block,
because instead of every single
node on the network trying to do
this, only one node needs to do
this. And then the rest of the
nodes just need to validate it.
The cons are that it's usually
considered a slightly less
decentralized network, due to
the upfront staking costs it
cost to participate. Now, this
gets into a little bit of a
philosophical battle on how
decentralized is decentralized
enough. And I think that's up to
the community to decide. And as
we progress, I think we'll learn
more and more about how
decentralized is decentralized
enough. The general consensus
amongst blockchain engineers,
though, is that proof of stake
is very, very decentralized and
very secure. This massive
environmental impact improvement
is one of the two main reasons
why eath is shifting to eath.
Two, it reduces the
environmental impact by up to
99%. Now, these are the main
pieces of proof of work and
proof of stake. But I did want
to talk about another concept
that's really important in these
ecosystems. And that is
scalability. When we were
talking about gas prices, we
were saying that the gas prices
can get really high if a lot of
people want to send a
transaction, because a block
only has so much black space,
and the nodes can only add so
many notes. So when a lot of
people want to use a blockchain,
the gas price skyrockets. This
is not very scalable, because if
we want to add more and more
people to these blockchains,
it's going to cost more and more
to use the blockchains. Because
more people are going to want to
get into these blocks. This
means that there's kind of a
ceiling to how many people can
use the system because of the
financial constraints that will
get imposed as gas prices keep
rising. Aetherium too is not
only attacking the environmental
impact of proof of work by
switching to proof of steak, but
they're also implementing this
new methodology called sharding.
And sharding is a solution to
the scalability problem, a
sharded blockchain really just
means that it's going to be a
blockchain of blockchains
there's a main chain that's
going to coordinate everything
amongst several chains that hook
into this main chain. This means
that there's more chains for
people to make transactions on
effectively increasing the
amount of block space that there
is sharding can greatly increase
the number of transactions on a
blockchain layer one now there's
another term that might be the
first time you heard it, a layer
one, we're going to talk about
layer one and layer twos in
terms of scalability really
quickly as well. A layer one
refers to any base layer
blockchain implementation
Bitcoins, a layer one Aetherium
the layer one avalanches, a
layer one, these are the base
layer blockchain solutions. A
layer two is any application
that is added on top of a layer
one added on top of the
blockchain. Some examples of
layer twos are going to be chain
link arbitrage, or optimism.
Arbitrage and optimism are very
interesting because they are
layer twos that also look to
solve this scalability issue.
Arbitrage and optimism are
what's known as roll ups and
they roll up their transactions
into a layer one like Aetherium,
we're not going to go too deep
into roll ups and how they
actually work. But all you
really need to know is that a
roll up is kind of like a
sharded chain, they derive their
security from the base layer
from the layer one like
Aetherium. And they bulk send
their transactions onto the
layer one, they solve some of
the scalability issues by being
another blockchain that people
can make transactions on, still
on kind of this base Aetherium
layer. Now they're different
from side chains. Because side
chains derive their security
from their own protocols, roll
ups, derive their security from
the base layers. So arbitrage
and optimism, for example, is
going to be just about as secure
as Aetherium. There's some
fantastic guys in there that go
a little bit deeper into roll
ups and I've left a link in the
description for you. All right,
so we just talked about a lot of
stuff. So let's do a quick recap
before moving on. Aetherium and
Bitcoin are currently both proof
of work blockchains that follow
Nakamoto consensus, however,
Aetherium is moving to Aetherium
two, which will be a proof of
stake sharded blockchain Sybil
attacks are prevented due to
protocols like proof of work and
proof of steak 51% attacks grow
increasingly harder with the
size of blockchain. So you
should run a node consensus is
the mechanism that allows a
blockchain to agree upon what
the state of the blockchain is
sharding and roll ups are
solutions to scalability issues
on layer ones. Layer One is any
based blockchain implementation
like Bitcoin or Aetherium. A
blockchain scalability problem
is that there's not always
enough block space for the
amount of transactions that want
to get in them. This leads to
very high gas prices and a
Again, gas prices or how much it
costs to interact with the
blockchain.
So that's it for the blockchain
basics and the blockchain
explainers. With just this
information, you now can go off
into the world and start working
with blockchains and interacting
with blockchains. With at least
some level of knowledge as to
what's going on, you should be
incredibly proud of yourself for
just making it this far.
Definitely be sure to give
yourself a pat on the back and a
round of applause. Now that
we've gotten a lot of the basics
and the fundamentals of the way,
let's start jumping into the
coding aspect. This is where
you're going to learn how to
actually build these smart
contracts, how to build these
trust minimized agreements, in
these blockchains. And in the
smart contract platforms. This
next section, this solidity
basics, the solidity
fundamentals section will give
you all the skills to start
actually coding solidity and
understanding how these smart
contracts work underneath the
hood. So at this point,
absolutely, give yourself a high
five, maybe say hi, in the
GitHub discussions, maybe say hi
in the community, on Twitter, on
Reddit, etc, and be proud of
just making it this far, the
journey has really only just
begun, but you've already
learned so much. Let's begin the
next section. And let's
jump into the code.
Now that we're getting to the
coding sections, I need to
stress to absolutely use the
GitHub repository associated
with this course. If you come to
the GitHub repo, and you scroll
down, and you click the lesson
that we're on right now, we're
on lesson two. Welcome to remix,
simple storage. If you click on
it, it'll give you a ton of
timestamps and, and other
helpful links associated with
this lesson. Additionally, the
biggest piece is that all the
code will be available right
underneath the lesson title.
This will have all the code that
we're going to be working with,
as well as some more additional
information on how to work with
the code. Please, when asking
questions and entering in
discussions, though, please ask
your questions and the full
blockchain solidity course
repository. Thank you. And if
we're at the top of the
repository, and we scroll down,
we have the resources for this
course section. Which brings us
to the GitHub discussions in
which you can ask questions in
the GitHub discussion section of
this course. Additionally, on
Stack Exchange, Aetherium, or at
Stack Overflow. I'll talk a
little bit about how to format
questions and ask questions the
best way so that you have the
highest chance of getting a good
answer in a later lesson, I
highly recommend you pause and
make accounts for Stack Exchange
Aetherium, Stack Overflow, and
GitHub right now, if you haven't
already, links to them, of
course, can be found in our
GitHub repository. Typically,
for each coding section, I'll
start it off by giving a quick
overview of the code of what
we're going to be working with
and what we're going to be
building towards, since
everything that we're doing is
going to be project based. And
that's how we're going to learn.
For our first one and remix
though, we're going to skip over
that because there's a lot of
stuff to get used to. Now, I
highly recommend that as I'm
coding this. And as I'm doing
all this in remix, you follow
along with me and you code along
with me. Remember, you can
change my speed if I'm coding
too fast, or if I'm coding too
slow. To start, we're going to
jump into a tool called remix.
If you're unsure how to get
there, there's a link to remix
in our GitHub repository. This
is where we're gonna be writing
all of our code. So welcome to
the remix IDE, or integrated
development environment. This is
where we're going to learn how
to code and interact with our
smart contracts. If you want,
you can go ahead and accept help
out remix. If you've never been
here before, it'll give you a
quick walkthrough of some of the
tools that remix actually has,
we're going to skip over them
for now. Because I'm gonna
explain everything that's going
up. Remix is such a powerful
tool because it has a lot of
features that allow us to really
see and interact with our smart
contracts. Eventually, we're
going to move off of remix,
actually to a local development
environment. However, remix is
absolutely fantastic for
learning the fundamentals of
solidity. And I highly recommend
everybody start with remix when
they're getting started. When
you come to the remix IDE,
there's a whole lot of different
things that are popping out to
us. There's a lot of different
plugins as well. Since we're
going to be working with
solidity, which is going to be
the language that we're using to
develop our smart contracts. We
can go ahead and get started by
clicking the solidity plugin,
and a couple of other tools will
show up on the side. Even if you
don't click the solidity plugin,
you'll still be able to code
solidity smart contracts, the
left hand side is where we're
going to start to actually
interact with things. The button
on the top most of the left is
our files or explore
directories, remix comes
boilerplate with some different
contracts, some different
scripts, some different tests,
and different dependencies. We
are going to minimize this a
little bit. So if you want to go
ahead and right click and delete
some of these folders other than
the contracts folders, feel free
to do so. Or if you kind of like
them there, feel free to leave
them as well. We're going to
leave our contracts folder and
we're going to delete the
different files inside of it
just so that we can start From a
blank slate. Most projects come
with something known as a
readme. Usually it's a
readme.md, which usually
explains how to actually work
with code. But for our purposes,
we're going to delete this as
well. And you can just follow
along with
me. Now we have a blank
remix Setup, click on the
contracts folder and click the
little page icon to create a new
file, a little box will pop up
and you can start typing text
into it. We're going to type in
simple storage dot Sol, dot Sol
tells our compilers that this is
going to be a solidity file, and
that we're going to code
solidity in this solidity is the
primary coding language of smart
contracts. There are a few other
smart contract languages as
well. But solidity by far is the
most dominant smart contract
coding language out there. And
now we have a simple storage dot
soul contract on the right that
we can actually start coding our
solidity with. So let's start
coding some solidity. Now if you
click on this button right below
the files button that looks like
the solidity logo, you'll see a
bunch of stuff pop up in here.
These are different parameters
for us to actually compile our
solidity code so that we can run
it. So the first thing that
you're going to need in any
solidity smart contract is going
to be the version of solidity
that you're going to use. And
this should always be at the top
of your solidity code, solidity
is a constantly changing
language, and it constantly
updating language. Because it's
relatively new compared to other
languages, we need to tell our
code, hey, this is the version
that I want you to use, we can
add the solidity version by
doing pragma. solidity. And then
the version that we want to use,
if we want to choose a very
specific version, we could say
zero, point 8.7. The most
current version to date is 0.8.
Point 12. But getting used to
different versions of solidity
is good practice, and different
versions of solidity are
considered more stable than
others. Zero point 8.7 is one of
those versions that is
considered more stable. These
double slashes here are what's
known as a comment, there are
places where you can type stuff
that won't actually get executed
in won't get compiled and isn't
really considered part of your
code. For example, I could write
Hello all. I'm Patrick. And if
we were going to run this code,
this part of my code would get
completely ignored. So this
double backslash is how we do
what's called comments. And as
we're coding, and as we're
building our projects, be sure
to use this comments tool to
your advantage every time you
write a new function, or you
learn something that you didn't
understand, or you learned
something new that you want to
remember, put it in a comment in
your code, you're going to be
most effective at taking notes
in this course, by making them
comments in your code and then
saving your code so you can
refer back to it later. So leave
comments in your code, leave
notes in your code. And that
will be one of the best ways for
you to understand what you're
coding when you want to refer
back to it later. Now when it
comes to the versions of
solidity, there's actually a few
different ways we can actually
write it, we can say we want to
use only zero point 8.7. And
this is how we would write that.
But maybe we're okay if we use a
more new version of solidity
than zero point 8.7 to tell our
code that we're okay with a more
new version, we can put a little
caret here. And this is how we
tell solidity. Hey, any version
of zero point 8.7 And above is
okay for this contract. This
means zero point 8.8 would work
zero point 8.9 0.8 point 10,
etc. But if we wanted to use
just 0.17, we would type in like
that if we want to use solidity
versions between a specific
range, we could do something
like this, we can say we want
our solidity version greater
than or equal to zero point 8.7
But less than zero point 9.0.
This means that any compiler
between zero point 8.7 and zero
point 9.0 would work. This means
zero point 8.8 would work. Zero
point 8.9 would work 0.8 point
10 would work. But zero point
9.0 would not work because it is
not strictly less than 0.9 point
00 point 9.1 would also not
work. To keep things simple for
us, we're going to use zero
point 8.8. And every line of
solidity that's completed, every
completed section needs to end
with one of these semicolons
this is how you tell solidity
it's the end of the line. Also
at the top of your code, you're
always going to want to put
what's called an spdx license
identifier. This is optional,
but some compilers will flag
your warning that you don't have
one. This is to make licensing
and sharing code a lot easier.
We have a link to more about how
licenses work in the section of
this lesson in our GitHub
repository to do an spdx license
identifier, we just say spdx
license identifier, and we're
gonna choose MIT, the MIT
license is one of the least
restrictive licenses out there.
So we use the MIT license for
most of our code samples once
you have a version and once you
have Is this much written, we
can actually go ahead and write
to our compiler tab and scroll
down and hit Compile, that
little turn thing will go. And
in a minute, we'll see, this
contract is attempted to be
compiled. Since we actually
don't have a contract, we see no
contract compiled yet, but we
see the compiler automatically
switched to zero point 8.8.
compiling our code means taking
our more human readable code
like pragma, solidity and
transforming it into computer
code, or very specific
instructions for the computer to
use. We'll go over what a lot of
this machine level code or this
computer level code is doing in
a later section. If you're using
a Mac, you can also hit command
S, and it will run the compiler
for you as well. On Windows, it
might be Ctrl S, we can actually
choose the compiler version that
we want to use. However, if we
tell in our code to specifically
use zero, point 8.8, and we hit
the compile button, it'll
automatically switch to zero
point 8.8. However, if we use
the carrot thing, we get
specifically say, hey, we want
0.8 point 10, we can hit
compile, and it will compile
with 0.8 point 10. Because
again, remember, the carrot says
we want to use at least zero,
point eight, all the way up to
the latest version of 0.8. Now
let's stay on zero point 8.8.
The next thing that we're going
to do in our code is define our
contract. And to get a full
screen view, you can go ahead
and hit the compiler button to
get rid of it there. To start
defining our contract, we're
gonna go ahead and write the
word contract. This tells
solidity that the next pieces of
code is going to be a contract
contract is a key word in
solidity, and it tells our
compiler that the next section
of this code is going to define
a contract. You can think of a
contract similar to a class in
any object oriented programming
like Java or JavaScript. Let's
go ahead and give our contract a
name here, we're going to call
RS simple storage. And then we
add this little open and close
curly brackets. Everything
inside this open and close curly
brackets is going to be the
contents of this contract.
Simple Storage. Now, if we go
ahead and hit command S or Ctrl
S, we can see this little green
checkmark show up. And if you
don't, you can always go back to
the compiler tab, scroll down
and hit Compile and see the
little green checkmark. That
little green checkmark means
that our code is compiling
successfully. And we don't have
any errors, we could
hypothetically deploy this
contract right now. And it would
be a valid contract. So
congratulations on writing your
first contract.
Now solidity has multiple
different types or primitive
data types. And if you go to the
solidity documentation, which
again, is in our GitHub
repository, you can read more
and learn more about the
different types that are in
here. The four most basic types
are going to be Boolean,
you int, int, and an address
or bytes, which is a lower level
type, which we'll talk about a
little bit later. A boolean
define some type of true false,
a you int is going to be an
unsigned integer, which means
it's going to be a whole number
that isn't positive or negative.
It's just positive, we have an
integer, which is going to be a
positive or negative whole
number. And then we have an
address, which is going to be an
address, like what we see in our
meta mask here. There are some
other types as well that you'll
learn later on. The reason that
we have these types is we use
them to define what different
variables are. Variables are
basically holders for different
values. For example, we could
create a variable called has
favorite number to represent if
somebody has a favorite number.
And we would put this bull
keyword before has to renumber
say, Okay, we have a variable
called has favorite number, and
it's of type boolean. So this
has favorite number is going to
represent a true or a false to
set its value, we could say has
favorite number equals true. Now
has favorite number is going to
be true. We could also say has
favorite number equals false. So
this Boolean has faded number is
now going to be false. For uns
we could say you went favorite
number equals and then set a
number 123. This means that our
favorite number is going to be
123 You'll enter is special
because we can actually specify
how many bits want to allocate
to this number bits and bytes
are pretty fundamental pieces of
information for computer
science. We're not going to go
over it here. However, there's a
fantastic video in the GitHub
repository that explains it
more. Basically, it's how much
storage or memory to allocate to
this number. How big can it get,
if we say a you int eight can
have eight bits all the way up
to you went to 56. If you don't
specify how big it is, it
automatically defaults to you
into 256. Oftentimes, it's
better when writing our code to
be very explicit. So usually
you'll see me just do you int
256 to represent a un 256. We
could also do an int favorite
number equals 123 or an int 256.
I'm just Going to go ahead and
add this Boolean back here,
we're going to change this back
to UNT to 36. And let's change
our favorite number to five
here, we could also do something
called strings, string, favorite
number in text
equals five
strings represent basically
words, and you can represent
them by putting them in these
quotes, it's going to be some
word or phrase, or really,
really just kind of any
combination of keystrokes in
here, our ends can be positive
or negative. So we could say,
negative five or positive five,
both are going to be valid,
since we can also do address my
address equals and grab our
address, right from Metamask.
And paste it in, you'll notice
that we end all of these lines
of code with the semicolon. We
also have bytes objects, or a
bytes 32, again, representing
how many bytes we want them to
be. And this says that we have
called favorite bytes, and we're
just gonna set it equal to cat.
So strings are actually really
interesting, because strings are
secretly just bytes objects, but
only for text to a cat is
actually a string, but can
automatically get converted into
one of these bytes object bytes,
objects typically look like 0x.
And then some random letters and
numbers that represent the bytes
object, but cat can
automatically get converted down
to bytes. We'll talk about bytes
more in coming sessions, you can
also do bytes, two bytes, three
bytes, five bytes 22, you get
the picture for our uns and our
into the sixth lowest we can go
is eight bits, because eight
bits is a byte. And we can go up
by steps of eight. So we can do
816 32, etc, all the way to 256.
For example, down here, we can't
do bytes 64. And if we go ahead
and try to compile this, we get
a little red thing here. And if
we scroll down, we get a
declaration error identifier not
found or not unique. Bytes 64
favorite bytes equals cats. And
we even got a little red warning
sign here in our remix. This is
remix telling us there's
something wrong with this line.
So we can switch back to bite
32. Since byte 32 is the maximum
size that a bytes can be, you
could also do just a bytes
object, which means it can have
any size, but we typically want
to be explicit. And we're going
to stick with bytes 32 For now
want to learn more about the
different types and how to use
them and all the different
features with them, be sure to
check out the solidity
documentation. For now for our
simple storage, let's say we
only want to store numbers. So
let's go ahead and delete
everything except for the
favorite number section.
Now in solidity,
if I do this, and I remove the
equals five, this favorite
number actually does get set to
a default value, the default
value for solidity is going to
be whatever the null value is,
which in solidity is case zero.
So saying you Intuit six
favorite number is going to be
the same as saying you 256
favorite number equals zero
since it gets initialized to
zero. So for now, let's not
initialize it to anything. So
that favorite number will
automatically start off as zero.
Now, if you get confused, as
you're coding along, and you're
following along with me, be sure
to write comments in your code
so you know what's going on. So
maybe, for example, a great
comment here would be this gets
initially alized to zero. And
then if that's even confusing,
you could say, this means that
this section is a comment. Now
let's go ahead and create a
function functions or methods
are self contained modules that
will execute some specific set
of instructions for us, when we
call it if you're familiar with
Java, or Python, or JavaScript
or anything like that functions
work the exact same way
functions get identified by the
keyword function, let's create a
function called store that will
change the value of favorite
number to some new value. And
the number that we're going to
change it to is going to be
variables that are passed to our
store function here. So we're
going to allow our store
function to take a variable of
type un 256. And we'll call it
underscore favorite
number, we'll make this a public
function, which we'll get to in
a minute. And all we're going to
do is we're going to set
favorite number equal to
whatever variable that we just
passed. So now we have this
function called store, that it
takes some parameter that we're
going to give it and it sets
this favorite number variable
equal to whatever number that we
give this function. Now to see
this actually in action, let's
deploy this to an even thicker
blockchain than a test net.
We're going to actually deploy
this to a local network or a
JavaScript VM. And first before
we can even do that, let's just
make sure that it's going
compiling correctly looks like
we have a green checkmark, which
is good. And we'll come down to
this button here, which is our
deploy and run Transactions tab.
Our deploy and run Transactions
tab has a ton of different
configuration pieces for
actually deploying this
contract. First, we want to make
sure we are on the JavaScript VM
London piece here, JavaScript VM
means we're going to be
deploying to a fake local
JavaScript VM. The JavaScript VM
is a fake local blockchain where
we can simulate transactions
really quickly without having to
wait for them to go through on a
test net, don't worry about the
London versus Berlin piece here
for now, injected web three and
web three provider we'll talk
about in a little bit. We also
have this account section here.
When we run on our fake
JavaScript VM, we're given a
whole bunch of fake accounts
from where to deploy from, and
we're given 100 eath. For each
one of these fake accounts, you
can kind of think of it similar
to our meta mask account in meta
mask, except for the difference
here is that this is this fake
JavaScript VM Aetherium that
we're given. For our
transactions, including
deploying contracts, we're
actually given a gas limit,
there's also values we can send,
and we can choose our contracts.
Right now we only have one
contract, simple storage, so
that's going to be the one that
we're going to deploy. So on the
left hand side, to deploy this
to our fake JavaScript VM, we're
gonna go ahead and hit the
Deploy button. And if we scroll
all the way down to the bottom,
now, we can see a contract was
deployed. It says simple storage
at x, blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah. And we see this orange
button store with come this
grade text you in 256,
underscore favorite number on
our fake local blockchain, we're
actually given an address every
single smart contract, it has an
address, just like how our
wallets have an address. So if
we hit this copy button here,
and we put it into a comment,
make this a little bit bigger,
we can see that the address of
this contract that we just
deployed, is located at this
address. Additionally, if you
pull up the slider over here,
you'll be able to see this
little green checkmark with all
this information about this
deployment. And you can hit the
little drop down and see a whole
lot more information about this.
Something you might notice is
you'll see some familiar
keywords like status,
transaction hash, from to gas,
etc. When we deploy a contract,
it's actually the same as
sending a transaction. Remember,
anytime we do anything on the
blockchain, we modify any value,
we are sending a transaction. So
deploying a contract is
modifying the blockchain to have
this contract, it's modifying
the state of the blockchain. And
if we had sent this on a
Rinkeby, or COVID, or main net
network, we would have had to
spend the gas to actually deploy
this contract. And this is the
simulation of how much gas and
the transaction hash and from
and to and all this other stuff
about our transaction had, we
actually deployed it to a real
network. But since it's
JavaScript VM, it's all fake
information. Now we have this
big orange button store, this
big orange button resembles the
store function that we just
created. So if we add some
number into this store, like
123, and we hit the Store
button, we actually call this
store button. And we actually
execute a transaction on our
fake Jasika. Blockchain to store
the number 1234 favorite number.
And if we scroll all the way up
to our account, now, you'll see
that we have a little bit less
ether in our fake account. This
is because we spent the gas to
actually call this contract. And
if we pull up this bottom bit
here, and I call this with five
I call store, you'll see it
flashed for a quick second, we
sent another transaction to
store the value five in our
favorite number. Now the
question might be having is,
that's really cool, Patrick, but
I can't see what favorite number
actually is, how do I know that
those transactions are actually
going through? Well, right now,
the visibility of our favorite
number is set to private, so we
actually can't see it. And we'll
talk about visibility in just a
second. To make it so that we
can see it. We'll change our
favorite numbers visibility to
public. So let's go ahead, we'll
recompile we'll go back to the
deploy tab. We'll click the
little x here, which is to say
let's get rid of this contract.
And it just gets rid of it from
our window here. It doesn't
actually get rid of it from the
blockchain, because again,
they're immutable, well, kind of
immutable, since again, this is
kind of a fake simulated chain.
But we go ahead and compile, and
now we hit Deploy again. And if
we scroll down, our new
contract, will now have two
buttons. One is the orange
button for store. But now we
have a New Favorite button. This
button represents this public
variable favorite number, and it
resembles a function saying,
Hey, show me what favorite
number is. So if I were to click
this favorite number button,
what do you think will show up?
Well, do you remember what this
gets initialized to? Well, let's
click it now. We do indeed See
that zero shows up, we see that
this is a YouTube ID six, and
the value stored in it is zero.
Now, if I were to change that
number to five by calling the
store function, and now hitting
favorite number, we do indeed
see, favorite number gets
updated to five functions and
variables can have one for
visibility specifiers, we have
public, private, external, and
internal. Public is visible
externally and internally,
meaning anybody who interacts
with this contract or sees this
contract can see what's stored
in this favorite number
function. You'll see here in the
solidity documentation, it says
it creates a getter function for
the storage slash state
variables. When we add this
keyword public to favorite
number, what we're actually
doing is we're creating what's
called a getter function for
favorite number, we're basically
creating a function that says to
return the value of favorite
number, and that's why this blue
button pops up. Because this
blue button is a function that
says, hey, return the value of
favorite number private means
only this specific contract can
call this function. Now for
storage, it doesn't mean only
this contract can read what's
stored here. And we'll get into
that a little bit later. But by
that means, this is the only
contract that can call the
favorite number function.
Private functions are only
visible to the current contract.
External functions are only
visible externally, meaning
somebody outside this contract
can call this function. And then
internal means that only this
contract and it's children
contracts can actually read it,
but we'll get into that a little
bit later, too. So oddly enough,
variables are just function
calls. Now, the reason that we
didn't see favorite numbers show
up on the left hand side, when
we first deployed this without
the public keyword. When we
don't give a visibility
specifier to functions or
variables, they automatically
get deployed as internal. And as
we know, internal functions and
variables can only be called by
this specific contract or
derived contracts, which again,
we'll get into later. So let's
just keep it public. For now,
the reason that we're prefixing,
our parameter here with an
underscore is a way to tell us,
hey, this variable here is
different from the favorite
number global, there are some
different naming conventions
that are used for parameters.
And as we get later into the
course, will understand more and
more of what good names are
parameters are, every time we
call this store function. And we
change the value here, we're
actually sending a transaction
because remember, every single
time we change the state of the
blockchain, we do it in a
transaction. And we can see all
the details here. If you go over
to the transaction details in
the logging area of your remix,
you can actually scroll down and
you can see the transaction cost
in units of gas, you'll see a
number of something around this.
And you'll notice it's more than
that 21,000 number from sending
Aetherium. That's because we're
doing something more
computationally expensive. We're
actually storing a number over
here. Now what do you think will
happen if we do more inside of
the store function as well. So
instead of just storing this
number, maybe what else we do is
we will store the number here.
And then we'll update our
favorite number will say
favorite number equals favorite
number plus one. Since we're
doing more stuff, now we should
see this store function actually
become more expensive. So let's
go ahead and recompile we'll do
delete this will redeploy. We
now have a new contract will
store five again. Now if we look
in the details of this
transaction, and we scroll down
to execution costs, we do indeed
see the amount of gas has
greatly increased. And that's
because we're doing more things,
this store function is now more
computationally expensive. And
like I said, each blockchain has
a little different way of how
they actually calculate gas. But
the easiest way to think about
it is, the more stuff you do,
the more expensive that
transaction is going to cost. So
let's go ahead and delete this
line to continue our example.
Now let's talk about scope for a
second, our favorite number is
basically in something called
the global scope, meaning
anything inside of these
brackets can access this
favorite number variable. But
what if I did something like
this? What if I made a un 256
called Test var? And I set it
equal to five? And then I
created a new function called
something will have it take no
parameters and be public? Could
I access the test var and then
change it to something like six?
Can we do that? Well, let's go
ahead and see what happens when
we try to compile this. We
actually run into an error. We
had expected primary expression
right here. Oh, well, that's
because I have the double
question mark. Let's try now. We
get undeclared identifier. Our
something function doesn't know
about this test var when you
create variables, they only can
be viewed in the scope of where
they are. Now if that's a little
confusing, just look for the
curly brackets. These two curly
brackets encompass this whole
We'll section here write, the
opening one is up here, the
closing one is down here. So if
I create a variable directly
inside of these curly brackets,
that means everything in here
can access it. However, test var
was created inside of these
curly brackets, which means that
only stuff inside of these curly
brackets can access test var,
since our functions something
isn't inside of store, or
something function won't know
about test var. So that's how
scope works, you want to look to
see if your variable that you
created is inside of these curly
brackets. And that's how you can
know if other functions can work
with them. So this is why this
fails. Now, like what we saw in
the documentation, when we add
this public variable to favorite
number, we're secretly adding a
function that just returns this
favorite number, we can also add
our own function that also
returns the favorite number to
resemble the function that's
getting created in the backend.
So we can say function, we call
it retrieve, and we make it a
public view. And we'll say it
returns, you went to 56. or
explain what that means in just
a second. And we'll say return
favorite number. Now, I'm going
to hit command S, which again,
I'm going to do that a lot
throughout this section. But
just remember that that's
equivalent to me going to the
compile tab and hitting compile.
Now if we go to the deploy tab,
delete our last one, deploy a
new one, we now have a retrieve
function, which is going to
return the exact same thing that
our favorite number is going to
return. Again, if we update this
to five, called favorite number
and then retrieve they both now
return five. Now as you can see
here, these two functions are
blue, but this function is
orange. What's the difference?
Why did these have these
different colors? Well, the key
lies in this view keyword here,
there are actually two keywords
in solidity that notate a
function that doesn't actually
have to spend gas to run. And
those keywords are view, and
pure. And let's also get rid of
this variable here. A function
that is a view function means
we're just going to read state
from this contract, we're just
going to read something off of
this contract. For example, our
retrieve function right now is
just reading what favorite
number is, a view function
disallows any modification of
state. So you can't update the
blockchain at all with a view
function. Pure functions also
disallow any modification of
state. So we couldn't update our
favorite number. Not only that,
but they also disallow reading
from the blockchain. So we
couldn't read favorite number
either. Instead, what you might
do with a pure function is maybe
something like
function, add public here, one
plus one,
or return, one plus one, this
would be turns you into 36,
maybe something like this, maybe
there's some math you want to
use over and over again, maybe
there's some specific algorithm
that you want to implement that
doesn't actually need to read
any storage, etc. Now, if we
call a view function, or a pure
function by itself, we actually
don't need to spend any gas.
Since we're just reading from
the blockchain. Remember, we
only spend gas we only make a
transaction if we modify the
blockchain state. So you'll
notice in our little console
down here, that if I call
retrieve this call things comes
up. However, it looks different
than when we call the store
function. And we call the store
function, we get this little
checkmark, we get a hash, we
don't get a little checkmark.
And we don't get a hash with the
calls. That's because clicking
these blue buttons doesn't make
a transaction. This is saying,
Hey, we're just going to read
off chain, we're just going to
read this value. However, if you
look in the details of this
call, there's this execution
cost bit here. So what's going
on? Well, we can read this part
right here, cost only applies
when called by contract. If we
do have a function that calls
retrieve, if there's a function
that is updating state that
calls a view or a pure function,
that's the only time it'll cost
gas. So for example, if our
store function which is not a
view function, were to call
retrieve at some point, then
we'd have to pay the cost of the
Retrieve because reading from
the blockchain cost this
computation and cost gas calling
view functions is free, unless
you're calling it inside of a
function that costs gas, in
which case it will cost gas. So
if we leave it here, we delete
this recompile redeploy. We had
favorite number retrieved, they
both still cost nothing. But if
we add, restore eight in here,
we can see, we can see our
execution cost has gone up from
what it was without retrieve,
which we can go ahead, we can
compile, I hit command us to
compile here, we can deploy.
Let's go ahead and store again.
We'll click on that transaction,
we can see that it's much
cheaper without that retrieve
function in there. And again,
our favorite number variable as
long as it has this public
visible solidity, it also is
counted as a view function that
returns a un 256. The returns
keyword means what is this
function going to give us after
we call it so we say this
function is going to give us
this function is going to return
a un 256. When we call retrieve,
it's going to return or give us
a utility six. This is the
result of calling the function
this six is the result of
calling arbitrary function.
Now our contract is
good as it is, it allows us to
store a single favorite number.
But what if we want to store a
range of favorite numbers? Or
maybe we want to store a whole
bunch of different people who
have different favorite numbers?
Well, how do we do that there
are several different ways that
we can approach this, one of the
ways we could start approaching
this is by creating what's
called a struct of people. Or we
create a new type. In our
solidity, we can create a people
object that holds both someone's
name, and their favorite number.
To do that, we say struct
people, you went to 56, favorite
number, and a string name. Now
we've created a new type called
people kinda like you intuited
six, or Boolean, or string. Now
we have a people type that we
can use. Now similar to how we
created a un 256 public favorite
number, we can do the exact same
thing. But with a people, we
could say people public, we call
this person, and we can create a
new people and assign it to this
variable person. So we'll say
equals people public person,
equals, and we'll add
parentheses here to signify
we're creating a new person. And
since we made this a struct, we
add little curly brackets here
to let solidity know that we're
going to be grabbing from these
struct variables, we'll say
favorite number is going to be
two, and the name is going to be
Patrick semicolon, and then we
can hit Ctrl S, or we can go
ahead and compile. Now if we go
ahead and deploy this we now
have a new person, since this,
again, is a public variable, it
has a getter function called
person. And if we click person,
we see our new object, the
favorite number is two. And then
the name is Patrick, you see
this zero and this one, because
these are showing the index of
the different variables. But
those of you new to computer
science, typically in computer
science, let's start with the
number zero. So what are zero
with index, we have you in 256,
called favorite number, which is
saved at two. And then at index
one, we have a string, which
stands for the name of Patrick,
whenever you have a list of
variables inside of an object in
solidity, they get automatically
indexed. So favorite number gets
indexed to zero, and name gets
indexed to one. Interestingly
enough, if you have a whole
bunch of variables inside your
contract, like we have public
favorite number, this favorite
number, actually, technically is
getting indexed at the zero with
storage slot. And if we were to
make another one of these, maybe
you want to get six public
brother's favorite number, this
would technically be indexed at
the first slot. And then if we
were to make one more, maybe
sister's favorite number, this
would be the next add the second
slot. So favorite number at
zero, this add one, and this a
two, but we'll learn more about
that much later in the course.
Similarly, favorite number is
index zero name is index at one.
Now what we have is great, but
if we want a whole lot of people
are we gonna have to keep copy
pasting and changing the
people's name person to their
favorite one, number one, number
three, will name them ally.
Person three, their favorite
number will be seven. Their name
will be Chad or something. This
obviously isn't great way to
create lists and large number of
people's because we have to
statically keep typing them in.
So a much better way to create a
list. And let's actually just go
ahead and delete Patrick to a
much better way to create a list
is to use a data structure
called an array. An array is a
way to store a list, or a
sequence of objects, creating an
array works the exact same we've
seen to initialize other
different types. Typically, we
do the type of the object, the
visibility of the object, and
then the variable name. We do
the exact same thing with
arrays. We'll say we want a
people array. These little
brackets represent that we want
an array of people. We'll give
it a visibility of public and
we'll call it people you could
do the same thing with you and
256 for example, you could say
you went to 56
public favorite numbers list
and just add this little array
key here. And now favorite
numbers list is going to be an
array or a list We're going to
comment that out for now. Now if
I were to go ahead and deploy
this contract, let's go ahead
delete the last one, let's
redeploy. We now have this blue
people button here. Remember,
since it's public, and it's a
variable, it automatically is
given a view function, it's
given one of these blue buttons.
And instead of just having a
single button where the value
shows up, it's giving us a form
to fill out, it wants to take a
un 256 as an input parameter. So
if I put zero, I get nothing
back, if I put one, I get
nothing back. No matter what you
put in this box, right? Now
we're gonna get nothing back.
This is because our people array
or our people list is currently
empty. And the value that it
wants is going to be the index
of the object that you want. So
for example, if at index zero, I
had Patrick, it would show
Patrick for zero, if it didn't x
one I had John, or actually
better yet, to Patrick.
Seven, John,
etc. This is what it would show.
But since it's empty, it's going
to show nothing. And let's go
ahead and remove the public
variable from favorite numbers
so that we don't get the
duplicate functions at the
moment, we'll just get the
Retrieve function, we'll show
you how to add to this array in
just a second. This type of
array is what's known as a
dynamic array, because the size
of the array isn't given at the
array initialization. If we were
to say, a people array and add a
three in these brackets here,
that means that this list, or
this array of people could only
be three people big, if we don't
give it a size, it means it can
be any size and the size of the
array can grow and shrink as we
add and subtract people, if I
add three, it can only have a
maximum of three in the array
ever, we're going to work with a
dynamic array, because we're
going to want to add a arbitrary
number of people to this array.
So let's go ahead and create a
function that's going to add
people who are people array, so
we're gonna say function, add
person. And we're going to take
string, memory, name as input
parameter, and I'll explain that
in a minute. And a un 256
underscore favorite number,
we're going to make this a
public function, or we're going
to do is we're going to call a
push function that's available
on our people object. So we're
gonna say people dot push, and
we're going to create a new
person, a new people object,
which is going to take in the
favorite number.
And the name.
Now, this might be a little bit
tricky to you. So let's break
this down. People here is
capitalized. So we know that
since capitalize, it's referring
to this struct people and not
our variable people, the
lowercase people here is
referring to this lowercase
array. So we're saying our array
dot push, or push is the
equivalent of adding basically,
a new people that grabs favorite
number and name. Another way
that we could actually do this
is we could create a variable of
type people and then add it like
so. So we could say people, new
person equals people. And then
we put those brackets the same
way we did before. You say
favorite number is going to be
this input value, this
parameter, and we could say name
is going to be this parameter.
Now if you hit save, you'll get
this error set here, saying data
location must be stored in
memory, or called data for
variable but no one's given. For
now, we're just going to add the
memory keyword here, and I'll
explain what it does in a little
bit. And then of course, we need
to add the new person into our
people dot push right here. So
this is how we're actually going
to push people into our people
array. And I'll get to this
memory keyword in a bit. Now if
we go back to our deploy tab, we
delete our last contract. Let's
deploy this new one. Right now,
if we try to look at the zero
with person in our people array,
we get nothing but let's go
ahead and add a person, we'll
call it, Patrick will be the
name, and seven will be the
favorite number. So we added
Patrick, we added seven. Now if
we look at people's zero, we
should see the zeroeth person
has a name of Patrick, and a
favorite number of seven, boom.
And that's exactly what we do
see, we see a favorite number of
seven, and we see a string name
Patrick, we tried to add John
and do his 16. We hit Add
Person, we can see our
transaction go through. And now
if we go to people at zero, it's
still Patrick with a favorite
number of seven. But if we look
at the people at index one, it's
going to be John with a favorite
number of 16. And if we look at
two, this, of course, should be
blank. And we do indeed see
nothing actually happens here.
Perfect. Now there's actually a
couple of different ways to
create this new person here,
like we showed before, we can
use this bracket notation, or
what we can do is we can
actually just add the parameters
in the order that they show. So
the first parameter for people
is going to be favorite number.
So we can just do favorite
number, comma, and the second
one is going to be name, the
second one is going to be name.
So if we save this, this, this
line we just created is the
exact same as the last line,
we're being a little bit less
explicit here. So the other way
is generally a little bit better
because it's more explicit as to
what variables are what or we
don't even need to save to this
variable here, we could take out
this whole line, replace new
person with exactly what we just
saw, like so now we don't even
need the memory keyword. Now,
you've probably seen this by
now. But if I go ahead and
compile, and I see a little,
little red one here, I roll
over. And it says something
about error, expected semicolon,
but got bracket, all these
errors mean that your code isn't
compiling. It's not working as
expected. So now I can go over
here and do a little semicolon
recompile, and I get a green.
Now if I delete this top line,
for example, and I compile it,
actually get a yellow thing.
Yellow stands for warnings, the
warning that I get is warning
SPX license identifier, not
provided, you should add it. So
let's go ahead and add that
back. recompile. And the warning
goes away. Warnings Don't stop
your code from compiling. So if
you get warnings, it's okay. But
it's usually a good idea to
listen to the warnings, because
often they'll give really
insightful information about how
to improve your smart contracts.
So to summarize, if it's red,
it's broken. If it's yellow, you
might want to check it out. But
it won't stop you from
continuing to code. So one thing
that you'll notice here is that
we have this memory keyword. And
you'll notice if you try to
delete it from our function
here, you try to compile, you
actually run into an error data
location must be memory or call
data for parameter and function.
Now there are actually six
places you can store data in
solidity you have the stack,
memory, storage, call data, code
and logs. We're not going to go
over these right now. But we are
going to focus on three of the
big ones, or three of the
important ones for this section,
which are called data, memory,
and storage. So for this
section, we're going to talk
about call data memory and
storage. And this is a little
bit advanced. So if you don't
totally grasp it the first time,
that's totally okay. Please
continue. Even if it's not
crystal clear what's going on
here, call data and memory mean
that the variable is only going
to exist temporarily. So this
name variable only exists
temporarily during the
transaction that this Add Person
function is called storage
variables exist, even outside of
just the function executing.
Even though we didn't specify it
up above, our favorite number is
automatically cast to be a
storage variable. Since it's not
explicitly defined in one of
these functions. Since we don't
need this name variable anymore
after this function runs, we can
keep it as memory, or we could
keep it as called data, you can
have a parameter as called data
if you don't end up modifying
the name. For example, we
couldn't reassign name to equal
cat here, if we compile we run
into an error. Type literal
string cat is not implicitly
convertible to expect the type
string called data. However, if
we have this as memory, and we
compile and save it, that error
goes away call data is temporary
variables that can't be
modified. Memory is temporary
variables that can be modified.
And storage is permanent
Now even though I just said
there's actually six places
where we can access and store
information, we cannot say a
variable is stack code or logs,
we can only say memory storage
are called data, you will learn
why in a much later section.
Now, this is a bit of an
oversimplification of this. But
that's essentially what's going
on. The next question you might
have is, well, why do I need to
say memory here, but I don't
need to say memory here. Well,
let's go ahead and put memory
here and hit CTRL S or compile.
And let's see what happens we
get from solidity data location
can only be specified for an
array, struct or mapping types.
A memory was given arrays
structs and mappings are
considered special types and
solidity. solidity automatically
knows where are you in 256 is
going to be slowly knows that
for this function, a un 256 is
going to live just in memory.
However, it's not sure what a
string is going to be. Strings
are actually kind of
complicated. Behind the scenes,
a string is actually an array of
bytes. And since a string is an
array, we need to add this
memory bit to it because we need
to tell solidity, the data
location of arrays structs, or
mappings and a string is
secretly an array. So that's why
we need to tell it it's in
memory. You'll notice we can't
add the storage keyword here
slowly also knows that since
this is a function, this name
variable isn't actually getting
stored anywhere. So it says Hey,
you can't have that you need to
have it beat memory or called
data and those are the only two
that it accepts So this is what
we want our function to look
like here. So the summary of
this is struct mappings and
arrays need to be given this
memory or called Data keyword
when adding them as a parameter
to different functions. We'll
learn more about storage memory
and call data in later
sessions. Now, this list
is great, but what if we know
someone's name, but we don't
know their favorite number?
Well, what we could do is we
could look through the whole
array looking for that person.
For example, in our contract, we
can say, Okay, I'm looking for
John. Okay, let's start with
zero. No, okay, that's Patrick.
Okay, let's go to one. Okay.
That's John. Oh, great. His
favorite number 16? Well, this
was really easy, because we only
had two people. But what if we
had hundreds of people in this
array? Well, we'd keep have to
iterating all the way up to the
index that that person was in,
it's obviously really
inefficient. What's another way
to store this information so
that it's much easier and
quicker to access? Well, another
data structure that we can use
is something called a mapping,
you can think of a mapping as
sort of like a dictionary, it's
a set of keys, which each key
returning a certain value
associated with that key. And we
create a mapping variable the