exact same way we create all of
our other variables. This is
going to be a type mapping of
string
to you and tivity sex,
this is going to be our type of
visibility keyword is going to
be public. And we'll call it
name to favorite number. Now we
have a dictionary where every
single name is going to map to a
specific number. So let's add
some capability to our Add
Person function. So we are going
to add our people to our array.
But let's also add them to our
mapping here, what we'll do is
we'll say name to favorite
number. App key name is going to
equal to
favorite number. So let's go
ahead, compile this.
We'll go to our deploy screen,
we'll deploy this click, we have
a new button named a favorite
number. If I type in Patrick,
nothing shows up. By typing
Patrick, you'll see I get zero
response. By typing John, I also
get a zero response. If I type
in Becca, I also get a with zero
response. When you create a
mapping, you initialize
everything to its null value,
every single possible string on
the planet right now is
initialized to having a favorite
number of zero. So if we want to
change that, we'll have to go in
and manually add that. So let's
go ahead and add a person to our
mapping here. So we'll add
Patrick. And we'll say my
favorite number is seven. And
looks like that transaction did
go through also add, Becca, and
we'll say her favorite number is
13. Let John and we'll say his
favorite number is 16. Now, if I
look up, Patrick, I'll
immediately get back what
Patrick's favorite number is, I
get seven back. If we look up,
John, we immediately get back
16. Back up, we may only get
back 13. And we also can see
them in our array. Because we
kept in this people that push
bit zero, we see Patrick's
there. At one, we see Becca. And
at two, we see John, in our
mapping, we're saying the string
name is being mapped to the UN
256 favorite number. And a lot
of my variables, I like to make
them explicitly named like that.
So this is name to
favorite number. So
now we're in a space where let's
say that we really like our
simple storage contract. Right
now we have a favorite number, a
global variable that we can save
a favorite number to with our
store function, we have a
mapping of name to favorite
numbers, and we have an array of
a new type that we created
called people, we can add to
both the array and to the
mapping. Using this Add Person
function that we've created,
we're able to save multiple
people's favorite numbers as
well as kind of a global
favorite number as well. Let's
say we really love this
contract, and we're ready to
send it to a test net to have
other people interact with it.
Now in future sections, you'll
hear me say that you shouldn't
do this until you write tests
until you do some really simple
auditing. But for now, let's go
ahead and learn how to actually
deploy this to a test net or to
a real network. Now remember,
test nets are run out of the
goodness of people's hearts. So
if it's a little bit funky, or
maybe doesn't work exactly as we
show here, that's okay. As long
as it works with the JavaScript
VM, you'll be all set but it is
good practice to learn how to
deploy these to a real test net.
Let's go ahead and do that. Our
contract is here. Simple Storage
dot soul. It's compiled,
compiling is passing we get this
little green checkmark here we
go to the deploy section. Let's
go ahead and do Get this. And
now we're going to change the
environment. So we were working
with a JavaScript VM or kind of
this fake simulated environment,
we want to now move to either
injected web three, or web three
provider. If you hover over
injected web three, there's this
really, really small text here.
But this basically means we're
going to inject our meta mask or
our web three wallet into our
browser to use similar to what
we did with the faucet, we'll
pick our account we want to use.
So I'm gonna go ahead and pick
account one. And now we actually
see our account in the Account
section of remix, injected web
three means we're using our meta
mask or whatever web three
wallet, web three provider is,
when we a little bit more
manually choose an endpoint. And
we're not going to go over this
right now. But as we get later
into the course, you'll
understand what this means. So
we're picking injected web
three, whatever network are
injected web three, or in this
case, our wallet is connected to
is going to be the network that
we deploy to. So for this
section, we're going to be
deploying to Rinkeby. But again,
depending on whatever the
recommended test net and the
recommended faucet is, that will
dictate which test net you
should actually deploy to. For
us, it's going to be Rigby. To
deploy to a test that remember,
we're going to need gas, so
we're going to need some tested
Etherium. Or if you're deploying
to a main net main Aetherium,
which you shouldn't be come to
the top of the GitHub repo to
make sure you have the most
updated faucet, the other place
you can go is link token
contracts page in the chain link
documentation and scroll down
the ranking. And you can see
test that link available here,
test that eath available here.
So this is the other location,
you can always look to find the
most up to date faucets, and
both of them point right back
here. So now that we're working
with injected web three, we can
just go through the exact same
steps to deploy to a test net as
to deploy to a virtual machine.
And remember, if you run out of
gas to deploy this, be sure to
check back to the faucets to
actually deploy this. So we're
going to do the same thing,
we're gonna go ahead and hit
Deploy. But this time Metamask
is going to pop up and ask us if
we want to actually deploy this,
this is the exact same as what
we saw with the blockchain
example, where we sign
transactions, we are signing and
sending this transaction, the
data of this transaction is this
massive, massive data thing
here, which represents the
contract that we just created,
we can see all the payment
information for this transaction
for deploying this contract, we
see it's going to cost around
this much Aetherium to deploy.
But again, we're on the Rinkeby
test network. So this is going
to be fake Aetherium. We're
gonna go ahead, hit Confirm. And
if you pop up a little console,
and remix, you'll see that after
a slight delay, it'll actually
say have this green checkmark
that it's confirmed that it went
actually went through, we can go
ahead right click, open a new
tab, and view this on ether
scan. And after a slight delay,
we'll actually be able to see
the transaction details here,
exactly the same as our
transaction details for sending
Aetherium we have a hash, we
have a status, we have blocked
block confirmations, we have
timestamp from which is going to
be us two, which is going to be
the average of the contract that
we just created. We didn't send
any value with this. So this is
going to be zero ether. And then
of course, we see the
transaction fee, and as well as
the gas price. Because again,
deploying a contract to the
blockchain is modifying the
state of the blockchain. So we
have to pay gas, and we can see
all the different pieces here.
As we can see, gas limit and gas
usage is much higher than just
sending Aetherium, since we are
putting a lot of data on chain
and adding a lot of computation.
So this number is much higher
than the 21,000 number of just
sending Aetherium. Now, if we
come back to our remix and
scroll down, we're able to see
our simple storage contract at
this address. If we hit this
copy button, and we go to the
rink be ether scan, we paste it
in the search bar, we will get
the contract that we just
deployed. And we see this first
transaction is going to be the
contract creation transaction.
So this contract that we just
created one transaction, which
is contract created. So now that
we have this contract created,
we have all the exact same
functions that we saw when
working with the JavaScript
virtual machine, or the our fake
environment, or our super fake
environment. Now we can do all
the exact same things that we
did with the JavaScript VM, but
on a real test network. So
you'll see if I hit retrieve
Metamask doesn't pop up. Because
again, this is a blue view
function. If we look people at
zero, this is also a view
function and nothing pops up,
named a favorite number should
be blank. So if I type in
Patrick now, absolutely nothing
happens, right? I get I get zero
returned because mappings
initialize every single key with
a blank or a null value, which
for you 256 is zero. Now, we can
go ahead and store a favorite
number store When your favorite
number is going to modify the
blockchain, so our meta mask
should pop up for us to confirm
the transaction and sign that
transaction to modify the
blockchain state. So I'm going
to store my favorite number of
16, we'll hit store, meta mask
will pop up, and we're going to
go ahead and actually confirm
this didn't confirm is
equivalent to US signing this
transaction and sending it to
the blockchain to modify the
state. So we're gonna go ahead
and confirm this, we should be
able to view this on ether scan.
And again, it might take a
little bit for it to actually
index or actually start working.
So please be patient with these
test nets. And again, this is
why when building your
applications, you want the test
net piece to absolutely try to
be your last step, because you
have to wait a really long time.
And it puts a burden on these
people running these tests into
running it out of the goodness
of their heart. So please try to
make this the last step of your
actual building process. For us
learning right here, it's okay.
And after a slight delay, once
we hit refresh, it looks like
it's indexing on ether scan, the
ether scan website is still
figuring out where the
transaction is going to remix,
it looks like on the blockchain,
this has actually already gone
through. So now if we hit
retrieve, we do indeed see, our
favorite number is 16. Of
course, these two are still
going to be blank. And it looks
like that transaction has gone
through and ether scan has
indexed. So now let's go ahead
and add a person will add
Patrick, and my favorite number
is going to be 16. We'll go
ahead and add person. Again,
since these are orange
transactions gonna pop up
because we're modifying the
blockchain state, we'll go ahead
and hit Confirm. And we're going
to be a little bit patient here
and wait for this transaction to
go through. And we should see
this update. And this update.
Now if I hit named a favorite
number of Patrick, I get 16. And
if I hit people of zero, I get
favorite number 16. And the name
is Patrick. Awesome. So you've
actually successfully deployed a
contract to an actual test net,
and actually seen on ether scan
what these transactions look
like, you should be incredibly
proud of yourself, be sure to
give yourself a high five pat on
the back, send a tweet saying
exactly how excited you are. But
make sure to celebrate these
little wins, celebrating these
little wins will give you the
motivation to keep going and
really excite you for learning
each new thing. So huge.
Congratulations. If you got this
far, you've deployed your first
contract to a test net,
congratulations. Now if you want
to see what it looks like to
deploy to a different network,
all you need to do in your
Metamask is switch to a
different test net. See, if we
switch to COVID remix
automatically updates and says,
ah, injected web three is now
the COVID test network. We could
switch again maybe to Grilley,
we say Ah, the injected web
three is now at the Grilley.
This is the test net that we'd
be deploying to of course, we
need actual test net Aetherium
to do any deploying, so we
wouldn't be able to here. And if
we go ahead and hit Deploy right
now Metamask pops up. But we get
this little red thing saying
insufficient funds. Of course,
later on, we'll learn how to add
new networks like polygon like
avalanche like phantom into our
Metamask. So we can deploy from
any one of them
as well.
Now, I mentioned this term
before, but all this code that
we wrote, when we hit this
compile button, it compiles it
down to the EVM or the Ethereum
virtual machine. Don't worry too
much about what this means. EVM
is a standard of how to deploy
smart contracts to Aetherium
like blockchains. And any
blockchain that implements a
type of EVM. You can deploy
solidity code to some examples
of EVM compatible blockchains
are going to be avalanche,
Phantom, and polygon. Since
these are EVM compatible, this
means we can write our solidity
code, and deploy to these
blockchains, which again, I'll
show you later on how to add
these new networks into your
Metamask. And then how to deploy
them. Let's do a quick recap of
our first smart contract. And
then you should actually take a
break, maybe get some ice cream
or coffee because you absolutely
deserve it. Congratulations. The
first thing you always need to
do in your smart contracts is
tell solidity, what version of
solidity that you're going to be
using. And additionally, you
want to add an spdx license
identifier, then you have to
create your contract object and
name your contract. The contract
in solidity is similar to a
class in other programming
languages, and everything inside
the squiggly brackets is a part
of that contract. There are many
different types in solidity like
unsigned integer, 256, Boolean
string, bytes, 32, etc. If we
want to create a new type, we
can create what's called a
struct in solidity. You can
create arrays or lists in
solidity, you can create
dictionaries, or what's called
mappings in solidity or hash
tables, which when you give it a
key, it'll spit out the value
that that key represents. We can
create functions in solidity
that modify the state of the
blockchain. We can also create
functions in solidity that don't
modify the state of the
blockchain view in pure
functions, don't modify by the
state of a blockchain, we also
can specify different data
locations in our functions,
called data and memory mean that
that data is only temporary and
will only exist for the duration
of the function. Storage
variables are permanent and stay
there forever. function
parameters can't be stored
variables because they're only
going to exist for the duration
of the function. All the
solidity code that we work with,
when we hit Compile, it actually
compiles down to this Aetherium
virtual machine specifications.
We'll learn more about those
specifications later. And last,
but not least, another huge
congratulations on your first
contract here.
Awesome.
All right, let's get started on
our lesson three, remember,
everything is in the GitHub
repository. And we can scroll
down, hit Lesson three and see
all the code here. I'm building
up this repo as I film. So
underneath this lesson three is
going to be a lot more
information than just the code
here, all of our code samples
end with dash f f, c, which
means dash Free Code Camp. So if
you see a GitHub repo that ends
with dash F, F, C, know that
that repository is associated
with this course, I'm going to
do a quick high level
walkthrough of what we're going
to be building in this lesson.
So you don't need to code right
now just sit back watch and
enjoy. In this lesson, we're
actually going to expand to
having three different
contracts. Let's say we want to
be able to deploy simple storage
contracts from a contract
itself. Yes, contracts can
indeed deploy contracts, we are
going to create a contract
called storage factory dot sole,
that's going to be able to
deploy and interact with other
contracts itself. So what we
could do is we could go deploy
this to a JavaScript VM, we're
going to choose storage factory,
and we're gonna go ahead and hit
Deploy. In our contract down
below, we have a number of
different functions. Our top
function is this function called
crate simple storage contract,
which we can click and it'll
actually create a simple storage
contract for us, then we can go
ahead and interact with it at an
IG zero will save a favorite
number of one. Now, if we hit SF
get zero,
we get one back. And
we can see the address of the
simple storage contract that we
just deployed. Additionally,
we're going to learn about a
number of solidity features,
such as importing inheritance,
and so much more. So let's go
ahead and jump in. And remember
all the code is available here
from the GitHub repository. So
be sure to refer back to these
contracts if you get lost.
So here we are
back in remix, and we have our
simple storage dot soul. If you
skipped over the last section,
be sure to go to the full
blockchain solidity course, Jas.
And scroll down to lesson two,
welcome to remix and grab this
code. Go to simple storage
outsole. And copy paste this
code into remix. Because this is
where we're going to be starting
from, we have this simple
storage contract, which is
great. It allows us to store a
favorite number. And it allows
us to store favorite numbers
across different people in both
mappings and arrays. But let's
say we want to get even more
advanced with this, we actually
can have a contract actually
deploy other contracts for us.
And then go ahead and interact
with those contracts from other
contracts, contracts interacting
with each other is an essential
part of working with solidity
and working with smart
contracts. The ability for
contracts to seamlessly interact
with each other is what's known
as composability. smart
contracts are composable,
because they can easily interact
with each other. This is
especially awesome when it comes
to things like defy where you
can have really complex
financial products interact with
each other incredibly easily,
since all their code is
available on chain. So we're
going to learn how to do that.
So let's keep our simple storage
contract exactly the way it is,
we're going to create a new
contract called storage factory.
So we're going to hit the New
File button and type in storage,
factory dot salt. And let's
close this off for now. So let's
go ahead and get this contract
setup from what we learned
before. First thing we're going
to want to do is the spdx
license identifier, which we're
going to do MIT. And then the
next thing we're always going to
need is our solidity version.
So we'll do pragma solidity
and we could do zero point 8.7.
But for this one, let's do zero
point 8.0 And then just add the
carrot, meaning any version of
0.8 point something will work.
And then let's add our contract
name, which is going to be
storage factory. Now hit command
S or ctrl S or go to the compile
tab and hit compile, and boom,
we have our regular setup here.
Now we want to create a function
that can actually deploy our
simple storage contract. So
we'll create a function called
function. create simple storage
contract, we'll have it be
public, so anybody can call it
will have to deploy a simple
storage contract and save it to
a global variable. But before we
can do it How can our storage
factory contract know what our
simple storage contract looks
like? In order to deploy it, if
our storage factory contract is
going to deploy simple storage,
it's going to need to know code
of simple storage. One way we
can do this is we can actually
go to our simple storage dot
soul and copy everything
underneath pragma, solidity and
down and paste it into our
storage factory dot soul
underneath our pragma, solidity.
If we go ahead and compile and
save this, it actually works our
storage factory, that soul
contract actually now has two
contracts in it. It has the
simple storage contract, and it
has the storage factory contract
in it, you actually go to the
deploy tab and scroll down to
deploy while you're on the
storage factory dot soul, not
the simple storage that's all on
storage factory, you can see
that you can actually choose
which one of these contracts to
deploy, a single file of
solidity can hold multiple
different contracts. Now that we
have our simple storage, that's
all in our storage factory, we
can actually go ahead and create
this function to deploy a simple
storage console, we're going to
create a global variable the
same way that we would create
any other global variable, we'll
do the type, which is going to
be type simple storage contract,
we'll give it a visibility of
public. And we'll give it a
variable name. Type simple
storage contract going to be
public, the name of the variable
is going to be simple storage.
Now in our function, create
simple storage contract, we're
gonna say simple storage equals
new, simple storage.
This new keyword is how solidity
knows Ah, okay, we're going to
deploy a new simple storage
contract. So we go ahead and
compile this, we'll go to the
deploy tab, make sure we're on
the JavaScript VM, we'll scroll
down to the contract. And we'll
choose storage factory. And
remember, you need to have
storage factory dot soul
selected. In order for that to
show up storage factory, we'll
go ahead and hit Deploy. And now
we see our storage factory
contract has two buttons. One is
create simple storage, and the
other one is going to be a view
of our simple storage contract.
If we click it right now, it's
going to show us that it's
currently at address zero,
because it gets initialized to
being blank. It's saying there
is no simple storage contract
currently deployed. Now if we
pull up our console and click
create simple storage, we see we
created a new function call
storage factory dot create
simple storage contract. And in
doing so we called this function
which created and deployed a new
simple storage contract, we can
now see what address the simple
storage contract is out by
clicking the simple storage
button and we see the address
associated with it. So now we
know how a contract can actually
deploy another contract. But the
thing is, having this massive
chunk of code above our storage
factory is a little bit
redundant, especially since we
have our other file called
Simple Storage dot soul. And
let's say we have a contract
that has got a ton of other
contracts in it. Always copy
pasting all these contracts is
going to be a lot of work. So
instead, what we can do is use
what's called an import. So
let's go ahead and delete our
contracts simple storage. And
now we're just going to type
import dot slash simple storage
dot soul. This import dot slash
simple storage dot Seoul is the
exact same as our copy pasted
version of simple storage.
That's all. It takes the path of
another file, it takes the path
package or GitHub, which we'll
get to in a minute of another
file and says, Okay, we're going
to paste that contract into the
top of this contract here, we
actually see we go back to
compile, we go to deploy, let's
delete our old contract, we can
actually see storage factory dot
soul again, we can deploy it,
click the drop down. And once
again, we can run those
functions exactly the same.
importing our contracts like
this is much nicer than always
copy pasting the code. This way,
if we want to change something
in simple storage, we have one
canonical place to go ahead and
change it instead of having to
change it in multiple different
places. Now additionally, you'll
notice the pragma, solidity if
we have our contracts in two
separate files, we actually can
have different versions of
solidity right now our storage
factory has carrot zero point
8.0 Which means that anything
within the 0.8 range of this
contract is okay. But for simple
storage that sole, it says
anything in the zero point 8.8
And above range is okay. So if
we were to try to change the
compiler version 8.5 And then go
ahead and compile, a remix is
going to automatically bump it
up to a better version that is
compatible with both of them, in
this case eight point 13. But if
we, for example, changed our
solidity version of storage
factory to zero point 7.0 And
then tried to compile them. We
actually end up getting an issue
parser error source file
requires a different compiler
version. This is because our
storage factory is saying hey,
anything in 0.7 means is okay.
However, our simple storage is
saying anything in the zero
point 8.8 And above is okay. So
those two versions are not
compatible. So what we need to
do is we need to make sure our
versions of solidity are indeed
compatible. So let's change the
version back recompile. And now
we're looking good again. Now
since we have this create simple
storage contract, every single
time we call it right now, it'll
just replace whatever is
currently in our public simple
storage variable. Let's go ahead
and update this so that we can
actually keep a running list of
all of our deployed simple
storage contracts. So instead of
having this be a single
variable, we'll make this a
simple storage array or list
public simple storage array.
Now, whenever we create a new
simple storage contract, instead
of saving it like this, what
we're going to do is we're going
to save it as a memory variable
by saying simple storage, simple
storage equals new simple
storage. And we're going to add
this variable to our simple
storage array. So the same way
we did it before, we're gonna do
simple storage array dot push,
simple storage. So I should
spell storage, right? Let's go
ahead and compile this looks
good. We'll deploy the storage
factory deploy. Like here, we
now have simple storage array
View button, we'll do create
simple storage. Now we can view
the simple storage contract
zero. Right now there's nothing
at one. But if we create another
simple storage contract, we can
see the new simple storage
contract address at index one.
All right, so this is great,
we can now keep track of all of
our simple storage deployments.
But how do we actually interact
with them, let's say we wanted
to be able to call the store
function on all of our simple
storage dot souls from our
storage factory, you can think
of the storage factory as almost
like a manager of all of our
simple storages. That's all
let's create a new function that
can do exactly that. So we'll
create function, and we'll call
it S F store, which is going to
stand for storage factory store.
And it's going to take you in
256, simple storage index, and a
UNT 256, underscore simple
storage
number. There'll be a public
auction as well. Now in order
for you to interact with any
contract, you're always going to
need two things. And we're going
to refer to this a lot. You're
always going to need the address
of the contract, and the ABI of
the contract. The API stands for
Application binary interface,
the API will tell our code
exactly how it can interact with
the contract, we'll go deeper
into API as we move on. But if
you go to your compile tab, you
hit compile, and things are
actually compiling. You can
scroll down, and you can see
compilation details. And you can
see a whole bunch of information
on your different contracts. You
can see the name of your
contract, which for our simple
storage contract is simple
storage, you can see a whole
bunch of metadata, like the
compiler, the language output
settings, all this other stuff.
You can see the exact bytecode
and the opcodes, which we'll
talk about much later. But you
can also see this API, this API
tells you all the different
inputs and outputs and
everything you could do with
this contract. For example, in
our simple storage, if we look
at the zero with index of our
API, we have a function add
person. If we look at one, we
see our name to favorite number,
we looked at two we can see our
people three retrieve for store,
it tells us all these different
ways we can actually interact
with our contract. And the
different functions that we can
call, we know where addresses
are, because we're storing them
in this array here, our simple
storage array, we can also get
the API because we're importing
simple storage dot soul when you
compile simple storage on soul.
As you saw on the compilation
details, whenever you compile
it, it comes prepackaged with
the ABI, we automatically get
the ABI just by importing it
like this. In the future, we'll
see other ways that we can
actually get API's really
easily. So to call the store
function on one of our
contracts, we're first going to
need to get that contract
object. So what we can do is we
can say simple storage variable
named simple storage. Variable
Name simple storage of type
simple storage is going to be
equal to a simple storage
object. And instead of doing new
simple storage, like we did last
time, we're just going to put
the address of this simple
storage object in here, which
again, we can get from our
array. And in this function,
we're passing the array index.
So we can say simple storage
contract at address simple
storage array. At index simple
Storage index. This bracket
notation here is how you access
different elements of arrays. So
if we want the zeroeth element
of our list here, simple storage
index would be zero, and we pass
it into this bit here, then
that'll give us the address of
our simple storage contract,
which we pass into simple
storage here. Since this is an
array of simple storage
contracts, we can just access
that simple storage contract
using the index. So we would
say, simple store, Edge array at
index underscore simple storage
index. Now we're saving the
contract object at index simple
storage index to our simple
storage variable. Our array here
is keeping track of the
addresses for us. And it
automatically comes with the ABI
is here. If this was just an
array of addresses of the
contract objects, instead, we
would have to wrap the address
in a simple storage object like
this. But we'll get to that much
later. So for now, all we have
to do is this and we now have a
simple storage contract object.
Now that we have it, we can call
our store function on the simple
storage contract. So we'll call
simple storage dot store. And
we'll store the simple storage
number to it. So this
is perfect. And if we were to
deploy this right now, though,
we wouldn't be able to read the
store function. So let's create
another function that can read
from the simple storage contract
from the storage factory. So
we'll create a function called S
F get, which stands for storage
factory get, it'll take a un 256
underscore simple storage index.
This will be a public view
function, since we're just going
to be reading from our simple
storage contract. And it's going
to return a UNT 256. And we'll
say simple storage.
Simple Storage. Equals
when you use this same syntax
from up here to get the contract
simple storage array at the
simple storage index. And then
we're going to do return,
simple storage.re retrieve
to get that number that we just
stored up here. And I should
spell retrieved correctly, so we
get no issues. Perfect. So now
we'll compile, we'll deploy JAVA
script, we're working on a fake
account, we're going to use our
storage factory, go ahead and
delete all the contracts we have
so far. Let's go ahead and
deploy the drop down rate. Right
now if we do SF get at zero,
we're going to get nothing.
Simple Storage address zero is
going to be nothing. Let's
create a simple storage
contract. Now it's simple
storage list, we get an address
at zero. If we hit SF get right
now it didn't zero, we get zero.
So let's store a value on this
contract here. So the index of
that contract is zero. So we're
going to pass zero as a symbol
storage index. And we're going
to save the number seven. So
we'll go ahead and do SF store.
And if we did this, right, this
is going to store the value
seven into this contract. So if
we do SF get of zero now, it
does indeed return seven. If we
do SF get one we're going to get
nothing's going to happen. And
we're actually going to get this
revert error here. So let's
create another simple storage
contract. Now if we do SF get
one, we get zero, because we're
gonna get that default value.
Let's go ahead on the simple
storage contract and index one
will store the number 16 will
hit SF store. Now we'll do SF
get one and we get 16. Feel free
to pause right now and play
around with this so that you
really understand it. The quick
recap is our storage factory
contract allows us to create
simple storage contracts, it
then saves it to our simple
storage array, which we can then
call different functions on, we
can store values from our
storage factory contract. And
then we can read values from our
storage factory contract for any
of the simple storage contracts
that we've created. This is
incredibly powerful, we can
additionally make these two
functions even easier. We can
call the Retrieve function
directly on this when we call
simple storage array. And then
we have these brackets and add
the simple storage index. This
returns a simple storage object.
So what we could do is we could
actually delete this whole part
and just do dot retrieve
right here, and then delete this
line and say return and just
have it be just like this. If
you go ahead and save or hit
Compile, you'll get the green
checkmark there. We're calling
the Retrieve function on
whatever this is. And whatever
this is, is a simple storage
object. So perfect. We can do
the same thing up here by
deleting this part and just
doing dot store, underscore
simple store edge number, we
save it. And this will work
exactly the same. Awesome, we
now have a simple storage
contract that can store
variables in a storage factory
contract that can be almost like
a manager of these simple
storage contracts and deploy and
interact with them themselves.
This is
fantastic. Now, let's say that
we really liked the simple
storage contract, but it doesn't
do everything that we want it to
do. Maybe we want it so that
whenever we actually store value
doesn't store the favorite
number, it stores the favorite
number plus five, for some
reason you want a contract that
that everyone's favorite number
is five numbers bigger than what
they think it is. But you really
like everything else that this
contract has to offer. Let's
create this new contract. And
we'll call it extra storage.
So we'll say extra storage dot
soul.
And we'll create this new
contract, we're going to set it
up the exact same way we
normally would spdx license
identifier, gonna be MIT, we'll
give it pragma solidity. And
we'll just do zero
point 8.0 with the carrot. And
we'll say contract, extra
storage, like so
if you save or compile, you'll
get the green checkmark. So what
can we do? Well, the first thing
we could do is we could copy
paste all this code back into
here, and then modify our extra
storage contract as we see fit.
This seems a little bit
redundant. And a lot of work
though. So what's another way we
can actually get our extra
storage contract to be like our
simple storage contract? Well,
this is where we can do
something called inheritance, we
can have our extra storage
contract, do what's called a
child contract of our simple
storage contract. And we can
have extra storage, inherit all
the functionality of simple
storage with two lines of code.
So first, in order for our extra
storage contract to know about
simple storage, we once again
need to import it. So we'll say
import dot slash, simple storage
dot soul. And we'll say our
contract extra storage is simple
storage. And we save or compile.
Now our extra storage contract
is going to be the exact same as
simple storage. And it's going
to do what's called inherit all
the functionality of simple
storage. And we can actually
even see that, let's go ahead
and make sure this is compiled.
And we'll go and deploy this.
And now in our deployed
contract, we can see we have
extra storage deployed with all
the functions that simple
storage has, if you want a
contract to inherit all the
functionality of another
contract, you can just import it
and say your contract is that
other contract. Now, we can add
additional functions to our
extra storage contract. That
will include all the
functionality of simple storage.
Now, let's say that we inherit
simple storage to extra storage.
However, one of the functions in
simple storage we don't really
actually like. So if we go back
to our simple storage contract,
our store function, all it does
is take a favorite number, and
then assigns the global favorite
number to whatever new number
that we give it in our extra
storage. We want the store
function to do something
different. We want it to add
five, to any number that we give
it. How can we achieve this?
Well, we can do something called
overriding the functions. And
there are two keywords that
we're going to use. Those are
virtual, and override. Right
now, if I were to try to
implement a store function for
extra storage, let's see what
happens. We'll say function
store, you went to the six
favorite number. There'll be a
public function. And let's say
instead of just storing favorite
number, we'll say favorite
number equals favorite number,
plus five. If we try to compile
this right now, we'll actually
run into two different errors.
First one is going to say
overriding function is missing,
override specifier. If the
parent contract, which in our
case is simple storage has that
same function, we need to tell
solidity that we're going to
override this store function and
instead we're going to use this
store function. But
additionally, we get this other
error saying trying to override
non virtual function. Did you
forget to add virtual in order
for a function to be overridable
you need to add the virtual
keyword to the store function.
Now it can be overridable.
However, if we save and compile,
we still have this issue
overriding function is missing
override specifier. And then all
we need to do is add override to
restore function. Now if we save
everything compiles correctly,
let's go ahead and deploy this.
Let's delete our old contracts.
JavaScript VM right account.
Great we're going to choose
extra store Reg, let's go ahead
and deploy. And here's our extra
storage contract. Right now if
we retrieve, we get zero.
Previously, our store function
would store the exact number.
However, if I were to store
five, it'll store five, plus
five. So we should have 10
stored here. Let's go ahead call
store looks like that one
through, and we'll hit retrieved
now. And we do indeed see 10 is
in here. So this is how we do
inheritance, and we override
functions. And that's it. For
this
section, you've just learned a
ton of incredibly powerful
solidity for having multiple
files. Let's do a quick overview
of what we learned, we learned
that we can actually deploy
contracts from other contracts
using the new keyword, we
learned that we can actually
import other contracts into our
contracts and into our code
using the Import keyword. And
the import keyword is the same
as copying pasting that file to
the location of the import line,
we learned that we can interact
with other contracts. As long as
we have the ABI and address. We
didn't learn too much about the
ABI. But we'll learn more later,
we learned that if we want to
create a child contract and
inherit the functionality of
some other contract, we can do
something called inheritance.
And the way to inherit
functionality is using the is
keyword and saying our contract
is some other contract. However,
if we want to change from the
functionality of the parent
contract, we have to override
that function. And additionally,
we have to set the function we
want to override to virtual now
we can have our own store
function, do whatever we want it
to do. That is the end of this
lesson. Once again, give
yourself a huge round of
applause a pat on the back for
making it this far. And for
finishing this section. You're
getting more and more advanced
facility so quickly, so be sure
to celebrate the little wins by
getting some ice cream, maybe
going for a walk or tweeting
about or posting on Reddit.
Congratulations, you have
completed this section.
All right, everybody. Welcome
back. We are now headed into
Lesson four remix Funmi. And of
course, all the code can be
found on the GitHub repository
associated with this course.
We're going to be working with
two contracts here, one of them
is fundament outsole. And then
one of them is price converted
outsole Funmi dot Sol is going
to be a contract that allows
people to actually fund a
collective good. So people can
send Aetherium send Aetherium,
or polygon or Avalanche or
Phantom, or whatever blockchain
native token into this contract,
and some owner of the contract
can then withdraw those funds
and do whatever they want. After
deploying this to a test net, we
can see the list of functions
this contract has, this will
have two red buttons, which are
used to notate to payable
functions in fund in our fund
function. And in our withdrawal
function, withdraw allows users
to withdraw the funding and fund
allows users to send money to
the contract, what we can do is
we can send some value along
with our transaction. When we
call this fund function, then
what we can do is we can
actually fund this contract with
a certain amount of eath, or way
by pasting some value into the
way value section. And then
hitting fund, we will now have
sent money into our deployed
contract. And we can see a list
of the funders and a mapping of
those addresses and how much
they've actually sent into the
contract, we can then withdraw
the funds out of the contract.
With a special exception with
only the person who deployed
this contract can actually
withdraw the funds back out.
Once the funds are withdrawn,
the amount of all the funds is
reset back to zero. Are you
excited? Well, you should be.
And if you've finished the
section, you've completed most
of the basics of solidity, and
you'll be ready to start making
even more powerful smart
contracts, we'll be using
channeling price feeds to
actually set the value of how
much these people should be able
to fund in USD as opposed to
just in terms of ether, we're
gonna go over a lot of advanced
sections here. And I'll let you
know what parts might be a
little bit harder to digest. So
you don't have to spend your
entire time trying to figure out
exactly what's going on. Be sure
to use the GitHub repo to your
advantage here and the
discussions tab to stay
connected with other people
taking this lesson. Alright,
let's jump in. So at this point,
in remix, you'll have a couple
of contracts here, simple
storage, storage, factory extra
storage, maybe you refreshed
remix, and these have gone away.
And in the case, make sure that
you just don't have any of those
tabs open, we're going to create
a new contract called funding.
So let's go ahead and start
creating our funding contract.
Again, we want it to be able to
get funds from users and
withdraw funds and set a minimum
funding value in USD. This is
what we're going to get our
contract to do. So first, let's
set it up spdx license I tend to
fire MIT do pragma solidity do
caret zero point 8.8. And we'll
do contract bunbee. Awesome. And
we'll compile, see if things
look good. And they do. Great.
Let's keep going. So before we
actually embark on creating all
of our functions here, let's
just add the different functions
that we're going to implement.
So we want a function fund for
people to actually send money
to, we want a function withdraw,
or the owner of this contract to
actually withdraw the funds that
different funders actually give
us. And that's pretty much it.
These are the two main functions
that we want this contract to
do, we will be implementing more
functions to help facilitate
these two functions. But let's
get started by looking at fund.
let's comment out withdrawal for
now. And let's just start with
fun. So we want anybody to be
able to call this fun function.
So we'll make this public. So as
we mentioned, we want to be able
to set a minimum font amount in
USD. So there's a lot of things
to think about here. First thing
we probably want to think about
is how do we send eath to this
contract, whenever we create a
transaction on the on any of
these EVM blockchains, there's
this value field that we can set
value represents how much
Aetherium we're going to be
sending with our transactions.
For example, when we transferred
Aetherium. between our different
accounts, we were actually
populating this value parameter
with different amounts of
Aetherium. In fact, every single
transaction that we send, will
have these fields, it'll have a
nonce or the transaction count
the account the gas price, the
gas limit that we've seen on
ether scan a to aka the address
that the transaction is sent to
a value which is going to be
this amount that we're talking
about. They'll also have data
which is going to be what we
send if we make a function call
or deploy contract, and then
we'll have this v r s
components. We're not really
going to go over these v r and s
because this is that
cryptographic magic that's
happening when a transaction is
signed, but just know that
that's it Now, for sending
value, we can populate some of
these fields, the gas limit, for
example, was populated to 21,000
data is going to be empty. And
then that two is going to be the
address of the transaction we
want to send to, for a function
call, we can also still populate
the way that we want to send. So
we can call a function and send
a value at the same time in
remix has a little drop down
here for way way Feeny and
ether, we're gonna ignore Feeny
for now. But of course, we have
our way, great and ether. Again,
we're one ether is worth this
much way. And this much way, the
first thing we need to do in
order to make a function payable
with Aetherium, or any other
native blockchain currency is we
need to mark the function as
payable. It's this payable
keyword that makes our font
function red, as opposed to
having it normal orange, just
like how our wallet can hold
funds, contract addresses can
hold funds as well, since every
time you deploy a contract, they
get a contract address, it's
nearly the exact same as a
wallet address. So both wallets
and contracts can hold native
blockchain token like Aetherium.
And you'll see that when we
deploy this later on in the
lesson, that actually will gain
a balance of Aetherium. Now that
we have it payable, we can
access this value attribute by
using one of the global keywords
in solidity with message dot
value to get how much value
somebody is sending. You use
message dot value in your
function. Now let's say we want
to set our message add value to
a certain value of Aetherium.
Let's say we wanted it to be
let's say we wanted people to
send at least one whole ether
with all the transactions. Or
put another way, if they sent
Aetherium, they would need to
send at least one Aetherium. How
would we implement that? Well,
we could do something called
require, we would say we want to
require the message dot value is
greater than one e 18. There's a
couple of things to unpack here.
One, e 18 is equal to one times
10 raised to the 18th, which is
also equal to
112345 678-910-1234 5678. This
is the value in way of one
Aetherium this much way is one
eath. So if we wanted the
message dot value to be at least
one eath, or one polygon or
whatever ranch etc, we would set
it like this require message on
value is greater than one. This
require keyword is a checker it
says hey, is message dot value
greater than one. If not, it's
going to revert, it's going to
do what's called revert with an
error message. And we can say
didn't send enough, we're gonna
try deploying this on a
JavaScript VM, deploy Funmi,
we'll hit Deploy, look at Funmi
we see this fun button is now
red. If we call Funmi right now,
and we look at the console, you
can see we actually get an error
here, call it again, we get an
error, we get an error here, we
know that the air is going to be
this didn't send enough. So what
we need to do is we need to send
at least one ether with this fun
transaction, in order for this
require statement to be
fulfilled. So back up in the
value section, we can change
this value to one. So that's
gonna be one ether, or this much
way or this much way. Now we can
hit fund oh actually needs to be
greater than one.
So let's send to for example.
Now we'll scroll down. And now
we'll hit fund. And we see that
that actually passes the require
statement says if our first
section is false, then go ahead
and revert with this error. What
is reverting? Revert can be a
little bit confusing, so I
wouldn't let this section hold
you back. If it's a little bit
confusing. Revert is when it
undos any actions that happened
before and send the remaining
gas back. So what does that
actually look like? Well, let's
say for example, we had a un
256. Public number. And in our
fund function, we said number
equals five. If we were to go
ahead and deploy this, let's
delete our old contract.
deployed this new contract or
number right now is zero. But if
we were to call our fund
function number gets set to
five. However, if we call a fund
and this require isn't met, this
transaction would revert an
undue setting number to five. So
let's go ahead and look at our
logs here. We'll keep value zero
so that our fun function
reverts. We'll call fund will
see that this transaction failed
because this require end up
reverting and number is still
zero. So then the question
becomes, did we actually spend
gas Yes, we spent gas to change
number to five and then any
remaining gas we would get
returned by this require for
example, if we had a ton of
computation here, it On a
computation here, we would have
need to send a ton of gas with
our fun function. But all the
extra gas that we send, after
this require gets returned the
original user after it gets
reverted right here, if reverts
are a little bit confusing for
you here, don't worry too much
about it, we'll go over it in
future modules. All you need to
know right now is that when you
do a require statement, if this
first section isn't met, the
transaction will be canceled,
and any prior work will be
undone, and it'll send an error
message. Cool. Let's delete this
number for now. And we'll delete
it from the global scope.
There's actually another way to
do these reverts, which we'll go
over
later in this contract. So what
we've done so far is great.
However, we're checking message
dot value in terms of Aetherium,
we're looking for one whole
Aetherium instead of $50, we
want to check that message add
value is greater than some
number like $50. Let's go ahead
and first set the minimum USD
value we want people to send
along with the fund function, we
can do that at the top of our
contract, we can say you went to
56 public minimum USD equals 50.
Now we have some place to check
for minimum USD, we're going to
update this minimum USD to make
it more gas efficient and a
little bit. Now that we've set
our minimum USD, we want to be
able to require the message that
value is greater than or let's
say greater than or equal to the
minimum USD. But minimum USD is
in terms of USD and value is in
terms of Aetherium. So how do we
convert Aetherium to USD, this
is where Oracle's and chainlink
are going to come into play. The
USD value of Aetherium is
something that we've assigned
outside of the blockchain to
Aetherium, or any other layer
one currency or any other native
smart contract platform
currency. So in order to get
this value that is outside the
blockchain, we have to use a
decentralized Oracle network to
get the price of one ether in
terms of USD. So before we can
continue on here, let's learn a
little bit more about the
architecture of these
decentralized Oracle networks
and the different solutions that
they have. So that we can create
this Funmi contract in the most
advanced way possible, as we've
talked about blockchains are
deterministic systems, which
means that they themselves can't
actually interact with real
world data and events. They
don't know what the value of an
Aetherium is, they don't know
what random numbers are. They
don't know if it's sunny
outside, they don't know the
temperature, they don't know
who's president, they don't know
any of this information. These
blockchains also can't do any
external computation. Maybe you
have some amazing artificial
intelligence model that you want
to integrate with a smart
contract. smart contracts by
themselves can't do anything
with that. As we've mentioned,
this is because blockchains are
deterministic by design. This is
so that all the nodes can reach
consensus. If you start adding
variable data or random data, or
values that returned from an API
call, different nodes could get
different results, and they
would never be able to reach a
consensus. This is known as the
smart contract connectivity
problem, or the Oracle problem.
And this is bad news, because we
want our smart contracts to be
able to replace traditional
agreements. And traditional
agreements need data and they
need to interact with the real
world. So this is where
chainlink and blockchain,
Oracle's come into place. A
blockchain Oracle is going to be
any device that interacts with
the often world to provide
external data or computation to
smart contracts. However, the
whole story doesn't even in
there. If we use a centralized
Oracle, we are reintroducing a
point of failure. We've done all
this work to make our logic
layer decentralized. But if we
get our data through a
centralized node or through a
centralized API, we decide we
want to make the API call
ourselves. We are reintroducing
these trust assumptions that
we've worked so hard to get rid
of, we're essentially ruining
the entire purpose of building a
smart contract. So we don't want
to get our data or do external
computation through centralized
nodes. Those are bad news. chain
link is the solution here. chain
link is a decentralized Oracle
network for bringing data and
external computation into our
smart contracts. As we mentioned
before, this gives rise to these
hybrid smart contracts, which
combined on chain and off chain
to make incredibly feature rich,
powerful applications. chain
link is a modular, decentralized
Oracle network that can be
customized to deliver any data
or do any external computation
that you like. So for example, a
lot of people say, Oh, I can
just make an HTTPS call to some
API, and we'll be good to go.
The blockchain nodes can't make
these HTTPS calls, because they
wouldn't be able to reach
consensus. If they called the
node at different times, or they
did something else. All the
consensus would be broken. So
instead, we need a decentralized
network of chain link Oracle's
to do this, and then in the
transaction, this network of
nodes will work Turn the data to
our smart contracts for us. Now
chainlink networks can be
completely customized to bring
any data or any external
computation that you want.
However, doing the customization
can be a little bit extra work,
there are a ton of chainlink
features that come out of the
box completely decentralized,
ready to plug and play into your
smart contract applications.
What are those features, the
first one is going to be
channeling data feeds, and
that's the one we're actually
going to be using for
application here. Channeling
data feeds currently at the time
of recording are powering over
$50 billion. In the defy world,
the way they work is a network
of chain link nodes gets data
from different exchanges and
data providers and brings that
data through a network of
decentralized chain like notes,
the chain link nodes use a
median to figure out what the
actual price of the asset is,
and then deliver that in a
single transaction to what's
called a reference contract, a
price feed contract or a data
contract on chain that other
smart contracts can use. And
then those smart contracts use
that pricing information to
power their defy application, we
can see an example. We can see
an example at data dot chain dot
link. And you can change
networks, you can change price
feeds, you can change a whole
bunch of different information
to see some of those popular
price feeds. Let's look at eath
USD for example. On eath USD, we
can see this whole network of
independent chain link node
operators that are each getting
different answers for the price
of eth USD, they're getting
aggregated by the network and
then delivered on chain, we can
see how often they're updated.
These ones are updated 4.5
deviation threshold or a few
hour heartbeat, whichever one
hits. First, we can see when the
last update was we can see the
number of Oracle responses etc,
we can see the contract address
directly on chain, we can even
look at the contract on ether
scan, we can see some of the
history, we can see all the
responses of the different
Oracle's. And then at the
bottom, we can see the different
users and sponsors, keeping this
network up. Similar to
transaction gas, whenever a node
operator delivers data to a
smart contract, the chain link
node operators are paid a little
bit of Oracle gas in the chain
link token. Right now these
users of the protocol are
sponsoring keeping these feeds
up and are paying the Oracle gas
associated with delivering this
data on chain. Here's an
illustration of what the current
model of these data feeds look
like a network of these chain
link nodes, each reaches out and
gets the information about an
asset and then signs the data
with their own private key in a
single transaction, then, one
node will deliver all the data
with all the different
signatures to a reference
contract. If that node doesn't
deliver the data, another node
will send it instead. Reputation
is incredibly important when
your chain link node operator if
you miss data updates, if you
forget to send transactions,
you'll probably be quickly
kicked off these networks and
have no chance of making any
more money in the future. These
data feeds are used by some of
the largest protocols in the
space, such as synthetics, sushi
swap compound, and Avi, with
several billion dollars each, we
can take a look at an example
over at Doc's dot chain dot link
work with EVM contracts, we're
going to hit EVM chains, scroll
down to data feeds. We'll scroll
down to the solidity section.
And we can see an example of an
entire contract that uses and
reads from one of these trending
price feeds. We can even open
this up and remix and work with
it and remix. It looks like this
example is reading from a price
feed on COVID. The reason we're
actually going to use a test net
to see this work is that there's
a set of chain link nodes
monitoring the test network.
Just to show you exactly how
this works out. Once we get
deeper into the course, we'll
show you how to actually run
tests and work with chain link
nodes without actually being on
a test net, which will make your
development much faster. But I
highly recommend walking through
this section along with me so
that you can see firsthand how
this actually works. So let's go
ahead and faucets dot chain dot
link slash COVID. We're going to
switch to the COVID network,
we're going to get some COVID
eath. But remember, look at the
network flag and use whatever
network is in the documentation.
So to get some COVID, we're
going to come to the faucet,
we're going to turn off test
link, we'll just stay with eath
I'm not a robot,
and then send request. Once our
COVID Aetherium has reached our
wallet, we can go ahead and
close we can take a look in our
wallet and see that we do indeed
have 0.1 eath on Kelvin. Now
let's go back to our remix,
we'll compile this contract, go
and deploy this on injected web
three. And again, the reason