we're going to use injected web
three instead of JavaScript VM
is that there's no network of
chain link nodes watching our
little fake JavaScript VM. There
are a network of chain link
nodes watching the test net. So
we'll scroll down. We'll switch
contract to the price consumer V
three, and we'll hit Deploy and
a mass will pop up and after a
brief delay, we can see our
price feed consumer down here
and we can hit Get the latest
price which shows us the latest
price of Aetherium in terms of
USD you may be wondering why the
number looks so weird. That
seems like a really large number
for the price of Aetherium in
terms of USD, and this is
because decimals don't actually
work so well in solidity, and
we'll get to that in a little
bit. There's a decimals flag
associated with this price feed
address, that tells us how many
decimals to include with this
price. It's also in the
documentation. However, I know
that this one has eight
decimals. So this is saying the
value of Aetherium right now is
$3,262. It may of course be
different when you go ahead and
try this. Now there's a number
of things that happened in this
contract that I'll explain in
our Funmi example. But if you
want to take a look now and see
if you can figure out what's
going on, I recommend you do so.
Price feeds are one of the most
powerful out of the box
decentralized features, you can
use your smart contract to level
them up, especially for
decentralized finance. If you're
looking for different addresses
of different price feeds, you
can check the contract addresses
section of the documentation,
choose the network that you
want, and then scroll down and
look some of the different
addresses of the different price
feeds. For example, this address
will give you the price of one
inch token in terms of
Aetherium. This address will
give you the price of the Apple
stock in terms of USD, and so on
and so forth. The next
decentralized application right
out of the box is going to be
channeling VRF or channeling
verifiable random dysfunction.
Once we do our lottery example a
little bit later, we'll talk
about how randomness can be
manipulated in blockchain.
blockchains are deterministic
systems, which by definition
means that they can't have
randomness. If you can determine
what a random number is, it's
not really random anymore, is
it? So we need to wait to get a
provably random number by
looking outside of the
blockchain and Oracle's are
perfectly positioned to do
exactly that. chainlink
verifiable randomness function
is a way to get provably a
random number into our smart
contract to guarantee fairness
and guarantee randomness of
applications. Many protocols
like pool together x infinity,
ether cards, avocado cheese and
more use channeling VRF for
lotteries, randomizing NF T's
for gaming and for more, we're
going to do an example of
channeling VRF in a later
section. Once we get to the
lottery section, if you want to
see if you can play with the
randomness yourself right now, I
recommend you go into Doc's
chain link EVM chains, and
scroll down to get a random
number. And this will teach you
how to get a provably random
number into your applications.
The next decentralized out of
the box feature of chain link is
chain like keepers, which is
decentralized event driven
execution. As we've seen, in
order to kick off some type of
transaction, somebody needs to
spend the gas and somebody needs
to sit down and hit the go
button or hit the transact
button or hit the sun. But this
is obviously a centralized
vector. If you have a
decentralized application that
needs to run at specific times,
or after specific events are
triggered. Channeling keepers
are the solution to this
channeling keepers are chain
link nodes that listen to a
registration contract for
different events that you
specify to fire. Maybe you say
every 10 minutes, you want to do
something or once a week do
something or if the price of
some acid hits some number, or
maybe a liquidity pool is at a
certain level, whatever event
that you want to code, you
absolutely can the chain link
nodes constantly listen for
these triggers to happen and
check the different contracts
for these triggers. Once a
trigger returns true, the chain
link nodes will then perform
whatever action that you tell
the chain link nodes to do,
we're also not going to go over
the chain link keepers examples
right now, because we're going
to get to them in a later
module. However, if you want to
try them out, go to Doc's
touching that link slash
Aetherium. Going and go to
making compatible contracts and
feel free to read the
documentation. Try it out
yourself. The last out of the
box feature of chain link is the
most customizable, but also the
hardest to get correct end to
end reliability is the ultimate
promise of our smart contracts.
And we want and need them to be
able to do anything, we want to
be able to take any input and
get any output making HTTP GET
HTTP POST request is an easy way
to customize our chain link
nodes to be able to do anything.
Remember how we talked about
making API calls that blockchain
nodes themselves can do that?
Well, chain link nodes can do
that chain link nodes can make
direct requests to any API that
you specify. In order to do
this, you both have to choose
the chain link node and the URL
slash data to send the request
to this is a little bit trickier
than chain link VRF keepers or
price feeds because you then
have to be responsible for
creating the chain link network
that gets data from many
different chain link nodes and
many different data providers.
But let's look at an example in
remix anyways. For this section,
feel free to just watch it since
we are working with a test net
here. And test nets, as we've
seen, can take a little bit of
time. As long as you're familiar
with what this process looks
like. That's good enough. You
don't actually have to try it if
you don't want to. So we'll open
up and remix will read through.
It looks like this example is on
the COVID network. So we'll go
ahead and compile API consumer.
We're gonna go ahead and deploy
on the injected web three, we're
going to make sure that we're
back on the COVID test network.
We're going to scroll down. And
we're going to change the
contract to the API consumer.
And we're going to go ahead and
hit Deploy, we're going to
deploy this contract to the
COVID. Test net. And now we can
call this function called
Request volume data to actually
make an API call. Now, like I
mentioned before, whenever we
request data from a chain link
node, we have to pay a little
bit of Oracle gas, or link
token, in order to pay some link
token, we're going to need to
have link token in our API
consumer contract. This is
what's known as the basic
request and receive model to get
link token, we go back to our
faucet, and this time, we'll
select 10 test link for our
contract. Let's go ahead and
verify that we're human. And
we'll hit Send Request. This
time, instead of sending us
Aetherium. They're sending us 10
test link, which is what's known
as an ERC 20 token. Or more
accurately, in ERC 677 We'll get
to understanding that a little
bit later, we can see the asset
in our Metamask. By importing
the token, in order to get the
token, we're going to come back
to the documentation. And we're
going to look up link token
contracts like that, we're going
to go to the network that we
just got the tokens on, which
for us was COVID. We're going to
copy this address, we're gonna
go to Metamask, hit import
tokens, paste that address, and
hit add custom token, and then
import tokens. And now we can
see in our account one, we both
have Aetherium and 10. Link, now
that we have our link or Oracle
gas, we're going to send it to
our API consumer, we're going to
copy the address of the API
consumer, open up our meta mask,
we're gonna hit send, paste the
address of our contract, switch
the asset to link. For now we'll
just send 0.2 link. We'll hit
next, next. And we'll hit
Confirm. And we'll wait for this
transaction to go through. I
chose 0.2 Link, because in this
contract, there's a fee
character, which tells us how
much making an API call for this
is going to cost. This one is
actually 0.1 link, I send 0.2.
Just in case, we want to make
that API call twice. Everything
that's going on in this function
will explain in a little bit
later section. But for now, I
just want to show you what it
looks like to do is, once we
send the link to our contract,
we can first check to see what
the volume is volume is zero, we
want to get the volume of the
last 24 hours of Aetherium
asset, we're going to be calling
this API which has a ton of raw
data, including one in specific
called volume over the last 24
hours, which can be this number
right here. Say we wanted to get
this into our contract from this
API, we're going to make an HTTP
GET call to this API. And what's
going to happen is we're going
to make the request in one
transaction. And in a second
transaction, the chain link node
is gonna return the value and
store it in this volume variable
in the global scope. So let's go
ahead and hit request volume
data Metamask gonna pop up,
we're going to go ahead and hit
Confirm. And you'll notice right
away volume doesn't update. This
is again, because we actually
need to wait two transactions,
we're sending a transaction for
the request. And then in a
second transaction, the chain
link node is actually going to
respond. And after a slight
delay, the chain link node has
indeed responded with the result
of making that API call back to
our contract. We'll go over this
process a little bit more in
depth in later sections. The
reason that I wanted to show you
specifically the API calls, is
because we're going to show you
a real life example of how to
use chain link VRF and chain the
keepers in a later lesson.
Now I know we've already gone
over a ton. So let's do a quick
review. In order to send
Aetherium or whatever native
blockchain token with a function
need to mark it as payable. If
you need something in your
contract to happen, and you want
the whole transaction to fail.
If that doesn't happen, you can
use a require statement. To get
the Aetherium or native
blockchain token value of a
transaction, you can use the
global keyword message dot
value. chain link is a
technology for getting external
data and doing external
computation in a decentralized
context for our smart contracts.
Channeling data feeds or price
feeds are ways to read pricing
information or other pieces of
data from the real world that's
already aggregated and
decentralized for us, channeling
VRF is a way to get provably
random numbers from the real
world into our smart contracts.
Channeling keepers are a way to
do decentralized event driven
computation. We can set some
trigger say if this trigger hits
do something and we get to
define what the trigger is and
what to do something is
channeling any API's is the
ultimate customization of
channeling nodes and allows us
to connect to anything on the
planet. To make this one
production ready. We have to do
the most work because it doesn't
come already with a
decentralized Oracle network,
like chaining the keepers and
price feeds. We'll learn more
about these channeling services
as we continue in this course.
Now in order for us to figure
out if our message dot value is
actually greater than the
minimum USD that we set, we
actually have to convert our
message dot value from its layer
one slash Aetherium to the USD
equivalent. So how are we
actually going to do that? Well,
first, we're gonna need to get
the price of Aetherium, or
Phantom, or Avalanche or
whatever layer, one blockchain
that we're working with. So
let's create a function to get
that price to get that
conversion rate. So we'll do
function, get price, and this is
going to be the function that we
use to get the price of the room
in terms of USD, so we can
convert our message dot value to
USD. And then we're also going
to do a function called Get
conversion rate. These are both
going to be public functions, so
that we can go ahead and call
them and test them and do
whatever we want with them. So
in order to get the price, we're
going to have to use one of
these chain link data feeds to
get the pricing information. And
we can look right here at this
contract to see what using one
of these channeling price feeds
looks like. What we're actually
doing when we're interacting
with this channeling price feed
is we're actually reading from
one of these contracts, there's
a contract out there called the
aggregator contract that has a
function called latest round
data, which returns a whole
bunch of data. But namely, this
int price. And this in price is
what we are interested in. Let's
look at our get price function
and figure out how do we
actually call this since this is
an instance of us interacting
with a contract outside of our
project, we're going to need two
things. What are those two
things,
we're going to need the ABI of
the contract, and also the
address of the contract. So the
address of the contract is going
to be easy, we can get the
address of the contract from the
contract address this section of
the chain link data feeds. Let's
scroll on down to bank B. And we
can find the eath USD address on
Rigby and we'll create this
contract so that it works on
Rinkeby. So we're going to grab
this address, we're going to
copy it. And we're going to move
back to our to our code here.
And we're going to paste the
address here. So great, we have
the address. Now we have the
address of the other contract
that we don't want to interact.
Now, how do we get the ABI?
Well, what we did before was
simple storage was we imported
the entire contract into our
code here. That's something that
we could do. But that's actually
a lot of code. So what's
something that we could do
instead, remember, if we're
looking at remix, and we look at
one of the contracts that we
compiled before, the ABI is
really just kind of this list of
the different functions and
interactions you can have with a
contract. The ABI itself doesn't
actually need to include any of
the logic, it just needs to
include, hey, here are the
different functions that you can
call, for example, in this
contract, we can call fund, we
have get conversion rate, we
have get price, they're not
implemented yet, but they will
be eventually now there
technically is another way to
interact with contracts without
the API. But for now, we're just
going to ignore that. So how can
we get the API, there's a
concept in solidity called an
interface. And let's look at an
example of an interface. If we
go to github.com/smart, contract
kits, chainlink, we can see a
number of different contracts in
the chainlink repository, we can
go to contracts, src, V 0.8,
interfaces, and we'll go to
aggregator v3 interface, dot
soul. And if we look at the
solidity in here, we can see a
whole bunch of function
declarations, but none of the
logic is actually implemented in
this. This is what's known as an
interface. If we compile this,
we'll actually get the ABI of a
contract, because it defines all
the different ways we can
interact with the contract. It
doesn't actually say, what these
functions do, which is fine,
though, because we don't need to
know what the functions actually
do, those are going to be stored
in the contract. So what we can
do is we can grab this interface
from the code and paste it into
our remix. Now hold on, if
you're following along, you
don't have to copy paste this
with me, because I'm going to
show you an easier way in just a
second. So for now, feel free to
go ahead and just watch. But
once we have this interface
aggregator v3 interface, we can
now use this to make API calls.
So now we could say, aggregator
v3 interface at this address.
And the combination of these
two, give us that aggregator v3
contract with whatever code is
here. If at this contract
address is aggregator v3
interfaces valid, we can do
something like dot version.
Let's look at this interface. Is
there a version function? There
sure is. So that means we can
call the version function on
this contract. So let's actually
go ahead and copy this into a
different section. I'm going to
create a new function called Get
version just to illustrate this.
I'm going to be public. It's
going to be a view and it's
going to return the UN 256 and
We're gonna split it up into two
steps here. We're gonna say
aggregate tour, v3 interface,
price feed. So we're creating a
variable of type aggregator v3
interface equals aggregator v3
interface at this address. And
then we're going to return price
feed that version. Now I'm going
to go ahead and deploy this
contract to Rigby just to show
you what this git version is
going to return. But you don't
have to follow along here if you
don't want because again, we're
working with the test net, you
can just watch if you'd like for
this section, we're going to
test a little bit more sparse.
Since we're going to be mainly
using the test net, since we're
going to be working with an
actual chain link Oracle
network, once you move over to
hard hat, and with JavaScript,
all this testing locally will be
a lot easier and a lot faster,
you're more than welcome to go
ahead and fiddle and try and
test a lot of this stuff as we
go along. But just know that it
might take a little bit longer
to do some of the testing on the
test net,
let's delete that last funding
contract, we're going to deploy
this one, we're going to scroll
up, we're going to switch to
injected web three, we're going
to switch from COVID to rink B.
And the reason we want to make
sure we're on rink beam is
because this address is specific
to rink B, the contract that
we're looking to interact with
might not be at this address on
every single chain, we want to
make sure we're on the rink B
chain for this, because of some
other contract is there on the
different chain, this version
function obviously won't exist,
and this function could error.
So let's go ahead, we're gonna
find me, we're going to deploy
this to the rink V chain. Again,
you don't have to follow along
with me here, you can just
watch. And once that contract
has been deployed, we now have a
view function called Get
version. And we can see it's
returning the variable for
showing us that this is the
fourth version of a price feed.
So this is a really easy way for
us to interact with contracts
that exist. Outside of our
project, we use one of these
interfaces, which can get
compiled down to the API, and
then combine that ABI with the
address to call a function. As
we work with these interfaces
more and more, they'll start to
make more and more sense. So if
it's a little confusing to you
right now, don't get
discouraged, the more you work
with it, the easier it will
become. Now, though, now that we
know how to call these functions
in here, we can start working
with this interface. However, as
you know, if we have a whole
bunch of interfaces, we're gonna
have to stick a whole bunch of
interfaces at the top of our
code, which looks pretty ugly.
What's a better way for us to do
this? Well, before we used
import, right, we imported from
simple storage. That's all for
this one, what we could do is we
could import from an array gay
Tore v3 interface. That's all,
we can go ahead and create a new
contract with this aggregator v3
interface. Or what we can do is
we can import this directly from
GitHub. If we go back to the
documentation of these chainlink
data feeds go to using data
feeds, we scroll down, we see at
the top, we have this import
statement, import at chain link
slash contracts slash SFC visa
right interfaces aggregator v3
interface, this, this import is
has the same path setup as the
GitHub repository for the chain
link code, instead of us
directly adding all the code
right into our remix, what we
can do instead is we can import
directly from GitHub, or what's
called an NPM package. Remix is
smart enough to know that at
chain link slash contracts, is
referring to the NPM package at
chain link slash contracts,
we'll talk about NPM, a little
bit in the future, it's what's
known as a package manager, and
can keep versions of different
contracts for us to directly
import into our code bases at
chain link slash contracts is
created directly from the
chainlink GitHub repository. So
remix downloads this code from
NPM, which is created from this
GitHub. So now we know that if
we import at chain link slash
contracts, src, V 0.8 interfaces
aggregator v3 interface dot
soul, this is the same as if we
had just stuck this whole
contract right at the top of our
funding contract, which makes
our code look a lot nicer. And
now we have this aggregator v3
interface that we can work with.
Okay, great. So now that we have
a minimalistic interface, which
will give us the API, how do we
actually go ahead and get the
price here? Well, documentation
has a good example, if you want
to play with it and try to
reverse engineer it as well.
Here's how we're going to do it.
In our code. We're going to
create an aggregator v3
interface object called price
feed an aggregator v3 variable
called price feed, which is
going to equal to aggregator v3
interface contract at address
this address exactly the same as
what we're doing down here.
We're assuming a contract at
this address is going to have
all the functionality of this
aggregator v3 interface, which
again, means it has this
decimals function, this
description function version,
get round data. And the
important one latest round data,
which has the latest price at
this answer piece, what we can
do now is we can call that
latest round data function on
the price feed. So we'll say
price feed dot latest round
data. Now if we look at the
interface, we see that this
latest round data actually
doesn't return one variable, it
returns a whole bunch of
different variables. And that's
what we're going to return in
our contract. So we're going to
put these parentheses, and we're
going to say, you went at round
ID, we can even look right at
the documentation to see what
else it returns int price, you
went,
you went started out, you went
timestamp. And then you went ad,
answered and round. Now there's
a lot of code here. Since this
function returns so many
different variables, we have to
set something up to capture
them. However, all we care about
is price. We don't care about
round Id started at timestamp or
answered in round. So what we
can do is just remove them and
just leave the commas.
Now we have int price equals
price feed that latest round
data. The reason that price is
an int 256. And not a un 256 is
because some prices or some data
feeds could be negative here, so
that it's an int 256. So it can
stay flexible. Now that we have
the price, this is going to be
price of eath in terms of USD.
And we saw an example of this
before, it was around 3000. And
it returned this number because
solidity doesn't work with
decimals for a number of
reasons. But we just need to
know that there are eight
decimal places associated with
this price feed. If you want to
double check how many decimals
there are, this contract has a
decimal function that you can
call as well, that will tell you
exactly how many decimals are in
this price feed. Now as we know,
message dot value is going to
have 18 decimal places. Why does
it have 18 decimal places? Well,
because one ether is equal to
1-234-567-8910 12345678 Is this
massive number in way which has
18 zeros, which is equivalent to
1.12345 678-910-1234 5678. So we
want these to have the same
decimal places, right? Because
right now this has eight, this
is 18. They're different units
right now. So to get them to
match up, all we need to do is
return price times one, ie 10,
or one raised to the 10th, which
is equal to 1123456789 10.
Message dot value, though, is
going to be a UNT 256. And right
now, price is an interval at
six. So why did we convert this
value from n into 56. To a human
to 56? Well, we can do what's
called typecasting, all we need
to do is add you into 56. And
wrap this whole thing up between
these two parentheses, you can't
typecast anything. But there are
some values like into 56 and you
into 56, that can be easily
converted between the two. Now
of course, since we're not
modifying any state with this
get price function, we can make
this view and say it returns
that you went to 36. And if we
save and compile, we go ahead
and we get that checkmark. Now
math can be a little bit tricky.
The first couple times you do it
in solidity. But the more you do
it, the easier it becomes. And
in the future, we can always
reference a function like this
to figure out okay, here's the
easiest way for me to get this
number. Awesome. So now we have
a get price function, which is
going to return a un 256, which
is going to be the price of
Aetherium. In terms of USD, all
we need to do is convert the
message dot value from
Aetherium. To terms of dollars,
let's create this get conversion
rate function. So this one,
we're going to take an input
parameter of un 256 of eath
amount, it's going to be a
public view function. And it's
going to return you went to 56,
we're going to pass it some eath
amount. And on the other side,
we're going to get how much that
eath is worth in terms of USD.
So we're going to do a u
intuity. Six eath price equals
get price. So first, we're going
to call our get price function
that we just created to get the
price of Aetherium. Then we're
going to do u and 256 eath
amount in USD equals eath price
times eath amount, and then
we're going to divide it by 118.
When you're doing multiplication
and division math in solidity,
you always want to multiply and
add first and then go ahead and
divide since eath price and eath
amount both have 18 additional
decimal places if we were to
just let them rock without this,
they would have an additional 36
zeros tax tacked onto the end.
So we need to divide by one EA
team. Now when we get to the
hard hat sections of this course
testing all this math is going
to be a lot easier. And if
you're really struggling with
some of the math bits right now,
I wouldn't let that slow you
down. Because once we get to
heart, it's going to become a
lot easier to actually test this
than working on a test net. And
this eath amount in terms of USD
is the number that we're looking
for. So we can just go ahead and
return eath amount in USD, CSB
returns here, and boom, now we
have a good conversion rate
function to walk you through the
math real quick. Let's say the
eath price is going to be
$3,000. So it's going to be
3000. But it's going to have an
additional 18 zeros tacked on
the end, it matches the message
dot value way units. And let's
say for example, we send one
eath or 112345 678-910-1234 5678
eath into this contract, one
eath should equal $3,000. So to
get the price, we're going to
now do the eath price, which is
3000 times the eath amount,
which is this one, and then
divide by one raised to the
18th. So method out we'll do
3123 1-234-567-8910 12345678
times we'd
1001 2345678 1-234-567-8910
times 112345678 1-234-567-8910.
And now we divide that by
112345678 1-234-567-8910, which
equals 2.9. Mmm, II 21, which
the calculator kind of messed up
them a little bit, but 2.9, not
2.99, ie 21 means this has 21
decimal places. So it'd be
2.1 234-567-8910 1-234-567-8910
one, or
1-234-567-8910 12345678 2900 I
9.99 and a nine. And this is
actually exactly the reason why
we don't do decimal math in
solidity, our calculator saw
that massive number was having a
hard time getting it. So it
ended up rounding that number to
2.999. And nine, when we work
exclusively with whole numbers
in solidity, we don't have a
chance of losing that precision.
And in solidity, this is going
to return exactly $3,000, which
is correct one Aetherium at
$3,000 per Aetherium is going to
be $3,000. And like I said,
since we're building this
contract, assuming we're going
to be working on this test net,
we're not going to test this
function on the test net,
because we're going to have to
wait for that transaction to go
through. If you want to go ahead
and deploy this and play around
with it yourself, you're more
than welcome to Okay, great, now
we have a function called Get
conversion rate that we can use
on our fund function to make
sure we've sent enough message
dot value in our fund. So what
we can do now is all we need to
do is to get conversion rate of
message dot value needs to be
greater than the minimum USD. Of
course, right now our minimum
USD is just in terms of 50. And
we know that conversion rate is
going to return it with 18 zeros
to represent the decimal places,
our minimum USD amount needs to
be upgraded to 10 to 50 times
one e 18. Or again, one times
10, raise the 18th, I'm going to
deploy this to a test net just
to demonstrate it. But again,
you don't have to if you don't
want to wait for this. So I'm
gonna go ahead and deploy this
confirm. And now we have this
funny contract. If I don't say
anything in value, and hit the
fun button, we're gonna get this
gas estimation error failed.
This is kind of a blanket error,
basically saying, Hey, you can
go ahead and send this
transaction if you want, it's
highly likely that it's not
going to work. And the reason
that remix knows that it's
probably not going to work is
because it can see this require
and simulate the transaction and
say, Hey, you didn't send enough
money with this. However, even
if we send some money, like 5000
way, it'll still give us this
error. Because that's not
enough. Let's do the calculation
right now based on what the
price of eath is. So we can
actually go to data dot chain
that link, we look and see
approximately what the price is.
So it looks like the price of
Aetherium right now is about
$3,000. And this might be
different for you depending on
when you do that. So if the
price of Aetherium is $3,000,
and our minimum is at least 50.
We could do 50 divided by
3000 0.016 eath should be
approximately enough. So if we
go to our Aetherium converter,
and we do 0.016, we'll get how
much that is in way, let's do
0.02 Just to make sure that
we're going to be over the
amount. So we'll paste that in.
We'll change this to way. And
now if I hit the fun button,
instead of us getting that error
popping up, it's going to
actually go ahead and let us do
the fun function and we could
confirm it and it wouldn't fail.
I'm going to reject it for now
just because I don't really feel
like waiting for the transaction
to go through. But great. We've
confirmed that our get
conversion rate is one working
as intended, awesome, great
work.
So what's the next bit of this
funding contract that we want to
do? Well, when people actually
send money to this contract, we
want to keep track of all the
people who send us money. So
let's create some data
structures. To keep track. Let's
create an array of addresses
called funders. And we'll keep
adding all the funders who send
money to us. So we'll say an
address array, or an address
list. We'll make it public
funders. And anytime somebody
sends us money, and this
actually does indeed go through,
we'll add that funded server
list. So we'll say funders dot
push message dot sender, like
message dot value. Message dot
sender is an always available
global keyword message dot value
stands for how much Aetherium or
how much native blockchain
currency is sent. Message dot
sender is the address of whoever
calls the font function. So if
we're on Rigby message dot
sender is going to be equal to
whatever address is calling that
function. Since our address is
sending the ether, we're going
to add our address to this
funders list. This way we can
keep track of all the wonderful
donators who are donating to our
contract, then maybe we won't
even make a mapping of addresses
to you and 250 sixes of
addresses to how much money each
one of these people have
actually sent. So we'll do
address to you and 256 public
address to amount funded. And
when somebody funds our contract
will say address to amount
funded of message dot sender
equals message dot value. Now we
have a function where people can
fund our contract. And we can
set a value in terms of USD and
we keep track of the different
funders who actually fund our
contract. This is fantastic. Now
I know we've gone over a lot of
really intense math and intense
stuff here. So so let's do a
quick refresher of what we've
learned so far. Whenever we work
with a contract, we always need
the API and the address when
compiled an interface gives us
that minimalistic API to
interact with contracts outside
of our project. When you combine
these compiled interfaces with
an address, we can call the
functions on that interface on
that contract. chain link. data
feeds are a decentralized way to
get information about the real
world. In this case, we're
getting the price of Aetherium
in terms of USD from a
decentralized collective of
chain link nodes. When working
with math and solidity. Decimals
don't work. So we need to keep
that in mind when doing any type
of math in solidity. And we need
to make sure we always have the
correct units, so that our math
makes sense. Message dot value,
and message dot sender, our
globally available variables
were message dot sender
represents the sender of the
message or transaction. And
message dot value represents the
number of ways sent with the
message. There's a whole bunch
of different special variables
and functions that we can access
at any time. And these are
available in the solidity
documentation. Alright, great,
we've got a great way that we
can actually start funding our
contract. But our code looks a
little bit messy, we've got a
couple of different functions
for getting the price and
working with these prices, is
there a way to make this math a
lot easier to use, this is where
we're going to introduce the
concept of a library. So what is
a library, I definitely
recommend checking out solidity
by example.org, as you're going
along with this course, as well,
they've got some fantastic
examples. One of such example is
going to be about libraries,
libraries are similar to
contracts. But you can't declare
any state variables and you
can't send ether. We can also
use libraries to add more
functionality to different
values. What do I mean by that?
Well, what we can do actually is
we can have get conversion rate
be a function of a un 256. So we
could do something like Messer
dot value dot get convert John,
conversion rate. And we can add
functions as if you went to 36
was an object or a struct or a
contract that we actually
created. So how do we do this?
Well, let's create a new
contract in our contracts folder
and create a new file. We're
going to call it price
converter, dot salt. And our
price converted outsole is going
to be a library that we're going
to attach to a un 256. So how do
you actually create a library
and what is a library? Well, a
library is going to be really,
really similar to a smart
contract. It's gonna start with
spdx license identifier. My
team, we're gonna give it a
pragma, solidity zero point 8.0.
And instead of typing contract
for the name of the contract,
we're going to do library for
the name of the library. We're
going to call it price
converter. Now libraries can't
have any state variables and
they also can't send ether and
all the functions in a library
are going to be in there.
kernel. So what we can do is we
can go back to fund me dot soul,
we can grab get price, get
version and get conversion rate,
copy them all, delete them from
Funmi dot soul and paste them
into our library. And of course,
since we're using aggregator v3
interface in here, we can also
copy the import from Funmi. And
since we're not using the
aggregate of three interface and
our contract anymore, and we're
using our price converter, we
can paste it into our price
converter. Now, if we compile
price converted at soul, we see
that it actually passes. Now all
the functions inside of our
library need to be internal. And
we're gonna make this library
price converter different
functions, we can call on you
activity six, for example, we're
going to be able to do message
dot value dot get conversion
rate, we're going to directly be
able to get the conversion rate
of a value of a U and 256 as if
that was a function for it the
whole time. So first, let's make
this internal. Let's make get
conversion rate internal. And
we'll make good version
internal. Now that we have this
library price converter back in
our Funmi, we can now import
this price converter and attach
it to you in 256. So we'll do
import that slash price
converter, dot soul.
And in Funmi, we'll do using
price converter for UNT 256. Of
course, if we compile our Funmi.
Now, this line is getting an
issue because saying hey, get
conversion rate isn't defined.
Now in our library, the first
variable that gets passed to the
function is going to be the
object that it's called on
itself. So in Funmi dot soul,
let's go ahead and comment out
this line for now. If we do
message dot value dot get
conversion rate, this is
secretly the same as we did get
conversion rate or message dot
value in our price converter
library, the message dot value
is going to be passed as the
input parameter to get
conversion rate, forget price
and get version we don't really
care about the number. So we're
just going to leave it blank for
now. So instead of require get
conversion rate of message dot
value, we can now do message dot
value dot get conversion rate.
And compile that you'll see that
here we're not passing a
variable, even though our get
conversion rate function says
hey, I'm expecting a variable.
Again, the reason for this is,
is this message add value is
considered the first parameter
for any of these library
functions. And that's how it
works. If we wanted another
variable in here, like you went
to 56, something else. Now we
would want to pass something
else in here 123. And this 123
would get assigned to this
something else. But we're going
to delete that for now. Okay,
great. And in doing that, we've
minimized our Funmi contract a
lot by moving a lot of that math
and price conversion stuff into
our price converter library dot
Sol. One of the most common
libraries that was used for the
longest time was this library
called Safe math dot Sol. And
you'll probably see it a lot of
different places, we're gonna go
off on a quick little tangent
here and teach you about safe
math. So let's close Funmi close
price converter. And let's
create a new file called Safe
math tester. That's all. And
let's start with some basic
stuff in here. Safe math was all
over the place before version
0.8 of solidity. And now it's
almost in no contracts. What
happened, why is safe math no
longer used as much? Well, let's
create a sample contract. This
is a section that you don't have
to follow along if you don't
want to code along with me. But
if you want to you absolutely
still can. This is going to be a
contract we are going to deploy
on a JavaScript virtual machine,
we can use any version of
solidity before version 0.8 of
solidity. So for example, we use
pragma, carrot, zero, point 6.0.
And we'll create contract safe
math tester, dot Sol. Now if I
create a you int eight, I set it
to public big number. And I set
this to 255 Oops safe math
tester. Let's go ahead and
compile safe math tester with
zero point 6.7 pragma, solidity,
the maximum size of a Yewande
eight is going to be 255. This
is going to be the biggest
number that we can fit in the
new int eight. And if I were to
deploy this to a JavaScript VM
or even a test network, safe
math tester, let's go ahead to
play up. If I hit big number,
we're gonna get 255. Well, what
happens if I create a function
called ADD? That sets big number
equal to big number plus one?
Let's save that. Delete that old
contract and deploy. All right
now big numbers 255 What happens
when we add one two? big number.
When 255 is the max size a, UNT
eight can be? Well, let's hit
add. Now let's check what big
number is. Big number gets reset
to zero. So what's going on?
Well, prior to version 0.8, of
solidity, unsigned integers and
integers ran on this concept of
being unchecked, which means
that if you passed the upper
limit of a number, it would just
wrap around and start back from
the lowest number it could be.
So if I call add a whole bunch
more times, and hit big number,
now let's say if I were to hit
this add button a ton more times
and get it back to two and a 55.
It would then continue to wrap
over to zero. So one of the most
popular libraries that was out
there was this safe math
library, which would basically
check to make sure that you
weren't wrapping around a un 256
or an intuitive six, basically,
it was a way to say, hey, you've
reached the max this number can
be and now your transaction is
going to fail. If we switch this
to 0.8, of solidity, delete the
old contract, go switch this to
0.8. We'll go ahead and compile
it. And now we deploy this to
JavaScript VM.
If I hit big number, we get to
under 55. But if we hit Add, it
actually fails. And we still get
to under 55. In version 0.8, in
solidity, they added this bit,
where it automatically checks to
make sure if you're going to do
what's called overflow or
underflow on a variable, we can
actually revert back to the
unchecked version by using an
unchecked keyword. So if we wrap
this big number equals big
number plus one in this
unchecked bracket, let's delete
our old contract will compile
will redeploy. We had big
numbers to 55. Now we hit add,
we hit big number again, it
reverted back to zero. So that's
a little bit more about safe
math, checked and unchecked. So
in version 0.76, and below this
code that you see in front of
you, is going to be the exact
same as this code in 0.8. And
above with this unchecked
keyword. Now you might be
thinking in newer versions of
solidity, why would I use this
unchecked keyword? Well, you'll
find out later that this
unchecked keyword makes your
code a little bit more gas
efficient. So if you're
absolutely positive that your
math is never going to reach the
top or bottom limits of a
number, that it might make sense
for you to use the unchecked
keyword. Let's head back over to
our Funmi contract, where we are
now using the price converter
library that we just created.
Alright, great. So now we've got
a pretty minimalistic contract
here for actually doing the
funding. And we have all of our
math for getting conversion
rates done in our library price
converter, which we're going to
import at the top of Funmi.
Cool. So at this point, we've
got our fun method. Awesome. And
so we can allow anybody to go
ahead and fund this contract and
send this contract Aetherium, or
any native blockchain currency
to this contract. Well, now what
do we want to do? Well, once all
the funders have gone ahead and
funded, we're going to want the
project to be able to withdraw
the funds out of this contract.
So they can actually go ahead
and use those funds to buy
things for this project. So
let's go ahead and create a
withdrawal function. So we'll
create a function withdraw. And
we'll make this public. Since
we're going to be withdrawing
all the funds out of this
contract, we probably also want
to reset our funders array, and
our address to amount funded.
Since we'll be withdrawing all
the funds, those amounts should
go back down to zero. So let's
go ahead and loop through the
funders array and update our
mapping object so that each of
these funders now has zero,
because in just a second, we're
going to withdraw all the money
from them. So to do this, we're
going to use something called a
for loop. So what is a for loop?
A for loop is a way to loop
through some type of index
object or loop through some
range of numbers or just do a
task a certain amount of times
repeating. So for example, let's
say we have an array or list.
And on that list, we have 1234.
If we wanted to get all of the
elements in this array, or in
this list, okay, 1234. How do we
get all the elements in this
list? Well, we would use a for
loop to loop through each one of
these objects. So at zero with
index would be one at the first
index would be two, and at the
second index would be three, at
the last index would be four. So
we would loop through the
indexes zero through three to
get all these elements. Or maybe
another example is if this was
A, B, C, D, A is at the zero
with index B is at the first
index sees the second Indy's at
the third and we will loop zero
through three. To get to each
one of these elements, we're
gonna do that exact same thing.
But with the funders array. So
how do we actually do that?
Well, we first start with the
for keyword, the for keyword
says, Okay, we're about to start
a loop. And inside of these
parentheses, we define how we
want to loop through it. Also
backslash star, and star
backslash is sort of like
brackets for comments. Anything
in between these two will be a
comment. So in a for loop,
first, we give it the starting
index, then we give it the
ending index, and then we give
it the step amount. For example,
maybe we want to start with
zero, we want to go to 10. And
we want to go up by one each
time. So we would go
01 234-567-8910. Or maybe we
start at zero, we want to end at
10. And we go up by two each
time. So we'd go 02468 10. Or
maybe we want to go from zero to
five, we want to go from two to
five, with a step of one, we'd
go 2345, etc. So this is what's
going to go inside of this four
bit here. So for our starting
index, and let me even just put
this above so that you can
reference it. So our starting
index is going to be you in to
VT six variable, and we're going
to call it funder index. And
we're going to start with
thunder index being equal to
zero. So we're starting with
zero here. And we're going to
end with the length of our
funders array, since we want to
loop through all of the funders.
So we're going to say, funder
index needs to be less than
funders dot length. So our
ending index is going to be
whenever funders index is no
longer less than funders dot
length. And then finally, we're
gonna say funder index equals
funder index, plus one, which
means that every time the code
inside of this loop finishes,
we're going to increase funder
index by one. That's how we go
from zero to one to two to three
to four to five, etc. Another
way you can type funder index
equals funder index plus one is
you can just do funder index
plus plus, this plus plus syntax
means funder index equals itself
plus one. So let's start looping
through our funders array to
access the the zero with element
or the first element, we're
going to say, funders of funder
index. So we're saying we want
to access the zero with element
of our funders object. And this
is going to return an address
for us to use, we're gonna go
ahead and say address under
equals funders at the funder
index. So now we have this
funder address. And we want to
use this to reset our mapping.
So we're going to say, address
to amount funded at at the
funder key is now equal to zero.
Because remember, in fund we
update the amount. Whenever we
fund the contract, when we
withdraw the money from the
contract, we're going to reset
it back to zero. Now let's walk
through this funder index starts
from zero. So we're going to get
the zero with funder, we're
going to grab that funder at the
zero with index and we're going
to reset the address to male
funded of that funder to zero,
then this for loop is going to
update by one, it's going to
move from zero to one, it's
going to check then if funder
index is less than the length,
let's say funders has 10 people
in it. If funders has 10 people
in it, it'll still be less. So
now funder links will be one
address funder will equal
funders of one now instead of
zero, and we'll grab that
address, and we'll reset that
addresses about funded to zero,
then we'll continue to two to
three to four all the way up to
the length of our funders array.
And this is how we can loop
through our objects. So saying
this middle one is the ending
index isn't exactly right, since
we're really checking for a
boolean to see if this is still
true, but hopefully you get the
idea. So we've reset the
balances of the mapping.
However, we still haven't done
two things, we still need to
reset the array to make the
funders a blank array. And then
we also need to actually
withdraw the funds. Since when
we funded this, we sent message
dot value along with calling
this fund function. However, we
didn't actually withdraw the
funds. So to reset the array, we
could loop through it and delete
objects from this address array.
Or we could Just totally refresh
this variable. So instead of
looping through the array and
deleting objects, we're just
going to say funders equals a
new address array, we're going
to completely reset the array by
saying this font is variable now
equals a brand new address array
with zero objects in it to
start, if we were to put a one
here, this would be there'll be
one element to start in the
array, two would be two, three
would be three, etc, we're just
going to start it as a
completely blank new array. So
great, we've gone ahead and
reset the array. But how do we
actually now with draw funds
from this contract? How do we
send the funds back to whomever
is calling this now to actually
send ether or send native
blockchain currency, there are
actually three different ways to
do this, we're going to look at
all three, and say what the
differences between the three of
them are, the three different
ways are going to be transfer,
send, and call. Let's go ahead
and start with transfer. Since
transfer is the simplest and at
surface level makes the most
sense to us. So if we want to
transfer the funds to whomever
is calling this withdrawal
function, we would do we would
say message dot sender, dot
transfer. And then we'd get the
balance of our contract here by
saying address this, this
keyword refers to this whole
contract dot balance, and we can
get the native blockchain
currency or the Aetherium
currency balance of this address
like this. And we can just do
that only thing that we need to
do is we need to cast we need to
typecast message dot sender from
an address type to a payable
address type. So message dot
sender is of type address.
Whereas payable, message that
sender is of type, payable
address, and in solidity in
order to send the native
blockchain token like Aetherium,
you can only work with payable
addresses. To do that, we just
wrap it in this payable type
caster. So this is the first way
that we actually send Aetherium
or send tokens from different
contracts to each other, we wrap
the address that we want to send
it in, in this payable keyword,
we do dot transfer, and then we
say exactly how much we want to
transfer. But there are some
issues with transfer. Here we
are on solidity by example, for
sending ether, which, again is a
fantastic resource to refer to,
if you get lost, the method that
we just looked at was this
transfer method. Now we saw way
earlier in the course, that if I
sent Aetherium, from one address
to another, it cost about 2100
gas or 2100. Gas, our transfer
function is capped at 2300 gas.
And if more gas is used, it
throws an error. The next one
that we're using is going to be
sent which is also capped at
2300 gas. And if it fails, it'll
return a Boolean. So with
transfer, if this line fails,
it'll air and revert the
transaction with send, it won't
air, it'll return a boolean of
whether or not it was
successful. So using send will
do payable message that sender
that send address this balance.
But we don't want to finish our
call here. If this were to fail,
the contract wouldn't revert the
transaction, and we just want to
get our money sent. So we want
to do Boolean send success
equals this whole bit here. And
then we want to require success.
And if this send fails will
throw an error saying sin
failed.
This way, if this fails, we will
still revert by adding our
require statement here. Transfer
automatically reverts if the
transfer fails, send will only
revert the transaction if we add
this require statement here. So
great. What's the third way that
we can actually send Etherium or
native currency wallets with
this call command. Now call is
going to be one of the first
lower level commands that we
actually use in our solidity
code, because this call function
is actually incredibly powerful.
And we can use it to call
virtually any function in all of
Aetherium without even having to
Have the API we'll learn the
advanced ways to use this call
much later. For now, we're just
going to learn how to use it to
send Aetherium, or your native
blockchain currency call is
going to look very similar to
send, we're going to do payable,
message dot sender, dot call.
And this is where we will put
any function information or any
information about the function,
we want to call on some other
contract, we actually don't want
to call a function. So we're
going to leave this blank, we
can show that we're leaving it
blank by just putting in these
two quotes here, we instead want
to use this like a transaction.
And as we saw in our deployment,
there's always this message dot
value bid, we're going to use
this call function as if it's a
regular transaction, and we can
add stuff like message dot
value. So in here, we're going
to add these squiggly brackets.
And we're going to say, value
address this dot balance, this
call function returns actually
two variables. And when a
function returns two variables,
we can show that by placing them
into parentheses on the left
hand side, the two variables, it
returns are going to be a
Boolean, that we're going to
call call success. And also a
bytes object called data
returned, since call allows us
to actually call different
functions. If that function
returns some data or returns
value, we're going to save that
in the data returned variable.
It also returns call success,
where if the function was
successfully called this will be
true. If not, this will be
false. And since bytes objects
are arrays, data returns needs
to be in memory. Now for our
code here, we're actually not
calling a function, so we don't
really care about data returned.
So similar to what we saw with
the price contract, we can just
go ahead and delete that and
leave the comma to tell solidity
Yeah, we know this function
returns two variables, but we
only care about one. And then
similar to the centerpiece
above, we're going to do require
cost access call failed, meaning
that we're requiring cost
accesses true. Otherwise, we'll
revert with an error that says
call failed. Now of learning the
difference between these three
is a little complicated for you
right now. Don't let that slow
you down. Feel free to come back
to this after you've learned
more about how some of these
lower level functions work. And
a little bit more about how
gasworks solidity by example,
does a fantastic job though of
saying what the difference is
between all three, our transfer
has a maximum of 2300 gas and
throws an error if it fails,
send has a maximum of 2300 gas
returns a Boolean, if it fails,
call forwards all gas so doesn't
have a capped gas. And similar
to send returns a Boolean, if it
is successful, or if it fails,
As of recording right now using
call is the recommended way to
actually send and receive
Aetherium or your blockchain
native token for now, if this
part's a little bit confusing
for you, for now, just look at
this and see ah, that's how we
send and transfer Aetherium or
native blockchain currency
tokens. And I'm going to delete
this part for the video, but
I'll keep those comments in the
code repository associated with
this course. And okay, perfect.
If we hit compile a fun meat
outsole, we do indeed see that
it's passing compliation.
However, there's a bit of an
issue here, right now,
anybody can withdraw from this
contract. So anybody can fund,
which is what we want. But we
don't want anyone to be able to
withdraw. We only want the
person who's collecting the
funds to be able to actually
withdraw the funds. So how do we
set this up so that the withdraw
function is only called by the
owner of this contract? Well, to
do that, we're going to set up a
couple new functions. So when we
deploy this contract, we want to
automatically set it up so that
whomever deploys this contract
is going to be the owner of this
contract. And then we can do
some parameters to set it up so
that only the owner of this
contract can call the withdrawal
function. So how would we do
that? Well, maybe we can create
a function called like, call me
right away. And right after we
deploy this contract, we call
this call me right away
function, which will set up us
as the owner. Now that's going
to take two transactions. And
that would be really annoying if
we had to do that. So instead,
solidity has something called a
constructor. And if you're
familiar with other programming
language, a constructor is
exactly the same as other
programming languages.
constructor is going to be the
function that gets called when,
immediately whenever or you
deploy a contract. So if I were
to deploy Funmi, dot Sol, and I
were to say, minimum USD equals
to minimum USD would no longer
be 50 times one e to the 18th,
it would be immediately updated
to two. Because constructor is a
function that gets immediately
called in the same transaction,
that we create this contract,
this constructor function is
going to be incredibly helpful
for us, because it allows us to
set up the contract the way we
want it to be. So for example,
if we want the withdrawal
function to only be able to be
called by the owner of this
contract, we can have the
constructor set up who the owner
of the contract is. So let's
create a global variable called
address, public owner. And then
in our constructor, we'll say
the owner is going to be equal
to the message dot sender. The
message that sender of the
constructor function is going to
be whoever is deploying the
contract. So owner is now going
to be whoever deployed this
contract. And don't worry, we're
going to demo all this very soon
and show you everything that's
going on with ether scan
everything, demoing this all
right now might take a little
bit of time, because we're using
a test net. So if you want to
test it all right now,
absolutely go for it, but just
know, it'll take you a little
bit longer to do so. Now that we
have the owner setup, we can
modify our withdrawal function
to make it so that only the
owner can actually call this
withdrawal function. So at the
top of the withdrawal function,
maybe we want to add a section,
maybe we want to say require
message dot sender equals the
owner, a note about double
equals versus equals, you can
think of this single equals as a
set parameter. So when I say
owner, is now set to message dot
sender, double equals is how you
check to see if these two
variables are equivalent. So
we're saying is message dot
sender, the same as owner. So
this is checking to see
equivalence. This is setting
checking to see equivalence
setting. So we're gonna say
require message dot sender is
equal to owner, otherwise, we're
gonna throw an error, saying,
sender is not owner. Perfect.
Now we have a quick way to make
sure the withdrawal function is
only called by the owner of this
contract. Now, let's say that
there's a lot of functions that
we have in this contract that
are going to be required to be
the owner, maybe there's a lot
of functions in this contract
that need a whole lot of
different requires, we don't
want to have to copy paste this
line to every single one of our
functions. So what can we do?
Well, this is where something
called modifiers come in. So for
now, we're gonna go ahead and
delete this line. And below,
we're going to create something
called a modifier, our modifier
is going to be a key word that
we can add right in the function
declaration. To modify the
function with that
functionality, we're going to
create a modifier and call it
only owner. And we're going to
paste that line that we just
made in withdraw. And underneath
that, we're going to put a
little underscore, what I can do
now is I can take this only
owner modifier, and stick it in
the function declaration of my
withdrawal function. So what's
happening with this modifier
with only owner in this function