declaration,
we're saying, hey, for this
withdrawal function, before you
read all this code inside of it,
look down at the only owner
modifier and do whatever is in
there first, and then do
whatever's in the underscore,
this underscore represents doing
the rest of the code. So now,
when we go call the withdraw
function, we actually do this
require statement first, and
then call the rest of the code.
If this require statement, we're
below the underscore, this would
tell our function to go ahead
and do all this code first. And
then run the require. Because
again, we have this only only
keyword, we're saying, Great,
we've got a function, it's
withdraw its public, oh, only
odor modifier. Let's look at how
that works. Okay, it tells us
how to do all the code of the
original function first. So
let's go ahead and do that.
Okay, now we're done. Now, what
do we do? Okay, now we'll run
the require, we want to go ahead
and put the require here first.
So this is how modifiers work,
and how we can use them to
improve our functionality. All
right, awesome. We have all the
basic functionality of our
contract that we need here. Now
we're finally actually going to
run everything on a test and see
everything happened live before
our eyes. Are you ready? Let's
do this.
So let's go over to the deploy
tab. And we're going to switch
of course to injected web three.
Remember But we're using
injected web three, because our
price converter dot soul is
using chainlink Oracle's that
actually exist and are actually
monitoring the Rinkeby network
for us. Now we're going to
scroll down to, and we're going
to choose the Funmi contract.
And we're going to go ahead and
deploy. Once again, we want to
make sure we're on the Rinkeby
test net. And we have a little
bit of rinky eath in our wallet,
let's go ahead and deploy,
confirm. And we'll wait a little
bit. And I'll pull up our log
here. And we'll wait a little
bit for our contract to get
deployed. Alright, great. It
looks like our contract has
indeed been deployed. If we
scroll down, we can see all of
our functionality, minimum USD
is going to be that $50. But
with 18 zeros so that the units
are the same as Aetherium, the
owner of our contract was set to
our address, the instant we
deployed this contract, it was
deployed by calling our
constructor function. So this
address 0x 106 x is going to be
the same as the address in our
meta mask, your address here, of
course, is going to be a little
bit different than mine, we have
our funders array, which, of
course is going to be blank, we
have our address array, which is
also going to be blank. And then
we have two functions that we
can use to modify the state of
the blockchain withdraw is going
to be orange, because we're not
paying any Aetherium we're
actually gaining Aetherium or
whatever native blockchain
currency fund is going to be
read, because fun is a payable
function that we are going to be
sending Aetherium to or sending
whatever native blockchain
currency that you're working
with. So let's go ahead and see
how this all works. So first,
let's go ahead and fund this
contract. Again, funding, we got
to do a little bit of math,
right now, since the price of
eath is around $3,000. And we're
looking for $50. Minimum, we do
50 divided by 3000. We can do
3000 divided by 50, we can do 50
divided by 3000. So we know that
around 0.02 Aetherium, should be
enough for this contract to
work. So 0.02 Aetherium is this
much way, we can copy that,
paste that into here. So when we
hit fund, it should actually
pass. And we do indeed see meta
masks pop up. And we'll go ahead
and confirm. Once this
transaction goes through, we'll
be able to see this contract on
ether scan with the funds in it.
Now if we don't add way here, if
we don't add a value, once
again, we had fund will say gas
estimation failed because we're
not sending enough here. And in
fact, we even see execution
reverted didn't send enough, we
can absolutely send this
transaction however, it's going
to fail. Great. So now that our
transaction has gone through, if
we go on to the rink the ether
scan, once we wait a little bit
for it to finish indexing here
on the Rinkeby ether scan, we
can see that transaction
actually went through for doing
the funding, we can actually see
a lot of different details going
on with this transaction as
well. And if we scroll down, we
once again, you can see all the
information about us calling
this fun function, gas limit
gas, you should the gas fees,
gas price, and we can see the
input data as well, we can see
that we called the fund function
down here. We'll learn more
about the input data later. If
we go to the contract that we
deployed, we can now see two
transactions, we can see our
contract created transaction.
And we can also see we called a
font method. And if we look at
the balance of our contract, and
now has 0.02 ether, which makes
sense, since we just sent it
0.02. If we put that 0.02 eath
in terms of way back into the
value section, and we call font
again, after this transaction
goes through, we should see this
number go from 0.02 to 0.04. Now
after we wait a brief delay, we
do indeed see the balance has
gone up to 0.04, which is
exactly what we'd expect.
Awesome. So our funding
mechanism is working correctly.
And if we go down into our
array, and our mapping
to do address to array, and we
paste our address, we should see
the phone number show up. And if
we go to funders of zero, we see
our address. And if we go to
funders of one, we also see our
address and we see that and we
see this call going through if
we go to funders have to in our
log over here, we actually see
that we get an error an
optimization that we could make
to our contract in the future is
to check to see if an address is
already in the funders array and
then not add it if it's already
there. Now let's go ahead and
try to call this withdrawal
function. But let's try to call
it with a different address than
the address we originally
deployed this contract with. So
to do that, scroll all the way
to the top of this here. And I'm
going to go to my Metamask. And
I'm going to switch to a second
account and hit connect. Now,
our remixes should be updated
with the new account that's in
here, you'll see that if I
switch back to account one, it
switches back to account one, so
long as they're both connected,
you can see which accounts are
connected to applications by
clicking this connected button
and see which ones are
connected. If you ever want to
disconnect that account, you can
click the three little dots and
it disconnect the account. And
now we can see that this account
is not connected. However, count
two is connected. Let's go back
to account one and Connect
account one so that both of them
are now connected. But we'll
switch to account two, let's
switch to account two, because
again, account two isn't the
owner of this contract. We
scroll down to owner, we can see
owner's 0x 1066 Something
something and account two is
0x 043. Something something
awesome. So what do you think
will happen when we hit withdraw
here? Well, our modifier only
owner should kick in. And we
should get notified that if we
send the transaction, we'll get
this error sender is not owner.
So let's try it. Ah gas
estimation failed, we do get
this error. Sender is not owner,
which is perfect. This is
exactly what we want, we could
absolutely send this transaction
if we wanted to. But that would
just be a waste of gas because
this transaction is going to
fail. However, if we switch back
to account one, and we hit
withdraw, meta mask will pop up,
enabling us to confirm and
withdraw the ether out of this
contract address. Now if we look
at this contract address on
ether scan, after a brief delay,
we'll see the balance go from
0.04 back down to zero. And
we'll see our wallet balance go
up from what it is back to 0.04
plus what it was. And after a
brief delay, you can see our
balance is indeed back down to
zero in our contract. Now, if we
do address to amount for our
wallet address that was doing
the funding, it's back down to
zero. And if we try to check the
address of funders at index
zero, we get called to funders
that fund me errored execution
reverted.
We've completed all the basics
of this section that I wanted to
go through. And you should be
incredibly proud of yourself for
getting this far, you've just
deployed a really advanced smart
contract, we're using a library
and chainlink contracts to build
some of the most powerful
applications in the planet,
we've learned to use a library
for any type we want in our
smart contracts. We've learned
more about multiplication, and
then units of measure in
solidity and smart contracts.
We've learned about mappings
more about arrays what the
constructor does, we've learned
how to send money we've learned
about for loops, we've learned
about the different ways we can
actually send money, at least
from a low level. And we've
learned about modifiers. This
section is one of the tougher
sections in this course. So if
you completed this, you should
be incredibly excited. We're
going to go through our code
now. And we're going to make a
number of tweaks. Now this
section, we are going to do a
little bit more advanced
solidity here. So if you get a
little bit lost, don't sweat it
too much. And feel free to try
some of this stuff in the future
on your own. We're going to
modify this contract to make it
a little bit more professional.
It's not going to be end to end
amazing, but it's going to be a
little bit better. And you'll
see why in a minute. So the
first thing that we're going to
do is we're looking we're going
to look at some of these
variables here. In particular
owner and minimum USD, owner
gets set one time in our
contract here. And then it never
changes. Again, minimum USD gets
set one time, even outside of
the constructor. If we have
variables that only get set one
time, we can actually use some
tools in solidity to make them
more gas efficient. For now
let's compile our Funmi
contract, and then deploy it to
a JavaScript virtual machine.
Remember, we can go ahead and
deploy it right now. However,
funding and withdrawing and
doing in the money stuff isn't
going to work. Because again, we
don't have a chain link network
on our JavaScript VM. So those
aren't going to work so well.
But for what we're gonna do
right now, we don't really care
so much. Here's what we do care
about. You do care about how
much gas this costs to actually
send. We do care about how much
gas is costs to create right now
creating this contract costs
about 859,000 gas and we're
going to Add a couple of tricks.
Right now to bring this number
down, we're going to add some
stuff back in in the bid, which
will bring it back up. But for
now, we're going to learn some
tricks to bring this number
down. The two tricks that we're
going to learn are the constant
keyword and the immutable
keyword, in their solidity.
There are two keywords that make
it so that your variables can't
be changed. And those keywords
are constant and immutable. You
can learn more about them in the
solidity documentation, if you
assign a variable once outside
of a function, and then never
change it, so if if it's
assigned at compile time, you
can go ahead and add this
constant keyword. We'll learn
later about storage. But when
you add a constant keyword, this
minimum USD no longer takes up a
storage spot, and is much easier
to read too. So now we recompile
this, and we deploy this new
contract. Let's see if we saved
any gas. We look in the
transaction logs, now, we can
grab the transaction cost of how
much this cost to deploy, let's
compare it to how much it was
before. Well, we saved almost
19,000 gas, that's almost as
much gas as a cost to send
Aetherium. Typically, constant
variables have a different
naming convention. Typically,
you'll want to do them all caps
like Min imaam. Underscore, who
is the CIO all caps with
underscores. So now let's just
find minimum use D, and replace
that with all caps as well. With
this interaction, we know that
this variable is a constant
variable, and it's much cheaper
to read from now, if we go ahead
and compile this and redeploy.
In our Funmi contract, even
though this is a view function,
remember, view functions do have
gas costs when when called by
contract as a constant variable,
we can see the execution cost of
this variable 21,415 gas. So
let's put a little note rather
Nathan.
If we remove the constant
variable, we delete this
contract. And we redeploy, like
Funmi. And we hit minimum ust
again, we can now see how much
gas this was cost. If it wasn't
a constant variable, we can see
the gas cost did indeed go up.
Now on chains that are much
cheaper, this gas difference
probably won't make that much of
a difference. But on more
expensive chains like Aetherium,
this is going to make a big
difference. For example, on
Aetherium, we can actually see
current gas prices on Aetherium.
Here, we can see the current gas
price of Aetherium is about 141
way, so we'll go to our
converter, way to way we'll copy
the way price times this will
get the gas price of calling our
minimum USD, which is this
number here, which if we put
back in our Aetherium
uniconverter, we can see cost
this much gas. And if we times
that by the approximate current
price of Aetherium, which is
around $3,000. Calling minimum
use D as a constant is going to
cost $9 on the inside is at a
nonconstant is going to cost
almost an entire dollar more,
you can see how all these little
gas optimization tricks are
going to make your life a lot
better. So let's keep this
constant keyword in here. We'll
learn more about constant and
storage in later sections of
this course. Now, as you're just
getting started with this
course, and with slip the Do not
struggle. And do not worry about
making your contracts as gas
efficient as possible in the
beginning, and especially right
now. Just write your contracts
as best as you can. Once you get
really good at gas. And once you
get much later on in the course,
and much more advanced with
solidity, then you can start
going back and working on gas
optimizations. But do not let
gas optimizations hold you back.
Or if you start stressing over
it, just let it go. Don't worry
about it and just write your
code as best you can. So long
story short, Do not stress about
gas optimizations right now. Now
another variable we only set one
time is going to be our owner
variable. Owner equals message
dot sender. We set this one time
in the constructor variables
that we set one time but outside
of the same line that they're
declared. And we set them for
example, in the constructor, we
can mark as a mutable typically
a good convention for marking
immutable variables is going to
be doing I underscore so that we
know that these are immutable
variables, they have very
similar gas savings to the
constant keyword. Owner, of
course, is a variable that we
can't set on the line here
because inside the global scope,
there's no function going on.
However, inside functions,
because inside the global scope,
there's going to be no message
that sender, there's only going
to be a message dot sender when
we're inside of a function. So
inside here, we might say I
owner equals message dot sender.
And then of course, we'll scroll
down and we'll change this
require only owner now equals i
owner. Now if we compile that
deploy up, we can see how much
gas we can see how much gas
calling I owner is going to be
by with immutable notice, we get
21,508, which we'll go ahead and
copy for now. And we'll put
right here, we'll say,
immutable. Now, if we remove the
immutable keyword, let's close
this redeploy. If we scroll down
to I owner, screw up the logs,
we go down to the call, scroll
down, we see the execution cost
was much more. So we'll do the
backslash, a seven here, yes, or
non immutable. So you want to
keep some of these tricks in
mind, when it comes to storing
variables. The reason that these
two save gas is because instead
of storing these variables
inside of a storage slot, we
actually store them directly
into the bytecode of the
contract. And like I said, don't
worry too much about that for
now, later on in the course,
we'll teach you more about
storage and a lot of this low
level stuff that comes to these
contracts. But for now, just
know that these exist. And
they're nice gas savers, if
you're only setting your
variables once. Alright, great.
So we've just made our contract
a little bit more gas efficient,
little gas efficiency
improvements are going to be
concept I sprinkled throughout
this course. And when we get to
the more advanced section, I'm
going to break down exactly
what's going on and why all
these gas efficiencies exist and
what's going on behind the
scenes for these gas
efficiencies to occur. It's a
little bit in the weeds, which
is why I'm going to gloss over
it right now.
So if it's confusing, don't
worry, I wouldn't let these gas
efficiencies be the thing that
slow you down. Awesome. So we
have these two gas
optimizations? How else can we
make this contract a little bit
more gas efficient? Well, one of
the ways we can make this more
gas efficient, is by updating
our requires right now with our
require statement, we actually
have to store this sender is not
an owner as a string array,
every single one of these
characters in this errorlog
needs to get stored
individually, this string may
not seem very big, but it's a
lot bigger than the alternative
with what we can do. As of zero,
point 8.4 of solidity, you can
now actually do custom errors.
For our reverts, we declare them
at the top and then use ifs,
instead of require and then just
add a revert statements. This
ends up saving a lot of gas,
since we just call the error
code, as opposed to calling the
entire string associated with
the air. So for example, with
our require down here, and with
actually with all of our
requires, well we could do is
instead of having this require
we could create a custom error.
So at the top, what we could do
is we could say error, not
owner. And you'll notice that
this is actually outside of the
contract here. Now what we can
do is we can take this error not
owner scroll down into our only
owner, instead of doing a
require we'll do an if
statement, we'll say if message
dot sender is not owner, then
we're going to go ahead and
revert with a non owner error.
This ends up saving us a lot of
gas, since we don't have to
store and emit this long string
here. Now in a lot of code
today, you'll still see require
a lot of places because these
these custom errors are pretty
new in solidity. So you'll want
to get used to writing in both
ways. I wouldn't be surprised if
in the future, the syntax for
some of these errors looks like
this so that it's more readable.
But for now, if you want to do a
more gas efficient way than
required, you can use something
like this, we could update all
of our requires here for these
customers. But for now, I'm
going to leave both in just to
show you the differences. This
revert keyword does the exact
same thing that required us
without the conditional
beforehand. So you can actually
go ahead and revert any
transaction or any function call
in the middle of the function
call. Now let's look at one more
way to improve this contract.
Sometimes people will try to
interact with the contract that
takes Aetherium or the native
blockchain token without
actually going through the
required function calls that
that are needed. For example, on
a JavaScript EVM here, I could
actually try to send this
contract money without calling
the fund function. However, if I
were to do that, what would
happen with our fund function
get triggered? No, it wouldn't
get triggered, we wouldn't keep
track of that funder, we
wouldn't have that person's
information updated in this
contract. So if later on we want
to give rewards or something we
wouldn't know about those
funders. And this wouldn't be
great because people would send
our contract money without us
ever knowing and we wouldn't be
able to give them any credit or
anything. Additionally, maybe
they called the wrong function
by accident, and they they
weren't using Metamask. And they
weren't using a tool to tell
them, hey, this transaction is
likely going to fail. So what
can we do in this case? What
happens if someone sends this
contract, ether without calling
the fun function? Right now, if
we were to send this Funmi
contract, ie it would just go to
the contract Right, and this
contract just wouldn't keep
track of those people. But
there's actually a way for when
people send money to this
contract, or people call a
function that doesn't exist for
us to still trigger some code.
And now there are two special
functions in solidity one is
called receive, and one is
called the fallback. Now in
solidity, there are actually a
number of special functions and
two of these special functions
are the receive special
function. And the fallback
special function, a contract can
have at most one receive
function declared using the
received external payable.
Without the function keyword.
This function cannot have
arguments cannot return anything
and must have external
visibility, and a payable state
mutability. What does that
actually mean? And or look like?
Well, let's create a separate
contract to go ahead and play
with this. So in here, we're
going to create a new file
called fallback example, dot
soul. And in here, we're going
to add our basic pieces, SPX
license identifier, MIT pragma,
solidity zero, point 8.7. And
we'll do contract fallback
example, like so, feel free to
pause the video to catch up to
this point, let's recreate our
fallback contract, let's create
a variable to go ahead and try
to test this function, we'll
create a un 256 public result
variable. And let's create this
receive function. So we'll say
receive, it's going to be an
external payable.
function, we don't add the
function keyword for receive,
since solidity knows that
receive is a special function
whenever we send Aetherium or
make a transaction to this
contract. Now, as long as
there's no data associated with
that transaction, this receive
function will get triggered.
What we can do in here now is we
can say result equals one. So
let's go ahead and test this out
on the JavaScript virtual
machine, we compile this, so
we're gonna go ahead and compile
this. And we'll go deploy it on
the Java Virtual Machine, we're
going to deploy our fallback
example. And we're going to see
what result is initialized to,
since we haven't set anything
for result, result, of course,
is initialized zero. But what if
we were to send this contract
some Aetherium? Well receive
would go ahead and be triggered
here, we can actually send this
contract some material directly
by working with this low level
interactions. But here, don't
worry about what call data means
for now, just know that this
area down here is a way we can
send and work with different
functions. And we can add
parameters to this transaction,
by going up here and adjusting
the variables up here. If we
keep called Data blank, it'll be
the same as if we were in
Metamask. And just hitting send
in the choosing this contract
address. Again, we can't
actually use Metamask, since
this is a virtual machine, and
not one of the networks that
we're working with. So if I do,
for example, I change this value
to one way, and I keep
everything blank. And I go ahead
and hit this transaction button,
which again, is going to be the
same as hitting this Send
button, but only sending one
way. What do you think will
happen? Well, let's try it. We
can see in the log area that we
did indeed send a transaction.
And if you look at the
description here, you can even
see it says from so and so to
fall back example, dot receive,
it looks like it called our
received function, which should
have updated our result to one.
So if we hit result, now we can
indeed see that result has been
updated to the value of one.
Well, let's go ahead and delete
this. Let's deploy this contract
again. And this time, let's have
this value be zero, does receive
get triggered this time. So
let's pull this down. Let's hit
transact. Let's leave the call
data blank, we'll leave value at
zero. So this will be the same
as if we had sent zero Aetherium
to this contract. Let's hit
transact. It looks like that
went through, do you think
result is going to be one or
zero? You thought one you were
correct or receive function gets
triggered anytime we send a
transaction to this contract
now, and we don't specify a
function. And we keep the call
data blank when working with any
other contract like Funmi. For
example, when we call one of
these functions, we're actually
just populating this call data
bit with certain data that
points to one of these functions
up here. If we send a
transaction and we add data to
it, we could actually call one
of these functions. Now let's
try this again. Let's delete the
contract again we'll redeploy
open this up result is currently
zero receive like I said only is
triggered if our call data to it
is blank. Now this time if I had
some call data to this
transaction, do you think
receive will be triggered this
time? If we hit transact and
remix we actually get a pop up
saying fallback function is not
defined. This is because
whenever data is sent with a
transaction solidity says, Oh,
well, since you're sending data
you're not looking for receive,
you're looking for some
function. So let me look for
that function for you. Hmm, I
don't see any function that
matches the 0x 00. So I'm going
to look for your fallback
function. Remix is smart enough
to know that we don't have a
fallback function. The second
special function in solidity is
called the fallback function.
This is very similar to the
receive function, except for the
fact that can work even when
data is sent along with
transaction. So our fallback
will look something like this
callback,
external payable. result equals
to Fallback is another one of
these functions where we're not
going to put the function
selector because solidity is
expecting this, actually, you're
already familiar with one other
special function, we go back to
our Funmi. Our constructor, for
example, is a another type of
special function. There's no
function keyword. solidity knows
that this constructor is
immediately called when we
deploy this contract. So now we
have our fallback function.
Let's go ahead and compile this.
Let's delete our old contract.
Let's go ahead and deploy this
new contract. Like here, we hit
result, we do indeed, see, it's
set to zero. Now, if I add this
0x 00, and I send this, and I
hit transact, this is equivalent
to calling our contract here
without a valid function. So our
contract goes, Huh, I don't
recognize what you're trying to
tell me here, I'm going to refer
you to our fallback. And now if
we hit result, we see that it's
been updated to two. If we take
this away, solidity will go,
Hmm, it looks like you're trying
to send some Aetherium, or call
this contract without specifying
what you want to do. Well, I
have a receipt function. So I'm
just gonna go ahead and forward
you to that. So if we call
transact, we hit result, we see
it updates back to one, add some
data, hit transact, we see it
updates to to no data, updates
to one slowly by example, that
org has a wonderful little chart
that we can use to figure out
whether or not receive is going
to get triggered, or Fallback is
going to get triggered. If it is
empty, and there's a receive
function, it'll call the receive
function. If it is data, and
there's no receive function,
it'll just go to the fallback
function. And if there's no
fallback function, it might just
it might air out. So this is a
lot of really fantastic
information here. How can we
apply this to our fund mi
contract here, or what we can do
now in our Funmi is we can add
these fallback and receive
functions, just in case somebody
actually sends us contract money
instead of calling the fund
function correctly. So what we
can do is let's add a receive
function. So if somebody
accidentally sends it money, we
can still process the
transaction will say receive is
going to be external payable.
And we'll just have the receive
function call fund. And we'll do
the same thing with our fallback
function will have fallback
external payable. We'll just
have it automatically call fund.
Now, if somebody accidentally
sends us money without calling
our fund function, it'll still
automatically route them over to
the fund function. This means to
that if somebody doesn't send us
enough funding, it'll, that
transaction will still get
reverted. So let's go ahead now.
And let's switch to rink B to
test this on a real test net,
Amman rink B and my Metamask.
Let's switch over to injected
web three. And we'll scroll down
we'll choose our Funmi contract.
And we'll go ahead and deploy
this Metamask pops up, I'm gonna
go ahead and confirm the
transaction. And we see our
Funmi contract here right now we
can see the owner we can see I'm
the owner, we can see minimum
USD. And we can see of course
that it's a blank contract, and
there's nothing funded in here.
If we the copy the address, and
then go to rink the ether scan,
paste the address in, we can see
that there's no ether in here.
And the only transaction
associated with this has been
the contract creation. We saw
what happened before when we hit
the fun function, our contract
was updated with a new balance,
and that funder was added to our
an array. Let's see what happens
now if we just directly send
this contract money without
calling the fund function here.
If we did this right, our
receive function should pick it
up and kick the transaction over
the font. So let's copy this
address. We'll go to our meta
mask. We'll hit send, paste the
address in here with 0.02 eath.
Again, because this should be
more than the minimum amount in
USD, we'll hit next. I'll go
ahead and confirm this. After a
slight delay, if we did this
right, we should see the
transaction having called the
fund function here, now that our
transaction has gone through
After a brief delay in waiting
for ethers can update, we do
indeed see that our balance has
updated to 0.02, which of
course, this makes sense. And we
see in the transactions list
here, we see that this actually
went through as a, as a transfer
instead of us calling the fund
function. Let's go ahead and
remix and see if our funders was
updated.
It looks like it was at the zero
with position of funders, we
have our address. And if we take
our address and pop it into
address to amount funded, we can
see exactly how much we had
funded. This means that since we
added this receive function in
here, we automatically had to
call our fun function up here.
So awesome work, we were able to
add a receive function to help
people who accidentally call the
wrong function or accidentally
send this contract money,
instead of correctly calling the
fun function. Now, if they had
directly called the fun
function, it would have cost
them a little bit less gas, but
at least this time, they're
gonna get credit and add it to
our funders array for having
sent our funding contract money.
We've even learned some advanced
sections of solidity. And this
is going to be the last time
that we start our projects in
remix, we're going to be moving
over to a code editor now, where
we can get even more advanced
with our solidity on our setups.
For the most part, you've gone
over the vast majority of
solidity basics, there are a
number of things that we still
haven't learned yet. And the
reason we haven't gotten into
them is because they get more
advanced. And understanding the
real use doesn't really make too
much sense until a little bit
later. Some of the things that
we're going to go over are itams
events, try catch function
selectors, abi encoding,
hashing, and then you will slash
and then you will slash
assembly. However, if you've
gotten this far, you probably
can read most solidity code and
understand what's going on,
which is absolutely fantastic.
So you should give yourself a
huge round of applause for
getting this far. And doing
this. Let's do a quick summary
of this more advanced section
and make sure we understand what
we learned in solidity there are
a couple special functions. Some
of them are receive fallback,
and Constructor. These functions
don't need to have the function
keyword. And instead it can just
be called like so. Receive and
fallback are two very special
functions. If data is sent with
a transaction, and no function
was specified, the transaction
will default to the fallback
function if that fallback
function exists. If data is
empty, and there's a receive
function, it'll call the receive
function. There are a couple of
keywords that can help us save
gas in the long run. Some of
those keywords are going to be
constant and immutable. Constant
and immutable are for variables
that can only be declared and
updated once. Once we say
minimum USD is 50 times 118.
This minimum USD can never be
changed again. And this helps us
save gas. Immutable can also
save gas similar to constant.
However, immutable variables can
be declared one time in the
constructor, once an immutable
variable is declared, it can't
be changed later on. In fact, if
we even tried to update an
immutable variable or constant
variable, and we compiled, a
compiler would give us an error
saying, Can't write to a mutable
here. Or if we tried to change a
constant variable. Our compiler
would say, Hey, you can't assign
to a constant variable, sorry.
In remix, if we want to send
ether to a contract that's on
the JavaScript virtual machine,
we can deploy that contract. And
then in the contract, we can
just hit the transact button
without any call data and update
the value that we send with the
transaction. If call data is
blank, it will trigger the
receive function if it exists.
But if there's data that doesn't
specify any of the other
functions, it'll trigger the
fallback function
Awesome, you've done
fantastically to get this far.
And for this section before we
get started actually moving over
to Hardhead. And moving over to
JavaScript and understanding why
we need to do that. Let's
understand a little bit about
getting help and running into
problems. So let's say we have
our Funmi contract here that we
just worked on. And we run into
an error. Let's say for example,
we forgot the payable keyword,
right, and we go ahead and
compile this compile fund, we
did so. And we scroll down. And
we see obviously, we have two
errors here, right, we're
getting some errors, and we
scroll down. And we see type
error message dot value and call
value can only be used and
payable public functions, make
the function payable or using an
internal function to avoid this
error. And then it goes ahead
and gives the line that's
airing. Now this error is pretty
clear, this error code is pretty
clear. It's saying Hey, make the
function payable, or using an
internal function to avoid this
error, right? This should be
pretty easy to to add payable,
and then recompile and be good
to go. And this is actually a
good example of what to do when
you run into errors. When you
run into errors. The first thing
you want to do is you want to
try to figure out exactly what's
going on yourself based off of
what the error says. This one's
pretty straightforward, but some
of them can be a little bit more
obscure step one when trying to
get unblocked trying to tinker
and figure out errors yourself,
right? Because maybe you go
okay, I'll make this payable,
right? And you go to save. And
then it gives a different error
saying, hey, you know, payable
doesn't go here. You resave you
recompile it goes, Hey, we're
still missing that payable
thing. First step is always
going to be trying to tinker and
figure it out yourself. For this
course, I want you to limit
tinkering, slash triaging to 20
minutes, if you take more than
20 minutes to tinker and triage,
then move on to the next step.
But I also want you to take at
least 15 minutes yourself or be
100% Sure, you exhausted all
options, you're completely out
of ideas. So typically try to
tinker try some stuff for 15
minutes. And if you're under 15
minutes, and you're saying, Hey,
I'm 100% Certain I've tried
everything that I can think of,
then you can move on to the next
step. So step one, when you run
into errors is always going to
be tinker and try to pinpoint
exactly what's going on. Try to
pinpoint exactly what's going
wrong. Step two, let's say you
tinkered and you tried payable
all over the place, and you
couldn't figure out what this
error was and how to debug this
here. Step two is always going
to be Google the exact error and
see if you can learn from that.
So zoom out a little bit, I'll
roll my mouse over this, grab
this, copy it, or quotes around
it, and do exactly that, in
Google search that exact error
and take some time going through
Google going through Stack
Overflow going through Stack
Exchange eath, and look to see
if somebody has asked this
question already. And it looks
like down here looks like
somebody has type error missed a
value and call though can only
be used on PayPal public
functions. And if we scroll
down, we see that somebody ran
into exactly this. And they went
ahead and solved it. They go, I
realized my mistake, I needed to
add the PayPal keyword to my own
implementation. And they go
ahead in this question, they've
added the payable. And hopefully
this would give you the insight
to say, Ah, okay, great. I do
need to come back here and add
payable. Let's say this
StackOverflow question didn't
show up. Right? This forum
wasn't here. What do we do next?
So step one, tinker. Step two,
Google the exact error, I'm
going to do a step 2.5 That only
is for this class, go to our
GitHub, repo discussions, and or
updates for this course,
specifically, go to this GitHub
repo, full blockchain solidity
course, Jas, it'll look a little
bit different when you all get
to it. But come to this repo,
and look in this chronological
update section to see if there's
an update on that section that
you're doing. Obviously, since
I'm recording right now, there's
no update. And if you don't get
anything, feel free to jump into
the discussion section. And ask
a question in here, right,
there's going to be a community
of people looking to help each
other out and looking to make
this a lot of fun. And the
reason I say 2.5 is because in
the real world, you're not going
to have our GitHub repo, when
working on stuff outside of this
course, you're not going to have
this GitHub repo. So instead, in
the real world, I'm still going
to give you the keys, I'm going
to give you what it takes to
still unblock yourself on
anything. Okay. So number three
is going to be asked a question
on a forum, like stack, exchange
eath and Stack Overflow. Stack
Overflow is a question and
answering tech forum like this,
right? You can ask tech
questions, and then you can
answer them as well. And as you
can see, when you search for
these issues, they'll show up so
Stack Overflow is more for
general Role programming
questions and Stack Exchange
Aetherium or Stack Exchange eath
Aetherium Stack Exchange, this
is for more Aetherium or EVM
based question and all the
solidity code that we're gonna
be working with, whether it's
polygon, whether it's avalanche,
whether it's whatever, those
questions are going to be valid
here, and you can ask here. So
what you'd want to do is you'd
want to sign up or log in, and
ask and format your questions on
these forms, you'll want to sign
up for GitHub, you want to sign
up for Stack Exchange, you'll
want to sign up for Stack
Overflow, so you can participate
in these forums. In fact, if you
haven't already, let's sign up
for GitHub right now. And let me
walk you through formatting one
of these questions, because the
better you format your
questions, the better chance you
have of actually getting the
answer. And remember, when
asking questions on these
forums, when asking questions,
in these discussion communities,
people answer these questions
out of the goodness of their
heart, right? So if you don't
get a response, there's a chance
that maybe nobody knows, maybe
it's your question isn't
formatted very well, and etc. So
we're going to learn how to ask
really good questions here. And
if you're new to blockchain, do
not skip this section. Okay,
this is going to be that piece
that's going to give you the
superpower to unblock yourself
from any coding issue you run
into. So don't skip this
powerup. Be sure to follow
along. Okay. So if you don't
have a GitHub already, you do
need an email to get started. So
I'm going to go ahead and sign
in, I made a burner account just
for this video. So what we're
gonna do, we're gonna go ahead
and sign up GitHub, enter your
email
and we hit Create Account,
they're going to send us an
email. So we're going to come
back to our email, and we got
our launch code here, paste it
in. And so a little bit of
information. We're going to
choose the free version. and
fantastic. We've now created a
GitHub profile. Now back over in
the smart contract kid full
blockchain solidity course, Jas,
I'm going to create a new
discussion, a new thread, and I
want you all to comment on to
make sure you understand how to
format and how to ask questions.
Okay, general thread for
practicing. Question formatting.
Oops. And so let's go back here.
So first, I'm going to format
this question poorly, two ways,
and then we're gonna format it
really, really well. So the
first way we're going to format
it poorly, is by not giving
enough information. So what
we're going to do is I'm gonna
just copy this issue we're going
to do is we'll just say like,
Hey, I'm having trouble with
remix and an error. Can someone
help me? Why is this not a well
formatted question? If this is
my question, there's not nearly
enough information here, I, as a
helper, have no idea what this
person's asking. So let's do
something else. What I'm going
to do is I'm going to copy this
entire contract all the fun,
read outsole, paste it in here,
and go, Hi, I'm having issues
here. Can someone help? I'm
gonna head start discussion here
want to hit start discussion, it
formats this all weird. And once
again, there's not really enough
information here. I don't know
what the issue is. But at least
with this one, we have some
code, we have some way to
actually debug. So this is a
little bit better. But it's
still not that good. Let's go
ahead and edit this. To make
this even better. We hit three
dots, we can hit edit, what we
can do is we can use something
called Markdown syntax, and
highly recommend learning a
little bit of markdown, it's
basically some syntax help make
discussions on GitHub. And also,
questions on Stack Overflow and
Stack Exchange a lot easier. So
we're going to format this code
by adding these three backticks
at the start, and then also at
the end of our code. And then
additionally, next, the first
three backticks, we're going to
type so lid did T which tells
the format or to to use solidity
to format this code here. Now if
we update discussion, we notice
we get some nice highlighting
here. So this becomes much, much
easier to read. Right? This is
way easier to read now than than
it was before. However, it's
still not specific enough. We've
given a ton of code here, and we
haven't given the specific
answer. So this is gonna be
really hard for somebody to
answer. So let's make this more
specific. So let's edit this
question again. And let's
specify, so we see here, our
issue is specifically on this
function. We're going to copy
this function and we're going to
delete everything else in here.
And now we have just this code
inside of here. Now we're going
to make this really specific.
We're going to say, on this
function, I'm running into an
error. And then what we're going
to do is we're going to come
back here, we're going to roll
the over this. We're going to
copy this we could have pull our
code if we want but we're going
to format this error like this.
And then we're gonna say Can
someone tell me What's going on?
Update? Now this is a much, much
easier question to debug. Right?
We have some minimalistic code,
we have the error that we're
getting. And we have Can someone
tell me what's going on?
Obviously, the answer to this
would be to add payable to this.
And that's what somebody would
say, hey, like, you need to add
payable to this, I want you all
to practice doing some
formatting, go ahead and add a
comment on this with your own
formatted question. So that you
understand how to actually do
the formatting. And this
markdown format. It's this
format here, that's gonna be the
exact same for asking questions
on Stack Overflow, or Stack
Exchange for this course, go
ahead and practice if you want
to create more new discussions,
feel free to create new
discussions. If you want to use
Stack Overflow or Stack Exchange
eath actually highly recommend
you Stack Overflow or Stack
Exchange eath as well, because
those are gonna get indexed a
lot better than GitHub here.
However, feel free to ask
questions, obviously, in this
GitHub as well. Now that I've
given you kind of the basics
rundown, we're going to watch a
video that I made that goes even
deeper into why and how to
format all these questions and
what to use. So let's go ahead
and watch that. Every developer
has run into this. Something
breaks or maybe you don't know
something, but you don't have
time to let these stop you.
There are a series of steps that
one should take to maximize
one's chances of solving any
coding problem, but you'd be
surprised at how few developers
currently use the superpower
effectively, our first one we'll
spend the least time on, because
it's just tinker and experiment.
When you run into an issue. Keep
trying different things you
think might work, maybe try
doing print statements
throughout the file, learn some
debugging tips, but don't be so
cocky that you only do this
first step. And this shouldn't
just be random running around.
This should be trying to
pinpoint exactly what's going
wrong in your code, so that you
can either ask an effective
question, or figure it out
yourself. So pinpoint exactly
what's going wrong, because
you'll need it for the next
steps. Anyways, next, check the
documentation. Not all tools
have good documentation. But
taking some time to explore
documentation can be a quick way
to find your answer, you'll want
to learn how to search a webpage
with Command F or Control F.
That way, you can look for
specific keywords on a page, or
hopefully they have a good
search bar that works well.
Sometimes documentation can be
really dense. So maybe you'll
move to the next step, which is
doing a web search. At the end
of the day, good software
engineers are secretly just
professional Googlers. And this
is one of their most powerful
tools, being able to search the
web for somebody else who has
already run into the problem
that you've just run into, and
then solved it. Most search
engines like Google have tools
you can use to get even more
specific about what you're
looking for. Often for specific
errors, the best thing to do is
actually just copy the exact
error and paste it in the search
bar with quotes or use the
Asterix in spots, your error
might be too specific. Most of
the results you'll get will be
from forums and q&a sites, which
leads us to our next step,
asking questions in these forums
and q&a sites. Just make sure
that before you ask a question,
you've done some ample Googling
around yourself beforehand. This
way you don't waste yours and
anybody else's time. And by
asking questions that you swear
you will promise me that at some
point, you will go back and help
other people learn as well got
it good. Before even asking your
question though, we should learn
where is going to be the best
place to ask. This is why I've
categorized for different types
of forums and QA sites, feel
free to pause to read them over.
And here's some specific
examples of each one of these
index code base forms like Stack
Overflow, index repositories
like GitHub issues, index
technology, specific forums,
like our slash eat dev or
unindexed discussion platforms
like chainlink discord, one of
the key differentiators in these
categories is the index keyword.
We typically want to ask
questions on forums that web
crawlers have gone through and
stuck them in their database or
index them this way. And three
weeks when we look back at the
code that we wrote, we can just
Google what was going on when we
forget what it does. And this
will help out other developers
who run into the same problem,
which in turn, they might go
ahead and help you out later.
Ideally, most of your questions
should be asked on one of these
index forms for this reason for
their searchability and
discoverability. However, at
some questions are a better fit
for DMS, Twitter or discord that
aren't index and we made a
little chart here to figure out
where's the best place to post
your questions, feel free to
pause the video take a look or
read our blog and the
descriptions with the picture as
well to take another look at it.
And of course, before actually
posting that in one of these
forums, be sure to read their
rules as they might state that
some kind of questions are
specifically for Ben. But
basically the breakdown looks
like this. Theoretical big
picture or opinionated questions
can go great on general q&a
forums like Quora or specific
technical forums like specific
subreddits or discord forums,
specific coding questions can go
on these forums as well, but
will often get more eyes on
coding forums like Stack
Overflow or Stack Exchange
communities often the question
of Oh, should I post this on
stack URL? flow or maybe a Stack
Exchange community is incredibly
blurry. And sometimes it doesn't
really matter which one you post
on. Now, if you run into a bug
or an issue with a technology
you're really familiar with, and
you think it shouldn't be
breaking, this is your chance to
pop an issue into their open
source code repository and
potentially improve the tool.
They don't have an open source
code repository, you throw that
closed source piece of shit into
the garbage, but just kidding
closed source Tech has its place
in our lives, too. Additionally,
if you're following a tutorial,
and they have a Git repo
associated with it, like all of
my videos that do, that's gonna
be the best place to leave your
issues. So as much as I hate to
say it, putting your issues onto
my GitHub repositories is going
to be much more effective for us
answering your questions than
posting it in the YouTube
comments. Now finally, Discord,
element, email, text message or
any other these unindexed chats
are still good places to ask
questions, but please try to use
them as a last resort. And if
they do end up answering one of
your questions, maybe go back
and add that question and answer
to one of the other forums that
we were talking about this way
it will be indexed next time you
or somebody else, Google's it
now these quicker chat forums
are places more for the
community to congregate and have
quick conversations with each
other. They're places to theory
craft, talk about new things
coming out new ideas, events,
and other things that shouldn't
be indexed by web crawlers.
They're also great places to
meet and network with people
that you might be able to bounce
ideas off directly as you get to
know each other, which leads
into our last section. But
before we do that, Oh, do you
hear that? Oh, that's the video
inside another video alarm
ringing. When you ask a question
in one of these forums, the
better you format your
questions, the better chance
you'll have of getting an
answered. Now there's no bad
questions out there. But there
are poorly formatted questions.
So let's teach you how to always
ask questions as format as best
as possible to give you the
highest chance of making sure
they get answered. Number one,
before asking your question,
make sure you followed all the
steps in the parent video. And
you've done some research on
this already and make sure the
question hasn't already been
asked. Number two, make a title
that summarizes the specifics of
the question three introduced
the problem before you write any
code, add minimalistic,
reproducible code minimalistic
code means it's not just a copy
paste your entire file. If
you're having problems on one
line, maybe just post that one
line reproducible code means
that others should be able to
run to the exact same error that
you're running into, or at least
post the steps for them to do
it. This doesn't mean that you
should put I was following along
Patrick's video and on our five
I ran into this problem, just
watch his video and you'll get
there. As flattering as this is
it's not reasonable that
everyone is going to have
watched my videos, even though
they should you want to give the
technical steps to reach the
error that you've reached. For
those of you watching my Free
Code Camp video, you're kind of
exempt from this, but you can
only say, Hey, I was on our Five
on this part of your video
inside of our discussions tab of
the GitHub repo associated with
this course. So you can do that.
But only in that GitHub repo
associated with this course,
learning markdown to format your
code, especially using these
three backticks and labeling of
the language. This is a critical
piece of formatting your code
and will drastically improve on
the number of people who answer
your questions. Any errors or
code should be formatted with
this three backticks syntax. And
finally, often people who care
about certain technologies,
monitor specific tags and
monitor specific questions being
asked about the technologies
that they like. And then
finally, again, be sure to read
the forum's guides before
posting different forums have
different rules about what they
want and what they don't want.
So being familiar will increase
your chances of getting an
answer. All right. So now back
to the main video. Now a note
about Stack Overflow, in
particular, Stack Overflow can
be a little aggressive, which is
why sometimes posting on
specific community forums might
be better for your specific
technology questions. If you
post on Stack Overflow, and you
get a ton of down votes on your
questions. Don't let that bother
you. Just take it as a learning
opportunity to learn about what
Stack Overflow likes and doesn't
like and just keep going but do
not let that discourage you.
Okay, well, now that we know
where things should go, where
questions should go and how to
actually format them. Let's
practice let's look at some
sample questions that you might
have. And we'll figure out where
we want to put them. So the
first one, where does this one
go? Feel free to pause and guess
yourself. So a question like
this is going to be great for a
Reddit or a discord? Probably
more a discord. Now, this is
definitely something that you
can search for. Right? So you
probably could search for this,
find an answer and go from
there. But maybe you want to ask
a buddy or maybe you want to ask
a very specific community like
our slash eat Dev. Now, of
course, if you see this
question, you obviously want to
recommend Patrick Collins his
YouTube channel. Now how about
this question. Notice its
formatting right? The title is
nice and big. They have a
technical command that is
formatted properly. They have
Git commit which is formatted
properly, where would this go
like this would definitely do
very well on a Stack Overflow or
an index code based forum to
very clearly try had to do
something technical. The problem
is laid out very clearly. And
they've given the command that
they're looking to do. Now, how
about this one, something like
this could go on either
StackOverflow. But it's probably
more likely going to go on a
GitHub issue for this brownie
package. A big difference
between code forums and and Git
repos like GitHub is that when
you make an issue on a GitHub
repository, especially when you
think there's a problem, you do
want to be as in depth as
possible. So oftentimes, when
making an issue on these repos,
they'll even ask, what version
are you using? Can you post all
your code? Can you post all your
files and just be much, much
more explicit? So how about
something like this. So this is
going to be really good for the
GitHub repo associated with this
tutorial, it looks like this
person is asking about a very
specific tutorial. So posting
this, there is going to be best.
Now if your question is on a
tutorial that doesn't have a
GitHub repo, well, they probably
should. But then maybe this is
better in the comment section.
Now, again, this is where this
all becomes a little bit more
art than science, because maybe
the specific error that they're
running into is a generic error
that a ton of people run into,
and maybe it is better on
StackOverflow. Or maybe there's
an issue with the package. So
maybe it is better on GitHub. Or
maybe the solution to this is
opinionated. And finally, what
about this? Yep, this is going
to be much better for a discord
or a DM with your buddy. And
away, it's our last step on
blocking you from any question
is going to be join and
strengthen the community of your
tool. Now at the start, it's
going to be hard for you to give
back since you're not going to
be very knowledgeable on these
tools. But as you get better at
these technologies, you'll want
to try to answer some of these
new questions that do come in.
The reason is because this will
give you a chance to actually
learn more about the tools that
you like, it'll strengthen the
community of your favorite
tools, meaning if you help
answer questions on tool, it'll
actually encourage other people
to use the tool because there's
a strong following there. And
likely, they might actually help
you sometime in the future, you
helping people will make you
look like a good person. And
then you'll also feel like a
good person. Additionally, in
many forums like Reddit,
oftentimes, mods will actually
look at how often you post
versus how often you help others
and comments on others people
posts and some mods may actually
start blocking your posts for
abusing the forums and not
giving back to the community and
only trying to take knowledge
you in the community will be
more successful if you join in
and help others and not just try
to extract things from other
people. Additionally, by
engaging with the community, I
can't tell you how many people
I've met and I've learned and
been able to brainstorm with.
And then the final step is going
to be iterate through these
steps. Maybe you get to the end
of these and you say, Oh, I'm
still blocked, but you'll likely
be much, much more
knowledgeable. So you want to go
back and try these steps again.
Now this is where this whole
process is a little bit more art
than science. Because some
questions might not have been
discovered yet. Only very few
people know not enough people
understand the importance of the
questions, or maybe people don't
understand your question. And
this is why it's important to go
back and iterate on these steps.
Now that you have the basic
building blocks of this
incredible superpower, I
encourage all of you to go out
there and try this and then let
me know how it went.
Alright, awesome. So now that we
know more about how to get
unblocked, we can move on. The
reason it's so important to
learn how to get unblocked is
because blockchain and web three
is more than just everybody on
their own. It is a very
collaborative space. So as you
get better, and as you learn
more a massive way to test how
much you've learned and give
back to the community is to
going to Stack Overflow and
going to stack exchange them and
trying to answer some questions
yourself. So I highly recommend
you all go to Stack Overflow,
and then you go to the GitHub
repo associated with the scores,
you try to answer some
discussions, try to answer some
issues and help other people out
because it's going to help you
become a much better software
engineer. The other reason I
want to do that part is because
when we install some of the
tools that I'm about to show
you, sometimes the installation
process is the hardest piece
there. Once you get past the