install process, it generally
becomes much, much easier. But
this can often be the hardest
part of the course is just
installing some of these tools
that we're going to give you.
And that's what we're going to
learn about right now. So we
have been working so far with
remix, remix IDE, or integrated
development environment. As
we've seen, it's this wonderful
place where we can try out code
we can try solidity out, we can
compile we can deploy, we can
pretty much do everything that
we need to do. It's web based.
It can do testing, debugging,
deploying local JavaScript VM,
it's very quick and easy to
create and test our smart
contracts. However, it does have
some limitations. It can really
only deal with smart contract,
it can't really integrate with
other parts of projects. It has
limited support for tests or
custom deployments. And you need
an internet connection to even
work with remix and it can be
tricky to do a lot more advanced
functionality. So it's a
phenomenal tool and absolutely
if you're looking to do
something very quickly, I
absolutely recommend everybody
just go to remix to go ahead and
try something out how are now
we're going to move over to a
more professional smart contract
developer setup. And this is
with hard hat. This is known as
a smart contract developer
framework similar to brownie or
foundry or, and likes, there's a
number of these frameworks. And
the reason that we're going to
do hard hat is because hard hat
is JavaScript based. It's a
JavaScript based development
environment. It's got JavaScript
based compilation, environment,
deploying, testing, debugging.
Now, for those of you who love
TypeScript, we will also have
TypeScript editions of every
single one of our code examples
for you. So if you love
JavaScript, we got you, if you
love TypeScript, we also got you
we're not always going to walk
through us doing the TypeScript.
But we will sometimes, and all
of the code for the TypeScript
will be available in the GitHub
repo. Now, before we can
actually learn hard hat, we have
to learn another package first.
So we're going to learn how to
do everything with ethers. Jas,
which is a JavaScript based
library for working with smart
contracts. And it's also what
powers the next tool that we're
going to be working with, which
is hard hat under the hood of
hard hat. There's a lot of
ethers Jas. So it's important
for us to learn ethers Jas so
that we can understand what hard
hat is actually doing. Now for
the rest of the course, I'm
going to be using a code editor
called Visual Studio code. This
is one of the most powerful code
editors on the planet. And if
you've already got it set up,
feel free to go ahead and skip
this part. If you already have a
professional coding setup with
no GS and VS code, and Git and
everything, feel free to use the
timestamps in the GitHub
repository. To skip over this
setup section. You'll often hear
people refer to this as VS code,
or Visual Studio code or just
Visual Studio. However, it's
important to note that Visual
Studio code this is different
than Visual Studio, which you
might see look like this. So
Visual Studio code is what you
want, not Visual Studio, Visual
Studio is a different
application, make sure you're on
Visual Studio code. Now, if you
choose so and you're a total
Harto, you can absolutely work
just with your terminal, or just
with PowerShell, or just with
whatever coding environment that
you want, like atom or Sublime.
However, for us, we're going to
be working with Visual Studio
code. And I'm going to be going
through setting up Visual Studio
code the way that I like to set
it up, you can actually set it
up whatever way that you feel
comfortable. And of course, in
our lesson six here, we have a
link to installation and setup.
And I'm going to be adding more
links as we go about here. And
once again, all the code that
we're going to be working with
is in this GitHub repository
down here where it says code.
Now we're gonna go through three
different installation processes
and pick the one that's most
appropriate for you. The first
one is going to be for Mac and
Linux users. The second one is
going to be for Windows users.
And then our third one is going
to be a last ditch effort. If
for whatever reason, you can't
get Windows or Linux or the Mac
instructions to work, we're
going to use a Git pod
installation. Now, I highly,
highly recommend that you try to
get everything working locally
without using Git pod. However,
if for whatever reason, you
can't get those installation
pieces to work, we will have Git
pod instructions for all of the
repos that we work with here.
But to get started, we'll start
with the Mac and Linux
installation instructions.
The first thing you're going to
want to do is download the Mac
or if you're working with Linux,
download the Linux installation
of Visual Studio code. Once you
have it installed, it'll look a
little something like this. And
if it's a fresh installation,
It'll even give you some tips
and tools to actually get
started. If you've never worked
with Visual Studio code before,
I highly recommend going through
any get started or getting
instructions tips that come with
opening Visual Studio Code.
Additionally, we have a Visual
Studio Code crash course in the
GitHub repo associated with this
course. Once you have Visual
Studio code installed, the next
thing that we're going to want
to install is going to be node j
s. And again, we have links to
all of these in the GitHub repo
associated with this course, you
can just go ahead and click
download for Mac OS or download
for Linux, I recommend using the
LTS version. lts stands for long
term support, which means that
they will be supporting this
version for a long time. So go
ahead and download Node js. I've
already downloaded this, so I'm
not gonna go ahead and
redownload this now one of the
awesome things about Visual
Studio code is it has this thing
called terminals, which are
command line prompts that allow
us to run scripts, basically,
it's where we're going to be
running all of our code where we
can open up the terminal is we
can go ahead and hit terminal
and select new terminal and
you'll get something like this.
Now you might have bash or Z ca
or some other type of shell type
that you have doesn't really
matter because on Mac and Linux
it's going to be Linux based we
can now test our no Jess
installation has been done
correctly by running Node dash
dash version, and you should see
something that looks like this.
The exact version of node that
you have doesn't really matter
here. But ideally you're at
least on Node version 14 or
higher. And if something like
this doesn't show up, remember
to go ahead and start looking at
Stack Overflow looking on the
GitHub repo in the discussions
tab, looking on the updated
section, etc. And like I said,
sometimes installing this can be
the hardest part of this entire
course so, so don't get
discouraged. And please use
Stack Overflow Stack Exchange
Etherium, and the GitHub repo to
move past any issues you run
into. Now, if you're on Mac or
Linux, you can actually hit Ctrl
back tick, to actually toggle
your terminal mode, this will
pull the terminal up and down
for you getting familiar with
keyboard shortcuts will actually
make your life a lot easier.
Because you'll be able to move
around Visual Studio code much
more effectively, we have a link
to a list of keyboard shortcuts.
Additionally, in the GitHub
repository associated with this
section, as we move along, I'll
give tip on different keyboard
shortcuts that you can
optionally use otherwise, you
can just go ahead and click as
well, you can click the trash
can to delete the terminal, go
back up Terminal new terminal to
pop it back up. Now the next
thing that we're going to need a
little bit later, we're not
going to need it for this
section, but it's good to
install it now is going to be
git no jazz is known as a
JavaScript runtime. And it's a
tool that we're going to use to
help run JavaScript code in our
Visual Studio Code slot exactly
JavaScript. And the difference
between no Jas and JavaScript
can be a little bit confusing,
but don't let that stop you for
now. Next, we're actually going
to go ahead and install Git, we
will have links to the
installation instructions in the
GitHub repository, installing
git on Linux, you're going to
use one of these two commands
and on macOS, if you just type
git on the command line, it
should go ahead and prompt you
to install it. So we're back in
our command line, and we just
type git, it should prompt you
to go ahead and stall it. And if
you do get dash dash version,
you should get something that
looks like this. You can also
use a Mac OS get installer by
clicking this link here and
running through the installation
process. Alright, now that you
have no JS yet in Visual Studio
code installed, we can continue
on to the next section. Awesome.
If you're not planning on using
Windows or get pod, feel free to
skip the next two sections.
I'm running this on Windows 11.
However, it should work on most
editions of Windows. So the
first thing that we're going to
want to install is Visual Studio
Code, which looks something like
this, it should auto detect it.
And we're gonna go ahead and
download this for windows in a
walk through all the
installation process. Go ahead
and create a desktop item, we'll
add this just in case we want to
open with code. And we'll go
ahead and install. And then
we'll go ahead and finish. Once
you've installed Visual Studio
code, you'll see something that
looks a little like this, it'll
go ahead and give you this get
started with VS Code section
where you can choose some
themes, and you can choose kind
of the way it looks feel free to
customize it the way that you
want. If you want to learn a
little bit more about Visual
Studio code, I highly recommend
you walk through this section to
learn more about the shortcuts
and making your development
experience more efficient. When
you're done, you can just go
ahead and close the tabs at the
top. And it'll look a little
something like this. Once we
have Visual Studio code
installed. The next thing that
we're going to want to install
is node j s. And of course, we
have a link to installing this
in the GitHub repository
associated with this course,
what we're going to do is we're
going to go ahead and come to
node j s.org. To download this
for Windows node. JS is a
JavaScript runtime environment,
it's not exactly JavaScript. And
the distinction can be a little
bit confusing, but just know
it's going to help us run our
JavaScript code for our
development environment. Let's
go ahead and download the LTS or
the long term support edition of
no GS. We'll go ahead and we'll
run through the setup wizard.
And we'll go ahead and make sure
that this is clicked just in
case we ever want to use some
different tools with our setup.
And then we'll go ahead and
click Install, you'll get a pop
up asking if you really want to
install this on your device. And
we'll go ahead and hit yes. And
then we'll hit finish, you might
get a pop up that looks like
this, go ahead and click any
button to go ahead and install
the tools, go ahead and press
any key again. And you'll likely
get a Windows PowerShell screen
pop up asking you to go ahead
and install a whole bunch of
different projects and files. If
you chose not to install this,
that's totally okay. But in the
future, this will be really
helpful since we are going to
use a lot of tools that this
package installs anyways, this
might take some time to install.
So go ahead and be patient. And
if it gets stuck, it might just
be waiting for you to go ahead
and hit enter. So go ahead and
hit Enter for any prompts. But
yes, please be patient with
this, it can be a little bit
slow to go ahead and install
everything. Once you have all
that installed, you can come
back to Visual Studio code. And
we're going to go ahead and open
up a terminal. To do that we hit
terminal and we hit new terminal
terminal is going to be our
command line prompt where we're
going to basically run all of
our scripts to work with our
code. And if you run Node dash
dash version, you should see
something that looks like this
to know that you've installed
Node js correctly. Now this
command line is known as Windows
PowerShell. If you want to work
with Windows PowerShell, you
absolutely can. In fact, if you
want to be a total Harto, and
write all your code through
Windows PowerShell, you can
absolutely do that as well.
However, we're actually not
going to be working with
PowerShell We're going to be
using a tool that makes our
Windows environments more like
Linux. The reason that we're
doing this is Linux is the
standard for most development
environments. And having
everybody work on a very similar
setup will make the rest of this
course a lot easier for everyone
to interact with each other, no
matter what coding environment,
they're working on. WsL stands
for Windows subsystem for Linux,
and allows Linux programs to run
natively on our Windows
environments. To get this setup,
we're gonna go ahead, go to the
WsL install. And we'll have a
link for this as well in our
GitHub repository. So what we're
going to do, you must be running
a Windows 10, version 2004 or
higher, or Windows 11. If you're
using an older version of
Windows, you can absolutely
continue with PowerShell. But
you might run into some issues
where all the commands don't
work exactly the same. So I
highly recommend working on a
newer version of Windows. To
install this back in your Visual
Studio Code, PowerShell, or just
the PowerShell app, or running
WsL dash dash install. Now if
you get this error, the
requested operation requires
elevation, it means that we have
to run our Visual Studio code or
our PowerShell application as
administrator. We close out our
Visual Studio code. And right
click it and say, Run as
Administrator, we get a little
pop up saying Do you want to
allow this app to make changes
to your device, we'll go ahead
and click Yes. And then we'll
reopen the terminal. And then we
can run WsL space dash dash
install. And we'll go ahead and
install WsL. This may take a
little bit so please be patient.
Once it's completed, you'll see
something that looks like this,
we're going to be working with
Ubuntu. And we have a list of
different commands to change
your Linux distribution. If you
choose to do so. And you'll see
the request set operation is
successful changes will not be
effective until the system is
rebooted. So you'll want to go
ahead and restart your computer.
There's also a troubleshooting
guide in the GitHub repository.
If you run into issues after you
restart your computer, you'll be
prompted for a name for your new
system and a password. This can
be different from your Windows
name and password, and then just
follow through with all the
prompts. And then once you're
done, you'll be dropped into a
Ubuntu shell, and you can run
Linux commands. Now you'll have
a Ubuntu instance, on your
machine. And you'll be able to
run Linux commands in your
terminal. Now that we have WsL
set up correctly, we're going to
head back over to Visual Studio
code. Once we have WsL, we'll
want to go ahead and install an
extension. So in our Visual
Studio code, we'll go to
Extensions, and we'll look up
remote development you can
install the whole thing or just
remote WsL we're gonna install
the whole thing you can follow
along to get started with remote
WsL if you like, or you can just
follow along with me right now.
Right now if I go to the
terminal and hit new terminal,
I'm still gonna get PowerShell
we actually want this to be our
Linux shell. So there are a
couple ways to open Visual
Studio code up in our Linux
environment. One way is you're
gonna hit Ctrl, Shift P and type
WsL. And then click remote WsL
new WsL window, and you'll get a
new window that looks like this,
you can also click the bottom
left and choose New WsL window.
Now if we go to our terminal and
hit new terminal, we'll be
dropped into a bash shell and we
can run Linux commands in here.
Awesome. Another way we can open
up Visual Studio code with WsL
on is we can go into our your
boon to application, we can make
a folder by typing MK dir
folder, we'll CD or change
directory into folder and type
code period. We'll go ahead and
trust the authors in here. And
this will open up Visual Studio
code already connected to the
folder that we're in. And we can
create files in this folder like
hi dot txt, and those will get
created inside the folder in our
WsL. Now that we're inside our
WsL environment, you'll notice
that node dash dash version
doesn't work anymore. That's
because we installed it on our
regular Windows machine and not
on our WsL or Linux environment.
The reason we installed it on a
Windows environment first is
that just in case you wanted to
go ahead and use PowerShell or
user Windows environment to run
everything you still can just
remember if you use the Windows
environment and PowerShell all
the commands that we use might
not work for you. So we're gonna
go ahead and install Node js on
our Linux environment. Now, all
the commands that we're going to
write are going to be in the
GitHub repo associated with this
course. We're going to do a curl
command to the nvm repository,
which stands for node version
manager.
And we're going to pipe the
install script into bash. And
this will go ahead and install
and VM. After running that, go
ahead and trash the terminal,
and then reopen it. And then we
can type MBM dash dash version
to see if it actually installed
correctly. Once we've installed
nvm, we can go ahead and install
no GS using nvm. Just type npm
install, and we'll do 16 point
14.2 Is that same long term
support version we installed on
our Windows machine. Once we
have it installed, we can type
in Node dash S version. And now
we have no JS installed. Now I
know there was a lot here, but
if you made it this far, this is
fantastic. You've done a great
job to push through to this
point and get everything set up
so you can code in the best
environment there is. So if
you've made it this far, huge
congratulations. Now the next
thing that we're going to
install is Git. And now we're
not going to use Git for this
lesson. However, we will
definitely be using it in the
future. See if gets installed
type git dash dash version,
sometimes Linux will
automatically come with Git
installed and you'll see
something output like this. If
you don't have Git, we can just
look up the get install. Which
again, link to this is in the
description. And you'll actually
run the installing on Linux. Now
again, now if you want to use
PowerShell, and you want to do
everything with Windows, you can
absolutely follow the installing
on Windows instructions here
instead, when you're working in
WsL, you'll want to use the
Linux commands instead of the
windows commands even though
you're on a Windows because WsL
makes it so that you're
basically running in a Linux
environment. And now if you've
made it this far, you should be
able to follow along with the
Mac and Linux instructions as if
you're running on a Mac and
Linux even though you're running
on Windows. Just be sure that
whenever you're in your VS code,
you take a look at the bottom
left and make sure you're on WsL
Ubuntu. Like I said before, if
you want to run in PowerShell,
or in a Windows environment,
you're more than free to do so.
But like I said, if you've made
it this far, huge
congratulations. Awesome work.
And then finally, our last setup
is going to be using a tool
called Git pod starting from
Lesson five. The lesson that
we're on right now, ethers,
jazz, simple storage, all of our
code repos are going to come
with a button in the repo scroll
down, they'll come with this
open in get pod button. Now git
pod is a cloud development
environment where you can
actually run your code on a
remote server, it's kind of
similar to remix IDE, but it
allows you to run Visual Studio
code in the browser or connected
to another server. This is good
because then you don't have to
do any installation on anything.
Since all the tools that you can
want to use are just going to be
running on this remote server.
This has its downsides, though,
obviously, since you'll only be
able to code if git pod is up
and working for you.
Additionally, when it comes to
private keys, you absolutely do
not want to run any code with a
private key that has real money
in good pop. Why? Well, once
again, since you're running your
scripts on a remote server,
those servers have access to
your private keys. But since
you've Pinky promise that for
this course, you're not going to
be using a meta mask or a
private key with actual money in
it, it should be fine. The other
downside is that these often
cost money to use and get pot
isn't free. But it's an option
if you absolutely cannot get any
of the installation working. So
if you go ahead and you hit this
opening get pod button, you'll
get a welcome to get pods
showing up. We're gonna go ahead
and continue with GitHub. Since
you've signed up for GitHub
here, you want to go ahead and
authorize get pod. And it'll go
ahead and start creating this
workspace for you. And you'll
notice it looks exactly like
Visual Studio Code. Since I
opened the repo up in Git pod,
it came with all the code, and
you can even open this workspace
up in VS code desktop. So this
is might be a little bit
confusing. But basically, you
can run off of Git pod using
your local Visual Studio code.
And if you see git pod here,
that's how you know that you're
running off of Git pod. If you
see this pop up, do you want to
open this workspace in VS code
desktop, you can hit Open. And
it'll ask you if you want to
open up Visual Studio Code,
which I'm going to go ahead and
hit yes. And you'll get
something that looks like this
on your Visual Studio Code.
It'll tell you that it wants to
install the Git pod extension,
and then open that Git pod URL.
So you can go ahead and install
it. Reload window and open and
it's going to go ahead and start
connecting to our the Git pod
workspace. And this is going to
be the same as running git pod
in the browser here. Or you can
also do it manually by hitting
the Git pod in the bottom left,
and then type in open in VS code
And then you should be able to
run it in your Visual Studio
code. For now, I'm going to
recommend that if you're using
Git pod, just stay in the
browser, just so that you know,
okay, I am running this on a
remote server. And just as a
reminder for you that you're not
actually locally developing. And
hopefully, this will be a
trigger to not actually put any
special private keys or anything
like that. But you can make
workspaces, you can make new
folders, and you should be able
to run all the commands on here,
as if you are running locally
with Visual Studio code. To open
up the terminal, you can hit
this little bar at the top left,
go to terminal, new terminal, or
use CTRL tilde exact same as Mac
OS and Linux keyboard shortcuts
to create a new folder, we can
change directory, CD, dot.mk,
dir, new folder, MK dir makes
make directory called New
Folder. And then we're going to
change our directory into a new
folder, and hit enter. And now
we're in that new folder. For
each section, you can either
open up the entire source code
right into GitHub, or you can
create a new folder for each
section yourself and start from
blank. And then you would just
type code period. And you'd be
in a brand new folder. All
right, this is fantastic. At
this point, you should be set up
with Visual Studio Code no Jas
and get. And I'm going to be
working out of a folder called
Hard Hat Free Code Camp at this
point, you should have node,
dash dash version, get dash dash
version. And if you're using
Windows, this should say WsL or
your boon to or something like
that. And if you have all that,
that means we're ready to go.
Now a quick note something that
you'll see me do a lot. And you
can do this as well. Oftentimes,
when my terminal gets really,
really big, or there's a ton of
commands in here gets a little
bit overwhelming for me. So one
thing that you can do is you can
type clear, and hit Enter to
clear it. Or what you can do is
you can hit Command K, if you're
on a Mac, or Ctrl K, if you're
on a Linux or a Windows, and
it's one of my favorite keyboard
shortcuts that I use all the
time. Additionally, the trash
can and the X here are very
different. If I go to a couple
of enters here, and we're down
here, if I hit the trashcan, and
then pull my terminal back up,
by doing the toggle, or by doing
terminal new terminal, you'll
see all those lines are still
here. But if I hit the trashcan,
and then pull the terminal back
up, you'll see it actually
refreshes mine a special command
that prints stuff out. trashing
your terminal is basically
deleting whatever's running in
it, and the x is just hiding it.
And as hitting Ctrl tilde or
toggling our terminal or
whatever command it is on your
environment, that's equivalent
to hitting the hide, not the
trash. So if we want to remove
and start a terminal over, we
hit the trashcan, and then we
pull it back up. Alright, so now
we're gonna start working with
ethers. And we're going to start
learning to code, our
transactions and our contract
deployments and everything
programmatically at a relatively
low level. And we're gonna learn
how to deploy and interact with
the contracts using the ethers
JS package. Now to get started,
I'm going to recommend you
create a folder where you're
going to put all of your
projects in it, I'm going to
create a new directory called H
H. hyphen, FCC, which stands for
hard hat Free Code Camp. And
once we run that command, we can
cd into hh FCC. And this is
where we'll create all of our
projects for this course moving
forward, so that we have them
all in one place. Now to get
started, whenever you create a
new project, you always want to
create a new folder. So to
create a new folder, we're going
to do MK dir, and we're going to
call this ethers, simple
storage, like that. And now, if
you type ls, you'll see that
there is one folder named
ethers, simple storage. ls is
how you list all the contents of
your folder. You might have a
lot of other folders in here, I
only have the one since I
created this new folder for
this. Now what you can do, you
can type code, ethers simple.
And then if you hit tab, it
should autocomplete for you. And
if you enter, Visual Studio code
should open up a new Visual
Studio code for you. That is
inside of either simple storage
if you open up your terminal
now, your home directory for
this workspace is going to be
through simple storage as this
is what pops up. If that doesn't
work for you, we can also do is
you can hit File, Open folder
and then open the folder that
you just created or that you
want to open this again we'll
open up VS code. And if we open
up our terminal we see we're
inside of ether simple storage.
This is so powerful because as
we create files
we'll be able to See those files
in our Explorer here, this
button here stands for the
Explorer. If we click it, we can
see the different files in here.
And I'm going to go ahead and
actually delete this file dot
txt, because we're not actually
going to use that. Now it's this
part of the course, where we're
actually going to start jumping
into some JavaScript. Since this
course is in JavaScript course,
if you're unfamiliar with
JavaScript, it might be a little
bit tricky. If you want to come
into this with a better
understanding of JavaScript and
Node js, there is a Free Code
Camp YouTube video teaching No,
Jas for beginners. And a link to
this will be in the GitHub repo
associated with this course.
There's also a JavaScript Free
Code Camp video that I'm also
going to put in the description
for this course, keep in mind
that JavaScript and Node js are
slightly different. And we are
going to go over some of the
differences as we code along
here. But for the most part,
learning one means you've
learned the majority of the
other. So if you want to pause
and go through these videos,
before continuing here, please
feel free to do so you don't
have to, you can absolutely
continue on with the course as
is. And if you get confused or
stuck on some JavaScript piece,
feel free to pause, Google it
and come back. But just to
reiterate, you can check out the
JavaScript programming full
course. And also the Node js
full course, as those are both
going to help you. Like I was
saying before, Node js is a
JavaScript runtime. So it's not
exactly JavaScript. But we're
going to write our code in
JavaScript. And if that's
confusing, just don't worry
about it right now. And as we go
through this course, I'll show
you where the differences are.
But basically, you can think of
no Jas and JavaScript kind of
being the same thing. The big
thing about Node js is it allows
us to write JavaScript code in
the back end, as opposed to
running JavaScript on the front
end, JavaScript is made to be a
browser run language, like
running inside of, you know,
Chrome, brave Firefox, etc. No,
Jas allows it to become a a
scripting language, a back end
language, which is why the
syntax between the front end
JavaScript and the back end
JavaScript or the no JS
JavaScript are going to be a
little bit different.
Additionally, as we go along in
this code, if you're familiar
with TypeScript, all of our code
is going to come with a
TypeScript edition. TypeScript
is what's known as a statically
typed version of JavaScript. And
it'll be it'll be this one.
It'll be TypeScript, not
TypeScript edition. I'll go
ahead and fix that and remove
this one to make it clear.
TypeScript is a type safe
version of JavaScript, which is
that's confusing, don't worry
too much about that. But we are
going to do all of our
programming in JavaScript. And
then if the code is different
enough, I'll show you how to do
it in TypeScript as well.
However, for most of them, we're
not going to show you the
TypeScript editions, because
it's going to be really similar.
But you can always refer back to
the GitHub repository to see all
the code for the TypeScript.
Now, if you're new to this
space, I actually do recommend
you go ahead and start with
JavaScript and learn how to do
TypeScript later on. TypeScript
actually catches bugs early on,
making it a lot easier to code
your projects in the long run.
However, it does take a lot of
extra typing. And it can be a
little bit frustrating learning
how types work for beginners,
JavaScript is a little bit more
loose as a language and lets us
kind of do whatever we want, but
it can cause a headache later
on. So if you do run into some
issues, and you do run into some
bugs, it might be a good idea to
try TypeScript on for size, and
see how that fares. Well. Let's
go ahead and begin working on
our local development
environment and getting set up
to do everything in ethers Jas
and in JavaScript. Oops. And I
actually went and renamed this
folder to ether symbol storage
dash, FCC. Reason I added this
dash FCC is all the GitHub
repositories associated with
this course, all the GitHub
repos that have this dash FCC to
know that it is part of this
hard hat JavaScript course.
Awesome. Let's jump in. Let's
start working with solidity and
our smart contracts locally in
Visual Studio code, as you can
probably tell by the name of
this folder. And of course, if
you looked at the code, this
project is going to be our
simple storage project, but
developed locally using ethers.
So the first thing that we want
to do is want to get in that
smart contract code. So what we
can do is make sure we have the
Explorer selected, we can go
ahead and right click and select
new file and do simple storage.
So just close this for now. And
we can copy paste our simple
storage code from our last
section into VS code.
If you closed remix or you
forgot where it is, you can just
go to the ethers simple storage
FCC repo, it's simple storage
dot Sol, and we can just copy
all the code in here and then
come back over select Symbol
storage that Saul and paste it
in. Now an important note about
Visual Studio code is that when
you see this little white.up
here, it means that this file
isn't saved to save your Git
file. To save, and it'll go away
like that. Or what you can do is
you can hit command S or Ctrl S,
depending on if you're on a
Windows, Mac, or Linux. Now
you'll see here that this code
is a little bit hard to read the
simple storage dot salt, it
doesn't have the syntax
highlighting that we saw in
remix. So we want to go ahead
and add a Visual Studio Code
extension to give this syntax
highlighting. So what we can do
is come over to this bar over
here looks like this. And if you
don't see it on the left hand
bar, you should click these
three dots, and it should be in
here. But we'll go ahead and
click Extensions. And what we're
going to do is we're going to
look up, solidity plus hard hat.
And we're going to install this
solidity plus hard hat
extension. For VS code. Now that
we have this installed, if we go
back over to our simple storage
dot sole, you'll see that all
the highlighting is back in. And
now it's much easier to read.
Right? So this is good. We have
our code in here we have our
syntax highlighting. Now let's
add an auto format or or default
format or right now our code is
pretty good with the way that
it's formatted. But what if we,
we accidentally do some stuff
like this or like this, or maybe
even like this, we add a ton of
new lines, etc, our code can
start to look pretty gross. And
even though the code itself is
fine, and it'll run the exact
same way, with all this extra
whitespace, it doesn't look very
good, right. And due to that, it
can be a little bit hard to
read. What we want to do, then,
we want to open up our settings
and adjust our vias code so that
it auto formats whenever we
save, so whenever we save, so
that whenever it goes from the
little white dot here to no
white dot, this whole thing gets
automatically formatted to some
looks really nice. Okay. So what
we can do is we can open up our
command palette to open up our
command palette, you can hit
View command palette, and we'll
get a little pop up that looks
like this. Another way to open
up your command palette is
you're gonna hit Command, Shift
P, or Ctrl, Shift P, depending
on your Mac, or Linux or
Windows. And what we want to do
is we want to type in settings,
and we're going to open Settings
JSON, we don't want to open the
default settings JSON. We don't
want to touch these. But we want
to open our JSON settings.
You'll also notice there are
user settings and workspace
settings. These are pieces that
we can adjust as well. But we're
going to just go right into the
JSON settings. So So I already
have some stuff in here, but
yours might be blank. Or you
might have some stuff in here as
well. So what we're going to do
is if you have stuff in here
already, we're going to add a
comma, then we're going to do
quotes, solidity. Close the
brackets, we're gonna do a
little colon and something like
this. This means that we're
going to apply some settings to
our Visual Studio Code. Whenever
we're working with solidity, one
of the things we're going to add
in here is going to be an
editor, Doc's default, for
matter. And you might even get a
pop up that tells you some
different things that we can use
for a default format or our
default format, or is going to
be Nanak, foundation, dot hard
hat, hyphens solidity. This will
mean that any time we go to
format our code, it'll use the
hard hat solidity plug in, as
its default format, or the hard
hat solidity plugin comes with
some formatting, and a lot of
other really useful tools for us
writing our code. So now that we
have this part in, the next
thing we're going to do is add
format on Save. If we haven't
already, we could add it in here
in our JSON, but I'm going to
add it not in the JSON file, I'm
going to add it in the overall
file. So if we open that command
palette back up, and we type in
settings, open user settings,
this is another really good
place where we can look in add
settings with the UI. So these
two do essentially the same
thing. It's just that this one
has dials and a little bit more
context versus settings that
JSON just says Okay, give me the
raw code for it. This tells us a
little bit more. So you can use
either one. But we're going to
look for format, on save. And
you're going to want this
checked if you haven't already.
This means that every time we
save VS code is going to try to
format our code for us. So now
that we have this checked, we
have settings dot JSON added in.
And remember, we want to save
this. Remember, if you see this
white dot, that means not saved.
So you're gonna want to save it
and close it out. Let me close
this out too. If we come back in
here and we add a bunch of
random new spaces or whatever,
you want to make it look a
little bit ugly, and then we
save it. It should automatically
reformat to look much nicer,
right. So if we do something
like this, we'd save it
reformats it to look much nicer
this one make them more readable
for you, and more readable for
anybody else who looks at your
code. And it's just really nice.
And this line of code for your
settings dot JSON is located in
the full blockchain study
course.js. So you can also just
copy paste it, we are going to
end up overriding that default
format or with another format
are called prettier pretty soon.
But it's great to have a default
format or so that if you don't
feel like adding the prettier
code sometime in the future, you
can just rely on your default
formatter. Awesome. While we're
doing formatting, let's also add
a default format or for our
JavaScript code. And just to
test it out, let's go ahead and
create our new file, we'll call
it deploy dot Jas. And in here,
we can do something like
function Hi,
console dot log, hi, and then
just add and then just make it
look kind of gross, maybe
something like this. If you hit
save, and it does some auto
formatting, that's great, you
can actually turn that off by
going back to your command
palette, and saying, Save
without formatting. And that way
it will be saved and not
formatted. The way we can add
some other formatting here is
we're gonna install another
extension, this one is going to
be called prettier. So we can
just look up prettier and
extensions here. And you'll want
to install this prettier code
formatter. So we're gonna go
ahead and install this. And
great, now it's installed
prettier is a form is a code
format, or that works for many
languages like Python,
JavaScript, and even solidity.
And pretty soon we're going to
use prettier for both JavaScript
and solidity. But for now, we're
just going to use prettier for
JavaScript, we can enable this
by opening back up our command
palette, we'll go to
preferences, open Settings. And
the same way we added a solidity
section, we're going to add a
JavaScript section. So we're
going to add a comma here, some
quotes, brackets, we're going to
type in JavaScript, close that
colon brackets. And we're going
to do the same thing at the door
dot default, or matter. Net
we're going to do and then in
here, we're going to do e s
BENP, that prettier, hyphen VS
code. And this will make
prettier the default editor for
JavaScript. Now, like I said,
pretty soon, we're going to have
prettier override both of these
for solidity and JavaScript. And
we're going to give prettier
some parameters so that no
matter who uses your code, they
will always have the exact same
formatting. But now that we have
prettier in here as the default
editor, if we come back to
deploy dot j s, and we hit save,
it should format to look a
little something like this. Now,
we go ahead and we do something
like this. If we go ahead and do
something like this, it'll
reformat to look like look like
that. And then additionally, if
you want to go back to the
command palette, open user
settings, not in JSON mode, and
we go to default format, or you
can actually even select the
default format or for all
languages, if you want to use
prettier for all formatters.
Feel free to go ahead. Alright,
great, got our JavaScript
format, or in as well, let's
start writing some JavaScript
code.
Awesome. So now that we have our
code in here, it's time for us
to learn how to actually deploy
our contract using JavaScript.
This is going to teach us a lot
about transactions and what's
going on under the hood, and
even what's going on under the
hood in remix, and remix, we
usually just hit a compile
button, and then hit a Deploy
button. And that's really it. In
JavaScript, we're actually going
to create our own functions that
are going to help us do both of
those. And as I mentioned, this
is the part of the course we're
going to start working with
JavaScript, and optionally,
TypeScript if you like. Like I
said, all of these sections come
with a TypeScript edition as
well. So let's set up our
deployed out js script to
actually deploy our simple
storage dot soul. So how can we
get started here? Well, let's
first learn how to run a script
using JavaScript and Node J S.
So if you want to do a print
line, or just print something
out to your terminal, we can do
something called a console dot
log. And if I do console dot
log, hi, I hit Save. And I open
up my terminal. I can now run
Node deploy.js. And it'll print
out high node is how we say hey,
we want to run this JavaScript
code using Node js. Other
languages you might be familiar
with, sometimes we'll do Python,
you know, deployed up py, or
Java, C deploy dot Java, you
know, etc. But with JavaScript,
since the front end and back end
JavaScript are different. We run
code on the back end with node.
And with JavaScript, you can do
a lot of things that you'd see
in something like solidity with
a little bit looser have a
structure. If I wanted to create
some variable, I could say let
variable equals five, this kind
of similar into solidity like
you and 256, variable equals
five. But in JavaScript, we use
let or var or const. And then I
can print this out, I can do
console dot log variable. And I
had saved JavaScript is optional
on whether or not you actually
want to have semicolons. Here, I
think prettier, defaults to
putting semicolons. And we'll
get rid of those in the near
future in your terminal. Once
you start typing the name of a
file, if you hit tab, it could
autocomplete the rest of the
file name for you node deploy
hit Tab, it'll autocomplete and
if we hit enter, now, we get Hi,
and then we get five. Since this
prints out Hi, and then it
prints out five. JavaScript
automatically starts with
whatever code you have at the
top of the file. So it does
console dot log first and
variable. And then this one as
well. However, a good practice
is to actually wrap everything
you want to do in a main
function, and then run that main
function. But what we could do
is up at the top here, we'd say
function, mean, add parentheses
and some brackets, a closing
bracket at the bottom, and hit
save for its auto format. Right
now, if we run this, nothing
will happen, because we've
wrapped all of our code in a
main function. So if I run it
now node deployed to Jess,
nothing happens, because I need
something to call the main
function. So if I then take
this, this main function down
here, and I call main, our jobs
from code is actually going to
say, ah, the first line of the
script is actually this main
function here. So now if I do
node deploy dot j, s, it'll run
high and five, which is what we
want. Now, this is going to be
the setup for most of our
scripts moving forward,
including the scripts that we
write, when we get to hard hat,
however, there is going to be
one major difference. Instead of
regular functions, we're
actually going to use something
called async functions. And
we're going to do something
called asynchronous programming
to do this. Now, if what I say
next is really confusing for you
don't let it slow you down, feel
free to go ahead and watch that
JavaScript course to learn more
about this. But I'll also let
you know, hey, this is an async
function. Here's what we need to
be aware of when working with
it,
okay. But I do want to give you
a quick bit background on
asynchronous programming. So
far, the programming that we've
done has been synchronous. And
solidity is an example of a
programming language, that
synchronous, Synchronous means
it just goes one line after
another. If our code looks like
this, this is synchronous write,
our main function is the first
thing that actually gets called.
Then we do console dot log, that
variable equals five, and then
console dot log. Again, this is
synchronous programming in
JavaScript, all of our solidity
is synchronously programmed.
There will be some exceptions to
this when working with oracles.
But for now, everything is
synchronous. JavaScript can be
asynchronous, meaning that we
can actually have code running
at the same time. A good example
I like to use to understand the
difference is with cooking. In
synchronous programming, for
cooking, you might put popcorn
in microwave, wait for popcorn
to finish. And then, and then
maybe you'll pour drinks for
everyone. And now this is
synchronous programming. Now, it
might be a little bit weird for
you just to put the popcorn in
the microwave, and then just
stare at it, waiting for it to
finish. And then pour the
drinks, you typically can pour
the drinks while your popcorn is
in the microwave. And this is
where asynchronous programming
comes in. If setting up for this
movie night, we're asynchronous,
what you would do is you'd put
popcorn in the microwave. And
while the popcorn is in the
microwave, or drinks for
everyone, and then you'd wait
for popcorn finish, since
there's nothing left for you to
do, but it doesn't make sense
for you to wait for the popcorn
to finish to pour your drinks,
you can just go ahead and pour
the drinks right away and then
wait for the popcorn to finish.
So asynchronous programming is
way for us to do stuff without
waiting around for things to
finish. And this is really
advantageous in JavaScript by
default allows us to do this
asynchronous programming,
however, sometimes we do want to
wait for our popcorn to finish.
For example, if instead of just
pouring drinks, maybe the next
thing instead of pouring drinks
was placed salt on popcorn. Of
course, if we want to play salt
on our popcorn, we do have to
wait for the popcorn to get out
of the microwave. So even though
placing popcorn in the microwave
has this wait time we need to be
able to tell our code I want you
to actually wait for it or No,
you're good. You can go on and
do another task. So that's kind
of the difference here. And I'll
leave some links in the GitHub
repo associated with this course
to understand this a little bit
better functions that have
functions that come with this
waiting period return something
called a problem. This, if put
popcorn in the microwave was a
function in JavaScript, it would
be a promise based function. A
promise can be either pending,
fulfilled, or rejected. And this
is how we know if our popcorn is
done. If our popcorn was a
method, putting popcorn in the
microwave, were a function in
JavaScript, when we're waiting
for the popcorn to finish, it's
in a pending state. When it's
when the popcorn is finished, it
would be fulfilled. And if we
aborted halfway through, and we
stopped waiting, it would be
rejected. So putting the popcorn
in the microwave returns a
promise. With this promise, we
have to tell our code, hey, we
want you to wait for the popcorn
to finish or you can go ahead
and you can just keep doing
stuff. So let's put this all
together with some JavaScript
syntax here. Let's say again,
we're going to be setting up
this movie night. And we need to
cook popcorn, pour drinks for
everybody. And then we need to
start a movie. So let's write
some pseudocode to pretend what
this code would look like if
this was actually a function. So
we create some function called
setup, Movie Night. And in here,
we would say okay, what's the
first thing we need to do? Okay,
we need to cook popcorn. So
let's say we have some cook
popcorn function. So we'll say,
okay, cook popcorn, then the
next thing we're gonna have to
do is we're gonna have to pour
drinks, or drink. So we'll call
some pour drinks function. Now
here's the thing, we only want
to start the movie once our
popcorn has been cooked. And
once our drinks have been
poured, so if either one of
these returned a promise, so if
either one of these returns a
promise, like cook popcorn, for
example, we would need to tell
our code here to actually wait
for the popcorn to finish
because cook popcorn is going to
be a function where we could say
let status equals cook popcorn.
And while the popcorn is being
cooked, the status is going to
be ending. Once the popcorn gets
cooked, it'll be fulfilled. If
the popcorn breaks, the
microwave explodes, the status
would be rejected. But we don't
want the status to be in a
pending situation. Before we
move on, we only want to start
our movie once these two
functions have completed. And
let's say both of these return
these promises things. So we
need to tell our code, hey, you
have to wait. Or you have to
wait for cook popcorn and for
poor drinks to finish. So what
we can do now without getting
too deep into the weeds on how
all this works, one of the
easiest things that we can do
and you'll see us use this
syntax quite often is we'll turn
this function into an async
function. When our functions are
async, we get access to a
keyword called await the await
keyword tells any promise based
function to wait for that
promise to be fulfilled or
rejected. So we say okay, we
want to await for our popcorn to
cook. And then we want to await
to pour drinks. And then we can
just go ahead and start the
movie. And we only start the
movie here once these two have
been completed. And this is why
throughout all of our code,
you'll see this await keyword
used a lot. But it can only be
used in async functions. So
basically, whenever you see this
await keyword just now Ah, okay,
the function that's being called
is promise based. And we don't
want to move on to the next step
until that function has
completed. So that's a little
bit more about promises and
asynchronous programming.
Hopefully, that's clear. If not,
like I said, there's some links
in the description to learn more
about asynchronous programming.
The reason I wanted to go
through this is because most of
the functions that we're going
to be working with are going to
be asynchronous. For example,
when we deploy a contract, what
do we have to do? Well, we have
to wait for it to be deployed.
If we don't use synchronous
programming, and we just leave
our function main like this,
what would happen is we would
write some code like contract
dot deploy, and we wouldn't wait
for it to finish. Obviously, if
we don't wait for it to finish,
and we try to run some code on a
contract that hasn't finished
deploying it, it's not going to
work. So we want to do this, we
want to have our main function
be an async function, so that we
can we can wait for our
contracts to deploy, we can wait
for things to happen, we can
wait for our popcorn to finish,
we can have the flexibility to
tell our code to either wait for
our popcorn to finish or
continue on. So now that we have
our main function as an async
function, we're going to add
some code to our main function
down here. And the code that's
added here is some syntax for
working with asynchronous
functions. And if this part is
confusing, I'm just going to say
for now, absolute, don't worry
about this. If you want to try
to understand that later. That's
fine. But for those who are
following along, we're just
going to add an add
then catch air air you can
follow along typing this
yourself or you can just copy
paste it into your code.
Basically what this allows us to
do is we have our main function,
that's an asynchronous function.
So when we call the main
function, this is some other
syntax for waiting for it to
basically finish and then
printing any errors it gets. And
that's why we do this but Again,
if this big lump of code, if
you're like what is going on
with this big clump of code,
honestly, for now, just copy
paste it. So great. We have our
asynchronous function main, we
have some code. And then we have
this lump of code, which
basically just calls our main
asynchronous function. Okay,
great. I'm gonna delete all this
for now. But you can still find
that common in the GitHub repo
associated with this course.
Awesome. Okay, so now that we
have our real basic setup, let's
go ahead and start coding. And
if this set apart is confusing,
and the async await stuff is
confusing, don't worry too much
about it. It'll make more sense
as we progress. All of our code
basically is going to be inside
of this async function main,
which is going to be our main
script for deploying our simple
storage dot soul store deploy
script is going to replicate
exactly what goes on in remix,
in remix, what was the first
thing that we always did? Well,
the first thing that we would do
is actually compile all of our
code. So we're going to want to
compile our code in our
JavaScript project as well. In
order for us to compile our
simple storage contract, we're
going to use a tool called Silk
Jas, and JavaScript actually has
a way to install projects
directly into our setups and
into our folders. If we scroll
down this silk Jas is exactly
what we're looking for. Because
it has a way to compile a
contract that imports other
contracts via relative paths,
you can see a section in this
readme and most documentation
will have something like this,
if it's JavaScript compatible.
For Node js usage, it says to
use the latest stable version of
the solidity compiler via Node
js, you can install it via NPM
npm install. So NPM is what's
known as a package manager. And
we actually installed NPM just
by installing no Jess, right, if
we do no dash dash version, you
should also be able to do NPM
dash dash version. Another tool
that it comes with is something
called core pack. And you can
type core pack dash dash
version, now we can install with
NPM using npm install silk,
however, I like the yarn package
manager a little bit better. So
we're actually going to install
the yarn package manager instead
to do all of our package
management. If you go to the
installation page, the newer way
to install yarn is just by
running core pack enable. And
the older way is to install with
NPM. If you go ahead and run
core pack enable after that
finishes, you should be able to
run yarn dash dash version.
Alternatively, you can just run
NPM i dash g core pack, and then
you can run core pack enable.
The last option you have is you
can run NPM i dash g
yarn. This will install yarn
globally for your system. But
this is considered the outdated
way to install yarn. And ideally
you run core pack enable. But in
any case, after you run those,
if you run yarn dash dash
version, you should get
something that looks like this.
Now that we have yarn, we can
actually use yarn to install all
of our projects, instead of NPM.
Back in silk Jas where it says
npm install soak, we can do the
yarn equivalents of NPM install
sock, which is going to be yarn,
add sock, this will actually go
ahead and install solc to our
project. If we open up our
folders, you'll actually see
that this added a couple of
different folders, it first
added a package dot JSON package
dot JSON is a file that tells us
a lot about our project and the
dependencies that it works with.
For example, we've installed the
soap package of 0.8 point 13.
Our yarn dot lock tells us the
exact version of all the
different packages of our
project. For example, the reason
this is so important too, is
solc has a ton of dependencies
as well. So yarn dot lock tells
us exactly what version of solc
and all the different
dependencies of solchen. Any
other project that we add. This
is autogenerated file, don't
edit the file directly. The
final bit is we got this node
modules folder. This node
modules folder is going to be
where all the installed code
that we just downloaded is, for
example, if we look at node
modules, we can see there's a
sock folder. And inside this
sock folder is all the code
associated with this soap
package that we just installed.
And since we're working with
zero point 8.7 of slowly, we
actually want to install that
specific version. So we're going
to do yarn add solc at zero
point 8.7 Dash fixed and you'll
see in our package dot JSON you
can now see zero point 8.7 Dash
fixed in our dependencies
section for sulk. Normally you
can just add your salt version
like yarn add zero point 8.7 But
there was an issue with zero
point 8.7 So we had to do zero
point 8.7 Dash fixed.
You can find the different
releases and the different
versions if you go to sulk Jas
releases and then to tags
Alright, great. Now that we have
sold, we have the ability to
actually compile our contracts,
we could either compile them in
our code and have it
automatically run whenever we
hit Deploy, or, or we could
compile them separately. If you
want to go back after this
section is an example in the
sculpt Jas repository that shows
you how to actually compile silk
right in your code. We are
actually going to compile them
separately using a soap Jas
command. The yarn command is
both used to install
dependencies and it can be used
to run scripts. If you go to
sulk Jas and you scroll down, it
says in order to use the command
line, you actually need to
install it globally. If you want
to install this globally using
yarn Global Add solc at zero
point 8.7 Dash fixed you can
absolutely go ahead. However,
since we're inside of this
folder here, which has the yarn
dot lock the package json and
the node modules yarn will be
smart enough to know i You're
looking for the soak in this
folder. So we can actually go
ahead and compile our contract
using yarn and solc Jess if you
want to see all the different
commands soak Jas allows we can
just run yarn. So Jas dash dash
help, and you'll see it'll spit
out a list of all the different
options that soft Jas has. You
can also run yarn, so Jas dash
dash version to just make sure
that we're on the correct
version, which is indeed zero
point 8.7. Now to actually
compile our simple storage at
soul, let's run the compliation
command we will run yarn, so J
S, dash dash bin since we want
the binary dash dash ABI since
we also want the ABI dash dash
include path node modules. Since
we want to include any contracts
or files in our node modules, we
aren't using any for this
project, but in the future, you
will need to include this dash
dash include path node modules
do dash dash base path of
period, this period means that
the base path is going to be
this folder dash O period, which
means we're going to output the
compiled binary and ABI to this
folder. And then finally, simple
storage dot soul. Since this is
the contract that we want to
compile, auto completed it from
simple storage to simple
storage. So by typing simple,
and then hitting Tab, but let's
go ahead and hit enter, you'll
see it's running this command to
compile this contract. And
you'll see two files get output.
One called Simple Storage soul
underscore simple storage that
API in simple storage Sol
underscore simple storage dot
bin, the ABI is obviously the
ABI of this contract, which will
need in the future. And then the
bin is going to be the binary,
or the really low level of this
code back and remix. If you
compile simple storage, that
soul, you can actually look at
compliation details, like the
ABI which we just got, or the
bytecode, which if you look at
this object 60806 That's the
same as the binary here 60806.
Alright, great. So now we've
compiled our contracts here.
Now, obviously, now if you hit
up on your keyboard, you can
actually cycle through your most
recent terminal commands. And if
you hit up enough, we can see
this command that we just ran
typing this out or hitting up a
whole bunch every single time,
it's going to be really annoying
to do anytime we want to
recompile. So what we can do is
we can add a script section in
our package dot JSON to shorten
some yarn scripts for us. So
what we'll do is back in our
package, dot JSON, a lot of
comma, and we'll add a section
called scripts, add the colon
and the brackets. And in here,
we'll say anytime we say
compile, we will run this long
command. So I'd compile we'll
put some quotes. And we'll paste
that in there. So now instead of