typing that whole thing out, as
long as we're in the same folder
that our package json is in, we
can run yarn compile. And this
will run that whole script for
us without us having to type the
whole thing out scripts are a
really useful way to make it
easier for us to run long
commands. All right, great. Now
we have our code compiled, this
is going to be equivalent to US
hitting this compile button for
us to actually go ahead and
deploy.
So now we have our simple
storage. That's all compiled,
let's learn how we can actually
deploy this thing. Remember, in
remix, we actually deployed it
to one of two different places,
we deployed it to either a
JavaScript VM, or with our
injected web three, with our
Metamask. Let's learn first ad,
do the JavaScript VM. And then
we'll learn how to use the
injected web three, or a meta
mask or some connection to an
actual test net. So in order to
deploy this to a JavaScript
virtual invite I'm in or kind of
a fake blockchain, we're gonna
need to get a fake blockchain.
Now in the future, we're going
to be using the Hardhead runtime
environment as our JavaScript
virtual machine or aka our fake
blockchain. But for this
section, I want us to use a tool
called ganache. There's a link
to this in the GitHub
repository. Ganache is similar
to a virtual machine in remix.
It's a fake blockchain that we
can run locally to actually
test, deploy and run code. It's
also a nice way to see things
that are going on in a
blockchain. Let's go ahead and
spin up the ganache application
after you install it, the
ganache application will look a
little something like this. And
to spin up a fake blockchain
really quickly, you can just go
ahead and click Quickstart. This
will spin up a fake blockchain
that's running locally on your
computer right here, which is
fantastic. It comes with a whole
bunch of fake accounts exactly
like how remix comes with a ton
of fake accounts with 100 ether
each ganache comes with a bunch
each. They also come with the
private keys that we can use in
our applications to actually
take control of these fake
accounts. Remember, don't use
these private keys on a public
blockchain. They're for
development purposes only
because a lot of people know
these private keys in our code.
One of the first things that
we're going to need to do is
actually connect to our
blockchain remix does this a
little bit behind the scenes, if
we're choosing JavaScript
virtual machine remix chooses
its own fake blockchain that it
runs. If we choose injected web
three, as we know, meta mask
pops up, and it connects to our
meta mask, this connection that
remix does, is actually doing
something really interesting.
It's not just connecting to our
meta mask by some magical
powers. It's actually connecting
to our meta mask, which has a
connection to the blockchain
behind the scenes. If you open
up your meta mask, and you go
down to you select the networks
and you select ad networks,
you'll get popped up into a UI
that looks like this. If we go
back and hit select networks
over here, we can actually see
information about these
different networks. One of the
main things that we can see is
that all these networks have
something called an RPC URL. RPC
stands for remote procedure
call. And then URL is uniform
resource locator. This RPC URL
stands for a connection to a
blockchain node that somebody is
running this this URL connects
us to make API calls and to
interact with a blockchain node.
Blockchain nodes run with
software, and some of them
expose an API call. If you look
at the NGO Aetherium website,
there actually are instructions
for you to run your own
blockchain node for a real
blockchain like Aetherium. Most
of these have flags like dash
HTTP dot ADR to expose these RPC
endpoints. So if you ever want
to run your own node, your own
real blockchain node, instead of
using meta masks or any other
the providers that we're going
to go through, you can use go
Aetherium, or whatever
blockchain you're working with
software to run your own notes.
But it's this RPC URL that
allows us to connect to Rinkeby,
if on Rinkeby ropsten, if we're
on ropsten main net if we're on
Main net, etc. And it's going to
be the way that we're going to
connect to our ganache
blockchain that we're running
inside of this application. So
if you look at the top of your
ganache here, there's a section
called the RPC server. And this
is the endpoint of our ganache
node right now. So what we can
do is we can copy this and go
back to our VS code, and paste
it in here to see if we can
connect instead of HTTP. With
these capitals, we're gonna have
a B lowercase instead of the
uppercase, because the lowercase
is more correct, and it looks
nicer. But now we have the
endpoint. Hypothetically, with
just this, we can start making
calls and API calls to this
endpoint, go to this JSON RPC
specification. Again, link will
be in the GitHub repo, we can
actually see different calls we
can make directly to our node to
get different information. eath
get blocked by hash eath get
blocked by number. And all of
these wonderful pieces in here.
Making these API calls directly
is is a little bit annoying to
do ourselves. If you want to do
it yourself, you absolutely can
using an API endpoint like Axios
or fetch. However, we're going
to use a rapper to interact with
our node and do things like
deploy and interact and other
such things with our blockchain
node. This is finally where
ethers comes
into play. Ethers js is one of
the most popular JavaScript
based tooling kits, that allows
us to interact with different
blockchains and has all these
rappers that make all these API
calls and do all these things
with Aetherium, and polygon and
avalanche and any EVM compatible
chain. The other incredibly
popular package that does the
same thing is going to be web
three.js. And you've probably
heard about this and you'll
probably see it a little bit
more throughout this course and
throughout your web three
journey. The reason that we're
using ethers is that ethers is
the main tool that powers the
hard hat environment and I
really enjoy it myself. And
remember, if you ever get lost
with any of this, you can always
come back to their documentation
to install it. As you can see
here, you can just run npm
install ethers, we're just going
to do yarn, add ethers.
And now you should see in your
package json, we now have ethers
added in here. Awesome. Now back
in our code, we're going to
import ethers into our
deployed.js script so that we
can use all the wonderful tools
that comes with so we'll say
const ethers equals require
ethers. For those of you doing
the TypeScript edition of this
course, this will be import
instead of require now that we
have ethers in here, we can
create our provider object in
our main function. The reason we
we pull ethers outside of the
main function is because we do
want to pull our package into
our script. Before we call main,
we want to make sure all of this
is done first. So you'll see
this is kind of the the normal
setup of our scripts. At the
top, we import any dependencies
or external packages, we'll have
our main function, and then
we'll call our main function at
the bottom. const is a keyword
similar to let the const keyword
makes it so that ethers can't be
changed. So we can't change
this. Our ethers variable,
anytime we use const require is
a function for us to import the
ethers package. Now remix does
all this behind the scenes. But
the way we're going to do it in
our code here is we're going to
say const provider equals new
ethers dot providers dot JSON
RPC provider. And then we're
going to pass this string as our
provider. So we're saying hey,
we're going to connect to this
URL right here. Awesome. So this
is the way that our script is
going to connect to our
blockchain, our local
blockchain. Now let's get an
actual wallet here. With a
private key and a balance and
everything, we can see all of
our wallets and private keys in
our ganache here. So the way to
get this set up is we can say
const. Wallet equals new ethers
dot wallet. And this wallet
function takes in a couple of
input parameters, like a private
key, and a provider, the private
key will go to Kenosha and just
choose one of these private
keys. And we're going to paste
this right into our code. And
then we're gonna do comma
provider and save that. Now
pasting your private key
directly into your code is a
huge nono. And we're going to
learn how to avoid this in the
future. It's okay right now,
since we're just using one of
the ganache private keys, and
you have no risk of having any
money associated with this
account. These two lines alone
give us everything that we need
to interact with smart contract,
they give us our connection to
the blockchain, and they give us
a wallet with a private key so
we can sign different
transactions. If you remember
back to our blockchain basics
section. This is the private key
that we're using to sign all of
our transactions to encrypt our
transactions. Now that we have a
provider and a wallet, let's go
ahead and grab our contract
objects from these two files
here. In order to deploy our
contract, we're gonna need the
ABI and we're going to need the
binary compiled code of the
contract. So we're going to need
to read from these two files to
read from these two files, we're
going to need to use a package
called Fs. So back at the top,
we're gonna do const Fs equals
require Fs extra I autosave, all
the time, you'll see like, I'll
do something and then my white
dot will go away a lot. It's
because my fingers have a habit
of pretty much anytime I stop
typing I save so so please
remember to save early and
often, this Fs extra should come
directly with your node project.
But if not, you can always add
it with yarn, add Fs extra, and
you should see it in our package
dot JSON. Now we can get the ABI
and the binary, we can say
const, abi equals Fs dot read
file sync, which means we're
going to synchronously read from
this file, we could do it
asynchronously. But we want to
wait for this file to get done.
So we're gonna say read file
sync. And depending on your VS
code, if you scroll over, you
might even get some information
about this function popup like
this, which can be really
helpful, we can see that we need
the path for the file we want to
read. And then any options as
well path the file that we want
to read the at the ABI located
at dot slash simple storage,
underscore soul underscore
simple storage dot AVI and then
we're going to do a comma of U
T, F eight is UTF. Eight is the
encoding that we do for this
file here. Don't worry too much
about what that means for now.
So we need the ABI. And we also
need the binary, which is in
this second file. Simple Storage
underscore soul underscore
simple storage dot bin. So we're
gonna say const binary equals Fs
dot read file sync. We're gonna
give it the path Hear, which is
going to be dot slash, simple
storage soul, simple storage dot
bin, and then the encoding
option, which again is going to
be, and it should look like
this. Now that we have the
binary, we have the ABI, we can
create something called a
contract factory, which is not
to be confused with the factory
pattern in ethers. A contract
factory is just an object that
you can use to deploy contracts.
So we're gonna say const,
contract factory equals new
ethers dot contract, factory.
And we're going to pass it, the
API binary. And the wallet, we
pass the ABI so that our code
knows how to interact with the
contract the binary, obviously,
because this is the main
compiled code in our wallet so
that we have a private key we
can use to sign deploying this
contract, then I usually like to
write a little console dot log,
saying something like deploying
these wait. And we can actually
deploy this contract with ethers
by doing const. Contract equals
await, contract factory dot
deploy. Now, this is the first
time we've seen this await
keyword and you can only use the
await keyword inside of an async
function. The reason we want
this await keyword we're telling
our code to stop here, wait for
contract to deploy. And this
await keyword means that this
will resolve the promise
contract in this contract
factory dot deploy with the
await here returns a contract
object. So now I could do
something like console dot log
contract. Let's see what happens
when we run this code node
deploy dot j s, we scroll up, we
see deploying, please wait. And
then we see this massive object
that gets printed out. This is
the contract object that we just
deployed. And in fact, if we go
over to our ganache, we can see
that the address that we're used
for our wallet has a little bit
less balance and has a
transaction count of one. If we
were working with truffle, we'd
be able to see the contracts
here we're working with hard
hat, so you won't be able to see
the contracts in here. But if
you go to transactions, we can
indeed see the transaction that
we just created. This is similar
to ether scan. But for our local
blockchain, we can see the
sender address, the creation
address, the value, gas price,
all this stuff associated with
this contract. You can also see
the different blocks. Since
we've only made one transaction
only one block has been mined.
And this is awesome. We have all
this other stuff associated with
it. Great job. You just deployed
a contract to your own local
blockchain with ethers. Jas.
This is fantastic, Awesome work.
Now let me show you what happens
if we don't use the await
keyword here. We're not telling
our code to stop. We're saying
hey, deploy this contract and
then just keep going. So we
never actually checked to see if
this deploy function finished.
So let's see what happens when
we run this instead. Instead of
that big contract object, we get
this promise in its pending
state because our code actually
finished before our contract
could finish deploying. So we
see promise pending here
instead, this is why the await
keyword is so important. We're
saying hey, wait for this to
finish the await keyword also
resolves a promise. So it'll
wait for the promise to exit
it's pending state. And then
it'll return whatever the
pending promise returns. So
contract factory to deploy
returns a promise that returns a
contract. In fact, if we go to
the ethers documentation, we
look up deploy. And here we can
see contract factory methods
contract factory dot deploy. If
we look at the definition of the
function, it says contract
factory dot deploy takes a whole
bunch of arguments and some
overrides this arrow is saying
this is what it returns, it
returns a promise that resolves
to a contract. And that's why we
need this await keyword because
contract factory to deploy by
itself just returns a promise.
But if we do await contract
factory dot deploy, we're saying
it returns a promise that
resolves to a contract. And
we're waiting for it to finish
deploying to resolve to a
contract object. So that's gonna
be a major difference here.
Awesome work. So that's gonna be
why this await keyword is so
important. And again, you can
only do that in asynchronous
functions. So you need this
async keyword at the top of your
function names. Awesome work. So
we've deployed a contract to our
ganache. Shane, this is
fantastic. Let's play with this
a little bit more. So what else
can we do? Remember how in remix
and in Metamask, we could add a
whole bunch of stuff. We could
add a gas limit, we could add
some value when we were doing
our trends. that we could press
the transact button. We know
that when we're working with
Metamask, and we want to send
some money between our accounts,
we can actually choose our gas
price, our priority fee, all
this other stuff, we can
actually do all that in ethers
as well. So if we wanted to
await contract factory to
deploy, but with a certain gas
price, we can add these
overrides in this deploy
function here. Another really
neat trick that your Visual
Studio code might have is if you
click Command or Control,
depending on your setup, you can
actually click into a function
and see where it's defined and
see everything about this
function. So if I command
clicked, I could see that I'm
now in Node modules ethers
project contract source of Ts,
all this stuff. And I can see
exactly the function definition
of this deploy function on the
contract factory object, which
shows us the same code as what
we saw in the documentation. We
see we have a deploy function,
it takes some arguments, and
then it returns this little
semicolon means it returns a
promise that resolves to a
contract, which is really nice.
These are in here are actually a
list of overrides that we can
specify with some brackets. So
what we can do is we can put
some brackets in our deploy
function here and specify
certain things like for example,
we can specify the gas price to
being some number. And now if we
were to run this, we would
deploy this contract with a gas
price of this, we could add a
gas limit, we can add a whole
bunch of different overrides in
our deploy function here. Well,
what else can we do? Well, we
can wait for a certain number of
blocks for our contract finish
with so we've deployed the
contract. But maybe we want to
wait one block to make sure it
actually gets attached to the
chain. So we can say const.
Deployment received equals
await, contract dot deploy
transaction dot Wait, and
specify the number of
confirmations that we want to
actually wait. So we'll wait one
block confirmation to make sure
that this happened. And then we
can do console dot log, this
deployment receipt option. So if
we run the code now, we can see
all this information about our
transaction, and we can see
exactly what our transaction
looks like, we can see there's
two is no because we're creating
a contract from is going to be
this ganache address that we got
the private key for, we see the
contract address that we created
transaction index, we can see
gas use gas use log bloom block
hash transaction, and we can see
all this information about our
transaction, something I want
you to take note of is the
deployment receipt and the
deployment transaction, I want
you to separate these two
because it's going to make your
life a lot easier. So we're
going to do quick console dot
log, here is the deployment
transaction. And then we'll do
console dot log contract, dot
deploy transaction. And then I'm
going to copy this whole line by
just typing Command C or Ctrl. C
right there. And then here is
the deployment. Here is the
transaction receipt. And then
this deployment is receipt is
the transaction receipt. So I'm
just going to rename this to
transaction receipt. To make it
a little bit clearer, which ones
which, and we'll run this one
more time. You only get a
transaction receipt, when you
wait for a block confirmation.
Otherwise, you're gonna get the
contract object, which has the
deploy transaction with it, this
distinction will be more
important later on. But I wanted
you to know what the difference
between the two transaction
receipt is what you get when you
wait for a block confirmation,
the deployment transaction or
the transaction response,
transaction response is what you
get just when you create your
transaction. So transaction
receipts transactional response,
they're different receipt is
what you get when you wait for a
transaction to finish. And then
response is just what you
initially get. Make sense? Okay,
great. We're gonna go ahead and
delete those. But those lines
will be in the code associated
with the GitHub. Now you saw
when we actually printed out
those receipts, we got all this
stuff in here, because deploying
a contract is actually just
sending a transaction, as we've
said before, so if we want to
see what's really going on under
the hood, we can actually create
a transaction ourselves and
create a contract ourselves just
by specifying the transaction
information. So how will we do
that? Let's deploy this contract
again, but only purely using
transaction data. So we'll do a
console dot log.
Let's deploy with only
transaction data. And this is
going to be the way you can
actually deploy or send
transactions purely with
transaction data you can send
any transaction this gives you
unlimited flux. ability with the
transactions you want to send,
what we can do is we can say
const, or let TX which is going
to stand for our transaction
equals, and we can just add all
of our transaction information
in here. So the first thing that
we're going to need is our nuts,
or the number that we only use
once we go back to our
transaction count, we're on four
transactions here. So we'll use
the nonce five, because that's
going to be a nonce that we
haven't used before. Every time
you send a transaction, it comes
with one of those nonces. Right,
so the nonce is a bit of a over
overused term, we saw it back in
our blockchain basics that we
use the nonce to solve that hard
problem. nonces are also used in
wallets and in signers, to send
transactions and they use a
different nones for every
transaction. So nonce, when
we're talking about wallets
talks about a number associated
with a unique transaction.
nonce, when we're talking about
blockchain mining is a value
used to solve that hard problem,
they both mean the same thing.
They both mean a number only
used once. But they're different
in these different contexts. So
we're going to use this number
only use once this unique number
for a transaction to send this,
so we're going to say nonce is
going to be five, we're going to
pick a gas price of, of this
right here, we're just going to
use the gas price of ganache
like that, we're going to pick a
gas limit of some big number,
we'll use 1123456, we'll just
use that we're gonna say two is
going to be no, right, exactly
like what we saw in our receipts
and responses down here. Since
we're creating a contract value
is going to be zero. Since we're
creating a contract, we don't
want to send an ether polygon or
avalanche. And then data is
going to be that massive binary
object in our binary bit. So in
the binary section, we're gonna
copy this massive binary piece,
and we're going to put some
quotes in here, we're gonna do
0x, and paste that in here. So
this massive, massive data piece
is the binary that we're
sending. Whenever you send a
transaction, you have this this
data object that you can fill
this stuff, we're filling our
data object with the binary with
the code that tells the theory
that tells our blockchain to
deploy our smart contract that's
going to look exactly like this.
And then finally, we want to add
the chain ID.
As we've seen before with
Metamask, if we go back over to
our networks, each one of these
EVM chains has a different chain
ID Etherium. Main net is one
ropsten is three Rinke, B is
four COVID is 42, etc. And other
EVM chains like avalanche like
polygon, are going to have their
unique chain IDs as well, or
ganache, we can see the network
ID appear is 1337 in some
people, so we can just paste
that in here. Some people have
run into some issues where the
chain ID and the network ID are
different. And the chain ID is
actually 31337. So if you have a
problem with this, try 31337
instead, but it should be 1337.
Now this is a transaction with
all this information propagated,
which is awesome. However, this
transaction isn't signed. So
nobody's sending this
transaction right now this is
just the transaction details of
what somebody wants to do, we
actually need to sign this
transaction, and then send it to
our blockchain. Cons sign, TX
response equals await, wallet
dot sign transaction, and we can
pass that TX object. And then
we'll do a console dot log of
the sign TX response in
JavaScript. Same as solidity. If
you type two backslashes, before
some code, it won't run that
code. So I'm gonna go ahead and
comment out the three lines
above. And the way that I'm
doing it is by highlighting the
sections and hitting Command
backslash, or you might hit Ctrl
backslash, but this is a
keyboard shortcut you can use to
quickly comment out entire
sections. And the reason I'm
doing this is because I want to
show you what happens when we
just run scientex response
wallet that signed transaction
back in nosh, we see that we
have four blocks in here. Let me
ask if we do this sign
transaction and we get the
signed transaction response,
will we propagate another block?
Well, let's find out run no
deploy.js, we get this massive
thing here. But if we go back to
ganache refresh, we actually
don't see another transaction
sent. That's because we're only
signing a transaction here,
we're not actually sending it.
So the signed transaction
response. This big number here
represents a signed transaction
but not a cent transaction,
which is different. You can
actually send one of these
transactions by changing this
line a little bit. So instead of
scientex response, we'll change
this to send TX response equals
await wallet dot send
transaction TX then once We send
the transaction here, we can do
a wait, send transaction
response, that Wait, one, we're
gonna wait one block
confirmation to make sure this
transaction actually goes
through. And we can run node.js.
And it looks like it's done. But
if we actually scroll up, we
actually got an error here. So
there's this huge, massive thing
here. And if we scroll up, we'll
eventually see TX reject error,
the TX doesn't have the correct
nuts, which just for some
practice, let's go ahead, type
this into Google and see what we
get. We actually get a web three
Jas from four years ago, trying
to call leaf picked, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah. It looks like this is a
meta mask issue that they ran
into. And they said, you have to
reset your account in meta mask,
which we could do. But let's
make this a little bit more
specific. Let's say ethers. JS
looks like we don't get it looks
like as of right now, from this
recording, we don't get a Stack
Exchange eath or a Stack
Overflow question for this
trolley, because this is pretty
straightforward. We don't have
the correct nonce for our
transaction. But this would be a
good time to actually make this
a question on Stack Overflow or
Stack Exchange Aetherium so that
it shows up first. So we
actually don't get the correct
nuts, we're going to want to
make this a nonce of four you
can see here account has a nonce
of four TX has a nonce of five.
So we actually would want this
to be four. Now an easier way to
always get the correct nonce
here is going to be actually
just calling the transaction
count from the wallet. So back
in the ethers documentation,
there's actually some good
samples here on how to assigning
a message and then how to
actually send these messages. So
we can do a weight wallet dot
get transaction count to get the
nuts. So back in our code, we
could do const nuns equals
await, oops, copy pasted, await
wallet dot get transaction
count. And then we can just
place the nonce right here.
Now, let's try running this
again. And it looks like this
one did indeed go through. We
can verify on ganache here. We
do indeed see we're currently on
block five now and we have one
extra transaction. Now we could
go ahead and just run this
again. And we'll never have to
worry about actually updating
this nonce ourselves. Since
we're just calling wallet dot
get transaction count to keep
updating it current block is six
and the our additional
transaction has indeed gone
through awesome. I showed you
how to actually sign the
transaction. But we didn't sign
the transaction for our central
injection. Well, why not? If you
command click or control click,
or you go to the documentation
for ethers, we can see the code
for send transaction. So first,
it does some check provider
stuff. There's some stuff to
populate the transaction. But we
can actually see that before it
sends the transaction even in
ethers, it signs the transaction
first, and then calls this dot
provider dot send transaction.
So if you just call send
transaction with the transaction
details like we did here, it's
the same as signing it first and
then sending it with the
provider. Okay, great. So we've
learned how to send a
transaction using pure
JavaScript and using pure
ethers. One of the main
takeaways from this is that
every time we change the
blockchain, every time we change
state, every time we use gas,
we're sending a transaction that
looks pretty much exactly like
this, the data is going to be
the differentiator, the data for
us here was data saying to
create a new contract, when we
make transactions, like adding
people or storing the data that
we're going to be passing in our
transaction is going to be data
associated with calling these
functions. And when we actually
call functions in ethers, or in
Hardhead. We're not going to do
this kind of raw const, TX, and
list out all the stuff like here
and list out the raw data,
right? Because that's really,
really hard ethers and hard hat
are going to make this process a
lot easier. So for now, let's go
ahead, comment out this whole
section, which again, if we copy
this whole thing, and then hit
Command, slash, or control
slash, or whatever the shortcut
is on your environment, that'll
actually comment this out. Let's
go ahead and uncomment this
section so that we deploy our
contract using kind of the ether
is much easier to read way than
this weird TX stuff. Oh, cool.
So we've changed our script back
to deploy our contracts like
this. Now that we've actually
deployed our contract, we can
learn how to interact with our
contract through code as well,
the same way that we click these
buttons in remix, we're going to
code it out for ourselves here.
So if we look at symbol storage,
we have a button for add person
for store. And then we have
these view functions as well.
The easiest one is going to be
the Retrieve function, which
grabs our favorite number,
retrieve returns favorite
number. So we can call that in
ethers by doing const. current
favorite number equals await.
contract.we retrieve. The
contract object that we have is
what's returned from our
contract factory as long as
we've awaited it the contract
object is going to come with all
the functionality described in
our API. That's why we had to
pass the API to our contract
factory. If we look inside our
API piece here, we can see it
has a ton of information on the
different functions that we can
call and the types that it has
and the return types and
everything like that. For
example, if I look up retrieve,
I can see down here, we have
retrieve, we can see that the
name of this function is going
to be retrieved. And the outputs
are going to be a un 256, of
type Nuun 256. Now, this is a
little bit difficult to read
because it's not formatted.
Since we call this dot API, it's
going to be a little bit hard to
read. But we could change it the
dot JSON. And then you'll see
it's highlighted a little bit, I
can even do format document with
prettier. And you'll see it
actually formats to be a lot
easier to read now and go back
to retrieve. And we can see,
this block of code here defines
what the Retrieve function can
and can't do. I'm going to
change it back to abi. And it
looks like my formatting has
stayed, which is great. This is
much easier to read than it was
before. As I said, the ABI or
the application binary interface
is incredibly important for
working with our contracts. If
we give our code just this huge
bytecode thing, it's gonna be
really hard for any processor to
decompile this or understand
what exactly what the functions
are that are going on here.
There are decompiler options out
there, like ether VM, that IO
slash decompile. That can
decompile some bytecode into the
solidity. But it can be really
tricky to get it exactly right.
So it's much easier just to have
the ABI to say, hey, this lump
of code, this lump of numbers
and garbled nonsense is this.
When we deploy this bytecode to
the blockchain, and we call
functions on it, the code will
automatically allow those
functions to get called if they
do exist. But in order for our
code to know that they exist,
it's much easier just to give it
the API. So we can get our
current favorite number like
this. Let's go ahead and console
dot log, the current favorite
number. Now that we've edited
this code, we're going to let me
zoom out a little bit. Now that
we've edited this code, we're
going to connect organ nosh
instance, we're going to connect
a wallet with a private key that
we got from the top of our
ganache here, we're gonna grab
the ABI and the binary of our
contracts, and connect them to a
new contract factory object,
which is connected to that
wallet. So that wallet will be
the one to actually deploy the
contract, we'll deploy the
contract with const contract
equals await contract factory
dot deploy, we will wait one
block for that transaction to
finish. And in fact, we're not
going to use transaction
receipt. So for now, we're just
going to delete that part. We're
not going to do any of this
here. So I'm going to delete it
for now. However, I'll leave
this section commented out in
the GitHub repo. And then we're
going to call contract retrieve
which should return our current
favorite number. Since this is a
view function, this contract
call won't cost us any gas. If
we look at simple storage, that
soul we can see retrieve is a
view function. And remember view
and pure functions, if called
outside of a contract function
call don't cost any gas, we're
just reading up the blockchain,
we're not changing any variables
on chain, we're not changing the
state of the blockchain. So this
won't cost any gas. So let's go
ahead and run this. Perfect, we
get deploying, please wait. And
then we get this big number
response. So what's this big
number response here? Big number
is a library that comes with the
ethers application that helps us
work with numbers. If you
actually scroll down, they even
have a section saying why can I
just use numbers, you'd expect
current favorite number to just
be zero, but it returns this
weird hex thing that says his
big number true this weird, big
number thing. So solidity can't
use decimal places, and
JavaScript has a hard time with
decimal places. And this is kind
of the more specific rationale
for why not to use numbers, what
you'll see a lot of the time
instead of numbers is you'll see
strings like zero, you'll see
JavaScript use strings like
this, or big numbers. Now, if I
were to try to pass a number
like this in JavaScript, this
number would be too big for
JavaScript to understand. So we
want to use big numbers or
strings when working with
ethers. Now we can make this
more readable by adding.to
string at the end and printing
out the string version of this
big number. Now, if I rerun this
code, we can see we get zero,
which makes sense again, because
our favorite number gets
initialized to the zero value,
if not specified, and we haven't
called store yet. So awesome. So
that is, that's working
perfectly. So this is what our
current favorite number is.
Let's make this console dot log
a little bit more syntactical.
We're going to use something
called string interpolation. So
we can interpolate our string
here with variables. Typically
in JavaScript when working with
strings, use double quotes.
However, if you want to mix
variables with actual strings,
you can use backticks instead.
So we're going to use some that
backticks here, and we're gonna
say current favorite number to
call in here. And to tell
JavaScript that this is a
variable that we want to read,
we put a little dollar sign and
a bracket around it, like this.
Now, if we run this code again,
it's saying deploying, please
wait, and we get current
favorite number is zero, because
JavaScript goes, Okay, this is a
string, ah, dollar sign, curly
brace looks like this is going
to be some variable or some
JavaScript that you want me to
interpret and close it off, and
then backtick. Cool. So our
current favorite number is going
to be zero. Great. So let's
update on the contract the
number by calling the store
function. So we'll say const,
transaction response equals
await, contract dot store, and
we'll add seven. Now since seven
is a small number, you can just
pass it like seven. But passing
it like seven in a string also
works. Again, this is because if
we want to pass some crazy
massive number, JavaScript would
get confused. So it's usually
best practice to pass variables
to contract functions as
strings, even though that might
be a little bit confusing ethers
is smart enough to know that
this seventh string is actually
seven the number then we can do
const. Transaction received
equals await transaction
response that Wait, one. So
we'll wait one block here. This
is similar to us doing contract
dot deploy transaction dot Wait,
the syntax here is a little bit
different than what we saw up
here. Because this is using a
contract factory. And this is
calling a function on a
contract. So when we call the
function on the contract, we get
a transaction response. When we
wait for the transaction
response to finish, we get the
transaction receipt. Now I can
do const, updated, favorite
number two equals await on track
dot retrieve. And then console
dot log updated. favorite number
is, and we'll do a little string
interpolation, updated, favorite
number like that? Now let's go
ahead and run this. So in this
process, what are we doing,
we're deploying the contract,
we're getting the initial value,
we're going to update our
contract by calling store which
is going to cost gas. So this is
a transaction, we're going to
get the transaction response,
then we're gonna get the
transaction receipt, we're not
going to do anything with the
transaction receipt, I want to
ingrain in you all that these
two are different transaction
response and transaction
receipt, and you'll see why in
the future. And then we'll get
the updated favorite number, and
then we're just going to print
it out. So let's do this. Boom,
and perfect. Deploying, please
wait, current favorite number is
zero, updated favorite number is
seven. And if we go to our
ganache instance, we go to
transactions, we can see, we now
have a contract call at the top,
we have the sender, the contract
address, the gas price, all this
stuff, and we see our
transaction data right here. So
this transaction data is what
gets sent in that data slot of
our transaction object. Ethers
is just doing that on the back
end for us so that we don't have
to make that big transaction
object there. All right,
awesome. You've successfully
deployed a contract to your own
local ganache instance, or your
own JavaScript virtual machine.
This is great.
Now let's clean this up a little
bit. Because if we look up here,
we have both our connection to
the blockchain and our private
key stored directly in our code,
we were to push this code up to
a GitHub or some other code
repository, if you will, will be
able to see our code. If we look
into ploy dot j s of my code,
ah, there's something else in
here, we don't actually see the
private key or the RPC URL in
here. So what's going on?
Remember, if you give out your
private key, whoever has your
private key owns your funds. So
even though this is a fake,
private key that doesn't have
any real money in it, we still
don't want to have to hard code
our private keys into our code,
just in case we accidentally
share code with somebody. So
what can we do? Well, one of the
most popular methods is actually
creating something called a dot
EMV file or an environment
variable. And if you're familiar
with environment variables, you
can actually set them right in
your terminal, but we're gonna
set them in our dot env. So what
you want to do is you're gonna
want to create a dot env file.
And this is going to be a file
where you store its sensitive
information. And this is going
to be a file, we're never going
to share this with anybody. This
dot env file will stick
variables of our choosing into
the environment of our code. So
for example, if I pull up my
terminal here, and I do echo
cat, this is going to reflect
what the cat environment
variable is for us. Right now
there is no cat environment
variable. However, if I do
export, cat equals dog, and now
I do echo dollar sign cat, I get
dog output. This is what an
environment variable is, it's a
variable in our terminal or in
our scripting environment, since
I don't want to have to type
export, private key equals blah,
blah, blah, every time, what
we're going to do instead is
we're going to stick them into
this dot env file. So when this
dot env, we can put private key
equals. And we can grab this
private key from our script, and
paste it in like this. And a
note, some tools look for the
0x, at the beginning of the
private key ethers, and hard hat
is smart enough that either one
works, but if you run into some
issues, just know that sometimes
you might have to put your 0x at
the front of this. Great. So now
we have a private key in an
environment variable. What do we
do now? Well, in our deploy.js,
we want to grab this environment
variable and stick it into our
script here, so that our script
can then stick it into our
environment. So we're going to
add a tool called dot env. To
make this easier, so we're gonna
do yarn, add dot env. And if we
look at the dot env package, can
read more about it and read
about how to add it with NPM.
Again, we're just using yarn
add. But then we can just call
this require dot E and V dot
config. And this will pull in
all our environment variables.
So we can just do require
dot EMV config, we should see
this on our package that JSON,
we do. Excellent. Now that we
pulled it in, we actually get
access to our private key
environment variable, you can
access environment variables in
JavaScript, are using process
dot EMV. So instead of putting
our private key here, we're
gonna delete that whole thing
and substitute it with process
dot EMV, that private key, and
we'll save and it'll reformat
for us to make sure this is
actually working, we can just
hit up after we save up, up up
up up a bunch and go back to no
deploy to Jas. And we see we get
the exact same setup. And if we
scroll back, you can see a
transaction has indeed gone
through. If you want to double
check that this is actually
printing out your private key,
we could do console dot log,
press study and via private key
we run, we see that that is
indeed the private key coming
from our environment variable
here. Awesome. Now our RPC URL
here is isn't really something
that we need to secure however,
maybe we're going to use a
certain API key or maybe a
certain endpoint that only we
want to have access to. And we
don't want anybody else to be
using our RPC endpoint. So we're
going to add this to our dot env
file as well. So in our dot env.
When I copy this here, I'm gonna
say RPC URL equals, and I paste
that in there, just like that.
And we're gonna delete here. And
we're gonna do the exact same
thing, say process dot e NV dot
RPC URL. And now we're going to
run this again. And I'm going to
take out that console dot log.
And we should get the exact same
response because all we did was
swap out our RPC URL with our
environment variable, which is
going to be exactly what it was
before. So we go ahead and run
this, and we get the exact same
response. And if we go to
ganache, we see that we do
indeed get a transaction here,
which is perfect. Awesome. So
we've learned how to add
environment variables to our dot
env file. So that so that just
in case, we want to share our
code, or we push our code up to
GitHub, which we'll do in later
sections, we don't accidentally
expose our private keys or our
RPC URLs. Now all the code that
we have in our project here, if
we push it up to GitHub, or
share it with somebody else, all
this code will get pushed up,
including our dot env file.
However, if you look at my code
samples here for this course, we
don't see a dot env file in
here. So how is that possible?
Well, what we want to do
whenever we have a project is
create a dot Git ignore file.
And in here, we want to put in
v. And we also want to put in
Node modules. This means that
when working with Git and
working with version control,
which we're going to do a little
bit later, we won't push our dot
env file up to GitHub. And we
also won't push up known
modules. So if we go back to my
example here, we don't see, we
don't see a dot env file, but we
do see a dot env dot example,
just to show you what one would
look like. So it doesn't really
matter that I have them in here.
Now, if you're really paranoid,
there's something else you can
actually do when running your
scripts and running your
commands. Let's say you didn't
want to put your private key
into a dot env file because you
were nervous that you would
accidentally push it up or
something. What you can do is
you can add your private key in
your RPC URL as environment
variables right in the command
line. So before you run Node
deploy, that's as well you can
do, you can say RPC URL equals,
paste your RPC around. And then
you can say private key. equals
and then paste your private key
and then do node deploy.js.
Setting these right before we
run our script is the exact same
as if we had set them into dot
env. Here If we hit run, we see
the exact same output, which
means that our RPC URL and our
private key went through
successfully. This way for key
management is fine. But our
rights doing this, it's going to
be much better. But it still
makes me a little bit nervous in
our development environments
with our fake private keys,
having our code in the dot env
file like this is, is okay,
right? Because we don't really
care if this key gets hacked,
like nobody's using it. But when
we move to a more professional
setup, this can be a little bit
scary. So how can we make this
even more secure? Well, what we
can do is actually we can
encrypt our private key and
store our encrypted key locally.
That way, if for some reason
somebody does get into our
account, our private key isn't
just sitting around in plain
text, it's encrypted. And you'll
need to know a password that
only you know to get into it. So
how do we add that? Well, first,
we're going to create a new file
called encrypt key.js. And this
is some code that we're going to
use to actually encrypt a key.
And we'll store that locally
instead of our private key in
plain text. This will make us
even more secure so that we
don't have our private key just
hanging around in plain text
here. So let's go ahead and
build the script to encrypt our
private key. So we're going to
use the exact same setup as we
did for our deploy script. We're
going to do an async function
main.
And then down here, I'm just
gonna go ahead and copy from
deployed J S. We're gonna use
this exact same setup, and paste
it. Okay, great. We're gonna be
using ethers J, s, and r dot E
and V again. So we're going to
add these in const ethers equals
require ethers const, FS equals
require Fs extra. And then
require dot env. Config.
Alright, so right now, in our
dot env, we do have this private
key. And again, if you don't
want to have the private key in
their way you can just do is you
can do private key equals and
then you know, node, whatever
script you want to run. So we're
going to set this script up to
run our encrypt key one time.
And then we can remove our
private key from anywhere in our
workspace so that it's no longer
in plain text anywhere. So what
we want to do is we want to say
const wallet, and we're gonna
create a new wallet, but a
little bit differently. We're
gonna say equals new ethers dot
wallet, process dot E and V dot
private key. So we do need our
private key to stick in here.
But then once we create this
wallet, we're gonna say const.
Encrypted JSON key equals await
ethers dot encrypt, this encrypt
function is going to return an
encrypted JSON key that we can
store locally and that we can
only decrypt it with the
password. And it takes two
parameters. It takes a private
key password and a private key.
So in our dot EMV, just for
right, now we're going to create
a private key password. And I'm
going to say it's password. But
obviously, this is a terrible
password. And you should never
use password as your password.
But for now, we're just going to
leave it as password since I'm
encrypting this big key anyways.
So we're going to encrypt it by
passing the password process
study and v dot private key
password. And we're also going
to pass the private key, it's
going to be ethers, it's going
to be wallet dot encrypt. We're
also going to pass it process
dot EMV dot private key. Now
let's go ahead and run this
right now. And then we'll
console dot log out this
encrypted JSON key and see what
happens when we run this. So to
run this, we're going to do
node, encrypt key.js. And hit
enter. And we'll see what
happens when we console log it
out this JSON object here is
what our key looks like,
encrypted. So it's got the
address this ID version, all
this other stuff. And all this
other stuff is the encrypted
version of this key. If somebody
gets into our account and they
see this, they'll have to know
the password to decrypt this
private key, they'll need to
know the password to decrypt
this JSON object back into a
private key. So what we're going
to do, now that we've encrypted
it, we're going to save it. So
we'll do Fs dot write, file
sync, we're going to pass it to
dot slash dot encrypted key dot
JSON, comma encrypted JSON key.
So we're saving it to a new file
called dot encrypted key dot
JSON. And we're passing it this
encrypted key that we just made.
So if we open up our file
explorer, and we run this
command,
you'll see we get a new file
called dot encrypted key dot
JSON. And it's this encrypted
key here, which is awesome. So
now what we want to do in our
dot Git ignore is add dot
encrypted key dot JSON, so that
we don't accidentally push this
up to GitHub. And now we have an
encrypted key and we can go to
our private key and delete this
from our dot env file. We can
also delete our private key
password from our WMV file so
that the password isn't just
hanging around in plain text.
Now that We have an encrypted
key. Back in our deploy script,
we can change the way that we
actually get a wallet. So at the
top, we're getting our wallet
just by passing in the private
key like this, we're not going
to do that, we're going to use
our encrypted key that we just
created. So we're going to do is
we're going to say const
encrypted JSON equals Fs dot
read file sync. That slash dot
encrypted key dot JSON, comma
UTF eight, this Fs dot read file
sync is just going to read from
our encrypted key dot JSON into
this encrypted JSON variable
here. Next, we're going to
create a wallet from this
encrypted key. We're gonna say
let wallet equals new ethers dot
wallet, dot from encrypted JSON
sync. And all these commands
that we're working with ethers,
we can of course, find them in
the documentation from encrypted
JSON sync takes the encrypted
JSON and a password and returns
a Wallet Object. So we're going
to pass it that encrypted JSON
that we just read. And then
we're going to pass it password
which we're going to do process
dot EMP dot private key
password. And then finally, the
reason I use let here is because
now we have to connect this
wallet back to our provider. If
you look here, we're not
connecting our wallet with a
provider. When we make our
transactions with our contract
factory, we need to make sure
the wallet knows about the
provider here. So we can just
say wallet equals await wallet
dot connect provider. Now, if we
run our deploy dot j s with our
private key password as an
environment variable, it should
still deploy. So we can do
private key password equals
password, which yes, we know is
terrible. But that's what we're
using for now node deploy dot j
s, we should get the same output
we've been seeing this whole
time and we do we're able to no
longer have our private key in
our dot env file not in
plaintext anymore, it's in this
encrypted key. So that just in
case somebody hacks our
computer, they still won't be
able to send in new transactions
unless they know the password.
This is awesome. One more thing
to know, if you type history, if
somebody got into your computer,
a hacker could actually see
private key password equals
password in your bash history.
If you run history, dash c, you
actually will clear your
history. Now if I type history,
I can just see that the most
recent command I wrote was
history, this is really just
some of the bare minimum for
encryption and keeping your key
safe. And it might seem
ridiculous that somebody might
be able to hack your computer
and read your encrypted private
keys and everything. But as your
projects get bigger and bigger,
it is really important to know
about private key security and
private key safety and, and for
this course really just giving
you the bare minimum here and
showing you how to encrypt keys
and how to be a little bit safer
here. Now for the rest of this
course, we are going to be just
using this syntax with our
private key in a dot env file.
The reason why we're doing like
this for the rest of the course
is it is a little bit easier,
I'm really hoping Hardhead add
some additional features to make
private key encryption much
safer and also easier to use in
the future. And they probably
will. And the other reason that
we're okay to do this here is
because you've solemnly sworn
that you're not going to use an
account that has any real money
in it for the duration of this
course, you're only going to use
private keys that have tests on
Aetherium or are fake private
keys like this one that we got
from ganache. In fact just to
really hone this in in the smart
contract kit slash full blocked
in solidity course, Jas GitHub
repo in the discussions tab, you
go to announcements, I've
created one called the dot end
pledge. Because recently I've
seen too many people follow a
tutorial that doesn't tell them
about the security risks of
doing this. And I've made this
dot EMV pledge, I would love
everyone to jump on and read.
And if you agree, at the bottom,
leave a comment saying I will be
safe, I will be safe, make sure
you read and you understand
what's going on in here. And I'm
not doing this to scare you.
Because again, at the end of the
day, if you use a Metamask that
only has tests that funds for
the duration of this course, you
will never have to be worried
because of your key gets
compromised. It's just test it.
So who cares? This is if you're
using a meta mask or you're
working with a meta mask that
has real funds. So I'm going to
read up the pledge because it is
really important. You understand
this when you're working with
real funds. And if you're like,
Hey, I'm not working with real
funds, I don't care, great move
past this, whatever. But when
you do work with real funds,
when you do decide, hey, I
actually want to deploy this to
a real network. Now I need real
money to do that. Come back to
this pledge. Scroll the bottom
say I will be safe and make sure
you read and you understand
this. Okay, so the pledge is, I
solemnly swear that I will never
place a private key or secret
phrase or pneumonic in a dot env
file that is associated with any
real funds. Basically, you
basically never have your
private key or your pneumonic
phrase, in plain text, anywhere.
You'll all only place private
keys in a web file that only
have tested e FF link or other
cryptocurrencies. Because again,
if your private key has only
test net funds, then that's
great. I don't care, we are
aware that if we forget a dot
Git ignore, and we push our key
phrase to GitHub, even for a
split second, or even show our
key slash phrase on the
internet, wherever it may be for
a split second, it should be
considered compromised. And you
should remove all funds
immediately. So even if you
deploy your private key to a
website, and then immediately
delete your website and think,
Oh, nobody probably got to it,
you should consider that private
key compromised, and you should
remove all your funds. And
again, this is just for real
funds. If your private key was
only tested, funds gets
compromised. Well, who cares? I
do that all the time, you've
been seeing me do that all the
time, because it only has tested
funds in it. If at the end of
this course, you want to steal
all of my tests that funds I
mean, have a blast, it would be
annoying to me at worst. If I'm
unsure if my account has real
funds in it, I will assume it
has real funds in it. So if you
don't know if it has real funds,
assume it has real funds, and
you will not use it for
developing purposes. And then
finally, I am aware that even if
I hit Add Account on my meta
mask or other eath wallet, I
will get a new private key, but
it will share the same secret
phrase slash pneumonic of all
the other accounts generated in
the meta mask or other eath
Wallet. So if I'm in my meta
mask here, and I hit Create
account, I will get a new
private key with the new
account. However, all of these
accounts that I've created with
this Create Account button have
the exact same pneumonic phrase
or secret phrase. If I import an
account with a private key, it's
going to have a different
pneumonic phrase. But all of the
ones that I generate inside the
wallet are all going to have the
same phrase. Okay, great.
Hopefully that'll make sense. I
have some pledge additions here.
For this course, I will only use
funds associated with a brand
new never before use meta mask
or other eath wallet. Again,
this is not to scare you, if you
just work with a brand new meta
mask, you don't have to worry
about any of this and just refer
back to this when you start
looking at real money and real
private keys. I'm aware that my
account associated with my
private key is the same on test
nets that it is on Main nets. So
like I was showing you, my
private key on Rinkeby is going
to be the same as my private key
I'm on a main net, if I must use
a private key associated with
real funds in the future, until
I am 100% sure what I am doing,
I will always either use one of
the encrypted methods that
Patrick showed you some better
encryption stuff that I didn't
show or use the command line way
to pass private keys and then
delete the command line history
right after. If I'm never
actually deploying anything to
make that myself or work with a
private key with real funds. I
do not need to be concerned.
Take a look at this. Read this
internalize it, it should make
you confident. Now again, I'm
not saying this to scare you.
I'm saying this to instill
confidence in you that these are
some of the things that we want
to think about. Okay, great. In
here, I will be safe.
Boom, I will be safe. And if you
want to copy paste this on
Twitter, put this in a huge
tweet thread. Go for it. The
more people who know about this,
the more people who understand
the security risks of their WMV
files and their private keys,
the better. So thank you for
listening to this. I know I
definitely belabor the point,
but it is really important.
Let's continue with the course.
Alright, so we're just about
done here. However, there's one
or two more things we want to do
just to clean this all up right
now when we're auto saving
reason, the VS code plugin for
us to auto format. However, in
the future, if anybody else
comes across our repository,
they might not have the Vyas
code auto format or on. So we
want to give users a way to
format their code. So it matches
the styles that we use. So we
have prettier the extension
installed. We can also add
prettier as a Node js module
that can tell other users who
don't have a Vyas code exactly
how to format both their
JavaScript and the solidity.
There is a prettier plugin
solidity located here, there
will be a link to it in our
GitHub repo. And if we scroll
down, we can see how to install
with npm install dash dash save
Dev, which again, we're just
going to use yarn, so we're
going to do yarn, add prettier,
and then prettier plugin
solidity. So we're installing
both prettier, and the solidity
plugin for prettier. And if we
check our package, JSON, we can
see that these two have been
added. And what we can do now is
we can create a new file called
dot prettier, R C. And in this
file, we can define some little
curly braces. And here, we can
define what we want for both our
solidity and for a JavaScript,
so for example, our simple
storage has a tab width of