412344 spaces. Maybe we want to
change that. We want tab width
to be two. So we would save it
here and come back to simple
storage To save it here, and it
would get auto formatted to r
dot prettier RC. So in our
settings here, we have the
default editor for solidity, our
hard hat, solidity plugin, and
the default for meta for
JavaScript being the prettier
vs. Code one, when we add
prettier RC in here, this file
will take precedent over the
default configuration, so long
as we have downloaded the module
in our node modules, which we
can see it right here. And we
have this dot prettier rc file.
I'm going to keep the tab with
form. So we're going to update
it to that one thing that we
currently do have that I do not
like is these semicolons at the
end, so we're going to do semi
boss, and I'm going to save
this, come back to deploy it
save and you'll see the
semicolon automatically goes
away. I'm also going to add use
tabs false, since I want to use
spaces or spacing, and then
single quote, false. This way,
we'll always use a double quote,
instead of a single quote, in
JavaScript, you can actually use
the single quote or double
quote, to define strings, but
we're going to make it so that
no matter what quote you use,
it'll always be double quote.
And then for all your open
source repos, and for all your
projects that you make, you want
to make a readme.md readme files
are generally where people put
instructions or information
about your project or anything
like that. This way, whenever
anybody comes across your
project, they'll know what it's
about your readme dot MDs, our
Markdown syntax again, remember
how when we made that trial
discussion, we use some
interesting tips to format our
solidity in our code here. Well,
that formatting process is the
exact same for.md files for
markdown. They're both going to
use markdown. In fact, if we hit
Ctrl, Shift V, you'll enter
preview mode for the markdown
you'll see pound sign here in my
preview of the hard hat. This
ethers simple storage FCC is
huge. And it looks like a
heading at the top. So Command
Shift V to view your.md files or
or MIP Ctrl, Shift V for Windows
and Linux users.
The last thing that we're going
to do is we're going to deploy
this to a test net and interact
with this on a test net, we're
going to use the Rinkeby test
net. But be sure to use whatever
recommended test net the GitHub
repository for this coerce
recommends. Now looking at our
code, you might already have a
good idea of how to actually
make this slight change. Based
off of our last section, we know
that all we need is an RPC URL
and a private key and we can
begin making transactions on a
blockchain. So we're probably
going to need a rink B RPC URL,
and a rinky private key. Where
can we find both of those, if
you want to do everything on
your own, and in full
decentralized context, we could
run a rink B version of geth, we
could run it locally, and then
just connect to our guest node,
we're not going to be showing
how to do this here. However,
this is 100%, something that you
could do. Instead, we're gonna
use a third party RPC URL in the
GitHub repo associated with this
course. Go to Lesson five, we
can scroll down to get a link
for alchemy. Alchemy has a node
as a service and allows us to
connect to any blockchain that
they have support for two
alternates might be quick node,
Morales, or infura. These all
have node as a service options.
But we're going to work with
Alchemy, because it's the one
that I liked the best, we can go
ahead and get started for free
or login or create a new
account, I'm going to go ahead
and sign up with our hard hat
Free Code Camp user. And we're
going to select the Ethereum
blockchain ecosystem. Let's go
ahead and create our first app.
This is going to be we'll call
it Free Code Camp. RT hat. Our
app name will be ethers, simple
storage, FCC, and the network is
where we're going to choose rink
B. But you can see in here, we
can actually choose more than
just rink B, we can choose
really Kovan, rink B, ropsten.
And layer twos like arbitrage
and optimism, we're going to be
using rink B. So let's go ahead
and create this app. We're going
to choose the free plan and hit
Continue. We're going to skip
adding payments. If you want to
tweet your referral code, feel
free to tweet your referral
code. We're going to skip for
now. And we're going to keep it
at capped capacity. Since we
don't have a we don't have a key
in here. And then how did you
hear about us go ahead and give
me that shout out at Patrick and
Free Code Camp and then hit
Let's go. Now we get to the
alchemy dashboard, where we can
see a ton of information about
our node and different ways to
connect to the nodes and and
stuff like that. This is going
to be really similar to to this
RPC server endpoint of ganache,
except it's going to be a
connection, except it's going to
be a connection to a real test
net or real main net. What we
can do now is we can select our
our app that we just made. And
we can hit View key. And we can
see here we get an API key Key,
we add an HTTP endpoint and we
also get a WebSocket. We're only
concerned with the HTTP
endpoint. This is going to be
our RPC URL that connects to
rink B. So what we can do now is
we can copy this and come over
to our Visual Studio code. And
in our dot env, we can
substitute these out for their
actual tests and values. So for
RPC URL, we're going to delete
this and replace it with our
Rigby RPC row. And now how do we
get a private key for an actual
test set that has actual rank be
on it? Well, here is where we
can use our meta masks. So back
in your browser, go over to your
meta mask, select the three
dots, go to Account Details,
export private key. And this is
where you can export your
private key, type in your
password and boom, you now have
your private key for your
account on meta mask. Now
remember, please, please, please
don't continue with a meta mask
that has actual money in it. A
quick way to check is by going
to your networks tab and seeing
if on any of the main nets or
the networks with actual money
in it, you see any money, I
don't have any money in this. So
I know I'm good to go. If you
have tests that money, that's
fine, because that's fake money
anyways. And again, most
browsers have a profile
mechanism where you can create a
new profile for you to use. But
here now that I've copied my
private key, we can come back to
our Visual Studio code, paste
the key in here. And now I have
a private key that has actual
rink be in it. Awesome. And
remember, if you ever get low,
just come over to faucets dot
chain dot link slash Rigby get
some tests eath I'm not a robot
will send the request. Now that
we have our private key in our
rink being here, we can now try
to run this on an actual test.
Net, we look at our code, we see
we're grabbing an RPC URL, which
is going to be from r dot end,
we're grabbing a private key
which is going to be from our
daughter Yun V, which points to
our rink D Metamask. And our
rink B blockchain. So let's just
add a console dot log under our
contract deployment so that we
know what address it's at. So
we'll do console dot log, we'll
do some string interpolation,
contract, address,
contract dot address. All right,
great. Now let's go ahead and
run this. So we'll do node
deploy dot J. S deploying Please
wait, you'll notice this takes a
lot longer. Because we're
deploying to a test net instead
of our own fake local
blockchain, test nets and real
networks often will take a
little bit longer because they
need to wait for the blocks to
propagate the transaction to go
through, etc. But after a brief
delay, we will indeed see that
we get a contract address here.
And we have a current favorite
number. And it's being a little
slow again, because we're
waiting for our next transaction
to go through to update the
number and boom, looks like
we've successfully updated it.
Now something that's important
to know if ever you run command,
and you want to kill it, you can
do Ctrl C, and that will stop
it. So any command in the
terminal that you want to just
abort Ctrl. C is your Get Out of
Jail Free card and that will
kill it. That'll stop it
wherever it is. So we'll use
Ctrl C a lot in the future. So
now let's grab this contract
address and go over to Frank V
ether scan and paste it in, we
can see our two transactions
here, we can see we have a
contract creation. And we can
also see we call a store
function. This is awesome. We've
successfully deployed a contract
to the wrinkly chain using our
own code. Congratulations, this
is massive. Now on ether scan,
we actually can verify and
publish our contract code. What
is verifying and publishing your
code? Well, right now, our code
looks like a huge gerbil of
bytecode. And anybody looking at
our contract directly on chain
will just see this huge jumble
of bytecode, we can use a
decompiler to try to decompile
the bytecode into what it looks
like in solidity. But this can
often take a long time and, and
a lot of processing power. So
instead, we can just make it
much easier by verifying and
publishing the code ourself, you
go ahead and hit verify and
publish. We can scroll down and
we can add compiler information
to compile this on ether scan
and other block explorers. This
is a single file compiler
version is zero point 8.7. And
it's open source is licensed is
MIT. Let's go ahead and
continue. And we're going to
copy paste our solidity code
into this large section. Paste.
We don't have any constructor
arguments so we can skip this
section. We don't have any
libraries or any other
miscellaneous settings. So we'll
select I'm not a robot and we'll
hit verify and publish. You
might have to wait a few
minutes, but awesome. Our
contract was successfully
compiled. Now if we go back to
contract source code, we can see
all the code in here. And if we
grab our contract address, place
it into place into the search
now, and we go to contract, we
get a little green checkmark.
And we can see, anybody can now
read our source code.
Additionally, those buttons that
we saw and remix for reading
from our contract, and writing
to our contract, are in this
read contract and this write
contract. If we read the
contract, and we retrieve the
most recent number, we do indeed
see that we have seven here
because we recently stored
seven. Awesome, quick note, this
might already be verified for
you, since ether scan might get
smart enough to notice that a
lot of people are deploying the
same bytecode it's already
verified for you just go ahead
and walk through these steps
anyways. Now the code
verification we just did was
pretty simple and
straightforward, because our
code was pretty simple and
straightforward. Using larger
and more complex code can make
the verification process a
little bit harder. Additionally,
we don't always want to have to
click buttons on ether scan. To
verify our code, we want to do
it programmatically. So in later
sections, we'll learn how to
verify all of our code directly
through our code editor, you can
imagine the process is this easy
for deploying to any EVM chain
in our alchemy, we could easily
create a new app and change our
network. And you could see how
easy it would be to just switch
out this RPC URL and your
private key to work on a
different chain. This process is
also the same for harmony
Phantom, avalanche, etc. And if
we wanted to switch chains, we
would just switch the RPC URL
and switch the private key, and
everything else would stay
exactly the same. Now, Alchemy
also shows us and can teach us a
lot about transactions and about
things that are going on behind
the scenes, including a concept
called the mempool. To help us
understand a little bit more
about those transactions that we
just sent, and how to work with
Alchemy. To see more about our
transactions, we have Albert
from the alchemy team to give us
a little demonstration.
Hello, Albert here from alchemy,
I'm that guy in tech on Twitter,
feel free to follow if you want
to engage and ask any questions
about this section of the video.
But super excited to join
Patrick here to explain a little
bit of what goes on behind the
scenes when you are using
alchemy to submit a transaction.
And we have a ton of tools to
actually provide a window of
visibility into what's going on
so that you can actually debug
in case there are usage errors
on your website, or there are
pending transactions that are
stuck. Whatever it is, we
provide that window into the
data that you control. Remember
that all the transactions that
you submit are recorded on the
blockchain. They're not
controlled by alchemy, they're
not controlled by any other
service provider. We are just a
window, we're just the plumbing
the piping to be useful to you.
So let me show you exactly what
that means. Right now I have a
bunch of applications in my
dashboard. You can see here that
there are different projects
that I've used over time. This
one is the most recently active,
and it is the one that I have
currently set up to connect to
my meta mask. So actually use a
custom RPC provider here. And
let me make my face a little
smaller. And you can see here,
I've misspelled Rinkeby. But
this right now, my my network is
actually connected to the
Rinkeby test network via
alchemy. So this is actually
this application. So if I click
into here in the dashboard, you
can see here, a bunch of really
interesting statistics, this is
the first thing that you'll
probably use. If you're trying
to understand more about your
application, you'll go here and
you can see how many compute
units per second your
application is currently using.
And this is kind of great for
specifically alchemy usage,
understanding. But then this is
also really useful to see like,
what's the median response time,
and so 33 milliseconds is pretty
good. If that starts to
increase, then you might want to
figure out, you know, what's
going on here, success rate, it
has been kind of low. So that is
a clue for me to click on this
tab to view recent invalid
requests. And that I can
actually see oh, there's a bunch
of
failed transactions where the
transaction has already been
sent or the nonce is too low, or
whatever it is, I can actually
use this tab to debug. So that
success rate is pretty useful.
Throughput that's been limited.
So if you are sending too many
requests or your website is
getting spammed, you might start
getting some requests blocked.
So that's what's useful to view
their concurrent requests over
here, success rate in the past
24 hours versus the past one
hour, the total number of
requests in the last 24 hours.
And this is different than
compute units, because each
request can have a different
level of computing cost. And
computing cost as measured by
compute units. Total requests is
just the actual number of
absolute requests. And then of
course, the number of invalid
request. Cool. So one thing I do
want to show you that's
interesting is when I do submit
a transaction, and I actually
have one right here, I want to
send so let's transfer between
my accounts, and I'm just gonna
send it to tiny amount of
Rinkeby eath. But I'm going to
purposefully edit my gas fees to
be super, super low so that the
node will actually not muck send
the transaction to be mined, or
there are no miners that will
actually pick it up. So you can
see here I've divided the the
priority fee and the max fee by
a ton. So it's super low. And it
might confirm that in the MME
Max UI, you'll see that the
transaction has been pending for
a bit. And we'll go over to this
mempool tab. This is another
really useful visualization. And
what the mempool is, is a kind
of a holding ground, I like to
think of it as the waiting room
of a restaurant, where if you're
a transaction, and you're
waiting to get mined, the
mempool is kind of like the
waiting room where you're
waiting to get seated. So there
are different statuses for your
each of your transactions, the
ones that you always want to see
are the mines transactions,
because that says that your
transaction is successful. And
it's now part of the blockchain.
Now, the mempool, every node has
its own, you know, holding
ground. So I can actually show
you this quick visualization.
Remember, blockchains are run by
a network of nodes. And each
node or each computer that's
running the theorem, software
maintains a copy of the
blockchain. And as a developer,
you have to use these nodes to
make requests to the blockchain.
Now you can use alchemy, you can
use another RPC provider, you
can spin up your own node if you
want to. But regardless, you
need to use a node to
communicate with the chain. Now
each node beyond having a copy
of the entire blockchain state,
it also has a local memory of
transaction. And that's called
mempool. So if there are pending
transactions that are waiting to
be mined, you can consider them
as being in the mempool. Now
that's what we're looking at
right here. If we click on the
app that I am currently using
for my Metamask RPC, then you
can see here that there are,
this is not the right one, this
one is the right one for
wrinkling. For all the
transactions here, you can see
some more drop in placed
somewhere mind and there's one
that's pending, and this
pending, one actually matches up
with the one that is pending,
here, it's being sent to 0x, C,
BB. And if we click on this
transaction hash, you get all
the information that you need to
debug. So you can see here that
it's from my current address,
0x, five F, and then it's two
0x, C, BB. And here's the value
that I'm trying to send. Here's
the gas fee that I've attached
to this transaction. And you'll
notice that that is super low,
even for the Rinkeby test
network. So knowing this, and
seeing, wow, this transaction
has been pending for one minute
and 46 seconds, it was sent at
this time, I should probably fix
that. And so over here, you can
actually use the metamath RPC,
meta meta mask API. And speeded
up. And then I'm just going to
use the auto high speed up to
update the gas fees. And then if
we go back to our dashboard back
to our application, you can see
that there are some new recent
invalid requests. And this is
because we've resubmitted a
transaction, and then in their
recent requests we have, let's
refresh that real quick. You can
see that we are sending a raw
transaction, this one's already
known. And there's another one
before, but it that's resulting
in a get transaction receipt
that is successful. And then if
we go back to the mempool, you
can see boom, no more pending
transactions only dropped and
replaced and mined. So this
transaction nonce number five is
now successful, and you're on
your way to developing and
maintaining the rest of your
application. So yeah, thanks
hope that was useful. Let me
know if you have any questions.
Now, other than the TypeScript
portion, which I'll do at the
end, you've successfully
completed this section. And wow,
you've learned a ton. Let's do a
quick review of everything that
we've learned. Well, first,
we've learned how to create new
projects with Node js, we've
learned what the node keyword
does and how we can use the node
keyword. To run JavaScript in
our local development
environment, we learned that we
can add different dependencies
of external packages into our
local package using yarn or NPM.
And we can see those
dependencies added in package
dot JSON, we know that they've
been installed because they get
installed into the node modules
folder, we can also create a
script section where we can
minimize long commands that we
need to run into a single
keyword, like compile for
example, we can just run yarn
compile. To compile all of our
code, we learned the basic setup
of our JavaScript scripts, we
import our packages at the top,
we have some main executor
function at the bottom. And then
we have our main function in the
middle, we use the async keyword
so that our function can use
asynchronous programming, and we
get access to the await keyword,
which basically means Hey, wait
for this promise to finish doing
its thing. We're able to connect
to any blockchain we want using
an RPC URL, and then we're able
to connect our provider to a
wallet or a private key in
ethers by doing something like
this. Speaking of So we've
learned about the ethers
package, which is a tool that
makes our life a lot easier to
interact with the blockchain in
JavaScript, if we decide to,
we've also learned we can
encrypt our private keys so that
even if our computers get
hacked, our private keys aren't
lying around in plaintext. And
we've learned how to run scripts
from our encrypted keys. We've
learned how to get the ABI or
the application binary
interface, and the binary of our
code to deploy to a blockchain,
we've learned how to deploy our
contracts to a blockchain
programmatically. And then we've
learned how to interact with our
contracts programmatically as
well. Additionally, we've
learned how to add a default
editor in our settings dot JSON
of our VS code. But we've also
learned how to override those
settings by adding prettier
using a dot prettier rc file
this way, we can auto format our
code to make it look a lot nicer
and much easier to read.
Finally, we learned how to
deploy one of these contracts to
a real test net or a real
network. And then we finally
learned the manual way to verify
our contract source code. Like I
said, we're going to learn a lot
of shortcuts. And a lot of ways
to make this all a little bit
easier in coming sections. Oh,
you have done a phenomenally to
reach this section, give
yourself a pat on the back, take
a break, go for a lap, and feel
really proud about yourself that
you made it this far, we've got
a lot more to go. But you have
come a phenomenally long way.
Congratulations. Or take that
five to 10 minute break and come
back when you're ready.
Now the one thing left I want to
show you all is the TypeScript
addition to this. However, if
you're not interested in the
TypeScript edition, which you
don't have to be, then you're
done, there's only a couple of
changes we need to make to make
this TypeScript compatible.
First, of course, we're going to
change our deploy.ts and encrypt
key, we're going to change our
deploy and our encrypt key from
dot j s two.ts. And then we're
also going to swap these
requires out for imports. So
we're going to import ethers
from ethers, we're going to
import star as Fs from Fs extra.
And then we're going to import
dot TMP slash config. And then
we're just going to copy these,
and we're gonna come over and
paste them into here, deleting
or commenting out the requires,
okay, great. Now, if we try to
run Node deploy.ts, we're going
to get cannot use input
statement outside of a module.
In JavaScript, if we'd want to
use an import statement outside
of a module, we'd come in here
and do some like type module
like that. But in TypeScript, we
actually don't even need that.
All we need to do is run this in
TypeScript note. So to add
TypeScript, we're going to do
yarn, add TypeScript. And we're
also going to add TS node. TS
node is the TypeScript edition
of node. So now that we've added
that we can try a TS node
deploy.ts. And we're still going
to run into an error. And if you
scroll up, we're gonna get a
couple errors here. We're gonna
say, could not find a
declaration file for Module Fs
extra, we need to add the
TypeScript version of them. So
we're gonna do yarn at types
slash Fs extra. That, and if we
run it again, it still shouldn't
work. But for a different
reason. Yes, we're gonna get
something like this type.
Undefined is not assignable to
type bytes. Like the reason we
get this is because process dot
EMV private key in TypeScript
technically, is type string, or
undefined. So we need to tell
Typescript and and the Wallet
Objects. And the Encrypt
function is looking for a type
string, not string or undefined.
So we just need to tell
TypeScript that this will not be
undefined. So we can just put a
bang here. And everywhere that
we use process, study and be,
oops, I got to do that on
deploy, as well. Bang, looks
good. Now that we've added
everything in here, we run TS
node deploy.ts, we're gonna see
the exact same output as we saw
with just using regular node.
And as long as our private key
password is in our dot env file.
If we run TS node and crypt
key.ts, we're gonna get the
exact same setup as before. And
we're gonna get a new encrypted
key dot JSON. And that's all you
need to do to make this
TypeScript compatible. And you
should give yourself a huge
round of applause for getting
this far and learning what's
going on underneath hardhat. The
next tool that we're going to
learn and learning all about
these transactions and how to
interact with these blockchains
this is absolutely massive, so
huge. Congratulations.
Alright, so now that we've
learned about ethers js and how
to do some more raw JavaScript
coding, we're now going to move
into hardhat. We saw with our
ether symbol storage that
deploying a contract can take a
lot of code. And there's a
number of things we didn't even
do in here. Like we didn't save
where this contract was
deployed. So we'd have to go
remember where it was deployed
every time. Instead of having it
just added programmatically. We
didn't write any tests here, and
we'd have to build our own
testing infrastructure. Maybe we
want to make this a cross chain
application. And we want more
than just one private key and
RPC URL, you can absolutely work
with your smart contracts in
JavaScript purely through ethers
and small scripts like this. But
we want a more robust framework
for doing all this. And that's
where hard hat comes into play.
Hardhead is easily one of the
most, if not the most popular
smart contract development
framework out there. It's used
by massive several billion
dollar protocols like Ave
uniswap, sushi swap, and more.
In fact, I recently did a poll
on Twitter. And even though a
lot of my content has been more
brownie and Pythonic, Hardhead
was well and beyond the most
popular framework, and Hardhead
has quickly become one of the
most advanced frameworks out
there. Hardhead is a development
environment, which allows for
JavaScript based development,
kind of like what we saw with
ethers, it gives us even more
tools to integrate our code with
common things that we want to
do. It's incredibly extensible,
and it has really nice debugging
features as well. And it's just
an overall fantastic tool. So
let's go ahead and let's jump
in. If you want to follow along
with the code, come over to the
GitHub repo and scroll down.
Lesson Six heart had simple
storage, and all the code is
located here. And a quick note
for the future ever, you want to
just download all the code from
one of these repositories, the
way you can do that is by doing
a git clone, what you do is you
come to the folder that you want
to put this code in, and you run
git clone. And then you grab the
URL that you want to clone,
paste it in. Now, you can CD
into your new folder here that
has everything downloaded
directly from GitHub, but only
do that as a backup or to just
download the code yourself. But
for now, just follow along with
me. Right, so let's do this.
Let's create our next project
using hard hat. The project that
we're going to be making is
called Hard Hat, simple storage
dash FCC or Free Code Camp. This
is going to be us working again
with that simple storage
contract. But in hard hat, we're
going to show you a ton of the
fantastic tools that we can use
to make our coding life way
easier. So I'm in a brand new VS
code, and we're going to create
a new folder for us to run all
this. Now what you can do to
create a brand new folder is you
once again you can do MK dir,
hard hat, simple storage of CC.
Now we can cd into hard hat
simple storage of CD, and type
code, period. And this will open
up a new Visual Studio code
inside of that folder. Now if we
open up our terminal, you'll see
that we are indeed inside that
folder. Now if that doesn't work
for you, you can still of course
to File, Open folder and select
the folder you'd like to open.
And you'll be inside of that
folder. Now that we have our
folder setup for working with
hard hat, we can begin setting
up our environment to be
incredibly professional using
the hard hat framework got a
link to the hard hat
documentation inside our whole
blockchain solidity course, yes,
the hard hat documentation is
phenomenal. And I highly
recommend everybody have it up
as they go through the section.
Because it's going to give you
pretty much everything that you
need to know for working with
hard hat, you can simply go
ahead over to tutorial and get
started. If you want to pause
the video here and read through
the tutorial, I recommend doing
so it'll give you a lot of
information about how to work
with hardhat. And more about
hardhat. However, we're just
going to jump right into setting
up the environment. We've
already installed no Gs on
Linux, or Mac OS. And those of
you who are using Windows, I set
you up with WsL. So you can just
follow the Linux instructions.
Now to create a new hard hat
project, you can actually just
go ahead and run these steps
right here. Instead of NPM,
we're going to be using yarn,
but if you want to use NPM, you
can absolutely do so the hard
hat Doc's say run npm init dash
dash, yes, we're just going to
run yarn in it, which is going
to create a new project for us
in this folder. So let's give it
a name, which if we want it set
to this hard hat symbol storage
FF FCC, we just hit enter, we'll
give it a version. And when if
we want it 1.0 point oh, we just
hit enter. We're going to skip
the description for now just by
hitting enter. And we're just
going to hit Enter for this as
well. And for this as well enter
for this as well and for this as
well and over this as well. Just
to keep those as blanks. And if
we look in package json, we now
see we have a name Hardhead
symbol storage that FCC we have
a version we have a main which
we're actually going to delete
the main and then we have a
license as well. yarn in it just
sets up this package json for
us. Now we're going to do yarn,
add dash dash dash
of our app. So far, we've just
been running yarn add, and then
whatever our package name is.
But for most of what we're
doing, we really want to do yarn
add dash dash Dev. The reasons
for this is a little bit
nuanced. But we can see some of
the information on this
StackOverflow question here. The
main difference is that
dependencies are required to run
your project. Whereas dev
dependencies are required only
to develop. For the most part,
we're going to be doing just
dash dash Dev, when we get to
the front end portion of this
course, we'll be installing more
packages that we don't need just
for development. Now in the same
directory where we install hard
hat, you can run MPX hard hat.
So a quick note about MPX is
that the yarn equivalent of NPM
is just yarn. So yarn goes NPM,
the yarn equivalent of MPX is
also yarn. So pretty much
anytime you see MPX, do
something, you can just replace
that MPX with yarn, and it'll do
the exact same thing. If you
want to run this with NPM or
MPX, you can absolutely do that
as well. So for us, we're going
to run yarn hardhat. And we'll
see we'll get prompted to
actually start creating a
hardhat project, run yarn
hardhat. And we'll get this
wonderfully cute prompt right
here and saying welcome to
Hardhead. What do you want to
do, create a basic sample
project, create an advanced
sample project can advance some
project uses type script or
create an empty
hardhat.config.js. For us, we're
just going to select create a
basic sample project. And this
is going to give us all the
boilerplate for a really simple
hardhat project. The hard hat
project route is going to be
this folder that we're in right
now. Do you want to add a Git
dot Git ignore? Yes, we
absolutely do. Because we're
going to be using dot env files.
Do you want to install this
sample projects dependencies
with yarn at nomic labs hard hat
at a theory and waffle at Chai?
We're going to go ahead and say
yes, and I'll explain what all
these dependencies are in a bit.
Let's go ahead and say yes for
now. And we're going to install
all these dependencies. Now, if
we look in our package, JSON, we
can see we've added a number of
dependencies like nomic labs,
Hardhead ethers, not MacLeods,
Hardhead, waffle, Chai,
Aetherium, waffle, and ethers.
Obviously, we're already
familiar with ethers, but the
rest of these might be a little
new. We'll talk about those
later. And great, we now have a
sample hardhat boilerplate
project. Let's walk through what
we just installed here. The
first thing we have is a
contracts folder, which comes
pre populated with greeted
outsole is really minimalistic
contract here. Next, you'll see
node modules, which of course is
our installed JavaScript
dependencies. Something I want
to know because it was really
confusing to me when I first
started working with this is
some of these node modules start
with an add sign, and then a lot
of them don't. What's the
difference between those two,
these outside node modules are
known as scoped packages, which
effectively allow NPM packages
to be namespace or yarn
packages. This allows
organizations to make it clear
what packages are official and
which ones are not. For example,
if a package has a scope at
Angular, you know, it's
published by the Angular core
team. So it's the same thing
with this anything with AP ens
domains we know is by the ens
domains team, anything with
abnormal Labs is going to be by
the team that created hard hat.
So that's why this at nomic
labs, hard hat ethers and at
nomic labs, hard at Waffle has
this at sign, because we know
it's published by the nomic labs
team, then we have a scripts
section. This is going to be
where we're adding any and all
of our scripts that we want to
write like deploying contracts,
interacting with contracts, etc.
And then we have a test folder.
We haven't started building any
tests yet. But tests are
incredibly important for working
with smart contracts. And this
sample test folder gives us a
minimalistic test for testing
our smart contracts. We of
course have Git ignore, which of
course comes pre populated with
some important things to ignore
like Dotty and V. And also node
modules because node modules
might get too huge push up to
GitHub. And one of the biggest
changes here is it adds this
hard hat.config.js. This file
even though it's minimalistic,
right now, you can think of as
the entry point for all the
scripts that we write, it's the
configuration file that
determines how the rest of our
code is going to work and
interact with the blockchain.
Then of course, we have package
dot JSON, we get started with a
readme. Remember how the first
time we ran yarn hard hat, we
were prompted with this Getting
Started piece. Now if we run
yarn Hardhead, we're actually
going to get output of all the
different options and commands
we can use
with running hard hat. Now, if
you run into an issue where you
run yarn, hard hat, and this
pops up, but you don't see a
hard hat.config.js in your
folder, it likely means that
there's a hard hat dot config
dot j s in a higher level
folder, or there's a node
modules with hard hat in a
higher level folder. So if that
happens, maybe CD down a
directory and do a little LS and
look to see if you've got a hard
hat.config.js or node modules in
earlier folder. And because I've
actually seen a number of
engineers have a couple of
different problems here. My
friend CAMI is going to explain
A couple of different
troubleshooting tips you can
take to try to avoid these
common errors.
As a developer the most annoying
thing to deal with our
environment set of issues. My
name is Camila Ramos. I'm a
DevRel engineer at edge node
supporting the Graph Protocol.
And I'm going to show you how to
solve two common problems that
you might see when working on
this project. After installing
hardhat. And running the command
and px hard hat in your new
project folder, you're going to
expect to get back a menu of
options like this, but sometimes
you're not going to get that
back. And when you run into this
error, there is a solution for
you. And it usually just means
that you have a config file
somewhere that it shouldn't be,
and deleting it will get rid of
that error. What you're going to
do in order to find this file
that you need to delete is run
the command MPX hardhats space,
hyphen, hyphen verbose. And this
is going to spit out where this
file is if you have one, and
it's going to tell you exactly
where it is so that you can
delete it. After you've deleted
this config file, you should be
able to run MPX hardhat in your
project folder and get back that
many that we were expecting.
Another problem that is pretty
common. And I still run into all
the time is forgetting to npm
install, whenever you're working
with a repo that other people
have been working on on GitHub.
So let's say you're pulling down
some code that you and some
collaborators were working on
together, and then suddenly,
it's not working for you, you
probably just need to npm
install. So in your terminal, go
ahead and navigate to where this
project is located and then run
the command npm install. If
there are any new packages that
were installed in the time that
you weren't working on the code,
those will get installed locally
for you so that when you run the
code, it will be able to run
successfully.
What are some of the main things
we can do with hardhat in its
raw state here, these are some
of the main tasks that we can
run with hardhat different tasks
or just different commands, we
can run with hardhat. For
example, we can do yarn hardhat
counts, which will print out a
list of fake accounts we can use
with Hardhead. Similar to the
list of fake accounts that we
used with ganache, we can
compile our contracts by running
yarn Hardhead compile. Very
similar to what we did with
ethers Jas and soap Jas, you'll
see when we run compile, we get
a cache, which is just going to
be a quick way to access
solidity files, and we also get
an artifacts section. This
artifacts folder contains all
the information about our
compiled code we look in here
now we can, for example, look in
the build info and see a ton of
information about our compiled
contract. If you're looking
contracts, we can see more
compiled information. And then
if we look in the hardhat, slash
console.so, we can see more
compiled information. So all of
our compliation information is
going to be in this artifacts
folder. And whenever you want to
look to see what's going on on
the lower level when you compile
this artifacts folder is what
has everything. There are a
number of other hard hat tasks
that we can run as well. But
we'll get to them as we go. So
now that we have some of the
basics of hard head down, let's
go ahead and try doing some of
the same things we did with
ethers before but with hard hat.
So one of the first things we
want to do is we want to write
and interact with our smart
contracts. So let's go ahead and
rename greeter dot soul to
simple storage dot soul, you can
click on the file and hit enter
and should be able to rename it.
Otherwise, you can go ahead and
right click, delete it, and then
create a new file and call it
simple storage dot soul. We're
going to copy paste all of our
code from our previous simple
storage that saw into this file,
we can make sure that our simple
storage is compiling correctly
by running yarn hardhat compile.
Whoa, it looks like we ran into
an issue project cannot be
compiled. See reasons below the
solidity pragma version of the
file. It doesn't match any of
the configured compilers in your
config. Hmm, well, what's going
on contracts slash symbol
storage that's Sol zero point
8.8. Ah, okay, let's go ahead
and fix them. So we can open up
our hard hat dot config dot j s.
Now a quick note on opening
files. If you're on Mac and you
hit Command P, you can actually
start typing in the names of
files to get them to them
quicker. Or if you're on Linux
or Windows, you can type Ctrl p,
this will bring up and
interestingly if you type man P
or ctrl p and then you hit the
greater than key. This will drop
you into the command palette,
know command palette, command
palette, search for files,
search for commands in our
Hardhead dot config. Jas, I'm
gonna scroll down to module dot
exports and change this to zero
point 8.8. So that the version
that we're going to compile for
simple storage, it's gonna be
the same version and that hard
hat is looking for. Let's run
that same command by just
hitting up yarn Hardhead
compile, and awesome we see
compiled one solidity file
successfully. We should now see
this in artifacts. If we go to
artifacts and contracts. We now
see two contracts in here,
greater and simple storage and
we can see a ton of the
information about simple storage
we can also see some more lower
level in Information and build
info. Alright, so now that we
have our simple storage contract
in here, the next thing we
probably want to do is learn how
to deploy it. This is where
we're going to write our deploy
script. Now, for this section,
I'm going to be showing you how
to write a deploy script. But in
the next section, we're going to
do it a little bit differently.
But this is still going to teach
you how to write scripts and
worked with scripts in heart
app. So we're going to come to
our sample script dot j s, and
we're gonna go ahead and hit
enter and renamed it to deploy
dot j s. And if you want to read
all the comments in here, you
absolutely can, we're just gonna
go ahead and delete them all. A
quick keyboard shortcut is if
you hit Command A or Ctrl, a,
you'll highlight all the text in
your file, and we're going to go
ahead and delete it all. So now
we're just going to start from
scratch here. Now the setup for
our deploy script in here is
going to look really similar to
the setup of our deploy script.
From our previous section, we're
going to do imports at the top,
we're going to have our async
main function, and then we're
going to call the main function.
So let's go ahead and define our
main function, we'll call it
async. function main, like that,
and then we'll call our main
function. And if you want to
just copy paste this from the
last section, you absolutely
can. So we'll domain that then.
Boom, just like that. And
because of these semicolons are
going to drive me absolutely
insane. We're also going to add
prettier, and our solidity
prettier plugins. So we'll do
yarn, add dash dash Dev,
prettier and prettier, plug in
solidity. Then we can go ahead
and create our dot prettier, rc
file, we're going to add tab
with four, use tabs, false, semi
false, and then single quote,
also false. Now we're going to
be using this prettier rc file
setup a lot. So in future
sections, if you want to just
copy paste it, you can
absolutely do that as well.
We're also going to add a dot
prettier, ignore, which tells
prettier not to format some
files, which we want, we don't
want prettier to spend a ton of
time formatting all of our
files, I'm just going to copy
paste from the GitHub repo. So
feel free to copy paste from the
GitHub repo as well, you'd find
all the code for this section,
like I said, in the GitHub repo
associated with this course.
Now, unlike in our last section,
where we had to grab our
contract code a little bit more
manually, with hard hat, it's
actually a number of different
ways to grab compiled contracts.
The first way we're going to do
it, we're actually going to use
ethers. And now this is where
one of the first confusing
changes actually comes in.
Previously, we did const ethers
equals require ethers. And that
was how we went ahead and worked
with ethers. However, you'll
notice in our dev dependencies,
we have this dependency called
Hard Hat ethers. Hard Hat ethers
is a package that actually wraps
hard hat with its own built in
ethers. This is really
advantageous because it allows
hard hat to keep track of
different deployments at
different scripts and all these
other things for us. So instead
of importing ethers directly
from ethers, we're actually
going to import ethers directly
from hard hat instead. This
might seem a little confusing at
first, but just know if we want
to work with ethers and heart
it, it's usually much better to
pull it in from heart and you
can still do this and ethers
will still work the same. But
hard hat won't necessarily know
about different contract
factories in different pieces
and, and you'll see that in
action in a second. Now that
we're pulling in ethers, we can
actually immediately grab a
contract factory using ethers.
We can say const simple storage
factory equals await ethers dot
get contract. Factory simple
storage. So in order to get a
simple storage, contract
factory, we can just do await
ethers dot get contract factory.
Now if we pulled right from
ethers, the package ethers
doesn't know about this
contracts folder and ethers
doesn't know we've already
compiled simple storage dot
soul. And it's in our artifacts.
Hard Hat, on the other hand,
does know about the contracts
folder and does know that it's
already compiled, which is why
this simple storage factory
grabbing work so well. Once we
have our factory here, we can do
the same thing that we did in
our previous section and deploy
the contract. So we'll do a
quick console dot log. Deploy
flooring, contract done, and
then we'll do Kant's simple
storage equals await simple
store edge factory dot deploy
And boom, with that little bit
of code, we're already able to
deploy our simple storage
contract, then to wait to make
sure it gets deployed, we can do
await, simple storage, deployed.
And that's it. Now let's see
what happens when we go ahead
and run this deploy script. As
you know, in our last section,
we had to put in a private key,
and we had to put an RPC URL.
Right now, we don't have either
one of those defined. So what do
you think should the script
actually work? Or do you think
it'll break because we, we
didn't define what blockchain
we're going to deploy you. We
also didn't find a private key.
Well, let's go ahead and try
this out. We can run the script
in our terminal by running yarn,
hard hat, run, scripts slash
deploy dot j, s. And again, I'm
hitting tab here to do a little
auto completion and see what
happens. Well, we got deploying
contract, it says done, but
that's really it. So what really
happened? Well, let's add one
more line in here.
Let's do console dot log. We'll
do some string interpolation
deployed, contract to. And then
we'll add simple storage. That
address. Let's run this now. We
get deployed contract, and then
we get deployed contract to, and
then we get a contract address.
Hmm, what's going on here.
Hardhead has this fantastic tool
built in called The Hard Hat
Network hard hat comes built in
with Hard Hat Network, a local
Aetherium network node designed
for development, akin to
ganache, that allows you to
deploy your contracts and run
your tests and debug your code.
Whenever we run a command in
hard hat, or a script and hard
hat or a task and hard hat, we
by default deploy to this fake
Hard Hat Network. This Hard Hat
Network is very similar to
ganache, except for instead of
having this UI, it runs in the
background for our scripts. In
fact, if we go to our hard
hat.config.js, we can scroll
down to the bottom to this
module that exports section and
add more information about our
default networks. So right now,
if we don't have anything in
this module that export, by
default, it adds this piece
called default network hardhat.
So anytime we run a script,
without specifying a network, it
automatically uses this fake
Hard Hat Network. And this fake
Hard Hat Network comes
automatically with an RPC URL
and a private key for you. So
you don't even have to add one
in. This is one of the major
advantages of working with
Hardhead. It just automatically
gives you this fake blockchain.
And these fake private keys, if
you want to be a little bit more
explicit. And I always recommend
being more explicit, we can add
the default network in to the
module that are experts. So now
our default network is
explicitly stated as hard hat.
However, in any script, you run,
you can choose whatever network
you want to work with. So if I
want to explicitly say I want to
run our deploy script on our
fake Hard Hat Network, I can do
yarn, hard hat, run scripts,
deploy dot j s, dash dash
network, hard hat, this is us
telling her that, hey, we want
to run this script on the Hard
Hat Network. Hopefully, you
might be able to see where this
is going. Having this network
flag makes it incredibly easy to
switch across different chains,
different block chains,
different private keys, etc. So
we have our default network set
the hard hat here, we can add
other networks in here as well.
The way we do that is we're
going to add a networks section.
And we're going to define any of
the network sections that we
want. And remember to put a
comment there so that your
Visual Studio code doesn't get
mad at you. So recently, we
worked with Rigby so let's go
ahead and add a Rinkeby network
in here. So we're gonna say
another network is gonna be
really cool. So I should just be
able to change the network flag
to Rigby now, right? Well, not
quite. If you try to run that,
you're gonna get invalid value
undefined for hardhat config
networks. Rigby, that URL, it's
expecting you to tell it, hey,
what the URL is, since this
isn't the hard hat network, we
need to tell hard hat exactly
how we're going to connect to
rink B. And this is where a lot
of what we learned before is
going to come in handy, again,
exactly the same as what we did
before. We're going to create a
new Dotty v file, and we're
going to add our Rigby URL in
this dot env file. Just
remember, dot env is an r dot
get ignore just in case. So in
our Dotty env, we're going to
add that RPC URL from alcmi back
in here before we just said RPC
URL. But since we might want to
work across multiple networks,
it's usually good to specify
exactly what network each URL
stands for. So we're gonna say
Rynkeby RPC URL equals and then
paste that URL in here. Now, as
you probably have guessed, we
can add our URL to our Rinkeby
network here. for readability, I
usually like to add them as
variables right above the module
that experts. So I'll say const
Rynkeby. RPC URL equals process
dot E and V dot Rynkeby RPC URL.
And once again, we're going to
be pulling that Rinckey RPC URL
from our environment variable.
Of course, in order to pull that
environment variable in, we're
going to need to use that dot
env package again. So to add
that in, we're going to yarn add
dash dash dev dot EMV. And at
the top of our Hardhead config,
we're going to add require dot
EMV, and then do dot config to
enable the config. Now this
means we should be able to pull
our rink the RPC URL from our
dot env. Now that we have that
in our Rinkeby network, we can
add URL Rinckey RPC URL.
Awesome. So we have an RPC URL
for different network. But what
else do we usually need? Well,
we usually need a private key to
work with an actual network, or
that doesn't automatically give
us a private key for rugby,
because Hardhead can't just give
us test and the Etherium, we
need to have an actual account
an actual test nets. Hardhead
doesn't control those. So we
have to actually give it a real
URL and a real private key. So
to add private keys, you
actually add something called
accounts, you add a list of
accounts that you want to give
to hard hat for us, we're only
going to add one, which is going
to be our private key. And for
our private key, we're going to
do the exact same thing. We're
gonna say const private key
equals process dot e NV dot
private key. And since this
private key is going to be a
real private key for a real test
net, again, we are going to have
to grab this from our meta mask.
So it will go to our meta mask,
three dots, account details,
export private key, and we'll
add our password in here.
And then in our dot env will add
private key equals and then add
our private key. Now I know I've
said this 100 times, but please,
please, please, for learning
this, do not use a real key that
is connected to any real money
just in case, please use a new
meta mask. I've know I've said
it a bunch. But some people go
no, I'm going to be okay, I'll
be safe. Just to be super, super
safe here, please use a brand
new meta mask. So now that we
have a private key, we're going
to add it in here account
private key. And now we have an
account here. One more thing I
like to do is I like to give the
chain ID of the network, which
for Rigby is going to be for
every single EVM base network as
a new chain ID and EVM network
basically just means solidity
works on it. This includes all
test nets, there's a good site
called chainless.org, which may
or may not be going down at some
point, it has a list of all
these different networks. For
example, you can see on here a
theory main net has a chain ID
of one byte and smart chain is
56, avalanches, 4311 for
Phantom, opera 250, Polygon,
137, etc. Each one of these EVM
compatible chains has their own
chain ID, rank V, the chain ID
is for adding the chain ID is
helpful here for later on. And
we'll get to that in the future.
But for now, just go ahead and
make sure to add your chain IDs.
Okay, now that we have the RPC
URL, we have the private key, we
can go ahead and test deploying
this to an actual test net, and
actually did something incorrect
here. And we're gonna get an
error here. And I want you to go
ahead and try to figure out and
debug this error yourself.
You're ready. Alright, let's do
it. We'll do yarn, hard hat, run
scripts, deploy dot j s, dash
dash network Rinkeby. And we get
this wonderfully weird error,
which we see we have deployed
contract. So we know that in our
deploy script, we get to at
least this line, but then we're
getting an error, I highly
likely hear what's going on
saying cannot read properties
have no reading send
transaction, if you want, you
can absolutely go to this spot.
But it basically it looks like
it's having a hard time
understanding what the private
key or what the account of this
is. And what do you think I'm
going to recommend we do? Well,
if it's not clear, after doing a
little bit of triaging and
debugging, we're going to copy
this air. And we're going to
come on over to Google and paste
that right in. It looks like we
do get a question here from
stackexchange Etherium. And it
looks like it's really similar
to what we're doing. We scroll
down. They're running nearly the
exact same script that we're
running, they're using MPX
instead of yarn. They've got a
pretty minimalistic deploy file.
Let's scroll down and see what
the answers have to say. I've
seen this error where my private
key wasn't properly populated. I
would also use an environment
variable I'm pretty sure Are
environment variables good. But
we have a second one saying in
your heart head, I can think
that Jas, it should be accounts
instead of account, it works for
me, let's go back to our head
config and see if that's what's
going on. Uh huh, we put account
in this should be accounts. So
let's swap that over to
accounts. We'll clear our
terminal. And we'll run this
again. Uh huh. And now it's
reading a little bit longer,
which is good. This means that
we're probably deploying this to
rink B, which is what we want to
see. Awesome. And now we can see
deployed contract to, and we
have a contract address here. So
we'll grab this contract. And
we'll pop on over to bring the
ether scan, that's numbering the
ether scan. And we'll go ahead
and we'll paste this in.
Awesome. And we see our contract
was created about 26 seconds
ago. Perfect. Now for this part,
you don't have to deploy this to
rink be with me, if you follow
along here. That's good enough.
So remember, the flying to test
that's can take a long time. So
for this one, you don't have to
deploy with me. Alright, great.
So we've deployed to rink be
using hard hat. This is
fantastic. Now something that we
notice, once again is oof, our
contract isn't verified? Do we
have to go back through and do
this verify and publish and all
that stuff again? Luckily for
us, we actually don't need to do
that. So what can we do? Well,
back in our deploy script, we
can add some code to
automatically verify right after
we deploy. So let's go ahead and
do that. Right below our main
function, we're gonna create a
new function called verify,
we're gonna say async function,
verify. And we're gonna have
this function get past some
arguments, we're gonna have to
get past a contract, address,
and some arguments or the
contract. Since our simple
storage doesn't have a
constructor, the arguments for
simple storage are just gonna be
blank. But in the future, when
we have contracts that do have
constructors, the arguments are
going to be populated. And when
we get there, you'll see what I
mean, we need at least the
contract address, and we're
going to add some code in here
to automatically verify our
contracts after they've been
deployed. This auto verification
process works on block explorers
like ether scan, it might not
work on block explorers like
eath, pler, or other block
explorers. But if you want to
verify on these other block
explorers, I'm sure they have an
API to allow you to do that as
well. Now, ether scan in most
other block explorers have a
section on their website called
API documentation, or something
to do with API's. These are ways
for us to programmatically
interact with ether scan, and do
stuff with them. One of the main
things that we can do is we can
actually verify our contracts
through this API. Ether scan
even has a tutorial in here
called verifying contracts
programmatically. And the link
to this will be in the GitHub
repo, they have an API endpoint
that we can make some requests
to to go ahead and verify our
contracts. Now, we could
absolutely make the raw API
calls and follow the tutorial
here. But there's actually an
easier way than even going
through this tutorial here.
Hardhead is an extensible
framework, meaning you can add
something called plugins to it.
There's even an advanced section
in the documentation called
Building plugins. If we scroll
down to the bottom, we can see
some popular plugins that the
nomic labs team or the Hardhead
team has created. And also a
number of community plugins as
well. One of the most used
Hardhead plugins is going to be
this hard hat ether scan plugin
that makes this verification
process much, much easier.
Install it, you can just run npm
install bash, just save dev at
nomic labs harden ether scan,
and then add it to our hard hat
dot config. Since we're using
yarn, we're just going to go
ahead and use yarn. So back in
our code, we'll do yarn, add
dash dash Dev, at nomic, labs,
slash hard hat slash hyphen,
ether scan. Now that we have
this plugin, we can go to our
hard hat dot config, scroll to
the top and add this plugin do
require at nomic labs slash hard
hat, ether scan. Now that we
have this plugin, the hard hat
documentation has some more
information about the usage, how
to actually use this plugin, and
how to run different commands
with it. In order for us to use
this verification, we actually
need an API key from ether scan.
This is basically a password for
allowing us to use the ether
scan API. So we're going to come
to ether scan. And we're going
to go ahead and sign in. And
actually we're going to click to
sign up and create an account.
And we'll go ahead and create an
account. We'll go ahead and
verify our registration by
clicking the verification link.
And we'll click the Login. Now
that we're logged in. On the
left hand side, we can scroll
down to API keys. And we can go
ahead and create a new API key.
We call this H H hyphen sec,
which stands for hardhat Free
Code Camp. Great, this new API
key will copy this and we'll go
back to our code and we'll add
this somewhere since the API
keys basically considered a
password. Where do you think we
should add this? That's right in
our dot env. So in our dot env,
we're going to add a new entry
called ether scan API key. And
we're going to add that API key
that we just got. Now that we
have our API key, back in our
Hardhead, config, we're going to
create a new section in a module
dot exports, tell hardhat that
we have this ether scan API key,
or new section is going to be
called ether scan.