And in here, we're gonna say API
key is going to be ether scan
API key that we're going to
define up here the same way we
define these other keys. So
we'll say const, ether scan API
key equals process dot e NV dot
ether scan API key. And if
something like this pops up, you
can generally just hit enter,
and it will autocomplete it for
you, which is awesome. Great. So
now we have an ether scan API
key back in the heart had
documentation, it tells us by
adding this, we actually get a
new task called verify. Let's
try that out. So open our
terminal back up. And we'll do
yarn, RT hat. Let's see what
pops up. Wow, we did get a new
verification here. When we run
yarn hard hat harder, it
actually looks into our hard
hat.config.js and checks for any
plugins. If there are new
plugins there, it'll add them as
a new task that we can do. You
can manually verify your
contract by doing yarn or MPX
Harnett verify dash dash
network, the deployed contract
address and any constructor
arguments yourself. But we want
to be a little bit more
programmatic than this. So what
we're going to do is we're going
to go back and create this
verification function, it is
good to know how to do it via
command line so that if you want
to verify something in the
future, manually, you can, let's
build this verify function
though. So we're going to take
the our contract address and
some arguments. And for our
sake, we're going to do console
dot log verifying contract that
that just so that we know we
might have to wait for a little
bit. And in our code, we can
actually run any task from hard
hat using a run package. So up
at the top, we're actually going
to import run from hard hat as
well run allows us to run any
hard hat task. So in our code
here, we're going to do a wait
to run. And then we can do there
it thought. Now part of that
allows you to add different
parameters as well in this run.
And it's usually best that you
go ahead and add them in here so
that we're really specific with
what we're doing. If we do yarn
hardhat verify dash dash help,
we can see what parameters we
can actually pass. Well, it
looks like we can pass the
Verify parameter. So we'll do
colon, verify. If you go to the
actual GitHub for the
verification tasks, you can
actually see you can do more
than just verify, you can do
verify, get minimum build,
verify, get constructor
arguments, verify, verify, which
is what we're going to be
working with, and a couple of
other subtasks as well. The
second parameter that goes
inside run is going to be a list
of actual parameters. This
second parameter here is just
kind of the sub task, if you
will, of our verify task. And
this is going to be an object
that contains the actual
parameters. And this is where we
pass in an address, which is
going to be our contract
address, and then our construct
or arguments, which is going to
be arcs. Now normally just this
right here should be enough for
us to go ahead and use this
verify contract in our main
function, but we're going to add
one additional thing to it.
Because in practice, sometimes
there's some errors that can
come up. One of the errors that
often comes up when running a
wait is that the contract has
already been verified. And
you'll actually likely run into
this, because ether scan will
get smart enough by seeing
enough bytecode that is exactly
simple storage that it will
start to just automatically
verify any bytecode that looks
like simple storage. And then
this await will throw an error,
which we want to avoid. So what
we can do is we can add a try
catch onto this await. So
outside of the way, we're going
to add a try. And we're going to
add these little brackets that
wrap around our weight. And then
we're going to put a catch. This
is known as a try, catch and
solidity also has tried catches.
But basically, this e is going
to be any error that this
section throws. So we're going
to do is we're going to say if
this message is already
verified, then we're just going
to continue. So we're gonna say
if e.message.to lowercase, we're
going to make sure it's to
lowercase that includes already
there. If five, then we're just
going to console dot log already
verified
like that. Otherwise, we're just
going to console dot log e. The
reason we do This is because of
this errors, our verification
function will break, and our
whole script will end. And we
don't want our whole script to
end, we want our script to keep
continuing if the verification
doesn't work, because it's not
really a big deal. So I know
this might seem like a lot of
code, feel free to copy and
paste it from the GitHub repo to
just move along. But awesome. So
we now have a verify function
using the Verify task in
hardhat. Let's go ahead and use
this now in our main function,
right below our deploy, we'll do
console dot log deployed
contract two, and then the
contract address. But before we
call this main function, let's
think for a quick second. What
happens when we deploy to our RT
Hat Network? Well, remember, if
we deploy to our Hard Hat
Network, will our contract need
to be verified I need to scan?
Well, we know there's a we know
there's a rink ether scan, we
know there's a COVID ether scan,
we know there's a main net easy
scan. But is there a Hardhead
ether scan? No, of course not.
Right? The hard at runtime
environment is a network local
to our machine. So it doesn't
make sense for us to verify a
hard hat network deployed
contract on ether scan. So we
actually don't want to call this
verify function, when we're
working with our local network.
This is where these chain IDs
are going to come in quite
useful. What we can do is we can
check to see if the network that
we're running on is a live
network or it's a test net, or
it's a network that actually can
be verified, we can actually get
network configuration
information by importing a
network like this. And we can do
something like console dot log
network dot config. Now, if I
run yarn, art, hit run scripts
deploy.js. On our Hard Hat
Network, since I'm not passing a
network flag, we get this
massive output that looks like
this. Our network dot config
contains a ton of information
about the current network that
we're on, you'll see here that
the chain ID of the Hardhead
network is actually 31337 gas
price, which gets set to auto
block gas limit the current fork
of Aetherium that we're working
with, and all these other pieces
here. This chain ID is really
important. Because we can use
this chain ID to figure out
which one is a test net, or
which one is a live network. And
remember, running the script is
going to be the same as doing
dash dash network, hard hat,
you'll see our channel ID is
still 31337. Again, that's
because the default network in
our heart had config, it's hard
hat, which is the same as saying
every single time we run a
script, we're secretly running
it with dash dash network hard
hat. So now we only want to
verify on our test net. So what
we can do is we can say if
network dot config, that chain
ID equals equals equals four,
which is going to be rank B, ad.
And a JavaScript equals equals
equals is nearly the same as
equals equals, except no type
conversion is done, which just
means in JavaScript, four equals
four, and four equals equals the
string of four, but four, but if
you were to use four equals
equals equals four, this is
false. This is true equals
equals four equals equals would
be true, four equals equals to
the string of four would also be
true, but four equals equals
equals to the string of four is
going to be false. So you can
kind of do whatever you want
here equals equals or equals
equals equals. So we want to say
if the network dot config dot
Trinity is four, so if we're on
Rinkeby, then we can go ahead
and actually verify. But we also
want to make sure we only verify
if our ether scan API key
exists. So we can also in here
is site and this double
ampersand means and we can say
process dot e NV dot ether scan
API key. This is some Boolean
tricks that we're doing here,
basically, so our first
conditional we're saying if
network dot config chinati
equals equals equals four, this
section can be true or false,
obviously, right? The chain ID
that we're running on can be the
hardest network, which would
mean this doesn't equal four, or
it would be Rinckey, which means
this does equal four. But
there's no conditional on this
side. So how does this side
work? In JavaScript, if an
object exists, and you try to
cast it as a Boolean, it will be
converted to true. If it doesn't
exist, it will be converted to
false. So in JavaScript,
basically, if either scan API
key exists, if we have this in
our data in VI, this will be
true. And if not, this will be
false. So another way to read
this line here is saying if
network dot config that Trinity
is for AKA, if we're on rink B,
and our ether scan API key
exists, then do some stuff. And
that's what we're going to do
here. So in here, we'd want to
run verify, or verify function
and pass it the contract address
which is going to be Simple
Storage dot address and the
constructor arguments which we
know are going to be blank. And
since our verify function is an
async function, and it deals
with promises and stuff, we want
to add the await keyword here.
Awesome. So we've added a way to
actually verify our contract.
But we're not quite done. See on
ether scan and all these block
explorers the instant we deploy
the contract and the instant we
send the contract, ether scan
might not know about the
transaction yet, it might take a
hot second for ether scan to be
up to speed with where the
blockchain is. So it's usually
best practice to wait for a few
blocks to be mined, until you
actually run your verification
process. We've actually learned
how to do this already with the
deploy transaction. So before we
actually verify we run, we want
to run a weight, simple storage.
Deploy transaction Wait, six. So
we will wait six blocks, and
then we'll run our verification
process. Now, if you want to go
and test this out right now, you
absolutely can. I'm going to
keep going, though, because
again, testing all these on a
test net takes a little bit of
extra time. So I'm going to
finish the rest of our main
function, and then I'm going to
run everything all together.
Okay, cool. So we've deployed
our contract, we've
automatically programmatically
verified our contract. What's
next? Well, what did we do last
time, we started interacting
with the contract. So let's do
const. Current Value equals
await simple storage dot
retrieve. To get the current
value, simple storage, that's
all. We have a retrieve
function, which returns the
favorite number, so let's get
the current value. And we'll do
console dot log, the current
value is and then some string
interpolation, current value.
And then we'll go ahead and
update the current value by
doing cons. Transaction response
equals await simple storage,
that store will store the number
seven, and then we'll await
transaction response dot Wait,
we'll wait one block for that
transaction to go through. And
we'll grab the updated value by
saying const updated value
equals await simple storage
dot retrieve. Then we'll do
console log. The added value is
updated value. Awesome. And this
is going to be our whole script.
So if I can zoom out for a
little bit, I know it will be a
little bit small here, we've got
this huge main function, which
does what? Well it deploys our
contract. If we're on a test
net, it then verifies our
contract. And then it updates
the value to seven. And we have
our verify function down here.
And we have a section of our
code that calls our main
function. Now for run this on
the hard hat network. What do
you think will happen? Well,
let's try yarn, or net run
scripts. Deploy dot j s.
Alright, awesome, we get exactly
what we saw before we get
deploying contract deployed
contract to current value is
zero, update value seven. And
there's nothing in here about
verification. That's exactly
what we want. Now, moment of
truth. Let's try this on
Rinkeby. We'll do yarn, RT hat
run scripts, deploy dot j s,
dash dash network Rinkeby. And
it's gonna go a lot slower,
because obviously now we're
deploying to an actual test net,
where the blocks actually need
to be mined. And we see we
haven't deployed the contract.
Now that our contract is
deployed. We know that we're
currently waiting six block
confirmations for us to go ahead
and verify. And actually I
should add console dot log,
waiting for block the x's so
that we don't get campus weird.
Oh, wait, what are we doing now?
That it looks like we ran into
this error, no such file or
directory, it looks like our
code might not have compiled
correctly here. So here's what
I'm gonna do. We're gonna go
ahead and delete our artifacts
to trash. We're gonna delete our
cache as well. And we're going
to try rerunning this whenever
you run a script with the hard
drive command Hardhead will
automatically recompile it for
you, especially if there's no
artifacts folder. So we're going
to rerun this command and
heartbeat, it's going to compile
first and we can see that it
does exactly that. And then it's
going to go ahead and redeploy.
Hopefully this time, it should
be able to find the contract
that had just compiled looks
like this time after I deleted
the artifacts folder, we
actually did indeed get some
successful compilation. And we
can see here successfully
submitted source code for
contract or verification on the
block explore waiting for
verification results,
successfully verified contracts
simple storage on ether scan,
and even gives us a link that we
can go ahead and Command click
or control click into. And we
can see the contract indeed
being verified. This is awesome.
This is perfect. We've now got a
successful deploy dot j s script
that can deploy, verify, and
then interact with our code.
This is fantastic. This hard hat
thing seems pretty cool. What
else can we do with hard hat
like I showed you before. Hard
Hat comes with these tasks. And
the number of tasks that
Hardhead can come with can be
extended by us writing plugins,
we can actually write our own
tasks in hardhat. And in our
Hardhead dot config, it can
defaulted with this task
account, we can see task
accounts, prints the list of
accounts, and just prints a list
of accounts here actually go to
the heart had documentation to
learn more about creating our
own tasks, one of the ways that
you can define tasks is directly
in our heart head.config.js. But
typically, what people do is
they have a new folder called
tasks where they put all their
tasks. So for now, I'm gonna go
ahead and delete this section
here. And we're going to create
our own task. You'll notice that
now that we've deleted that
section, if we run yarn RDAP, we
no longer see the accounts task
in here, because we've just
deleted that task. So let's
create our own new task. We'll
call this block number.js. And
we'll use this to get the
current block number or whatever
blockchain that we're working
with. So let's create this task.
First, we need to import the
task function, we can get it by
saying const task equals require
arhat slash config. The hard hat
slash config has the task
function. To define a task, we
can now just say task, give it a
name and a description, the name
is going to be blocked number.
And then the description is
going to be prints the current
block number. Now that we have
this task, there's a couple of
things we can actually do with
it, we can add different
parameters to it by using the
dot add command, which allow us
to pass parameters to the task.
And then we could also set
actions which define what the
task should actually do for us,
we're just going to do dot set
action. And define what we want
this function to do. So we're
going to make this an async
function, that's going to take
as an input, the task arguments,
which are going to be blank for
us, and the HR E, which I'll
define in a second. Now, let me
explain the syntax really
quickly. This might look a
little bit weird, but this is
what's known as a JavaScript
arrow function. In JavaScript,
you can actually define
functions without even using the
function keyword. For example,
if we go back to our deploy
function, we have our async
function verify down here.
However, another way we could
have defined this is is without
using the function word at all,
and actually turning this whole
thing into a variable, we could
have said instead, we could say
const verify is going to be an
async function that takes
contract addresses and
arguments. And here's the
function definition. These two
lines are essentially
equivalent. There's some slight
differences between between
using the function keyword and
having your function be a
variable. But for the purposes
of this course, they're
basically the same. Which means
though, that this by itself is a
function, just not assigned to a
variable. But essentially, the
two of these do are exactly the
same. And that's the syntax that
we're doing here. You can
imagine this sort of being like
const block task equals async
function, which takes the params
and then runs that arrow
function. Or you can think of it
as async. Function, block task
parameters, and then the
function definition, these are
all essentially the same. The
major difference is that we're
never giving our function a
name, we never give it this
block task variable. This is
known as an anonymous function
in JavaScript, because it
doesn't have a name. Now that we
have our function in here, we
can now call some function to
get the block number. Well, how
can we get the block number when
we run tasks, we automatically
pass our anonymous functions,
the task arguments, which in
this one, we don't have any, but
we also pass this HR II object.
This HRV is the heart hat
runtime environment. Back in our
deploy script, this is basically
the same as this require hard
hat in here. So this HRV can
access a lot of the same, this
HRV can access a lot of the same
packages that the hard hat
package can. So we can do Hae
dot ethers, just like how you
can import ethers from hard hat.
And in our ethers package,
there's actually a number of
functions we can use like dot
Pro, biter dot get block number.
Let's save this to a variable
const blocked number equals, and
this is going to be a
synchronous, so we're going to
want to add a weight here. And
then let's do console dot log
block number. Or better yet,
we'll string interpolate this
and say current block number
like this. Now though, if I try
to run this task, you'll notice
it doesn't show up in the heart
Atlas of tasks, let's do yarn.
Art app. Hmm, I don't see block
number in here. Well, this is
because we need to add it to our
config dot config will add
require dot slash tasks slash
block number.
And in order for us to import
it, and let's add a module that
exports I'll explain what this
does a little bit later. But now
that we've required it, if I run
yarn hard hat, and now see
blocked over is one of the tasks
that I can use. Now for a run
yarn, art hat block number, we
get current block number is
zero. And this makes sense
because this is defaulting to
our Hard Hat Network, which gets
reset every time we run it. But
if I run yarn, hard hat block
number A dash dash network
Rinkeby, what do you think I'm
gonna get? Again, a much larger
number, current block number is
right here. Because this is the
actual block number of Rigby
versus the block number of our
heart ad network is going to be
zero because it gets reset every
single time, we run one of these
scripts now scripts and tasks
both can basically do the same
thing. They both can interact
with contracts, they both can
deploy smart contracts, they can
both pretty much do everything.
I prefer scripts just as a
general rule of thumb, because I
don't always think adding a
special thing from the command
line makes sense. So I prefer
scripts, but you'll see a ton of
tasks and examples out there as
well. I think tasks are really
nice for specific use cases. But
for the most part, we're pretty
much going to use exclusively
scripts, but it is good to know
what a task looks like and how
to use it. I think tasks are
better for plugins and scripts
are better for your own local
development environment. But if
you want to do everything with
tasks, you absolutely can. As
you're starting to see, this
config piece is pretty powerful.
And we can use it to modify our
entire code base and our entire
project to give our project more
functionality. What else can
this do? Well, right now, as you
can see, every time we work with
a hard hat network, every time
we run a script, we run that
script, and then the Hard Hat
Network is deleted, right? We
can't interact with our
contracts anymore. Well, there's
actually a way for us to run a
hard hat network. Similar to how
we ran a ganache network with a
user interface. What we can do
in hard hat is run yarn, RT hat
node. And what this will do is
it'll spin up a node on a local
network, exactly the same as
ganache but in our terminal. So
you see here started HTTP and
WebSocket. JSON RPC server at
this address. And just like
nosh, it comes packed with all
these different accounts and
private keys, which is awesome.
You'll notice though,
interestingly enough that this
node that we're running isn't on
the Hard Hat Network, well, we
can actually create a new
terminal to try to interact with
this just by hitting this little
plus button and creating a new
terminal. Again, I'm using bash,
but based off of whatever your
operating system is, you can be
using a different shell. And
here, let's go ahead and run
yarn arhat run scripts, deploy
dot j s, and see what happens.
Well, our typical setup happens,
we deploy a contract, we get a
contract address, we update the
value. But if we look at our
node, it doesn't look like any
transactions went through what
we don't see any locking here.
So what's going on? Well, our
Hard Hat Network is actually
different from this locally
running network here. This
locally running network we often
want to refer to as our local
host. So it's slightly different
than the Hard Hat Network. It's
still using the hard hat runtime
environment, but it's just not
this default Hard Hat Network.
It's considered its own separate
network when we're running a
node that it's going to live. of
past the duration of a script.
So we can actually interact with
this by adding a new network to
our hardhead.config.js, we'll
create a new network and call it
local host.
And exactly as we did up here,
we'll give it a URL accounts and
a chain ID. So for URL, we can
get that URL right from our
terminal, I'll put a running
yarn hard hat node. by copying
that and pasting it in here, we
can then do a comma, we'll give
it a chain ID of 31337. Because
even though it's considered a
different network, it actually
has the same chain ID as hard
hat. Interestingly enough, I
know I just said we were going
to give it accounts, but we
actually don't need to give it
accounts. Because when we run
with this localhost hard hat
will automatically give us these
10 fake accounts for us. So you
can kind of think of the
accounts here for this localhost
as, as hard had already placing
them in thanks, hard hat. But
now, if we go back to our bash
here, let's clear the terminal.
Let's rerun the script. And
we'll do dash dash network local
host. Now we should be pointing
to this node. And when I run
this script, we should see some
logging output at the end of
this node. So let's go ahead and
hit enter. Well, we see our
normal stuff on our deploy
script, we flip back to our node
Wow, we see a ton of logging
here. Similar to ganache, we can
see a whole bunch of different
logs on what just happened, we
can see a contract was deployed,
we can see the address the
transaction hash from value,
gas, and the block number and
everything. We can also see our
contract call calling the store
function to update the value of
our favorite number. This is
incredibly powerful for quickly
testing and working with things
on a local JavaScript VM or hard
hat network to be able to see
how your contracts will interact
on a real test net. And this is
much quicker than working with a
real test net. Now additionally,
same as what we said before, any
process that's running in the
terminal, we can kill it with
Ctrl C. So if you want to stop
your node and then restart it,
you can hit Ctrl. C, to stop it,
and then just up and then rerun
that same command to re spin up
your node Ctrl C stops it. And
then you can up to start again.
Another way you can stop it, of
course, is if you hit the
trashcan, which deletes the
whole terminal, we pulled a
terminal back up, we can run it
again. And just remember, if you
hit the X that actually doesn't
delete the terminal, that just
hides it. So our hard hat node
right now is still running
because I just hit it. So I pull
it back up, I can see that it is
indeed still running. But if I
trashed candidate, and then it
pulled the terminal back up, I
can see that it is no longer
running. So running scripts is
great. But what if I don't want
to have to code an entire script
to do some things? What if I
want to just tinker around with
the blockchain? Well, hard hat
comes packed with this thing
called the console. The console
is a JavaScript environment. For
us to run JavaScript commands to
interact with any blockchain, we
can jump to the console by
running yarn, hardhat, console,
and then whatever network flag
if we want to work on rink B,
main net polygon, avalanche,
etc. That's just network local
host. And now we're dropped into
a shell him in the shell, we can
do everything that we do in a
deploy script. And we don't even
have to run these imports,
because everything with hard hat
is automatically imported into
our console. So for example,
let's say I wanted to get a
simple storage contract factory.
Well, I could run exactly this
line here. I could say const,
simple storage, factory equals
await ethers dot get contract
factory, have simple storage.
And now I can go ahead and even
deploy this. So I can even just
copy this line, paste it. And if
we flip back to our node, we'll
see that we just deployed a
nother simple storage. And now
we can do things like await
simple storage dot retrieve. And
I get the return value which is
going to be a big number with a
value of zero. I can also make
transactions so I can do a
weight, simple storage. That
store let's do 55 If I hit up
twice, I can go back to the
simple storage dot retrieve.
call that function and I can see
my big number has a value of 55.
Now, this is a great way to
quickly interact with any
blockchain that we want. Now you
can exit the shell by hitting
Ctrl C twice to get out. Or you
can also just you can also Trash
Can your terminal if you get
confused. This console works
with any network we can even do
yarn, hard hat console dash dash
network hard hat. And we'll get
dropped into a hard hat network.
Now this is not going to be the
same node that's running here,
this is going to be one that
only runs for the duration of
this command. So whenever we
cancel this command, this hard
hat network gets cancelled. And
close out that too. We can also
do yarn, hard hat, console, dash
dash network Rinkeby Rigby, or
polygon or test net or main net
or whatever we want. And we can
do things like ethers dot
provider that can do things like
await ethers dot provider dot
get block number, see the block
number of Rigby. We can also
deploy contracts, we can update
contracts, we can do anything
that we want, you can do
anything in these consoles, and
they're great ways to quickly
test and tinker in interact
with contracts. Now, there's a
couple other tasks that are
really helpful. You'll see
before I went ahead and just
deleted artifacts and deleted
the cache manually. Well, to do
that yourself, you can also just
run yarn Hardhead, clean. And
that'll delete the artifacts
folder and clear out your cache.
We already know what compiled
does. But one of the biggest
things that Hardhead is
fantastic for especially is
running tests. Now we haven't
run tests yet so far. However,
running tests is absolutely
critical to your smart contract
development journey. And we're
going to spend a lot of time in
the future writing really good
tests. The reason that writing
tests are so important is
because we want to make sure our
code does exactly what we want
it to do, especially in the
defy, and the decentralized,
smart contract world, all of our
code is going to be open source
for anybody to interact with,
and potentially exploit. There's
sites like req dot news, which
go through a ton of previous
hacks and how they actually got
hacked and what happened in the
smart contract to enable these
hacks to occur. So testing, so
writing really strong tests is
always going to be our first
line of defense. And we have
this sample test.js, that comes
default with the basic package
of hardhat. But as you probably
already know, we're going to
rename this and change it. So
we're going to rename this to
test deploy dot j s. And we're
going to delete everything in
here and start from scratch. We
want to be able to test all of
our solidity code locally, so
that we know exactly what it's
doing. And we can have a
programmatic way to make sure
that our code does what we want
it to do. So let's write a basic
test for our simple storage
contract. So that we can be sure
that it's doing exactly what we
want it to be doing. Hard Hat
testing works with the Mocha
framework, which is a JavaScript
based framework for running our
tests, you actually can write
tests directly in solidity, if
you'd like to, there's a bit of
back and forth on whether
testing with pure solidity is
better or testing with a modern
programming language. The
argument goes that testing with
a modern programming language,
you have more flexibility to do
more stuff to interact and test
your smart contracts. But the
argument for testing with us
with solidity is that we want to
be as close to the code as
possible. At the time of
recording, most projects do the
vast majority of their testing
in a modern programming language
like JavaScript. So that's what
we're going to be using here. So
to get started with our mocha
tests, we do, we're going to
write a describe function.
Describe is a keyword that
hardheaded mocha will recognize,
and it takes two parameters, it
takes a string, which we're
going to just write simple
storage for now. And then also
takes a function, we could make
function, test func and then
write some stuff in here, and
then pass it to our describe
here. But the common convention
is going to be to do is to make
it as an anonymous function,
which we can create by typing
function, putting an empty
parameter here, and then some
brackets like that. So our
describe function takes a name,
a string, and a function.
Another way that you'll often
see functions in describe is
using that anonymous function
syntax. So you might see just
these parentheses, an arrow, and
then some brackets, the two of
these are going to be basically
the same, there are some
differences. And this second one
is actually best practice, but
just know that you might see
this arrow syntax in other tests
as well. We have described a
sample storage and then our
function here, which is going to
have all of our tests in it.
Inside each one of our describe
blocks. We're gonna have
something called a before each,
and a bunch of It's Our before
each function is going to tell
us what to do before each of our
hits. So we're going to have a
ton of it and then we're going
to have a before each. All of
our IDs are going to be where we
actually write the code for
running our tests. And before
each is going to be some code
that tells us what to do before
each one of these hits, we can
also actually have describes,
inside of describes, which again
have more before each and more
before it's having these nested
describes can be really helpful
for separating and modularizing
our tests. But for this one,
we're just going to have a setup
that looks like this. And for
this demo, we're only going to
have one it. So in order to test
our smart contracts, before we
actually run our tests, we're
probably going to need to deploy
the smart contracts first. So
inside of our before each, we're
going to pass the our before
each a function, that's going to
tell our testing framework what
to do before each test. So we're
going to pass it an async
function like this. And in here,
we want to deploy our simple
storage contract. So to do that,
we're going to need to get the
ethers framework and do exactly
what we did in our deploy
script. So in here, we're at the
top we're gonna say const.
Ethers, equals require art have
an import ethers from hard hat.
Then in our before each
function, we'll say await ethers
dot get contract factory of
simple storage. And we'll assign
this to a const. Simple Storage
factory. And then we'll run
away, simple storage factory dot
deploy. Cool. And let's also
assign this to a variable cost
simple. Now, since right now,
our simple storage and simple
storage factory are scoped just
to inside the before each, we
actually need to stick these
variables outside of the before
each, so all of our events can
interact with them. So instead
of having simple storage,
factory, and simple storage, be
constant variables, we're going
to define them outside of them
for each with the let keyword.
And we're gonna say let simple
storage factory and we're going
to initialize it to nothing. And
then we'll say led simple
storage. Now, if you have a
whole bunch of let's just
initializing another way, you
can write them in JavaScript,
just let simple storage factory
comma, simple storage. And that
works exactly the same. And then
we can get rid of this const
keyword. Because it's not a
constant since we are assigning
it. And now we have simple
storage, factory and simple
storage that we can use inside
of our init function. Now we
have a before each section. So
before each one of our tests,
we're going to deploy our simple
storage contract. So we have a
brand new contract to interact
with for each one of our tests.
Now, inside of the ID, this is
where we're going to say what we
want this specific test to do,
and then describe the code
that's going to actually do
that. So we're going to say it
should start with a favorite
number of zero. So this is
saying what this test should do.
And then we're going to add our
async function to actually do
that. So we'll say async
function. And in here, this is
where we'll actually write the
code to make sure that our
contract does exactly this.
We're say const. Current Value,
equals await, simple storage.re
retrieve. And now in this test,
we want to say okay, now check
to see that this current value
is indeed zero. So how do we do
that? Well, we can say const,
expected value is going to equal
zero. And what we can do is we
can do either we can use either
the assert keyword, or the
expect keyword, which we're
going to import both of these
from a package called Chai. We
actually installed Chai
automatically when we downloaded
the basic parameters when we
downloaded the basic packages
for hardhats. So at the top,
we're gonna say const. Expect
and assert
equals require Chai, I'm a big
fan of using assert as much as
possible, because I think the
syntax makes a little bit more
sense. But there will be
scenarios where we need to use
expect instead. Now, assert has
a ton of functions that are
built in that help us make sure
this is what we expect it to be.
So I can do assert dot equal
current value.to string, because
remember, this is actually going
to be a big number, comma,
expected value. So I'm saying
I'm asserting this retrieve to
return zero, which is going to
be our expected value. Now to
actually run this, we're going
to run yarn, art hat test. And
we see we get an output that
looks like this should start
with favorite number of zero,
and it's indeed passing. You'll
notice that if I were to change
this to one, and this wasn't
correct, it would break and it
would say art Pass or not
passing assertion error expected
zero to equal one. It expected
zero to equal one, which is not
what we want. We want zero to
equal zero. So let's run this
again. Tada should start with
favorite number zero, and it's
passing. Alright, fantastic. So
that's how we wrote one of our
tests, let's write one more test
just to make sure that things
are good. So let's say it should
update when we call store,
because when we call the store
function, we want our favorite
number to update. And we'll make
this an async function as well.
And let's add our stuff in here.
So we'll say const. Expected
Value equals seven, we're
expecting that when we call
store it updates to seven. Now
we can say const. Transaction
response equals await simple
storage dot store. And we can
even just pass it the expected
value here. And then we'll do a
weight transaction response that
weight one. Now let's get the
current value. So we'll say
const. Current Value equals
weight, simple storage,
retrieve. And now we're going to
assert dot equal current
value.to string, comma expected
value. And now we can run all
these tests by running yarn
Hardhead test. And you'll see we
ran both of these tests. And now
if I have 10,000 tests, and I'm
only finagling with one test, I
can actually just run one test
by running yarn, art app, test,
dash dash grep. And I can search
for any keywords in any of the
text here. So I'm going to grep
for the store function. Because
the store keyword isn't in this
tax for this, it, it's only in
the text for this it. So if I do
grep store, it should only run
our second test, which does
indeed, one other way we can run
only specific tests is with the
only keyword. So we can type it
dot only like that. And then we
can run yarn, art hat test. And
it should only run, this should
update when we call store. And
it does indeed, then we'll go
ahead and delete this save, run
again, and it should run all
too. Fantastic. Now the other
way you'll see these tests
written is with instead of
assert, it'll use the expect
keyword. So you'll see something
like expect current
value.to string.to dot equal
expected value, the two of these
lines do exactly the same thing.
And it's sort of up to you on
which one you want to use. And
that's all we're going to do for
our testing. Now. This is
fantastic, great job. Now that
we have some tests, we can
actually start testing to see
how much gas each one of our
functions actually costs. One of
the most popular extensions for
hard hat is the hard hat gas
reporter. This is an extension
that gets attached to all of our
tests, and automatically gives
us an output that looks like
this, that tells us
approximately how much gas each
one of our functions cost. We
scroll down in here, we can read
the instructions on how to
actually install this npm
install Hardhead gas reporter
which we're going to use with
yarn. So we're gonna say yarn,
add hard hat, gas reporter, dash
dash Dev.
And now that that package is
installed, we can go over to our
config and add some parameters
in here so that we can work with
this gas pit. But our neath our
ether scan section, we're going
to add a new section called gas
reporter. To have it run,
whenever we run our tests we're
going to do enabled is going to
be true. And then up at the top,
we can add it by adding require
hardhat gas reporter. Now that
we have it in here, we can do
yarn hardhat test, and after we
run our tests, it'll
automatically run this gas
reporter. So we see our tests go
ahead and run. And then we get
this output that looks like this
that tells us how approximately
how much our contracts and
methods cost. So our store
function looks like It costs
approximately this much gas and
our simple storage costs
approximately this much gas.
This is incredibly helpful for
figuring out how to optimize our
gas as best as possible. Now I
usually like to take it a step
further though. Having the gas
output it like that is nice, but
we can make it even better. I
like to output it to a file by
doing output file. Yes, report
dot txt and then my dot get
ignore like to add it in here,
but doing gas report dot txt
sentence it's not really
important for the gas report to
get pushed up to GitHub. Do no
colors is true. The reason we
add this is because when we
output to a file, the colors can
get messed up basically. And
then the biggest addition we
could do is we can add a
currency in here. So that we can
get the cost of each function in
USD for a blockchain like
Aetherium. Now in order to get a
currency here, we actually need
to get an API key from corn
market cap, just like we did
with ether scan, you can go to
coin market cap, corn market cap
API, get your API key now, and
we'll go ahead and sign up.
Choose a basic plan. We'll agree
and create my account, we'll get
an email verification. And we'll
go ahead and verify. Now in the
coin market cap dashboard, we
can copy our key. And yep, you
guessed it exactly what we're
going to do with this key, we're
going to drop it into our dot
env file, or say coin market
cap, API key equals and then
paste it in there like that. Now
that we have our corn market cap
API key in here, we can go back
to our header dot config and add
it in this corn market cap
parameter. We're gonna do the
exact same way we did above,
we'll do const, coin, market
cap, API key equals process dot
EMV, that coin market cap API
key, and then we'll take this
sticking in here. So what this
is going to do is actually going
to make an API call to corn
market cap, whenever we run our
gas reporter. This is why
sometimes you'll see me comment
this out and uncomment it
because I don't always want it
to make this API calls. But now
what we can do now that it's
enabled, we have an output file,
we can see the currency and we
have our API key, all we can do
is run yarn hardhat test. And
after all our tests pass, we're
going to see a gas report.tx T
that we can go ahead and read
from which has that gas report.
And now it actually has the USD
price of each one of these
transactions, it looks like at
current prices, with Aetherium
being $3,000 per eath, and a gas
price of 43 Gwei, the store
function would cost $6. And the
simple storage function would
cost $64. The current the
Hardhead gas reporter actually
comes with some different
options, though, if you're going
to be deploying to different
network, for example, with
binance, Polygon, Avalanche or
hecho. For example, let's say we
wanted to deploy the polygon,
let's see how much deploying the
polygon would cost well in our
WMV UHD ad token,
Matic And now we'd rerun this
test. And if we look at our gas
report that takes T will now see
the gas price of polygon right
now is around 37 Gray per gas.
And the cost of Matic is 147
automatic and USD. Now we can
see the cost of calling the
simple storage method is going
to be $0.00. Now this of course
is rounded down, but it's going
to be really, really cheap to
call store versus deploying the
contract is going to cost three
cents, I make it a habit to
select false for my gas reporter
whenever I don't want to
actually work with the gas here.
Awesome. Now sometimes when
we're working with our code, if
we don't have these environment
variables specified Hardhead
might get a little bit upset
with us. So oftentimes, I'll add
some code in here. So that these
variables are always populated,
because we didn't specify our
rink prpc URL, ring P RPC URL is
going to be undefined. And that
might throw some errors blow. So
oftentimes, what we'll do is
I'll add an or parameter here,
these double pipes mean or, and
in JavaScript, if we say some
variable equals something or
something else, what is really
happening is we're gonna say,
okay, rink, the RPC URL is going
to be equal to process dot E and
V dot rink, the RPC URL. But if
this rink, the RPC URL doesn't
exist, it's going to be whatever
else is over here. And I might
write something like HTTPS eath
Rinkeby. Example, or something
like this, just so that I don't
make hard hat mad if I don't use
rank B. And we can do something
like that for all these. So
you'll see this syntax,
oftentimes in a lot of code
setups. Now the last thing that
I'm going to show you before
going into the TypeScript
edition of This is test
coverage. And as we progressed
to this course, I'm going to
show you more and more tools
that you can use to make sure
that our simple storage contract
is safe and secure. And we take
all the steps we can to prevent
any hacks from happening if we
deploy in real life. One of
those tools is a tool called
solidity coverage. And this is
also a hardhat plugin that we
can use for our code. solidity
coverage is a project that goes
through all of our tests and
sees exactly how many lines of
code in our sample store dot Sol
are actually covered. And this
can be a Good tip off. If we
don't cover some line of code,
solidity coverage will say, Hey,
you don't have any tests for
this line, maybe you should
write some tests for it. We can
add solidity coverage the same
way we've been adding all of our
packages. npm install dash, just
save Dev, or since we're using
yarn, yarn, add dash dash Dev,
solidity coverage. And we can
then add this to our config, the
same way we've been adding
everything to our config, go to
our config, and we'll write
require solidity coverage. And
there's some configuration
pieces we can add down here
below for this, but we're just
going to use the default now we
can do is run yarn, RT hat
coverage. And this is going to
go through our tests and print
out a file that looks like this,
we'll also get a file called
coverage dot JSON, which is
basically this chart broken down
a little bit more often put my
coverage dot JSON in my dot get
ignore. And I know we haven't
actually seen dot Git ignore, do
what it's supposed to do. But we
will soon we can see here that
about 50% of the code 50% of our
statements in simple storage dot
soul are covered. About two
thirds of our functions are and
50% of the lines, It'll even
give us exactly what lines
aren't tested right now, which
we can see exactly 31 and 32 of
simple swords, outsole aren't
covered, which makes a lot of
sense, because 31 to 32 is this
Add Person function, which we
didn't call and we didn't add to
our tests. If you want to take
this time to pause and try to
make this solidity coverage be
100% across the board, by
writing some more tests, I
highly recommend you do so it'll
be a great learning exercise.
We'll also add the coverage
folder. So covered adjacent and
the coverage folder, which
again, I'll explain what the dot
get ignore folder does a little
bit later. Now the last thing
that we didn't talk about and
here was what is this nomic labs
hard hat waffle. We talked about
Daddy and V heart and ether scan
tasks gas reports. So today,
what is this? Well, we can
actually Google search this and
find out exactly what this is
Hardhead waffle is actually a
plugin to work with the waffle
testing framework. waffle is one
of these frameworks that allow
us to do some really advanced
testing, we're going to be
working with some syntax that
looks really similar to this
really soon. And we'll be
showing you more and more of
this waffle tool
as we continue. Alright, the
next part of this section, I'm
actually going to go over the
TypeScript edition of this. But
for all intents and purposes,
you've successfully created your
first Hardhead project, you've
done a ton of amazing things. In
this lesson, let's do a quick
refresher of what we've learned
so far, we learned how to spin
up our own hard hat projects.
And now we can run yarn, hard
hat and see a list of the tasks
and different things that we can
do with hard hat. We learned
that hard hat looks for this
hard hat.config.js. And this is
sort of the entry point for any
task that we run that starts
with hard hat, we learned we can
add our contracts to this
contracts folder. And then we
compile it by running yarn, art
half compile, we learned that
all the compliation goes into
the artifacts and then the cache
as well. And if we want to clean
reset, we can either delete
these two files or just run
yarn, hard hat clean. So we
learned that we can use scripts
or tasks to actually deploy,
interact and do things with our
smart contracts. We also learned
that I'm going to be using
scripts for the rest of this
course. But if you want, you
could absolutely use tasks as
well. I've asked this question a
million times what's the
difference? Nobody really seems
to know what the main difference
is. But I think the main
difference is that tasks are for
plugins. And scripts are for
your local development Mart,
that is mind limiter, we learned
that we can import a whole bunch
of things, including tasks from
hard hat in our scripts, and we
can work with our async
functions to grab our contracts
and deploy them, we actually
then can programmatically verify
them using hard hat and using
hard hat plugins. And then
additionally, we can interact
with our contracts very similar
to how we did it with ethers. We
wrote a wonderful verification
script. And we also wrote our
own task, we wrote our first
test for this whole space. And
we showed what our tests are
going to look like moving
forward. And we talked a little
bit about their importance. And
I really should stress that
writing good tests is going to
be the difference between a
really professional environment
and kind of a side project.
Whenever I audit smart
contracts, or whenever I'm given
a project for someone to tell me
to take a look at. The first
thing I look at is the readme,
of course. And the second thing
I look at is the tests. And if
tests aren't good, I usually
tell them, hey, you need to go
back to the drawing board, and
you need to level up your tests.
So tests are really really
important, especially for this
space, we learned about a couple
of more environment variables we
can use. We learned about a
couple of tools to see how good
our tests are one of them being
coverage. We also learn about a
gas reporter to see how much
it's going to cost us when we
actually deploy to a real
network. We learned a ton about
the hard hat config, and how
there are multiple networks that
we can add add to our hard
heads, we can make our project
our EVM code, work with any
network out there, we started
working with dev dependencies
instead of regular dependencies.
Now, READMEs are something that
I'm not really going to go over
too deeply in here. But READMEs
are sort of like the welcome
page of your GitHub repository,
and really should give you an
understanding of what your code
does. Being a part of the web
through space. And being a part
of the blockchain ecosystem is
really more than just you coding
your stuff by yourself. You want
other people to interact and
engage with your code and engage
with your projects. I haven't
showed you how to use GitHub
yet. But don't worry, we're
going to but if you look at my
heart had simple storage readme.
If you scroll down, usually, you
really want to have a Getting
Started section where you define
how to set up all the code and
how to set everything up a
Quickstart section, and maybe a
usage section and some testing
section, which teaches people
how to actually use and interact
with your code. Since we're just
learning more of the code part
and not so much the readme part.
For now, we're not going to go
over how to make a fantastic
readme. However, I will leave a
link in the GitHub repository
associated with this course,
link to this best readme
template. It really is a
fantastic readme template that
you can copy to any of your
projects to make them look
really good and give them a
really good setup, so that other
developers can come to your
project, and learn and
participate with what you're
coding. But all right, you have
learned an absolute ton, you
should be incredibly proud of
yourself, and incredibly excited
that you've made it this far.
Now I'm going to jump into the
TypeScript section here. So for
those of you who are coding
along with TypeScript, feel free
to follow along. For those of
you who are not, you just
finished the Basic section on
hard hit, but stick around the
next to heart out sections are
going to be the ones that really
fine grain and hone your skills,
and give you all the
fundamentals for working with
these frameworks. So be sure to
follow along with the next two
sections, we've got a ton more
fantastic content for you, we
are just beginning to get deeper
into the smart contract
ecosystem. So take that lap, get
that coffee, and I'll see you
soon. Alright, also now let's do
this with TypeScript. So I am
going to go ahead and just start
this from our JavaScript
section. However, if in the
future, you want to start a new
Hardhead project, you can
actually start a new project
with yarn, hard hat. And then do
great and advanced sample
project that uses TypeScript,
you'll add a ton of plugins. And
you'll wait a while for
everything to get uploaded. And
you wait, and you wait a little
bit for everything to get
downloaded. We're not going to
do that though, because I'm
going to show you how to convert
this to JavaScript Anyways, if
in future hearted sections, as
we're coding along with
JavaScript, if you want to code
along with TypeScript, you
absolutely 100% can. But let's
go ahead and show you what the
main differences are. Now that
advanced TypeScript thing is
going to add a whole bunch of
packages that you may or may not
want, I will talk about some of
them in our next lesson. But
there are going to be some that
you absolutely do need. Those
are going to be at type chain
slash ethers, dash v five, at
type chain, slash hard hat, at
TypeScript, at types, slash
Chai, at types, slash node, at
types slash moko, TS node, type
chain and TypeScript. And I have
a link in the GitHub repo
associated with this course,
I've got this yarn ad that you
can just copy paste, if you want
to just copy paste that into
your project to run it. Oops,
and I should have added those as
dev dependencies. So we're going
to actually just make them dev
dependencies real quick, just by
deleting these two lines, and
adding a comma here. Awesome,
that looks much better. And then
of course, what we're going to
do is we're going to convert all
of our JavaScript to TypeScript.
So anywhere where we have J S,
we're going to put Ts,
obviously, if you're coding this
from scratch with TypeScript,
you would do the.ts From the get
go. This includes our hard hat
dot config, that's also going to
be TypeScript now. And
additionally, we're going to add
a TS config dot JSON. This is
going to be our TypeScript
configuration. Typically, for a
setup, we're gonna go with
something like this. And you can
copy this from the GitHub repo
associated with this course.
It's basically telling
TypeScript, what versions of
Typescript and what files to
include for working with
TypeScript. Now let's go ahead
and start with our deploy dot
TypeScript. For usual, instead
of using require, we're gonna go
ahead and use import, we're
gonna do the exact same thing.
We're gonna have import ethers
run network, from hard hat. And
then in our verify function,
we're going to add that we're
gonna add the types for these
arguments. So contract address,
is going to be a string. And
args is going to be an array of
arguments. So we're gonna say
it's gonna be any array, because
it could be string, it could be
numbers, it could be balloons,
it could be anything. We're also
going to say for IE, it could be
any, even though this is
technically an error type, we're
just going to put any for
simplicity. For now. All of our
TypeScript scripts are included
in our TS config, or any
TypeScript files are manually
added here, which we have Our
entire scripts folder here,
which is good. So now we need to
add ethers in here. Well, if we
look at our hardhead.config.ts,
we're using require here still,
and we need to swap this out for
import for Donnie V, you can use
dot env slash config for it to
grab your dot env file. Now that
we've imported everything, go
back to our deploy.ts, we can
see that that linting has gone
away. If you want to be even
more explicit, we can go ahead
and add import at nomic labs
slash hard hat ethers like so.
reason we don't need to import
it here is because these two
packages also work with Hardhead
ethers, so they automatically
import it. But if you want to be
super explicit, you can go ahead
and add it like so. Now, we're
almost good to go. But remember,
our Harnett dot config is also
importing our tasks. So we're
going to need to update our
tasks or block number to be
TypeScript fide. So of course,
instead of const require, we're
going to import task from our
that slash config. And we're
going to be sure to export our
task from lock number as the
default. So we're going to do
export default task like so. And
now we should be good to run our
scripts. So we can just do yarn,
art hat, run scripts,
employee.ts. We can do network
hard hat if we choose. And
awesome. Now, it's when we get
to the testing, that things get
a little bit different here. So
let's go ahead and change this
required to import. Just to make
it happy there. Let's try to run
yarn, art head test, we get a
whole bunch of errors, and in VS
code will actually go ahead and
get these errors right from the
linter. One of the trickiest
things that you run into as a
developer in this space is
calling functions on contracts
where those functions don't
exist, or vice versa. We're not
calling functions on contracts
that do exist. Right now the
typing for our contracts is just
type contract, which isn't super
helpful, because type contract
doesn't necessarily have all the
functions that we want it to
have. We want our contracts to
be of type contract, but we want
them to be of the type of our
contract, because if they're the
type of our contract, they can
have all the functions that we
want them to have. So to give
our contracts the correct typing
here, we actually can use this
tool called type chain, which
gives our contracts correct
typing type chain has a hardened
plugin, which allows us to use
type chain and TypeScript
natively together, type chain
slash hard hat was one of these
things that we already
installed. And to add it to our
hard hat, we got to just go to
the hard hat config, and add it
in import at type chain slash
arhat. Now once we import that
in to our config, if we run yarn
hardhat, we now get a new task
here called type chain, you read
the description, it says
generate type chain typings for
compiled contracts, this will
enable all of our contracts to
have their own typing. So we can
have a simple storage variable
of type simple storage contract,
which is much better, because
we're always going to know
exactly what we can do with each
contract. To create this, we run
yarn,
arhat type chain. And this is
going to create a new folder
called type chain slash types.
With types for all of our
contracts, you can even go into
our simple storage sub Ts, which
is going to have all the
different functions and
everything to do with our simple
storage contract automatically
coded into Typescript and
JavaScript for us, which is
incredibly helpful. And again,
no, I haven't shown you what
this is yet. But in our dot Git
ignore, we usually want to add
type chain and type chain dash
types into our dot Git ignore so
we don't push them up to GitHub.
Now back in our test, we're
going to add the exact types of
these different objects here. So
we're going to import them from
that folder that we just
created. So we'll do import
simple storage, comma, simple
storage underscore underscore
factory from dot dot slash
types, ain slash types, the
simple storage factory is going
to be simple storage factory and
then civil storage of course, is
going to be simple storage. So
now when do let simple storage
factory which is going to be of
type, simple storage, underscore
underscore factory, and then
simple storage, which is going
to be of type simple storage
contract. And if we command
clicked into simple storage,
once again, we can see all the
contract functions that we know
and love, are here. In addition,
we have all the functions of the
actual contract itself. Once we
do that, we're pretty much good
to go we just need to have a
couple of new things here. Get
contract factory returns a type