ethers dot contract factory. So
what we just need to do is we
need to wrap this in a simple
storage factory type. So We'll
just do a little wrap like this.
And we'll say, as simple
storage, I'm just going to sort
of factory. And that's good to
go. Now that we've added all
this, we can run yarn, Hardhead
test. And boom, our test run is
normal, but with TypeScript and
with this additional typing that
makes our lives substantially
substantially better. And that's
going to be all you need to know
for TypeScript, reusable, all of
the branches have an optional
TypeScript branch that you can
use to reference to work with
TypeScript.
We've learned really just the
basics of all the different
things we can do with hardhat.
And these next few lessons
Hardhead fun meme and hard hat
smart contract lottery are
really going to be the basics
for all the fundamentals of all
the tools that we're going to
learn in hardhat. Lesson Eight
is going to be our introduction
to full stack and working with
front end and building full
stack applications. Getting all
the way through this course will
give you all the tools to start
your web three journey. But if
you're looking to just learn
just the basics, make sure you
absolutely get all the way to
Lesson Nine. And if you get all
the way through lesson 18, you
are going to know all of the
cutting edge tools for this
space. And you're going to have
the knowledge to become easily
one of the best developers in
the space. So hope you make it
all the way through to the end.
Now one of the most important
parts of this section of this
lesson is going to be pushing
our code up to GitHub, and then
sending a tweet celebrating that
we pushed our first smart
contract our first web three
GitHub repository to GitHub. So
before moving on to the next
lesson, be absolutely sure to
get to the end of this and push
this code up to GitHub. And then
optionally, if you want to
celebrate by sending a tweet,
but be absolutely sure to get to
the GitHub section, because as
I've said, many times the web
three space is this incredibly
collaborative community and
working with GitHub or GitLab,
or any other version control
tool is going to be essential
for your success in the space.
So be sure to get to that part.
All right. Now, welcome back to
the hard hat Fund Me section of
our course. This is the section
where we're actually going to
upload our first code repository
to GitHub if you've never done
this before, this is going to be
the section where we're going to
learn even more about hardhat
using a familiar contract base
we've already worked with, which
is the fund me contract. And
again, if you're using the
GitHub repo associated with this
course, you can scroll down to
the Hardhead Funmi. And all the
code is located in our repo. If
you'd like to do a quickstart,
you can go ahead and get clone
it CVU into it, and then run
yarn, and then just run yarn
hardhat deploy this, I'm going
to briefly show you what that
looks like. So in your in your
VS code, you can do git clone,
grab the package, cd into it,
and then type code period. To
open it up in a new VS code.
Once you're in your folder, you
can go ahead and run yarn. To
install all the dependencies for
working with this project, you
plan on working with the test
net or working with ether scan
or coin market cap, feel free to
fill out your Dotty and V with a
private key RPC URL, corn market
cap key and ether scan key. And
then you can just follow along
with the readme to use this repo
to run yarn, hard hat deploy.
And it'll show you deploying
some contracts and some mocks,
etc. So let's get to building
this ourselves though. Now we're
gonna make a new directory for
this project, it's gonna be the
same setup we've seen before. MK
dir, hard hat. And me, FCC,
we're gonna cd into heart at
Funmi, FCC, and then type code
period. And if code period
doesn't work for you, you can
absolutely open this up by
hitting File, Open Folder, like
we showed you before. Now, we're
in a brand new folder here. And
we're gonna go ahead and add
hard hat here. And we're gonna
run yarn, add dash dash Dev,
hard hat. Now that we have hard
hat, in our package, JSON, and
in our node modules, we can go
ahead and run yarn, start app.
And this will say, What do you
want to do? I'm going to choose
the advanced sample project
here, just to show you what's
going on. And we're going to set
this up in a way that I think
works best. So we'll go ahead
and do the advanced sample
project. Yes, we're going to
have that as the root. Yes, we
want to add a Git ignore. And
there are a lot of sample
project dependencies that it
wants us to add. We're gonna go
ahead and hit yes. But we're
going to end up not using all of
these and I'll show you which
ones we're not going to use and
why. But for now, let's go ahead
and hit yes.
All right, awesome. And now we
have an advanced project in
here. Let me walk you through
the additional things that are
in here. So we have a
traditional contract node
modules, which is going to be
the same scripts is going to be
the same test is going to be the
same. But this comes with a dot
E and V dot example already
packed in for us. It also comes
with.es lint files.es lint, RC
dot j s.es. Lint, ignore es Lint
is known as a JavaScript linter,
which helps you find and
automatically fix problems in
your code for the JavaScript
that I work with. I'm not a big
fan of ES lint, so I typically
don't use it. So I'm going to go
ahead and delete the two of
these. If you want to keep them
in you absolutely can dot Git
ignore. We're going to finally
understand what this file does
in this lesson that NPM ignore
helps Ignore files if you want
to push your project up to be an
NPM package, which we're not
going to do. So if you want to
delete this, you can as well
pretty or ignore it and pretty
DRC. We already know what these
do small hint. And so hint
ignore, which we're going to
talk about it in a minute, or
Hardhead config, which just
comes already with a ropsten
network, a gas reporter and
ether scan package dot JSON with
all the additional packages, the
readme is a little bit more
robust. And then of course, our
yarn dot lock. So this advanced
project looks pretty similar to
what we're going to be working
with anyways. Now I do want to
talk about this soul hint,
though. So what is solvent
solvent is known as a solidity
linter that we can use to lint
our code linting is the process
of running a program that will
analyze code for potential
errors. It also does a little
bit of formatting, oftentimes,
es Lint is a way to lint for
JavaScript code. So hint is a
way to lint for solidity code,
we use prettier to format our
code, and we can use soul hint
to lint, our code, they are
often used a little bit
interchangeably, even though
that's not exactly correct, as
they are a little bit different.
We can run this linter on our
code by running yarn, sole hint,
and then type the name of the
files that we want to lint. So
we do contracts, slash and then
you can just do start out so
everything looks okay, nothing
will happen. Well, let's say we
have a variable that we don't
explicitly say the visibility of
it is. This isn't the best
practice because ideally, we
always say exactly what the
visibility of some variable is.
This obviously gets defaulted.
But it's usually better to be
more explicit. So now if we run
yarn, so hint, contracts start
up so it'll give us a warning,
saying we should explicitly Mark
visibility of state, this linter
is a good way to check for some
best practices for running our
code. So we're definitely going
to keep a small hint around. Now
that we've got a repo here,
let's add a couple of our common
setup pieces here. So in
prettier.rc, we're going to swap
this out with what we've been
using so far. Tab of the form us
tab is false, semi false, single
quote, also false. We're going
to update our prettier dot
ignore node modules, package dot
JSON image artifacts, cache
coverage ID v dot star, readme,
and coverage and anything else
you want to add in here. And
we're going to scroll up to our
contracts folder. And we're
going to swap this greeter dot
soul out with our fund me dot
soul. Now let's go ahead and add
our contracts in here. If you're
following along with the repo,
you go to the contracts folder,
there's actually another folder
in here and the contracts look a
little bit different. So if you
have those contracts, steal from
remix, let's actually grab them
from remix because we're going
to make a couple of changes to
them. If you don't have remix up
anymore, which you probably
shouldn't, because you should be
taking breaks, you can jump back
over to Lesson four remix Funmi
jump into the repo here and grab
the contracts from inside here.
Just go to the fun v dash Free
Code Camp tutorial and grab the
code from there. So we're gonna
grab just fun me and price
converter dot soul. So go ahead
and delete that old file, create
a new one and call it fund me
dot song. Paste it in there. And
then we're going to create the
price converter. That's all. Now
we have both our Funmi and our
price converter contracts in
here. Now one of the first
things that we want to do one of
the first things that we did
last time was we ran yarn
compile to make sure that our
code is actually working the way
we want to. And before we
actually hit Compile, one of the
things that we're going to need
to do is come to our Hardhead
dot config, we're going to make
sure we're on the correct
solidity version. So we're going
to do zero point 8.8 here. And
let's go ahead and try to
compile.
So we can run yarn Hardhead
compile. And you'll see we
actually get an error here.
Library at chain link slash
contracts imported from
contracts slash fund me dot soul
is not installed, try installing
it using npm. In remix, we went
ahead and just imported at
chainlink slash contracts, right
from our NPM and or GitHub. But
in our local code, we have to
tell Hardhead specifically,
where to get this from, we want
to download this specifically
from the NPM package manager at
chainlink slash contracts, we
can download it simply by
running yarn, add dash dash dev
at chainlink slash contracts.
Now that we've downloaded it
into our file, we'll be able to
see it in Node modules here.
Hardhead is now smart enough to
know that at chain link slash
contracts is going to point to
that node module that we have.
So we can now run yarn Hardhead
compile boom, now we can see
compiled three solidity files
successfully. So now we have our
contracts in here and our code
is compiling successfully. We're
probably going Want to deploy
our code? Now in our last
section, I know we use the
scripts module. And we made our
own manual deploy script.
However, something that you'd
notice, the more that you work
with just raw ethers, or even
just hard hat is that keeping
track of all our deployments can
get a little bit tricky. If you
just use a deploy script, it's
not saving our deployments to
any file. Additionally, having
everything in the deploy script
for deploying can make the tests
and the deploy scripts, maybe
not work exactly hand in hand.
And there are a couple of other
things that might be a little
bit tricky to work on, we're
actually going to work with a
package that makes everything I
just mentioned, and a couple
other things way easier. And
this package that I'm talking
about is going to be the hard
hat deploy package. There's a
link to this package in the
GitHub repository associated
with this course. It's a hardhat
plugin for replicable
deployments and easy testing.
And if we scroll down to
installation, we can see we
install it basically the normal
way. They're using npm. And
we're gonna go ahead and use
yarn. So for us to add it, we'll
do yarn, add hardhat dash
deploy. And then of course,
we're gonna do dash dash Dev.
Once done deploying this require
statement to our hard
hat.config.js. Once again,
basically the config is our
entry point. This is where we're
gonna get started. And we can go
ahead and delete our deploy.js
script. Now if we run yarn
hardhat, you see that we have a
bunch of new tasks in here, with
one of them being this deploy
task, this deploy task is going
to be the main task that we use
to deploy our contracts. Instead
of writing our deploy scripts in
the Scripts folder, we're
actually going to create a new
folder, we can create a new
folder by just doing MK dir
deploy. Or you can always right
click and hit New Folder. This
deploy folder is going to be
where a lot of hard hat Deploy
Module looks to deploy code. And
it's going to be where we are
writing our scripts. To write
our scripts, we usually need to
add one more thing in here.
Since we're going to be using
ethers JS in all of our scripts,
we want to add Hardhead deploy
ethers to our package here. Now,
instead of just doing yarn, add
dash dev hard at deploy ethers,
we're going to do something a
little bit weird. We're going to
do yarn add or npm install dash
dash Dev, and we're going to
install it like this. So let me
just copy this. And you can just
copy that from the repo. And
we'll do yarn, add dash dash
Dev, and paste that in here.
What we're doing is we're taking
at nomic labs, hard hat ethers,
which we've used before, and
we're overriding it with hard
hat deploy ethers. Remember how
in our last project, we used
hard hat ethers. So that hard
hat could override ethers to use
hard hat deploy. We use hard hat
deploy ethers, so that hard hat
deploy can override Hardhead,
which overrides ethers, which is
kind of funny. When you say like
that, this will enable ethers to
keep track of and remember all
the different deployments that
we actually make in our
contract. So if we look at our
package, JSON, and now we can
see our nomic labs dashboard had
ethers. Now the version of it is
going to be MPM. Hardhead deploy
ethers. This is our package dot
JSON, basically saying the hard
hat ethers package is now
overwritten by the hard hat
deploy ethers package, which is
what we want. Alright, great. So
now that we have that setup, we
can start writing our deploy
scripts, the way that Hart had
to play works is all the scripts
that get added to our deploy
folder will get run when we run
yarn, hard hat deploy. So a good
practice is usually to number
them so that they run in the
order that you want them to run
in. So since we only have one
contract that we want to deploy
the Funmi contract, we're going
to do 01 Deploy Funmi Jas, and
in this script, this is going to
be where we define how to deploy
the fundament contract. Alright,
so we're in our deploy Funmi
scripts. Now traditionally, what
did we do, we did imports, we
did the main function. And then
we did calling of main function,
that Hardhead deploy is a little
bit different, we're still going
to import our libraries and
packages, but we're not going to
have main function. And we're
also not going to call the main
function when we run Hardhead
deploy Harnett deploy is
actually going to call a
function that we specify. In
this script here. What we're
going to do is we're gonna
create a function, we'll call it
deploy funk.
We're going to export this
deploy function as the default
function for Hardhead deploy to
look for, so we could say,
module that exports dot default
equals deploy funk. To test it
out, we can go ahead and do
console dot log, hi. And then in
our terminal, run yarn, hard
hat, deploy. Oops, get rid of
the parentheses here. Sorry. Run
it again. And we can see it went
and ran our deploy func here.
Now if this syntax is easier for
you to understand, go ahead and
use this syntax and we're going
to be passing the heart at
runtime environment as a
parameter to this function.
However, if we go to the heart
hat deploy documentation, and we
scroll down to an example
script, the syntax looks a
little bit different. And let me
just explain what's going on
here and how we're going to be
writing ours. So instead of kind
of defining everything like
this, and defining the function
name, similar to what we were
doing before, we're actually
going to using a nameless, a
synchronous function, we're
going to make it an anonymous
function, similar to what we've
seen before. So instead, we're
going to say async parameters
like this, I'm going to pass our
parameters our heart at runtime
environment in here. And it's
going to be an arrow function.
And then we're going to wrap
this whole thing in module dot
exports. So we're gonna say,
module, dot exports, equals this
async function like this. This
syntax here is nearly identical
to what's up here, we just don't
have a name for our async
function. So this is how we're
going to set it up instead. But
if this syntax is a little bit
confusing for you feel free to
use this above as the two of
these are going to be the same.
Now the next thing that most of
the documentation does is it
pulls out the variables and
functions out of the HRV that
we're going to use. HRV is the
heart hat runtime environment.
Whenever we run a deploy script,
heart hat deploy automatically
calls this function and just
passes the hard hat object into
it similar to in back in hard
hat simple storage. In our
deploy script. We had ethers run
in network come from hard hat,
instead of coming from hard hat.
We're coming from HRV, which is
basically the same thing as hard
hat. For our script, we're only
going to use two variables from
a jury when you use const. Get
named accounts. And deployments.
This syntax might look a little
bit weird for you. But it's just
a way to pull these exact
variables out of a tree. It's
kind of the same thing as just
doing a tree dot get named
accounts and HRA dot
deployments. But pulling them
out like this means we don't
have to add a tree at the
beginning anymore. And then
additionally, additionally,
JavaScript has something called
syntactic sugar. So instead of
doing this on two lines like
this, we can actually do that
whole bit on one line. So
instead, we just extrapolate
those two variables, right in
the function declaration. So
this line is the exact same
thing as doing this line. This
is an asynchronous, nameless
function using the arrow
notation, or working with our
deploy scripts here. And we're
default, exporting it with
module dot exports. I don't know
that was a lot. And another is
kind of a lot of syntactic sugar
here. But if that's really
confusing for you, just feel
free to use the above. And
whenever we refer to get named
accounts, you can also just do a
three dot get named accounts, or
a three dot deployments. So
hopefully, that's clear that
this top part is gonna be the
same as this bottom part right
here, whichever one you feel
more comfortable working with.
But alright, now that we've
gotten all that out of the way,
let's continue with the script.
So we're using this deployments
object, reason this deployments
object to get two functions,
those two functions are going to
be the deploy function, and the
log function. So we're gonna say
const, deploy log equals
deployments. So we're going to
pull these two functions out of
deployments. And then we're also
going to do const Deployer.
Equals await, get named
accounts. So we are grabbing
this new deploy function, this
new log function, and we're
grabbing this deployer account
from this weird get named
accounts function. What's this
get named accounts function,
this get named accounts is a way
for us to get named accounts.
When working with ethers we saw
when working with ethers, we can
actually get our accounts based
off of the number in the Account
section of each network. So for
example,
in this list of private keys,
private keys zero private key
one private key two, it might
get a little confusing to
remember which ones which so
instead of working like that, we
can add a section at the bottom
called named accounts where we
can name each one of those spots
in the accounts array. So we'll
do named accounts. And we'll say
one of the accounts that will
name is going to be named
Deployer. And we're gonna say by
default, the zero with account
is going to be Deployer. We can
also specify which number is
going to be the deployer account
across different chains. For
example, on Rigby we wanted the
deployer account to be the first
position, we could do something
like this or on hard hat, we
could do it like this. We can
create multiple users. Like for
example, if we wanted to do a
user for some test or something,
and we'll just say the default
is one or whatever we wanted in
here. So back in our deploy fun
me We're going to say we're
going to grab that deployer
account from our named accounts.
And then finally, we're going to
grab our chain ID for reasons
that will come clear pretty
soon. So we'll do const, chain
ID equals network dot config dot
chain ID. Now, how do we
actually deploy this fund me
contract? Well, let's think
about this for a little bit.
When working with remix, it was
pretty easy, right? We just
deployed it to a test net. Ah,
that's kind of the issue there,
isn't it deploying to a rink,
the test net is a little bit
slow. We don't always want to
have to deploy to one of these
slow test nets or even a main
net when tinkering and fiddling
with our contracts, do we know
that's gonna be really bad, we
really want to deploy to a test
net as a last stop after we've
done all our testing locally. Or
we can deploy it to a test that
to see some very specific code
work, like for example, with the
chain link documentation. So
ideally, we deploy this to a
local network first. But can we
just do that? Well, if we look
in our price converter, dot
Seoul, we have this hard coded
address in here, this 0x
address, if we go to Doc's dot
chain that link EVM chains,
contract addresses for Aetherium
data feeds. That address is the
eth USD, specifically for
Rinkeby. What if we work on the
Hard Hat Network? Example?
default network?
Hard Hat. And then like I said
before, if you don't write this
in part, it is automatically the
default network. But if we're to
point to the Hard Hat Network,
harder network is a blank
blockchain. And it gets
destroyed every time our scripts
finish, or even if we're working
with a local node, this price
feed contract won't exist, one
of the code there won't be
updated with data. So what do we
do? How do we test and interact
with our code locally? Is there
a way we can do this? Well, one
of the ways that we can do this
that we'll learn a little bit
later is actually forking a
blockchain, where you can keep
stuff hard coded. But usually,
it's still better to figure out
how to do everything with
something called mocks. There's
a great Stack Overflow question
that just says, What is mocking
and mocking is primarily used
for unit testing, which we'll
talk about in a little bit. And
object under test may have
dependencies on other complex
objects. To isolate the behavior
of the object, you want to
replace other objects by mocks
that simulate the behavior of
the real objects. In short,
mocking is creating objects that
simulate behavior of real
objects. Now, this might seem
like a lot of words. But
basically, what we want to do is
we want to make a fake price
feed contract that we can use
and we can control when working
locally. So back here, I'm just
going to leave a note in here
saying, When going for local
host or Hard Hat Network, we
want to use a mock. Okay, great,
well, we can use a mock and
we'll learn how to make one of
those in a little bit. Well,
what happens when we want to
change chains, for example, back
in dots dot chain to link EVM
chains, contract addresses,
there are a ton of different
block chains that have price
feeds on them. And on each one
of these blockchains, the eth
USD price feed is going to be a
little bit different. For
example, we're looking at ETH
USD, the address of eth USD for
Aetherium main net is different
from the address of eth USD for
Rigby, which makes sense,
they're totally different
contracts on different chains,
they have very similar
functionality. And they do
nearly the exact same thing. But
they're still different. We're
also going to need a way for us
to modularize or parameterize,
this address in here, so that no
matter what chain we deploy to,
we don't have to change any of
our code, we can always have our
code be exactly the same. And we
don't have to come in here and
like flip values and flip
variables and stuff. So let's
keep that all of that in mind as
we write the rest of this. Now
in order to parameterize. This,
we actually want to prioritize
and do a little refactoring of
our fundamental soul.
Refactoring basically means
going back and, and changing the
way your code works. Right now
we have this constructor
function, right the constructor
function is the function that
automatically gets called
whenever we deploy our contract.
Right now it's not doing a whole
lot right now it's just updating
the owner variable to be whoever
sent in the contract. But we can
actually have a do much more
than that. Since this
constructor is a function just
like every other function, we
can actually have it take
parameters, one of the
parameters that we might like
for it to have is going to be
the address of a price feed. So
let's go ahead and add this and
figure out how to refactor all
this code. So we're going to add
constructor address, price feed
for the constructor in here.
When we deploy our contract. Now
we're going to pass it the eth
USD price feed address depending
on what chain we're on. If we're
on rink B, we'll use this
address if one polygon will use
a different one b&b, different
one, Gnosis hecho, avalanche,
etc, you get the picture. So
we're going to marginalize this
like so. Now that our
constructor takes a parameter
for the price feed, we can
actually save an aggregator v3
interface object as a global
variable in our price converter,
we just create a price feed
variable of type aggregator v3
interface, which again, we're
importing from the chainlink
repo, which is an interface
object which gets compiled down
to the ABI. If you match an ABI
with up with an address, you get
a contract that you can interact
with. So we're going to do the
same thing here. We're gonna
say, aggregate Tor, v3
interface, public price feed,
ration and call this price feed
address so that these don't have
the same name. And in our
constructor, we're going to say
price feed equals, and we're
going to do the exact same thing
we did with our price converter
equals aggregate tore the three
interface
of price feed address. Like so
now, we have this price feed
address that's variable and
modularized, depending on
whatever chain that we're on.
Now, what we can do is we can
grab this price feed address,
and we can use it for our price
converter. So where are we using
our price converter? Well, just
a quick reminder, we're using
using price converter for you at
256. We're using this as a
library on top of our unit 256
type. So we're calling message
dot value dot get conversion
rate. So we look at our price
converter, we have this function
get conversion rate, which takes
an FML as its initial parameter,
which again, since this is a
library, it automatically passes
the message dot value into this
get conversion rate function.
But we could also pass in this
price feed, and therefore we
wouldn't need to hard code it in
the get price anymore. So let's
go ahead and figure out how to
do that. Well, what we can do is
we can do message dot value dot
get conversion rate, we'll stick
price feed in here. And then
we'll have to update our get
conversion rate to do a comma so
that it takes a second
parameter, because remember,
again, the initial parameter is
going to be message dot value.
And the second parameter is
going to be what we define here.
So we'll do s amount, comma ag
reg gate Tor v3 interface. And
we'll call this price feed. And
now, when we call our get price
function, we can pass the price
feed to the get price function.
And up here we can have get
price. Take, you guessed it an
aggregate or the three interface
called price feed. And now we no
longer need to hard code in the
price feed. And we can just
delete those lines and have it
compile like this, which is
awesome. So quick refresher,
we're parameterizing that price
feed address and passing it in
with a constructor that gets
saved as a global variable to an
aggregator v3 interface type, or
passing it to a get conversion
rate function, which passes it
to the get price function, which
then just calls latest round
data. And we probably could have
made this even easier, probably
could have just got rid of the
get price function and stuck
this code in the get conversion
rate. But we'll leave it there
for now. Now that we've done
that refactoring, let's make
sure it works. Yarn Hardhead,
compile, invalid value undefined
for hardhat dot config dot
networks. Let's go to the let's
go to the config real quick.
That's because the default
network needs to be outside of
networks. My mistake. Let's try
that again. I spelled interface
wrong and the price converter.
And a quick note, if gives you
an error like this, oftentimes,
you can command click or control
click and open that file up
right in the editor, which saves
you some time, we're going to
have defined the line and find
the file. But yeah, let's spell
that correctly. And let's try
this again. And awesome. It
looks like it's compiling
correctly. And we just have some
warnings, it looks like these
warnings are just about this git
version, which is because we're
shadowing this, we're creating a
new price variable down here,
you've no we just created a
global price free variable.
Let's just go ahead and delete
the get version function
altogether since we're not even
going to really need it. And we
only use the Git version to show
you how to actually start
working with interfaces. And
then we'll compile it one more
time for good measure. Boom
compiled successfully. Awesome.
So now we've just refactored our
code. So we can pass a price
feed address depending on the
network that we're on. Okay,
great. With all that being said,
let's come back to our deploy
Funmi script, and let's learn
how to actually deploy the rest
of it. In order for us to deploy
a contract we remember from our
last sections that we use the
contract factories, with heart
hit Deploy, we can just use this
deploy function. And to use the
deploy function, we'll say const
Funmi, which is going to be the
name of our contract, equals
await. And we'll call this
deploy function, the name of the
contract that we're deploying
right now, and then a list of
overrides that we want to add
here. So we're gonna say who is
actually deploying this by
saying from, we're gonna say
it's from the Deployer. We're
gonna pass any arguments to the
constructor In this args piece
here, which we just added a
single Argh. So these brackets,
we're going to make it a list of
arguments, we're going to put
the price feed address in here,
which we'll show you how to do
in a second, put price feed
address. And then we're also
going to do some custom logging
here so that we don't have to do
all that console dot log stuff
that we've been doing this whole
time. And we need to put
something in here. We need to
put an address in here. And you
can use this backslash star to
put like a common in between
your code.
We can't just do const address
equals, you know the address and
stick it in here. Well, I mean,
we could but we're not really
prioritizing now. Right? We're
kind of back to just hard coding
it here. So what can we do
instead? Well, what we can do is
we can actually use the chain ID
to do something like if chain ID
is x, use address, Y, or if
chain ID is Z use address A. So
we can do something that looks
like this. And to enable this
functionality, we actually take
a page out of the Ave GitHub. So
Ave is another protocol that's
on multiple chains and has to
deploy their code to multiple
chains and work with multiple
different addresses. So what
they do is they use a number of
different useful tricks. But one
of the main ones is using this
helper hardhat config. Now
they're using TypeScript with
JavaScript, but it's gonna be
the same thing. With this
config, they have different
variables, depending on what
network that they're actually
on. And depending on the network
that they're on, they use
different variables. So they use
this network config almost to do
exactly what we're trying to do
here. So what we want to do is
we're going to create a new file
at the root directory, so just
click down here, new file. And
we're going to call it helper,
hard hat config dot j, s. And
this is where we're going to
define that network config. And
say, hey, if you're on network,
a, use this address network, be
this use this address, etc. So
we're going to create an object
called const. Network config.
equals and we're going to add a
bunch of stuff in here. So our
main network that we're working
with right now is rinky. dinky
has a chain ID of four. So we'll
say chain ID four is going to be
named Rinkeby. And the eth USD
price feed address is going to
be the price feed address of
rank B of the eth USD price
feed. So we're going to copied
from the documentation or from
the GitHub, whatever you want to
do, and paste it in here. Now we
have a simple methodology of
keeping track of different price
feeds a different contract
addresses across different
chains. Let's say for example,
we wanted to deploy to Polygon
as well. Well, first, what are
we going to need? Well, we're
going to need the chain ID of
polygon. So a quick little
Google Search brings us to the
polygon documentation. And we
see the chain ID is 137. So I'll
do 137. What's a little brackets
here, we'll say name, polygon.
Then we'll do a comma eth USD,
price feed. And then we'll add
the price feed of eth USD on
polygon. So docstoc, chain link,
polygon or Matic and then we'll
look up eth, USD. And boom, we
see it right here. We've grabbed
this address, and we paste it
in. Well, what about the
Hardhead? Network? We'll get to
that in just a second, don't you
worry. And then at the bottom,
we need to export this network
config. So our other scripts can
actually work with it. So we'll
do module dot exports equals
network config. And we're going
to actually export a couple of
things from this file, which is
why we're doing it like this
instead of that default way that
I showed you before. So back in
our script, now, what can we do?
Well, first, we want to go ahead
and import that network config.
So we'll say const. Network
config equals require, and then
we'll import it, we'll go down
and directory to help our
Hardhead config and save. And I
just want to mention this one
more time, just so that it
doesn't confuse anybody. This
syntax here, constant network
config with the little curly
braces around it is the same is
if I went const. Helper config
equals this thing, which helper
config is now kind of this whole
file. And then const network
config equals Hopper config dot
network config. So again, this
index is just kind of an easy
way to extrapolate or pull out
just the network config from
this file. So that's how that
works. And that's why we export
it at the bottom so that we can
do this, please use the GitHub
repository to ask questions and
discussions especially about
some of this JavaScript stuff.
Alright, great. So now that we
have this network configured
here, we can now do this part of
where we say if China d z use a
if chain ID is x use y. So Since
our helper config is nicely in
this kind of dictionary, key
value pair style, what we can do
is we can say const. eth USD.
Price feed address equals
network config at the chain ID,
because if Francina D, or it'll
be this object, French entity
polygon, it'll be this object at
the eth USD price feed, we're
going to save this to eth USD
price feed address. And now no
matter what chain we're on,
whenever we run hard hat deploy,
if I run yarn, hard hat deploy
dash dash network Rinkeby. This
chain ID is going to be four.
And so it's going to use this
price feed address. If I do dash
test network polygon, and I
remember to add both ring P and
polygon to my networks, like
here, the channel is going to be
137. It's going to use this
price feed address. So this is
awesome. This is exactly what we
want. But is it everything that
we want? Those of you who have
been questioning while I have
been coding and talking, you
might be thinking, Okay, well,
you talked about this marking
thing. You talked about
localhost and hard hat. And how
do we test this locally? Like
this is how we go to a test net
and a main net. But what about a
local network? And that is
exactly what we're going to talk
about now. So we've modularized,
our code and parameterize our
code so that we're going to use
the address based off of the
chain that we're on. But what if
we use a chain that doesn't even
have a price feed address on it?
What do we do there? This is
where we actually create those
mock contracts. The idea of mock
contracts here is if the
contract doesn't exist, we
deploy a minimal version of it
for our local testing, or our
local testing. And deploying
mocks is technically a deploy
script. So what we do actually
is back in our deploy folder is
we're going to create a new
file, and we're going to call it
00 Dash deploy mocks dot j s, we
started with 00. Because this is
almost like the pre deploy
stuff, we only do this,
sometimes we don't always deploy
mocks, right, we don't need to
deploy mocks to Rinkeby, or
polygon or or Aetherium main
net, because those already have
these price feeds, we're
actually going to deploy our own
mock price feed contracts. And
in our deploy Funmi script,
we're going to use our own
contracts, instead of already
established contracts. If we're
on a network that doesn't have
any price, few contracts, like
hard hat or locos, for example.
So let's write our deploy mock
script. So the setup of this is
going to look nearly identical
to our deploy Funmi. And again,
if you want to set it up like
this, you absolutely can. But
I'm actually just going to copy
this, this part, paste it in
here, because that initial part
is going to be exactly the same.
Oh, and over here, I just
realized that we're calling this
network thing without being
defined, JavaScript will kind of
be smart enough to know where
this network thing is coming
from. But it can be a little bit
confusing. So it's better to be
really explicit, and say, const.
Network equals require hard hat,
this network thing is coming
from hard hat. And we're going
to grab this line. And we're
also going to use this at the
top of our script here. And then
our top section is going to look
exactly the same as well, we're
going to grab these three lines,
and paste them in deploy
deployer chain ID, boom, it's
all going to be the same here,
because we're setting up to
deploy some stuff. Now we want
to deploy a new contract. But if
we look at our contracts folder,
this is all we have right now.
So we're going to need to add
this mock this fake contract to
our contracts folder. Now what
we can do is in our contracts
folder, we want to separate this
file from the rest of our file
so that we know okay, this isn't
part of our project, but it is
part of our testing. So we're
going to right click Create New
Folder. And we can either call
it mocks, or test I like to call
mine test. And inside of this
folder, we can go ahead and
right click create a new file,
I'm going to create a new file
and call it mock, v3 aggregate
tore that soul. And this is
where we're going to define our
mock price feed aggregator
ourselves. So how can we create
our own fake price feed
contract, so we can test
everything locally? Well, one
thing we could do is we go to
the chain link GitHub repo, and
go through the contracts and
find one of these price feed
addresses, source eight, or
maybe we'll go back to source
we'll maybe we'll check in V
six.
Looks like we could find some
stuff and look around and we
probably copy paste all this
code, but it really seems like
kind of a huge pain in the butt
to have to copy all this code.
Now we absolutely could we copy
paste the code in here, but
we're gonna do something a
little bit more clever. So the
chainlink repo actually comes
with some mocks. If we go to
contracts, SRC V 0.6 tests They
actually have a mock v3
aggregator dot soul in here that
we can use as our mock. So we
can copy paste everything, but
we'd have to revamp a little bit
of it because it's doing some
dot dot stuff. It's talking to
other contracts that are locally
in this file structure that are
not going to be in our file
structure. So instead though,
what we can do is we can use
this node modules package to our
advantage, we can just say
pragma, solidity, carrot zero,
point 6.0, we'll use the same
version that that package is
doing. And then just do import
at a chain link slash contracts
slash SRC slash v 0.6. Slash
tests slash mock, B, three egg,
Reg, gay tore that soul. And
then we'll add, and then of
course, we'll add spdx, license
identifier, MIT. And boom, this
is actually all we need. If we
just import the code like this,
remember, this is exactly the
same as copy pasting this
contract into our project, of
course, with this path resolve
to where it actually is in our
node modules. Now, actually, I
can run yarn hardhat compile,
and it will also compile this
contract. Except for of course,
we have an issue, hey, compiler
versions don't match. Right?
What's What's up with that now,
you're going to get into
situations where you will be
working with contracts that are
not the same version of solidity
as you why well because
contracts keep being deployed
all the time. And there are a
ton of contracts that are in
version 0.4, solidity,
0.5 0.678, and probably 910, or
15 billion, or however many
solidity versions will come to
be. So in our config, in our
hard hat dot config, when you
scroll to the bottom, we can
scroll to where we're defining
our solidity version. And we can
actually add multiple solidity
versions, so that our compiler
can compile multiple versions of
solidity. To do that, we'll say,
so Lyd, did T. And we'll turn it
into an object here, we'll make
sure to put this comma here. And
inside our solidity object,
we'll put compilers and we'll
have a list of compilers. Our
first one we'll say is version,
zero, point 8.8. And we'll say
our second one is going to be
version 0.6, point six, and then
we'll go ahead and save that.
And it looks like mine wanted to
format it like this, which is
fine. Now, we can go ahead,
rerun, yarn, Hardhead, compile,
and boom, compiled five solidity
files successfully. This means
that our Mark V aggregator
should also have been compiled.
And if we look in artifacts, at
chain link, do indeed see this
at chain link slash contract
slash SRC bid, and a v 0.6. In
tests, we see this mock
aggregator dot soul, which has
been compiled. Awesome. So now
that we have our mock contract
compiled, we now have a contract
that we can use to deploy a fake
price feed to a blockchain. So
how do we actually do this?
Well, it's going to be the exact
same way that we deployed the
Funmi contract. But we're going
to add a little if statement in
here, we don't want to deploy
this mock contract to a test net
or a network that actually has a
price feed on it, we could just
do something like if chain ID
does not equal, you know, some
chain ID, then deploy marks,
right. And then this is kind of
pseudocode. Obviously, this code
won't actually work. But
instead, what I like is I
actually like to specify which
chains are going to be my
development chains, which chains
are going to be the one that I
can deploy these mocks to, in my
helper, hard hat config, I'll
define these chains. So I'll say
const, development chains,
equals, and then I'll just say
hard hat, and local host. I'll
export these. And back in my
deploy mocks, I'll import these
with const. Development chains
equals require dot dot slash
helper Hardhead config. And now
I'll say if development chains
dot includes chain ID. This
includes keyword basically is a
function that checks to see if
some variable is inside an
array, then we're gonna go ahead
and deploy Max, and which is
what we want to do. So we'll do
log, which we're getting from
deployments, which is basically
console dot log. And we'll say
local network detected,
deploying mocks.
And we'll do a weight ploy, and
we'll deploy our new mock v3
aggregator mock v3 aggregator
will do a comma. There a little
colons here. If we want to get
really specific, we can say
contract v3 aggregator which
we're kind of already saying
we'll say from deployer We'll
say logging is going to be true.
And then we need to pass some
arguments, we need to pass the
constructor parameters for the
mock v3 aggregator, which are
what? Well, let's go to docs
chain to link to find out. Or
you can also just go to Node
modules chainlink, SRC V 06,
tests, and then all the way down
to mock V three, aggregated out.
So where you could also find the
constructor in here, whatever
one you like better, sometimes I
find it easier just to read
GitHub Ctrl plus F or Command
plus F for constructor. We see
it takes a decimals and an
initial answer. And if we read
through the code, we'll learn
that the decimals object is
going to be equivalent to the
decimals parameter is going to
be equivalent to this decimals
function and the initial answer.
And the initial answer is
basically just going to be what
is the price feed starting at,
we actually get to pick the
price of the price feed, which
works out really well, because
that works out great for
testing. I usually like to
define the decimals and the
initial answers somewhere
outside of this function so that
I can access it later. One good
place you can add it is once
again in our helper Hardhead
config.js. So I might do const
decimals equals eight. And then
const initial answer. Answer
equals, and we'll do 2000. So
since we have a decimals, we'll
do 2000 And then 123456788
decimal places, and then we'll
export these as well. Export
decimals, and export initial
answer. We could of course, just
do you know, const decimals
equals eight at the top and then
initial answer and then use them
down here. But I like to do it
like that. So Conce. So now we
have to import them in here.
const development chains. It's
also grabbed decimals. It's also
grabbed initial answer, we'll
save it. We'll take a look back
at the constructor looks like
it's decimals first, initial
answers second. So in our
arguments, we'll do decimals
first, initial answers second,
and tada. And then we will be
all done that we'll do a quick
log box deployed. And then I
also like to do kind of like a
big line at the end of all of my
deploy scripts just to be like,
hey, that's the end of this
deploy script. Anything else
after this is going to be a
different deploy script. All
right, great. Now our deployed
mocks script is actually done.
But our deploy Funmi script
isn't quite done. Is there a way
that we could run only our
deploy mock script? Well, yes,
there is. Great, thanks for
asking. What we can do at the
bottom of our deploy mock script
is we can add a module that
exports dot tags, equals, and
we'll say all and marks. Now
what we can do is if we run
yarn, hard hat deploy, we can
add this flag dash dash tags.
And it will only run the deploy
scripts that have a special tag.
So we'll run our mocks tag,
which means it'll only run our
deploy mock script. And, and
oops, actually, in our helper
config development chains is
actually hard hat and localhost.
And I said, we're going to try
to do with the chain ID, sorry,
we're going to do this, we're
gonna do development chains dot
includes network dot name.
Because our helper config is
using names and not chain IDs,
so if development chains that
includes that network the names,
then we're gonna go ahead and
deploy the mocks. So let's go
ahead and run this yarn here and
hit Deploy dash dash tags,
mocks. And perfect we do indeed
see our mocks getting deployed
here. This log true means that
it's going to spit out stuff
like this. It'll say contract,
it's deploying, it'll say the
transaction it's doing and it'll
say where it was deployed with
how much gas and awesome This
means our deployed Mach script
is working perfectly. So now we
have our deploy mocks script
working perfectly. So how do we
apply that back to our deploy
Funmi script? Well, we're gonna
do the exact same thing here.
Instead of making eth USD price
feed address constant variable,
we're gonna say let at USD price
you'd variable so that we can
actually update it. And we'll
say, if development chains dot
includes network dot name, what
we can do with hard hat deploy
is we can just get the most
recent deployment using a
command called literally get. So
we'll say const. eth USD
aggregator equals await
deployments dot get. And then
the name of the contract that we
deployed Mach v3 aggregator, and
if you wanted to just do get
instead of deployments dot get,
we absolutely could, just by
doing it like this. Those are
exactly the same. So we'll get
the address like this and then
we'll say eth USD price feed
address equals that eth USD
aggregator contract dot address.
And then if we're not on a
development chain, if we didn't
deploy a mock, we're just going
to do exactly what we did
before. With using the network
config. Oh, my goodness. Now,
now that we've done all of these
steps, let's add a little log
thing at the bottom here with
just a bunch of hyphens. Now, we
should have a very robust script
to flip between a local
development chain, a test net
chain, a main net chain, and
allow us to deploy literally
everywhere without changing any
of our solidity. And then we
just take this, this eth USD
price feed address and stick it
into logs here. And then at the
bottom, we can do module dot
exports, dot tags equals and
then we'll just do all and then
we'll call this one Funmi. Oh,
now moment of truth. If we did
all this, right, we should just
be able to run yarn, hard hat
deploy. And it should work on
our local chain, our hard hat
chain. And then it should also
work on any test net that we
give it. So let's give this a
try. Yarn, Hardhead deploy.
Let's see if this works.
Awesome. And we got this all to
deploy locally to our Hard Hat
Network, we can see that we went
ahead and we deployed mocks, we
did our little underline here.
And then we deployed Funmi
deployed at this address with
this much gas. Now, what are the
other awesome things about hard
hat deploy? When we run our
local blockchain, our own
blockchain node, hard hat deploy
will automatically run through
all of our deploy scripts and
add them to our node. So now if
I run yarn, hard hat node, we're
going to spin up a new
blockchain node, but it's
already going to have all of our
deployed contracts on it. So
every time we spin up a local
node, now it's going to come
automatically packed with the
contracts that we want on it. So
we are going to show us doing
this on a test net on Rinkeby.
But before we actually test it
on Rinkeby, I'm going to add a
little bit of the auto
verification piece in here as
well, because we did that in the
last lesson. And we wanted to
show how to do it in hard hat
deploy as well. So right after
we deploy our Funmi, we can do
something similar here, we'll
say, if developer chains
includes network dot name, we'll
say if developer chains doesn't
include network dot name,
because we don't want to verify
on a local network. So we'll say
if not development chains dot
includes network dot name, the
exclamation mark, aka the bang
means not when we're talking
about booleans. So we're saying,
if the name of the network isn't
a development chain, we want to
go ahead and verify and same as
last time. And if process dot e
NV dot ether scan API key,
then we're going to go ahead and
verify. Now before we had our
verify code, right in our deploy
code, we're gonna do something a
little bit different here.
Instead of having our verify
code in our deploy scripts here,
we're actually going to create a
new folder called utils, which
stands for utilities. And this
is where we're going to add
different scripts that we can
use across different
deployments. Because let's say
we have 50 Deploy scripts, we're
not going to make 50 Deploy
functions, we're just going to
add them to our utils folder,
and in our utils folder, or
create a new file called verify
dot j s, we're going to add that
code from our last project in
here. So if you want, you can go
ahead copy paste from our last
project over to this one, or you
can pause the video to type it
out yourself. Since we're using
the run command here, we're
gonna do const run equals
require RT hat. And then at the
bottom, we're going to do module
exports. Exports equals verify.
Now that we have a verify script
in our utils folder, back in our
deploy Funmi we're going to say
const. Verify equals require dot
dot slash utils. Slash verify.
And since now in our verified
Jas, we have a lot of this
trycatch stuff in here, we can
just do a wait. Verify and a
verify once again takes a
contract address and a list of
arguments. We'll say await
verify, fund me dot address and
then the list of arguments. To
make the list of arguments
easier to put in. You can go
const args, equals and then
we'll just stick our eth USD
price feed in here and then
replace this with args and then
take this args and pop it on
down into the second parameter
here. All right, great. Now
let's go ahead and deploy this
to With the Rinkeby test net,
and what do we need to deploy
this to the Rinkeby test net?
Well, let's jump into our hard
hat config first. And let's
clean this up, we don't really
need this accounts task, so I'm
just going to delete it, I don't
really need this comment. So I'm
going to delete this too. And
let's jump into the network
section, we're not going to be
working with ropsten. So we're
gonna go ahead and dump that. We
are however, going to be working
with rink B, the URL is going to
be that same Rinkeby RPC URL. So
we're going to define that up
here, like we did before. And if
you want to copy paste from your
last project, feel free to do so
you can also follow along with
me or fastforward me the counts
is going to be the same. I'm
going to go ahead and just copy
paste the gas reporter with what
we had from before. So we're
going to add this constant corn
market cap API key equals
process dot EMV dot corn market
cap API key. Do the same thing
with the ether scan API key
Licious add everything in here.
Now. We have our ether scan
section in here already, we're
gonna have our gas reporter be
false, because I don't really
feel like using it right now.
And then finally, we're going to
add one more thing in here.
Remember how in our last
project, before we actually
verified we waited some block
confirmations. That way ether
scan could make sure to catch
up. Well, we can do the exact
same thing in here in our hard
hat dot config, we can add a
section for each test net for
how many blocks we want to wait,
I'm going to add block
confirmations of six. Now back
on our deploy Funmi. In a new
section, I can add wait
confirmations of network dot
config. That block on for
motions, or one is or one means
if no block confirmations is
given in our Hardhead dot config
will just wait for one block.
And again, the reason we want to
wait for approximately six block
confirmations is we want to give
ether scan a chance to index our
transaction. And I added a chain
ID 42 when it should be for my
mistake. And of course, we're
going to need our dot env file,
where we add all of our stuff
from the last session, the RIP
ERP CRL private key ether scan
API and then coin market cap
API. All right moment of truth.
Let's try this out. If we run
yarn Hardhead deploy dash dash
network Rinkeby. It should not
deploy any marks because we have
this if statement in our mock
deployment. But it should deploy
our Funmi contract using the
correct price feed address. And
then it'll go ahead and verify
it. Since we're waiting for six
block confirmations, we can even
be super secure by adding dash
dash tags and just running the
funding tag. But we're just
going to do yarn hearted deploy
network Rigby. And let's see
what happens. All right, and
we're deploying funding. And we
can see the transaction that we
have for fun me, this is that
logging feature, we have log is
true for deploying Funmi. So it
gives us the transaction once it
has a transaction, and it will
give us the address once we have
the address. So we're going to
wait six block confirmations for
this transaction to finish going
through. Now we see we've
deployed this contract address
with X amount of gas. And now
we're running the verification
process. While the verification
process is running, we can pull
up Rinkeby ether scan, paste our
address in here and see that we
have indeed created this
contract. And now it looks like
we've successfully verified the
contract on ether scan. So if we
hit refresh, we can indeed see
that the contract has been
verified. Awesome. All right. So
this is fantastic. Our deploy
script is looking great, we're
able to deploy to a local chain,
we're able to deploy to a test
that and if we wanted to, we
could deploy to any network that
we wanted simply by updating our
hard hat config, and then
updating our helper config. This
is fantastic.
Great work so far. Now we're
about to jump in and level up
our tests. But before we do
that, we're going to clean up
our Funmi contract a little bit
to make it look a little bit
more professional. And I'm going
to talk about some of the syntax
and some of the reasons why some
conventions exist. We're not
going to do this full force on
all the projects moving forward.
But they are good to know and
they are good to keep in mind
when moving forward and working
with our contracts. While we go
through this we're going to
learn why some of these
conventions exist including
learning a little bit of low
level solidity. So don't skip
this part. When we get to later
sections. We're going to be a
little bit looser and not be as
strict with the code style
guides but That's basically what
we're gonna go over now. And for
now, you might see this event
funded thing here, please just
ignore that for now, in an
earlier take, I'd introduced the
events much earlier. And now
we're actually going to learn
about events a little bit later
in the course. So please ignore
that event funded for now. So
let's go ahead and tweak a
little bit of our contracts
here. Now what I'm talking about
tweaking this to make it look
professional, a little bit more
professional, I'm talking about
the solidity style guide, there
are some conventions for naming
and ordering that we can follow
to make our code look a little
bit better. Now, like I said,
this is going to be a little bit
more optional, because it can be
a little bit verbose. And it
doesn't really make that big of
a difference. But it can
increase readability of your
contracts by a lot and make your
code look a lot nicer. So if you
want, you can go through this
style guide to learn more about
what kind of makes solidity look
nice, and what makes it not look
nice. But well, that's some of
these style guides in here,
we're not going to follow the
style guide exactly to a tee.
But we are going to make some
best efforts to make our code
follow the style guide, we've
got a link to the style guide in
the GitHub repository for this
section, we can read some more
about the layout. But the main
thing we want to look at is this
order of the layout, we want to
start with our imports with our
pragma statement, our imports,
interfaces, libraries, and then
contracts. And then inside each
contract type declarations,
state variables, events,
modifiers, and functions. So
let's go back here and make sure
that we're up to speed, we want
our pragma first. Alright,
awesome, we did exactly that,
then we want our imports. Okay,
awesome, we have those too.
Something that's not in the
style guide is going to be error
codes, which we definitely want
next. So next is going to be
error codes. Now this is where
we're going to bump into one of
our first updates here. As of
recent, it's sort of becoming a
best practice to add the name of
your contract, some underscores,
and then the name of your error.
Whenever you're running into an
error. This makes it a lot
easier to understand which
contract is throwing the error.
So for this, we're going to say
error Funmi, two underscores not
owner, then we're going to
scroll down to the our revert
and set it like this. This way,
when if we ever run into this