error, we know that the error is
coming from the Funmi contract,
not from the aggregator v3
interface, or the price
converter or some other
contract. So that's how we want
to write our error codes here.
If we had any interfaces or
libraries not imported, we would
add them here. But then finally,
we add our contracts. In this
file, we only have one contract
here. It's our Funmi contract.
Awesome. Now the next thing we
want to learn about as far as
style guides go is this thing
called natspec. natspec stands
for Etherium natural language
specification format. And it's
basically a way of documenting
our code inspired by Doxygen
uses Doxygen style comments and
tags to help document our code,
you can click the link here in
the solidity documentation to
learn more about Doxygen. If we
scroll down in the
documentation, here, we can see
an example of using natspec.
Whenever we have a contract or a
function that needs
documentation, we can add some
syntax that looks like this to
it. So for example, if we wanted
to add this to our code, we
could add a comment explaining
this funding contract to start a
piece of natspec, you can do
three backslashes, or one
backslash, two stars, and then
another ending star here.
Everything we put inside of this
comment section basically gets
turned into a comment. For the
start of our contract, we'll do
the Add sign title to explain
basically, what this contract
is, it's fun, we contract is
going to be a contract
for crowdfunding, we'll add
another star. And we can add the
author of it, which is going to
be your name, I'm going to put
Patrick Collins, of course, then
we'll add a notice, which is
just kind of a note to people we
can say this contract is is to
demo a sample funding contract.
And we can also add apt Dev,
which is a note specifically to
developers. And we can say this
implements price feeds as our
library. The reason that we want
to add these tags here is
actually because we can use the
natspec to automatically create
documentation for us if we
download so we can actually run
solc dash s user doc dash dash
dev doc, and the name of our
file to automatically generate
documentation. So this is also
really helpful for automatically
creating documentation for other
developers who interact with the
protocol later on. You can use
this natspec For as many or as
few functions as you'd like.
Most of us probably aren't going
to be making documentation. So
we really just want to follow
those guidelines if we think
some function or some section of
our code is a little bit tricky
for other developers. Now that
we're inside of contract, we can
follow the order of our
contract. We're first going to
start with type declarations
which we don't really have any
except for the fact that we're
using our price converter for
the UN 256 type. Okay, great.
You Next, after our type
declarations, we're going to do
state variables. And in this
state variables section, this is
where we're actually going to
change the name of some of our
state variables. So we'll do a
little common here state
variables. Now in the solidity
style guide, kind of adhere to
the naming styles, we use upper
and lowercase, we use total caps
with underscores here. However,
these naming variables are going
to change in the future in this
section. And if you're following
along with the GitHub repo
associated with this course,
these are going to be actually a
little bit different than what
you see. However, for now, we're
going to leave them as they are,
because the reason why we're
going to change them isn't going
to be quite clear yet. Don't
worry. So these names are going
to change soon, but not yet.
Alright, after state variables
comes events, and modifiers. We
don't have any events, but we do
have a modifier. So we'll copy
this. And actually, we'll delete
this comment here. And we'll
paste our modifier here. Oh, and
it looks like looks like we're
not auto formatting here. So
we're going to uncomment
immutable actually, so that it
automatically auto formats.
Okay, great. We're out of
formatting now. And Cool.
Alright, so now we have our
modifiers. Next, we have right
here, and then we have all of
our functions. Great. We
actually want to group our
functions in this order that I
just print here. So we want the
constructor which we have
received and fall back, we do
have fall back and receive. So
we're going to actually copy
those and delete this comment.
We're gonna stick those veterans
Heath here looks like receive
goes first. So we'll put that
here. Then external functions,
then public, internal, private.
So we have public public. And
that's it. And then we can
delete this part down here.
Okay. Cool. And if we want, we
can do that syntax up here from
the net spec for our functions.
For example, for fund it, we
could even just copy paste, we
would remove title, we would
remove author, and we just say
add, notice, this function,
funds this contract. And we can
even leave a little dev thing
here to talk about it. Now if we
have parameters, you can do apt
puram. And say like what the
parameter is. And then if we
have returns, we can say
returns, or returns and then
what it returns for the
documentation. Since this
doesn't have any parameters in
here, and doesn't return
anything, we can just leave it
like this. And great, we've just
revamped our contract here to
make it a little bit more nicely
formatted. Great job. Now, like
I said, we actually are going to
change the names of our state
variables, and we're going to
add some functions in here and a
little bit. So if we're
following with the GitHub repo,
the state of the contract right
now is going to look a little
bit different. But it'll make
sense why change this up in a
little bit.
Alright, so now that we've
cleaned this up, we've got to
deploy marks, deploy Funmi.
Let's go ahead and start writing
some tests. And after we write
these tests, we're actually
going to run that gas estimator
and using that gas estimator,
we're gonna go back, and we're
going to update this contract
one more time to make this even
cheaper to use and work with.
And remember, that's going to be
one of the advantages of writing
these tests is how we can
optimize our contracts to be
even faster, more gas efficient,
etc, we want to make sure that
we write really good tests, and
this is going to be one of our
first jumps into these more
professional test setups. So
we're going to jump into our
test folder, we're going to
delete this sample test.js. In
our last section, we went over a
really minimalistic test, which
is great. However, when we get
bigger and bigger projects,
we're going to want to start
testing more and more different
things, we're going to get more
and more into at least two
different types of testing. So
if we cd into our test folder,
we're going to make one
directory called staging. And
then we're going to make another
directory called unit. And now
if we look in our test folder,
we now have a staging folder,
and a unit test folder. Now
we're going to talk about two
different types of tests. The
first one is going to be
something called a unit test.
Now what is a unit test? Unit
testing is a software testing
method by which individual units
of source code are tested.
Basically, what we want to do is
in our contracts, we want to
test minimal portions of our
code to make sure that they work
correctly. Then once our small
pieces of the test work, we want
to do a staging test or maybe an
integration test. This might be
where we run our code on a test
net or some actual network. You
can think of a staging test,
it's kind of the last stop
before you deploy to a main net.
They're not always 100%
necessary, but they can be
really, really helpful.
Remember, we do want to be
conscientious of how much we use
our test nets, but we absolutely
would 100% want to make sure
that everything works locally
and that we unit test and we run
all of our code locally. Then we
can use staging tests on an
actual test net to make sure
that our code will work with
actual other contracts. Now unit
tests can be done with local
Hard Hat Network or a forked
Hard Hat Network, we'll talk
about this for tar Hat Network
very soon, right, now, let's
build these unit tests, these
unit tests are going to be
basically what we saw in our
last section. So let's go in and
let's jump in and write some of
these unit tests. So let's
create a new test, we'll call it
on me dot test dot j, s. And
we'll start making our tests in
here. Now, we did test
previously in our last section,
but our tests here are going to
look a little bit differently,
we're actually going to use
hardhat deploy, to automatically
set up our tests as if both of
these deployed functions had
been run. So let's go ahead and
get this started. So we're still
going to do that same setup that
we're gonna do describe, we're
gonna say fund me. And this is
going to have that async
function like so. And in here,
we're going to have a before
each, and we're going to have
some hits and some describes and
everything. Now since we want to
unit test this, we're gonna go a
little bit heavier on the test
here, and then with our last
project, but in the future,
we'll go a little bit lighter
with some of the tests. So let's
get started. If we run yarn
Hardhead test right now, we're
gonna get zero passing. Now, if
we run yarn hardhat coverage,
we're gonna get something that
looks like this, saying, Hey,
you're missing a lot of stuff.
So let's try to cover some more
lines with our tests. And one
way we can do that is actually
we can group our tests based off
of different functions. So let's
have our first set of tests be
around our constructor. To do
that inside of our first
describe, we can add another
describe, have this describe the
just the constructor, this
larger scope will be for the
entire Funmi contract. And
everything inside this one will
just be for the constructor. So
this will also be an async
function. And these tasks will
be just for the constructor. But
before we even work on this
describe, we probably want to
deploy our Funmi contract. So
let's learn how to do that. So
we'll do a before each, which
will be an async function. And
we're going to deploy our Funmi
contract using hard hat deploy.
Since we use hard hat deploy,
our Funmi contract will come
even with our mocks and
everything. So above the before
each,
let's do let me HDMI. And then
here, we're going to deploy
Funmi, where we're going to
deploy our Funmi contract is
first by pulling in our
deployments object from Harnett
deploy. So we'll do const
deployments equals require
hardhat. And this deployments
object has, has a function
called fixture with fixture does
is it allows us to basically run
our entire deploy folder with as
many tags as we want. You'll
notice I added this alt tag in
both of our scripts. This means
that in this deployment stuff
fixtures, it's gonna be a wait
deployment of fixtures. If I run
away deployments dot fixture,
I'll run through our deploy
scripts on our local network and
deploy all of the contracts that
we can use them in our scripts
and in our testing, and we can
deploy everything in that deploy
folder with just this one line.
isn't that helpful. Now, once
all of our contracts have been
deployed, we can start getting
them will say fund me equals
await ethers, and we'll pull an
ether some hard hat as well. dot
and this is where hard hat
deploy is helpful. Again, hard
to deploy rapt ether is with a
function called Get contract,
this get contract function is
going to get the most recent
deployment of whatever contract
we tell it. So we'll say get
contract of fun to me. So this
will give us the most recent Lee
deployed Funmi contract in just
this one line. And now Funmi
will be equal to this line here.
Now we're going to make a bunch
of transactions on our Funmi. To
test it. Of course, we can also
tell ethers which account we
want connected to fund me. So I
can say const deployer equals
goes away get named accounts,
exactly like we did in our
deploy scripts. And then we just
need to import it from our tap
in our deploy scripts we
imported get named accounts
inside of our input parameters
for our deploy function.
Remember getting named accounts
and deployments was abstracted
from if we look up here, from
the hard hat runtime
environment, and like I said,
the hard hat runtime environment
is basically the same thing as
hard hat. So we can just go
ahead and import it like this,
actually like this. Because we
actually need to abstract just
the deployer from getting named
accounts. And now what we can do
is we can connect our Deployer
to our Fund Me account. So
whenever we call a function with
fund me, it'll automatically be
from that the player account,
which is great. Another way you
can get different accounts
directly from your heart had
config. Is you could take const
accounts equals await ethers dot
get signers, ethers dot get
signers is going to return
whatever is in this account
section of your network. If
you're on your default network
hard hat, it's going to give you
a list of 10 fake accounts that
we can work with you then of
course, can do something like
const. Account one equals
accounts. More correctly would
be account zero equals account
zero and work like that. We'll
leave that comment that out,
just in case you need a
reference to it in the future.
Okay, great. So now we have our
Funmi contract. Let's go ahead
and write some tests for testing
the constructor. And we're
probably going to want to use
this deployer object down here.
So we'll do let deployer above.
And we'll do something a little
finicky here. But we'll say
deployer equals Wait, get named
accounts, dot Deployer. And
we'll just wrap this up so that
we can just grab this deployer
object and assign it to declare
like so. Now in here, we'll
create our first test, we'll say
it will say it sets the Agra
Gator addresses correctly. Comma
will have this be an async
function. And we'll say const
response equals await fund me
dot, let's get this price feed
here, fund me dot price feed.
And then we'll want to make sure
this price feed is going to be
the same as our Mk V three
aggregator since we're going to
be running these tests locally.
So we should get our mark three
V three aggregator up top. Let's
do let mock v3 aggregate store.
And we'll grab this address the
same way mockbee Three
aggregator equals await ethers
dot get contract mockbee Three
aggregator comma, we'll connect
this one to the deployer as
well. So we'll want to say cert
dot equals cert dot equal
response comma lock v3
aggregator dot address. And of
course we'll want to say const.
Assert equals require gy. Import
that from DJI. Okay, cool.
Now, let's go ahead and try this
out. Yarn hardhat. Test. Oops, I
spelled response wrong. Let's
try that again. Awesome. So this
means that we are indeed
assigning the price feed address
correctly to the Mach v3
aggregator. Okay, great.
Awesome. I think for now, that's
all we really want to do for our
constructor. Now these two are
kind of a nice to have, I showed
them more just to kind of demo
what they look like, we're going
to skip writing tests for them
for now. And we're actually
going to go ahead and delete
them directly from the contract.
If you want to go ahead and
write some tests for them and
leave them in your examples for
your learnings. You absolutely
can pause the video and write
some tests for it if you choose
so, but we're going to skip
them. Next though, we are going
to move on to fund and running
some tests for fun here. So
let's go ahead and write
describe fund. This will be an
async function. And in here,
we're going to do a number of
tests. So if we're going to go
line by line here, what's the
first thing that we should look
at? Well, we should look at this
require line we should write a
test to see if this contract
actually does fail? If not
enough, eath is sent. So let's
go ahead and we'll say it fails,
if you don't send enough eath
have this be an async function?
Now, how do we test to see if
something fails? Right now we've
done assert equals, but if
something fails, we might run
into an issue. So for example,
if I run await fund me dot fund,
but I don't pass any value to
this transaction. Let's see what
happens. I run yarn Hardhead
test. Well, our test is actually
going to break VM exception.
While processing transaction
reverted with reason string, you
need to spend more eath. So our
tests are going to break which
is good. We want this to break.
But we want to tell our test
that this is okay. Right? Want
to tell that this is okay. So
the way we can do this, and this
is where our waffle testing
comes into play. With waffle and
with testing, what we can
actually do is we can use the
expect keyword and expect
transactions to be reverted and
for transactions to fail. So
instead of using assert here,
we're actually going to run a
wait expect fund me dot fun 2.2
dot B, that reverted and we've
actually even be more specific
here by saying to be reverted
with and then the exact reverted
error, you need to spend more
eath. Now if we run our tests,
oops expect is not defined. So
we need to import that from
Chai. Which chai is being
overwritten by waffle, we see
that it does indeed Pass, which
is perfect. So now we have a way
to both assert things and expect
things to fail. Awesome, even
with the specific failure codes.
Perfect. Let's write some more
tests here. Well, we probably
want it to correctly update this
data structure. So we could say,
it updates the amount funded
data structure, it's going to be
an async function. In here,
we're going to need to call fund
v dot fund. However, we're going
to need to actually pass some
value with this transaction. And
for now, we'll just hard code
the value that we're going to
send, say const. Send value is
going to be
112345 678-910-1234 5678, which
is going to be one eath. Another
way we can write this though, is
we can use the ethers utility to
make this a little bit easier to
read. Because all those zeros
are kind of confusing, and it's
hard to tell at first glance
what this actually is. So we're
gonna actually use ethers dot
utils dot parse ether, one, this
parse ethers utility converts
this one into that one with 18
zeros, which makes life a lot
easier. If you go to the ethers
documentation, there's also a
parts units function where you
can actually convert any unit,
either ethers or Gwei. Or really
whatever you want to do, you
could convert any number to any
other Aetherium you type. So
this is the set value that we're
going to use for our fund. And,
and this is definitely going to
be more than our minimum USD of
50. So after we call this fun
function, we'll say const
response is going to be equal to
a weight, fund me dot address to
Mt funded address to Mt funded
for the deployer dot address.
Because remember, this is a
mapping of each address and how
much they've actually funded. So
if we use the deployer address,
it should give us the amount
that we actually sent. So now we
can run assert dot equal
response.to string, right,
because this response is going
to be the big number version of
how much has been funded by that
account. And that should be the
same as our send value.to
string. Since send value, our
one should be the exact same as
the amount that we funded, we
can run just this one test, or
running yarn, art hat, test,
dash dash grep. And we'll put
this in quotes allow funded for
this amount funded line. And it
looks like we ran into an issue
here, because we don't need to
do deployed at address, we can
just do deploy here. And great,
it looks like we are indeed
passing. Now if we even run yarn
Hardhead coverage will now see
we've got at least a little bit
more coverage here. It's still
not going to be great. But we
have much better coverage. We
have some statements, some
branches, and at least some
functions covered. So this is
awesome. Let's keep going. Are
we all done testing our fun
function? Well, probably not.
What else can we do with our fun
function? Well, we're also
adding funders to a funders
array. So let's go ahead and
test for that. So it adds funder
to array of funders has been an
async function. And we'll say
await fund mean that fund value
is going to be send value. We'll
say const response equals await
fund me dot calling the funders
array at index zero. So this
will be funder equals await fund
me dot funders zero. And then
we'll say assert dot equal
funder should be the same as the
Deployer. So let's go ahead and
run this test. We'll hit up a
couple times. And we'll change
the GREP to under to array so
that it looks for this line. And
perfect. It looks like that one
is also passing. Great. So the
money's coming through, the
minimum amount is coming through
and our data structures are
being updated. Awesome. Now we
could be a little bit more
verbose and do even more testing
with this fun function. But I
think for the most part, we've
got the gist, right. So now
let's go ahead and move on to
the withdrawal function. So
we're going to create a new
describe or withdraw. This is
going to be an async function.
And let's see what the
withdrawal function does. Only
the owner of the contract is
going to be able to get the
balance, get the money back. And
we're also going to reset all of
the amounts that each one of
these users is done. So let's go
ahead and do some withdrawing.
Now in order for us to test
withdraw, we probably first want
the contract to actually have
some money and so what we can do
actually is we can add another
before each in the describe to
automatically fund the contract
before we run any tests. So we
can say before each async
function. We can say await, fund
me dot fund. Value, send value.
Now for all of our tests in this
withdrawal scope, we're first
going to fund it with eath.
Let's say it can withdraw,
withdraw eath. From a single
founder, this would be an async
function. And this is going to
be a little bit longer test. So
I'm going to set it up to be an
arrange, act and assert test. So
arrange act assert is just sort
of a way to think about writing
tests, you want to arrange the
test, then you want to act. And
then you want to run the
asserts, and you'll see what I
mean in just a second. So we're
going to arrange this test,
we're going to set this test up,
we want to actually check that
we're correctly withdrawing the
ether from a single founder. So
first, we're going to get the
starting balance of the
fundraising contract and the
Deployer. So we'll say const.
Starting under me, balance,
equals await, fund me dot
provider, dot get balance, fund
me dot address. So we're gonna
start with the balance of the
fund V contract after it's been
funded with some eath. And we're
also gonna get costs start
starting, deploy your balance
goes await, fund me dot
provider, dot get balance of
deployed employer.
So we're getting the starting
balance of the Funmi, we're
getting to the starting balance
of the employer so that we can
test later on how much these
numbers have changed based off
of what happens when we call the
withdrawal function. Now that
we've done a little bit of
setup, we can actually run this
withdrawal function, we can do
the act here. So we're gonna say
const, trans action response
equals await, fund me dot
withdraw. And then we can say
const, transaction receipt
equals await transaction
response. That Wait, one, and
now we should be able to check
to see that the entire fund
rebalance has been added to the
deployer balance. So now we can
say const ending fund me balance
equals a weight on me that
provider dot get balance of
Unreal dot address. Then we can
say const ending deployer
balance equals await, fund me
dot provider dot get balance
of Deployer. And now we can just
check to see if the numbers work
out here.
So we can say assert dot equal
ending fund me balance is going
to be zero, right, because we
just withdrew all of the money.
So ending funding balance should
be zero. And we'll say assert
dot equal starting fund me
balance plus starting deployer
balance. So the starting funds
the balance plus the starting
employer balance should equal
the ending employer balance.
Since we're grabbing whatever
the starting deployer balance
started with plus the starting
fund to be balanced, because we
just withdrew all of the
starting fund, we balance that
should equal the ending deployer
bots. Now a couple of notes
here, since starting Funmi
balance is calling from the
blockchain, it's going to be of
type a big number, we want to
use big number dot add actually,
instead of the plus sign here,
just because it'll it'll make
working with our big numbers a
little bit easier. So instead of
starting Funmi balance, plus
we're gonna be starting from the
balance dot add. Like that. And
that should be good. One other
thing about this, though, is
that when we called withdraw our
Deployer did what our Deployer
spent a little bit of gas. So
this actually isn't accurate. We
actually also need to calculate
in the gas cost, so we wouldn't
need to do dot add gas cost.
We'd also have to do.to string
because big numbers are objects
and so identities a little bit
weird. So to test to see if
they're equal, we'll just make
them both strings. Now we don't
have gas costs. So let's figure
out how to get the gas cost from
this transaction. So we can add
it to Are any deployer bounce,
so we can run this assertion
here. So what we can do is we
can actually find the gas costs
from our transaction receipt.
And I'm going to show you a
couple of phenomenal tricks you
can use with VS code. And if
using a different editor, then
don't worry too much about this.
What we can do in VS code
actually is create something
called breakpoints. unverified
breakpoint file is modified to
please restart the bug session,
or let's put it right here, put
it right in this line after
transaction receipt is created.
But before ending Funmi belts,
what this breakpoint does is it
stops the script at this line,
and allows us to drop into
something called a debug console
and see all the variables that
are happening. At this time, we
want to look at the transaction
receipt and see if the total gas
cost is in there. This is also
incredibly helpful for dropping
into tests and dropping into
scripts and seeing exactly
what's going on that's wrong. So
what we can do is we can move
down to this run into bug
section. And if it's not there,
you can hit additional views.
And we can click this JavaScript
Debug Terminal, which will
create a new terminal in our
terminal section. Now, what
happens here is if we run yarn,
hard hat test, it'll run our
testing and everything. But when
it hits this breakpoint, it'll
stop. Currently, there is no gas
cost. So we're just going to
delete this for now. So that we
compile and we work in
everything. But if we run yarn
Hardhead test, see, it's gonna
say debugger has been attached
to start running our tests. And
it's going to stop on this line
here. And if we look in this
variable section on the left
hand side, we can actually see a
ton of the variables that are in
here. And we can read a little
bit more about what's going on.
And if we go over to our debug
console, we can type in things
like transaction receipt, and we
can see a ton of information
about that transaction receipt
object, what we're looking for
is we're looking to see this
transaction receipt, which we
could look in the debug console
or over here, if there's
anything to do with gas in here.
And it looks like there is
there's a gas used big number.
And there's also an effective
gas price. So the amount of gas
used times the gas price is
going to give us all the money
that we paid for gas here. So
now that we've figured out
there's a gas used and effective
gas price variables in this
transaction receipt, which we
could have also found in the
documentation here. However,
sometimes it's even quicker just
to find it out yourself what we
can do, we can exit the debugger
by clicking this little thing
here. Go back to terminal will
trash can the JavaScript
debugger, we'll remove the
breakpoint. And we'll grab those
two variables we can pull them
right out of that transaction
receipt object by typing const.
Yes, used comma effective gas
price equals transaction
receipt. So again, with this
curly bracket syntax, we can use
this to pull out objects out of
another object. And now that we
have these two objects, we can
create a const gas cost or total
gas cost is going to be equal to
the gas used times the effective
gas price. Which again, since
these are both big numbers, we
can use a big number function
called dot mol to multiply them
together. Now that we have this
total gas cost, we can come down
and we can say the ending
deployer balance plus that gas
cost to string. Now the two of
these should be equivalent. I
know there's a lot of math that
we're doing in this section and
a lot of new things. So I want
to just quickly rego over what
we just learned. So first off,
the font of the contract comes
with a provider, we could have
also done ethers dot provider
dot get balance, but we're using
fun v dot provider because we're
using the provider of the Funmi
contract. It doesn't really
matter what we use here. We just
wanted to use this get balanced
function of the provider object
which gets us the balance of any
contract. We do the same thing
with starting deplore balance.
The reason that we needed the
starting balances is because we
wanted to compare it to the
ending balances to see if all
the money went to the right
places, we then call the
withdrawal function. And from
the transaction receipt, we
grabbed the gas used and the gas
price. If you want to debug your
JavaScript code, you can add a
breakpoint like so go to run
into bug, open your debug
JavaScript terminal, which is
different from your regular bash
terminals. And when you run
JavaScript commands in here,
they will stop where your
breakpoints are. Then you can
read the different variables and
see where different things are.
Using that knowledge. We pulled
out the gas use and effective
gas price from the transaction
receipt and used it to get the
total gas cost of this
transaction, we then got the
ending fund, we balanced the
ending deployer balance, and
used all those variables to make
sure all the money went to the
right places. And we, we can
check this by running yarn
Hardhead test dash dash grep
withdraw eath in quotes, since
there's a space here, and we can
see that our test does indeed
pass. Great job. If we didn't
add the gas cost here, and we
just did.to string, we would see
something like this, we would
see that the numbers are ever so
slightly off, because we're not
anticipating we're not
calculating the gas here. So we
always want to make sure we're
using the gas if we're doing
calculations like this. Now
another incredibly powerful
debugging tool that we're not
really going to go over here.
But it's important to know about
because it can be really helpful
is that you can actually use
console dot log in your solidity
with hard hat. If you're inside
of a heart hat project, you just
import hard hat slash console
dot soul. And then right in your
solidity, you can do console dot
log, and then type pretty much
whatever you want. When you
execute these functions, similar
to how we do a console dot log
in JavaScript, those will
actually console dot log out to
your terminal. Here's an example
of if you run yarn, hard hat
test and you have those console
dot logs, you'll see stuff like
this get printed out. So in
addition to the Visual Studio
Code debugger, importing hard
hat slash console dot Sol, and
using console dot logs in your
solidity can also be an
effective debugging strategy.
Feel free to give this video a
pause, implement this in some of
our contracts and try it out in
our tests. So we tested that
withdrawing eath when there's a
single funder works perfectly,
let's test withdrawing eath if
there are multiple funders, so
we'll do it, let's say allows us
to withdraw with multiple
funders. Why would this be an
async function. And let's do
this await Funmi not fun, but
with a number of different
accounts. So we can create a
whole bunch of different
accounts of course, by saying
const accounts equals await
ethers dot get signers. And we
can loop through these accounts
and have each one of these
accounts call the fund function.
And we're going to do this with
a for loop. So we're going to
say for let i equals we'll start
with the first index of the
accounts because the zero with
index is going to be the
Deployer. So we'll say let i
equals one is going to be less
than let's say six. And we'll do
i plus plus. And in here, we'll
say const. And me contract Funmi
connected contract equals await.
And me dot connect two accounts,
I, so we need to call this
connect function because right
now if we scroll up back to the
top, our Funmi contract is
connected to our Deployer
account. And anytime we call a
transaction with Funmi, the
deployer is the account that is
calling that transaction, we
need to create new objects to
connect to all of these
different accounts. So we're
gonna say fund me connected
contract, which is now connected
to one of these different
accounts dot fund. And this is
where we'll do value, send
value. Or excuse me, we'll do
await. Great. So this is going
to be our our range section. And
then same as we did above, we
need to grab those starting
balances. So we can just copy
that, those two lines and paste
that down here. Now we're going
to move into act, I'm going to
call that withdrawal function
again. So let's say const,
transaction action response
equals await and MI dot
withdraw. And we're going to do
the exact same thing as we did
above, getting the transaction
receipt and the gas costs so we
can get everything correct. Once
we've done the act, we move on
into assert. And we're going to
do some very similar things to
what we did above, like this,
for example, this whole first
part is going to be exactly the
same. We also want to make sure
the funders are reset properly.
So we'll make sure that this
funders array is reset properly.
So to do that, we can actually
just check to see that if
looking at the zero with
position throws an error so we
can run a wait expect fund me
dot get on me dot funder on me
dot funders of zero. This should
revert so we'll say await expect
Funmi dot funders dot two dot b
dot reverted and then we want to
loop through all these accounts
and make sure that it makes sure
or that in our mapping here, all
their amounts are zero. So we'll
say, for I equals one is less
than six,
i plus plus, we'll say assert
dot equal. Wait, fund me dot
address to amount funded, of the
accounts of I got address should
be zero. So we're making sure
that all of these mappings are
correctly updated to zero. So
let's go and test this. So we're
withdrawing with multiple
founders, we're going to go back
to our terminal, we're going to
hit up, we're going to change
this GREP or this one. We'll see
if this passes. And it does
indeed, so this means that our
withdraw function works really
well even when there's multiple
funders and we can be happy and
go to sleep knowing that. Now
the other thing we absolutely
want 100% want to test is that
our only owner modifier is
working, we want only the owner
to be able to withdraw the funds
from here. So we'll create a new
session, we'll say it only
allows the owner to withdraw
only allows you to withdraw.
This will be an async function.
And in here, we'll say const.
Accounts equals ethers dot get
signers again. And we'll say
const attacker equals accounts
of one. So we'll say the first
account will be some random
attacker will connect this
attacker to a new contract,
we'll say const attacker
connected contract equals await
on DB dot Connect. Attacker dot
address, excuse me a dot connect
attacker. Since we're not just
connecting the address, we're
connecting the account which
attacker is an account object.
And then we'll do a wait expect
attacker connected contract dot
withdraw dot two dot b dot
reverted, they should not be
able to withdraw. So let's go
ahead, we can even just copy
this whole thing if we want to
hit up, we'll delete this
section here. We'll paste that
in. And boom. This means that
when some other account tries to
call withdraw, automatically
gets reverted, which is what we
want. Now we can be more
explicit to make sure that the
correct error code is being
thrown, not just that it's
reverted. Right, it can be very
reverted because they sent ether
did it they did something weird,
we want to make sure it's
reverted with our specific error
code. So right now we have this
not owner error code. But it's
actually a best practice to put
the contract name to underscores
and then your custom error. This
makes it a lot easier in the
future when you have a ton of
different contracts, and you're
not sure where an error is
coming from. So we're going to
just update this really quickly
to be fund me underscore
underscore, not owner, now we
can do is now that we have this
custom error, we can say
withdraw that to be reverted
with, then we can add our custom
error in here. Now, if we rerun
our test, with only allows the
owner to withdraw, oops, we need
to do a wait here. My mistake,
wait a Thursday, get signers.
And now let's try this again.
And we are indeed passing
Perfect.
Okay, great. We have some basic
unit tests here. And we're going
to write some staging tests
pretty soon. But before we
actually do that, let's go ahead
and add the gas estimator. And
we'll see how much gas these
contracts in these functions are
taking. It looks like the
Hardhead gas reporter is already
here. So let's scroll down.
We'll do gas reporter true. And
we won't do coin market cap
here. And we'll just look purely
at the GUI. So you can just
comment it out like that. Now
rerun all of our tests. So we'll
say yarn, our test. And in doing
so we're gonna get that that gas
output in that gas report dash
text here. So looks like all of
our tests are passing, which is
perfect. Now we can look into
our gas report and see what's
going on here. i Well, it looks
like the fundraising function is
taking a decent chunk of gas,
the withdrawal function, take it
some guests to we'd see the min,
the max and the average. Of
course, we can see how much each
one of these contracts cost to
actually output. We don't really
care about the MOQ aggregator of
course, because we're never
actually going to use that.
Let's say we look at the average
gas for these and we go hmm,
this looks like it's actually a
lot more than what we originally
expected. Is there a way for us
to make this a little bit cheap.
If we go back to our funding
contract, we look at our
withdrawal function. And we
noticed something, oh, there is
actually a way to make this a
lot cheaper. And it has to do
with something called storage
variables, or these global
variables that we've been
working with this whole time.
Let me let me paint you a little
picture here, we're gonna look
at one of the first gas
optimization techniques you can
take to drop these down. And it
has to do with an R Funmi.
Contract these state variables
and how they're actually stored
and how this contract actually
keeps track of all this stuff,
this section is going to be a
little bit more advanced. So
we'll have a note here saying
that this is an advanced
section, if you want to skip
over it, you can, because now
we're getting into gas
optimizations here, this
information still is really good
to know. So if you want to skip
it for now, and then come back
later, you absolutely can. But
let's talk about what happens
when we actually save or store
these global variables. Okay,
these storage variables. Now,
everything I'm about to go
through is in the documentation.
And there is a link to this, of
course, in the GitHub repo
associated with this course,
whenever we have one of these
global variables, or these
variables that stay permanently,
they're stuck in something
called storage, you can think of
storage as a big giant array, or
a giant list of all the
variables that we actually
create. So when we say we have
some contract called Son of
storage, and we have a variable
called favorite number, we're
basically saying we want this
favorite number variable to
persist, right, we saw in a lot
of our examples, we had a
favorite number variable that we
can always call to see what this
contracts favorite number was,
well, the way it persists, is it
gets stored in this place called
storage. A storage box is this
giant list associated with this
contract where every single
variable and every single value
in the storage section is
slotted into a 32 byte long slot
in this storage array. So for
example, the number 25 in its
bytes implementation is 000 with
a ton of zeros 19. This is the
hex version of the yuan 256.
This is why we do so much hex
translation, the bytes
implementation of a yuan 256.
And each store saw increments
just like an array starting from
zero. So for example, our next
global variable or next storage
variable just gets slotted at
the next slot that's available.
So bullions, for example, get
transformed from their bull
version two, their hex and we
modified our some bool variable
to be true and X edition of the
true Boolean 0x 001. Every time
you save an additional global
variable, or more correctly, one
of these storage variables, it
takes up an additional storage
slot. And what about variables
that are dynamic in length, or
that can change length? What
about something that's dynamic?
Well, for dynamic values, like a
dynamic array, or a mapping
elements inside the array or
inside the mapping are actually
stored using some type of
hashing function. And you can
see those specific functions in
the documentation, the object
itself does take up a storage
slot, but it's not going to be
the entire array. For example,
my array variable here at
storage, slot two doesn't have
the entire array in storage slot
two, what has actually is just
the array length, the length of
the array is stored at storage
slot two. But for example, if we
do my array dot push 222, we do
some hashing function, which
again, you can see in the
documentation what that is, and
we'll store the number 222. At
that location in storage, the
hex of 222 is 0x 0000 D, so it
gets stored in this crazy spot.
And this is good, this is
intentional, because 32 Bytes
may not be nearly big enough to
store my array if our array gets
massive. And it wouldn't make
sense for to put the elements
inside the array at subsequent
numbers because again, the size
of the array can change and
you're never going to be sure
how many subsequence that you
need. So for my array, it does
have a storage slot for the
length for mappings. It does
have a storage spot as well
similar to array, but it's just
blank. But it's blank
intentionally so that solidity
knows, okay, there is a mapping
here, and it needs a storage
slot for attaching functional
work correctly. Now
interestingly, constant
variables and immutable
variables do not take up spots
in storage. The reason for this
is because constant variables
are actually part of the
contracts byte code itself,
which sounds a little bit weird.
But you can imagine what
solidity does is anytime it sees
constant variables name is it
just automatically swaps it out
with whatever number it actually
is. So you can kind of think of
not in storage is just a pointer
to 123 and it doesn't take up a
storage slot. Well when we have
variables inside of a function,
those variables only exist for
the duration of the function.
They don't stay inside the
contract. They don't persist
they're not permanent. So
variables inside these functions
like new var and other var do
not get added to storage. They
get added in their own memory
data structure. Which gets
deleted after the function has
finished running. Now you might
be asking, Okay, well, why do we
need this memory keyword,
especially when it comes to
strings, we saw before that we
had to say String memory. The
reason we need it for strings is
because strings are technically
this dynamically sized array.
And we need to tell solidity,
hey, we're going to do this on
the storage location, or we're
going to do it into the memory
location where we can just wipe
it. arrays and mappings can take
up a lot more space. So slowly,
just wants to make sure Okay,
where are we working with this
is it storage is a memory, you
have to tell me, I need to know
if I need to allocate space for
it in our storage data
structure. And again, everything
here you can read in the
solidity documentation. Now, in
the GitHub repo associated with
this course, if you go to
contracts, we've actually got an
example contract section called
Fun with storage, where you can
play with and look at a lot of
this stuff. And we even wrote a
little script called deploy
storage fun, where it'll print
out the storage location of some
of the different variables, feel
free to give it a run, if you
want to try a challenge anybody
to write some functions that
find the storage slots of the
elements of the arrays, and the
mappings, and then find the data
inside of those as well. We use
a function here called Get
storage app, which allows us to
get the storage at any one of
these slots. And this is to
reinforce that even if you have
a function as private or
internal. Anybody can still read
it. Anybody can read anything
off the blockchain. And you can
test it exactly what this if you
go ahead and get clone that or
copy paste the code yourself.
You can then run yarn part at
deploy dash test tags, storage.
And you'll run the deploy script
for that storage.
And you'll see printing out the
location of storage in each
storage slot with a fun contract
that we made as an example. And
you might of course be asking,
Okay, Patrick, why are you
telling me all this? We're just
trying to get this gas price
down? Why are you telling me all
about this storage thing? Well,
the reason I'm telling you all
about the storage thing. Anytime
you read or you write to and
from storage, you spend a ton of
gas. Remember I said when we
compile our code, we compile it
down to some crazy weird
bytecode. Well, let me show you
on remix what this looks like.
We go to compliation details, we
can go to bytecode. And we see
this weird hex object zero,
blah, blah, blah. But we also
see these things called op
codes. Now, this bytecode here
represents these op codes. Each
one of these op codes represents
a small piece of everything in
this bytecode. And in fact, in
our heart hat, we can go to
artifacts, build info, and we
can see, we can see these op
codes in the build info, we can
do a command F or Control F for
opcodes. We can see op codes for
different contracts. These op
codes represent what the machine
code is doing. And they
represent how much computational
work it takes to actually run
our code and do stuff with our
code. The way that gas is
actually calculated is by these
opcodes. There are a couple of
lists here. But here's one that
I'm going to use this EVM
opcodes. And again, there's a
link to this in the GitHub repo
associated with this lesson.
Well, if we scroll down, we can
see exactly how much it costs
for each one of these op codes.
So for example, anytime we add,
it costs three gas, anytime we
multiply, that's five gas,
subtracting three gas, we have
all of these op codes that cost
different amounts of gas in in
our functions, here's kind of a
sample contract. If we're doing
adding, anytime we add it's
going to cost three gas. Anytime
we save to memory, it's going to
cost gas from some other
opcodes. These op codes combined
show us how much gas we actually
use. Now, let's look at a lot of
these op codes and how much they
cost three 510, three, three,
balance is 700. So getting the
balance is is a ton of gas.
Let's keep going. Getting the
sides of an Accounts code is a
lot of gas copying and accounts
code into memory. But oh my
goodness, what is this save word
to storage costs a ton of gas
that is 20,000 gas and s load
load word from storage cost 800
gas. These are two of the most
important opcodes s load and s
store which stands for storage
load and storage store. Anytime
one of these op codes fires,
we're spending 800 or 20,000.
You know, there's a big asterisk
there because that can change a
lot. But we're spending a ton of
gas anytime we work with storage
as developers. Anytime we work
with some stuff in storage, we
want to go boy, this is about to
cost me a lot of gas and the
best convention or making sure
we know that we're working with
a stored variable and we're
about to spend a lot of gas is
to append an S underscore right
before them which stands for
storage right So we're saying
address to amount funded is
going to be a storage variable
wonders is going to be a storage
variable. Owner is not going to
be a storage variable. It's
immutable. The best practice for
immutable variables is
prefixing. It with an I
underscore constant values are
also not in storage. So for
constant values, we want to keep
them capslock, like that
aggregator v3 interface public
price feed. Yep, you know what
that is going to be a storage
variable. So we want to append
an S underscore with it. So
we're going to do a little bit
more refactor, we've appended
these appropriately to update
everything. So instead of owner,
it's going to be I underscore
owner, and as a developer will
read this, and we'll go ah, this
is going to be much cheaper than
a regular variable. Okay, that's
great. I'm going to work with
this. This I underscore owner
for my modifier. Awesome. Is
owner anywhere else in here?
Okay, right in the constructor.
I own underscore owner is
message dot sender. Price feed
is a storage variable. We should
as developers, we should see the
s underscore when reading this
and go, Okay, we're spending a
lot of gas to store this.
Perfect. Okay, great. Let's keep
going. Great. We've updated all
the owners. Okay, well, what
about address to amount funded?
In VS code? If you do Command F,
or Ctrl, F, and you hit this
little down arrow, you can
actually find and replace all of
these address to amount funded
with s underscore address to Mt
funded. Hit it like that. And
since I updated one, I got a
backspace that one no. So now
these are all updated. Let's do
the same thing with s funders.
Let's update everywhere. It has
funders just to be s funders.
And we probably doubled up here.
Yep.
Let's undo that. We already
updated all the AI owners. So
now it's updated all the price
feeds. So let's look for price
feed, we'll update it with ES
price feed. And then we probably
doubled up right here. So we'll
undo that. Okay, great. Now that
we've updated everything in
here, we can scroll down and we
can oops, sorry, doubled up
there too. Sorry. We can we can
green through our code and go
okay, where are we reading and
writing to storage way more
often than we probably need to.
And that's when we get to this
withdrawal function, which seems
rather suspect to reading and
writing to storage a lot. So
let's take a look at what we're
doing here. Okay, so first of
all, I can see that we're doing
a for loop here. And every time
we do a for loop, we're just
constantly looping through all
of this code. Every single time
we're doing a little compare
option here we're saying, okay,
is our funder index less than s
funders dot length? S funders
dot length, this means the
longer our funders array is, the
more times we're going to be
reading from storage, that's
incredibly expensive. We're also
recalling this, oh my goodness,
we're reading from storage a lot
and saving it to this memory
variable, and then updating our
storage variable with it. Wow.
So we're reading from storage a
ton here, and we're reading from
storage a ton here, okay, then
we have to reset our funders
array, there's really no way
around it. And that's pretty
much it for our reading and
writing to storage, we could
probably create a withdrawal
function, that's a lot cheaper.
So let's go ahead and create a
function called cheaper
withdraw, function, cheaper
withdraw. That's going to take
what we've just learned and make
a cheaper withdraw, that's much
more gas efficient. So we'll
keep this public payable. and
have it be only owner, we're not
going to change anything there.
But what can we do for at least
this part here, we don't want to
keep reading from storage here.
And we don't want to always have
to keep reading from storage
here. We're like doubling up the
amount of storage we're reading
from. So instead, what we can
do, we can read this entire
array into memory one time, and
then read from memory instead of
constantly reading from storage.
And that's going to make our
lives a lot cheaper. So we can
create an address array. Memory
funders equals s underscore,
funders. And now it's going to
start making sense why for
arrays and strings in our
functions, it makes us say, hey,
is this memory is a storage?
What is this? And we're telling
it, we want it to be memory
because memory is going to be a
lot cheaper. So now that we're
saving it into our funders, oh,
and a quick note mappings can't
be in memory. Sorry. They're
just too weird and too wacky. So
flooding just doesn't let you do
that right now. But now that
we've saved our storage variable
into a memory variable, we can
read and write from this memory
variable, much, much cheaper,
and then update storage when
we're all done. So what we're
going to do now is we're gonna
say for you into V six, fund or
index equals zero, and we're
going to basically rewrite
everything but just using this
memory array. instead. We're
gonna say funder index is less
than funders dot length and
instead of s funders dot length,
and then we're gonna say funder
index plus plus. And then in
here we're gonna do nearly
exactly the same thing, except
we're gonna say address funder
equals funders, using our memory
array and not s funders have
funder index. And then we're
gonna say s address to amount
funded. funder equals zero. So
we're resetting our funders
mapping here, we're using our
memory variables instead, then
we're going to do the same thing
s underscore funders equals new
address array of zero. And then
we're gonna do the same thing
bool success, comma equals S
owner, dot call value,
address this balance, and we're
going to send it nothing and
then require success. Like that
actually, sorry, Iona on a sonar
now that we have this function
that we think is cheaper, let's
go back to our test. And let's
run this same multi test here,
but with our cheaper function.
So I know this can be a little
bit tricky to copy, paste, but
let's copy this entire massive
test. Let's come down here,
paste it, and we'll change the
name saying cheaper withdraw,
testing dot that done. And in
here in in this giant it here,
all we're going to change is
we're going to change withdraw
to cheaper withdraw, and the
rest of the test is going to be
exactly the same. So with that,
let's see if if we were
successful in making our
withdraw function cheaper with
cheaper withdraw, we're gonna
pull apart our terminal now. And
we do yarn, art hat test, which
is going to run our gas
estimator because it's enabled
right now. And of course, all of
our functions have been broken
because we renamed everything.
So we'll do a quick final
replace of funders, to change
funders to ask funders. And then
we're gonna change price feed to
ask price feed. And then do we
have owner anywhere? We don't
have owner or anywhere. We need
to change this one. Address to
amount funded. Let's come in
here. Address to amount funded.
S adderstone. well funded. What
else do we need to change price?
We price feed funders. Okay, I
think we changed everything.
Alright, so let's try our test
now. Yarn Hardhead test. All
right, great. Everything's
passing. And we ran our cheaper
withdraw testing. So now, if we
go to our gas output here, our
gas report, zoom out just a
hair, we can see the difference
between cheaper withdraw and
withdraw, we see something
really interesting. Here we see
our cheaper withdraw on average
was actually more expensive than
our regular withdraw. And the
reason for this is because
actually, if we go to our tests
are cheaper withdrawal, we only
tested on the multi withdraw. So
we had to reset many, many more
accounts. But this was also
technically its maximum as well.
And if we compare the maximum of
the cheaper withdrawal, the
maximum of the withdraw, it
looks like the cheaper
withdrawal was indeed cheaper.
And if we go to our hard hat dot
config, and we add our API key
back in, what we could even do
is in our test, we could copy
withdraw eath from a single
funder, copy that, paste it in
and just change withdraw to
cheaper withdrawal, rerun it
with the key and now do yarn
Hardhead test, we can see
exactly how many dollars we
would save if we ran this on the
Matic blockchain. Now let's go
back, we'll reopen up our gas
report. And we can see, in the
minimum cheaper withdrawal was
actually a little bit more
expensive. This actually does
make sense because if we look at
funding, if we only have to
withdraw when there was one
funder, well this loop only runs
one time. And our cheaper
withdraw will do the exact same
but it will have this this extra
thing here of loading them all
in, we see that the savings The
more people our funders in our
contracts. So automatic, we can
see we pretty much didn't save
anything. But if I change this
one more time to eath run the
test again. Now we can see
people withdraw saved a few
cents. This is how we can start
optimizing our contracts will be
cheaper and cheaper. And this
two cents was just in the
average. It's not even comparing
the max to the max, which was a
lot more gas than their
averages. We have just learned
an absolute ton here. Now, this
next part is going to make some
of you mad because we're going
to refactor our code one more
time if you don't want to
refactor it and you want to
leave all your tests as s
underscores you absolutely can
but to other users using our
application. Dealing with this s
underscore is a little Little
bit gross and actually can make
our code a little bit more
confusing for those who use it.
And additionally, right now all
of our state variables are
public. And actually internal
variables and private variables
are also cheaper gas wise. And
we don't need to make every
single one of our variables
public, because anybody can read
them off the chain anyways. So
one more refactoring that we're
going to do is we're actually
going to set the visibility of
these to private or internal,
based off of whether or not they
need to be private or internal,
and then we'll create getters at
the bottom of our function here.
So minimum USD, we can keep this
public because we want other
people to know what the minimum
USD of our contract is, without
having to go right through
storage, the owner of our
contract isn't important for
others to know or other
contracts to know. So we can go
ahead and make this private, and
then at the bottom at a function
get owner. That's a public view
that returns I owner, turns
address as funders, as funders
can be private as well. So at
the bottom, we're gonna say
function, get funder, and we're
going to pass a un 236 index,
public U, turns, address, return
as funders of index, the address
to Mt funded can also be
private. So the bottom, we're
going to create function, get
address to amount funded. And
this is going to take an address
under the public view returns,
you went to 56. And we're going
to return amount funded of the
funder did this one we did this
one, we did this one. And then
price feed, function get price
feed. This is going to be public
view as well, that returns
aggregate tour of the three
interface that's going to return
so I'm just gonna price feed.
Oh, okay. The reason why we did
that is because we want to have
this s underscore so that we as
developers can know, okay, this
is a storage variable, I want to
be very careful about how I
interact with this. But we don't
want people who interact with
our code to have to deal with
this s stuff. And we want to
give them an API that makes
sense, and that it's easy and
readable. So we add these getter
functions at the bottom to do
that. And also changing the
visibility can save us some gas
in the long run as well, because