we're gonna be calling from
private variables or internal
variables, which are cheaper gas
wise, of course, we do need to
upgrade our test one more time.
And like I said, if you want to
just leave them with the S
underscores, that's absolutely
fine. So s underscore price feed
is now going to be replaced with
get price feed, s underscore
amount to fund it is going to be
now replaced with get address to
amount funded. For now going to
change SW, underscore funders,
to get funder. We're going to
change Iona, there's nowhere
else in their mind, we don't
need to change them. And I think
that was everything. Let's just
look for s underscore, we don't
see it, I underscore, we don't
see that either. Let's just run
our tests one more time to make
sure we refactor that correctly.
And it looks like we did
awesome. Okay, we have just
learned a ton. we've refactored
our code a ton. And everything
is starting to look really,
really good here. One more gas
optimization we could make. And
an optimization for errors as
well is we could update all of
our requires to instead be to
instead be reverts. Because
without requires, we're actually
storing this massive string,
this massive array of text on
chain, these error codes are
much cheaper. But that's
optional. If you want to do
that. The whole reason we were
doing this is we were going
through the style guide in
updating things here. So we have
public internal private, and the
bottom is going to be our view
slash pure functions, which they
are they're just all these
getters that we just added.
So now our style in here looks
good. We've learned a lot about
gas, we've learned a lot about
storage. This is fantastic.
Let's do a quick refresher on
everything we just learned
because we went through a lot
right there. And like I said,
this is one of the harder parts
of this course. Any variable
that is changeable that we want
to persist across contract
executions and transactions. We
save to a giant array called
storage this array is
sequentially indexed starting at
zero. So the first variable the
first value that we have in our
contract gets stored to the zero
with index. The next one gets
stored to one and so on and so
forth. Dynamic arrays and
mappings and other dynamically
sized objects use specific
hashing function that you can
find in the documentation to
determine where the elements of
those dynamic Data Structures go
memory variables, constant
variables and immutable
variables don't go in storage.
And one of the main reasons
talking about storage is so
important is because the op
codes for loading from storage
and for reading from storage and
writing to storage are
incredibly gas expensive. So in
everywhere we can we want to
reduce the amount that we read
and load from storage. And it's
one of the easiest ways to save
gas and try to optimize our code
to be gas efficient. Like I
said, some of this gas stuff can
be a little tricky and a little
bit confusing. So if you don't
get this right away, it's okay.
It is totally fine. If you're a
little bit confused, and you're
like, What is he talking about?
Like I said, this is some of the
more advanced stuff it'll come,
the more you work with solidity,
and the more you work with
everything here. So don't let it
stress you out. Don't let it
stop you from continuing. You're
doing fantastic being here. So
far. We've written some really
good unit tests. Let's now write
some staging tests. And these
are the tests that we can use on
an actual test net. This is a
test that we're basically going
to run after we've deployed some
code just to see if everything
is working approximately the way
we want it to. So let's go ahead
and we'll create a new file
here. We'll call it fund me. Dot
staging dot test, dot j s. And
it's going to look really
similar to what we were just
doing with our unit tests. And
we're going to assume this is on
a test net. So these are tests
that we're going to run, right
before we deploy this to a main
net, this is the last step in
your development journey, we
want to just make sure that
everything is working
approximately correctly on an
actual test net. So what we're
gonna do is we're gonna do the
same thing describe, fund me,
and I'm gonna go a little quick
through these tests here,
because we've basically written
this type of test before, so
we're gonna say before each,
it's gonna be an async.
function. We're gonna do the
same thing as our unit tests. So
we're gonna have a Funmi
variable, we're gonna have our
let Deployer, we're gonna have
our constant send value equals
ethers.utils.rs ether of one,
and in here, we're going to do
const. Get named accounts.
Equals require hardhats, we're
going to say deployer equals
weight, get named accounts,
we're going to wrap this up, dot
Deployer. We're gonna say fun me
equals await ethers dot get
contract.
And me, comma, we're going to
connect it to our Deployer,
we're not going to deploy this,
we're not going to do any
fixtures like we did in our unit
tests, because in our staging
tests, we're assuming that it's
already deployed here. And we
also don't need a mock because
on a staging, we're assuming
that we're on a test net, now we
can actually wrap this whole
thing to make sure that we're on
a test net by using our helper
config. And looking for our
development chains, we can say
we only want to run our describe
bit if we're on a development
chain. So first, we'll say
const. Development chains equals
require, we'll pull that that
helper config in. And we'll say,
development chains dot includes
network dot name. And we'll
basically will say if developer
chains that includes network dot
name, we're going to skip and we
can actually skip using this,
we're going to use something
called a ternary operator is
basically like a one liner if
statement. And you can think of
this as a special type of F.
I've got a link to this and the
GitHub repo associated with this
course. And here's some
JavaScript documentation,
showing it in action. You say,
Okay, return is member. And if
it's true, have it be $2.
Otherwise have a B $10. And
that's pretty much it. So
another way of thinking about is
like, you say, let variable
equals true, then we could say,
let some var equals variable
question. Yes? Or no? Some var
will end up being Yes. Because
variable is true. If variable
was false than some var would be
no. So it's literally saying, If
variable, if variable, then some
var equals yes. Else. Some var
equals no, these lines are
literally the exact same thing.
This one is just a little bit
more succinct. That's really it.
So that's what this operator
does. We're gonna say
development chains that includes
network dot name. So if our
network is a development chain,
which we're going to import
network as well from hard hat
and ethers as well. Then we're
going to do describe that
skipped and this tells our test
to just skip this whole
describe, and then we're going
to put this little colon here
thing and save and boom. So now
we're only going to run this if
we're not On a development
chain, and we want to take this
exact same syntax, we'll go to
our unit testing here, and we'll
do the exact same thing, we'll
paste it will have this be the
opposite by putting a little
knot here, sticking that colon
in. So now, our unit tests only
run on development chains in our
staging tests, only run on test
nets. Perfect. That's what we
want, allows people to fund and
own and withdraw. And this will
be an async function, of course,
and we probably can make this
pretty robust, but we'll just
say await, fund me dot fund is
going to be send a value. And
then we'll say a weight on me
dot withdraw. CERT equals
require try. Now we'll do kind
of a lame final one, we'll say
const ending balance equals a
weight on me dot provider dot
get balance, fund me dot
address. And then we'll say
assert dot equals ending
balance.to string, comma zero as
a string, we're only going to
run this on a test net, I'm just
going to give you this one more
run to show you it in action.
Feel free to skip this part
again, because we are going to
be working with a test net, I'm
going to run yarn, hard hat
deploy dash test network
Rinkeby. And it's going to run
through our deploy. And after
it's all deployed, we're going
to run our staging tests to make
sure that everything works even
with a price feed on a real test
net, and I need to do const
development chains equals
require dot dot slash dot dot
slash helper heart config. Now
for run yarn, hard hat test,
we'll see just our unit tests
get run. But if we run yarn hard
to test dash dash network
Rinkeby, we're not going to run
nine tests, we're only going to
run our singular staging test.
And of course, this is going to
be a lot slower, because we're
on a
test net. Net will we write
written all these tests, we can
write a couple of scripts. And
then we're going to finish this
out by pushing this up to GitHub
making this our first smart
contract GitHub repository, when
it comes to the blockchain, when
it comes to smart contracts,
interacting with community
interacting with open source
being a part of GitHub, or git
labs or whatever Git hosting
service you're using is
essential to being successful
here. So let's write our
scripts. And then we'll upload
this to GitHub to start building
our portfolio. So first, we're
going to create a script to
interact with our code called
fund dot j s. And this is going
to be really similar to our
tests. And this way, in the
future. If we want to just fund
one of our contracts very
quickly, we can just run this
and we can do it, we're gonna do
the same thing that we've been
doing, we're gonna do an async
function main. And down below,
I'm just going to copy paste
this because we're going to be
copy pasting in a lot. We're
going to paste this little
syntax here. So let's write a
script that allows us to fund
our contracts. So first, we're
going to need const get named
accounts just like in our tests,
equals require arhat we're gonna
say const Deployer. Equals await
yet named accounts, just like
that. And then we're gonna say
const fund me equals await
ethers dot get contract. From
funding comm a Deployer.
Literally, almost exactly the
same as our tests, then we'll do
a little console dot log funding
contract that that and we'll do
const transaction response
equals await funding dot fund.
And for the value, we'll do
something like ethers dot utils,
that parse ether of 0.1 or
something, whatever you want to
do here, we of course, need to
import ethers, which it looks
like we already have. We'll do
await transaction response dot
wait for one transaction. And
then we'll do console dot log
funded, we can run this little
script by running yarn, RT head
node will run a local node with
all of our contracts deployed.
We'll see if our script looks
okay by running yarn, hard hat
run scripts fund dot j s dash
dash network localhost. And it
looks like it's funding Great.
Let's now write a withdraw
script withdraw that J S. And we
can even leave our localhost
Node running because we're going
to withdraw the funds that we've
just funded it with. So we're
going to do the exact same setup
here. We can even copy this main
bit to our withdraw Ah, the top
will do async function main will
say const deployer equals await,
get named accounts, which wow, I
hit enter and my VS code auto
imported it, that's pretty nice.
Maybe yours will too, maybe
won't if it won't, you just
gotta write it out or copy paste
from the other one. And then
we'll do cars Funmi equals await
ethers dot get contract on me,
course. And this is going to be
the exact same. Now we're going
to do console dot log funding
data dot, we'll say const
transaction response equals
await on v dot withdraw, await
transaction response dot wait
one, then console dot log. Got
it? Back. And we can test this
out by running yarn, hard hit
run scripts, withdraw dash dash
network localhost, we'll see if
this works. And cool and our
script is working. Fantastic
crushed out two scripts
incredibly quickly. And now we
have a way to easily interact
with our code with our contracts
if we want to via a script.
There's actually one more thing
I want to show you before we
actually work and we push all
this wonderful code up to GitHub
in our package dot JSON. I've
shown you a little bit of this
before, but we can add this
scripts section to make our
lives a lot easier and condense
all these long tests into a yarn
script for us. So usually, what
you'll see in common package dot
JSON is you'll see a list of
these in here for people to look
and just automatically run, one
of the most common ones is going
to be test. And to run test,
we're going to do yarn, hard hat
test. So now instead of running
yarn, Hardhead test, someone can
just come to your package once
this is saved and just run yarn
test. And this will grab this
test from your script section
and it will run yarn heart at
test and Bada bing, bada boom,
okay, cool. What else do we
probably probably want to do in
here? Well, we probably want to
have a test staging section
that'll run yarn Hardhead test
dash dash, network Rinkeby. I'm
not going to run that. But
that's probably something we
want to have in here, we're
probably going to want some
linting. So we showed you
briefly that linting thing. So
we'll have a yarn lint, which
will just run yarn, sole hint.
And then we'll just have it so
hence the contracts folder. And
anything that starts out soul.
So now if I run yarn, lint,
it'll run soul hint, and all of
our code here and it'll give us
some warnings here, which we can
pretty much all ignore. And
Solon actually has an auto fix
and auto fix that we can add, by
doing yarn lint fix, we'll say
yarn. So hint, contracts slash
start out. So we'll do dash dash
fix. So now we run yarn, lint
fix, it'll auto fix, which
there's nothing to auto fix. So
nothing happens. But it's good
to have anyways. And then we can
do our formatter, we're just
going to format our code format,
that which will do yarn,
prettier, dash dash write to,
and we'll just do a period to do
everything. And then we can just
do yarn format. And it's gonna
fix all of our, it's going to
fix everything for us, which is
great. And then we finally can
have coverage. By running yarn
hardhat coverage, now we can
just run yarn coverage, will
give us this wonderful little
coverage report. Awesome. So our
packages looking fantastic.
Maybe we'll even come into
package json. We'll give this a
name. We'll call this hard hat.
And me give it an author, which
is going to be your name. So I'm
just gonna say Patrick Collins,
and we'll give it a version in
here. of 1.0 Point Oh, oops. And
let's do icons instead of
spaces. Oh, and one more thing.
We're not using ES lint. So all
this es lint stuff, we can dump
and we could delete the yarn dot
lock and reinstall. But yeah,
whatever. We don't have a
readme, but that's okay. If you
want to go back, like I said, go
check out that best readme
template and go update your
READMEs to make them look as
awesome as this, you can do that
as well. But other than that,
we've got an awesome code repo
here. What do we want to do with
it? Well, we've been playing
around with GitHub so much,
we've been looking at all these
good hubs. It's time for us to
join GitHub with our own with
our first repository. Let's go
ahead and let's make this happen
in the lesson seven full
blockchain solidity course, yes,
there is a link to this GitHub
Quickstart that we're going to
follow to set up our first
repository. This is going to be
the moment where you are
starting to build your portfolio
building and GitHub is
borderline crucial for your
development journey. It's going
to be your portal folio, it's
going to be where you say, Hey,
look at all the cool products
that I'm engaging with, that I'm
working with, that I'm
participating in. If you've
already made GitHub before, I
highly recommend you still push
this up to GitHub as proof that
you've done it. And then you can
also tweet it at me saying, hey,
look how far I've gotten. Look
where I've done, look at how
fantastic I'm learning smart
contracts, and be incredibly
excited about now, this
quickstart will walk you through
creating a repository, creating
a branch and teaching all this
stuff, we're going to follow the
instructions from the GitHub
documentation about adding
locally hosted code to GitHub,
we already have a project, and
we're just pushing it up. Since
the Windows users are using WsL,
you can just follow the Mac or
Linux instructions here, the
first thing that we're going to
do is in your GitHub profile, or
your GitHub login, we're gonna
hit this little plus thing, and
hit new repository, you can call
this whatever you want, let's
call it hard hat, fund me b code
camp, you can put a description
if you want, learning from
recode camp, and Patrick, about
smart contracts.
We'll make it public because we
want other people to see you
being fantastic and learning
smart contracts. We'll leave
this blank, and we'll hit Create
repository. Now, this is our
public code repository. This is
our first one, if you've done
these already, this will be your
first smart contract one. It
even has some instructions in
here, too, that teaches us how
to create a new repository from
the command line, you can follow
this if you want, or you can
follow like so the first thing
we're going to do is we're going
to initialize a git branch. And
from way back when you should
already have Git installed.
Remember, you can check by
running git dash dash version
like this. Git is a little
different from GitHub, Git is
known as version control. And it
allows us to make changes to our
code, but keep a history of all
the code changes that we've
made. GitHub is a place where we
can push all of these changes
and keep track of all of our
code. So the first thing that
we're going to do is we're going
to create a new branch. And I'm
not going to explain Git and
working with Git too, too
deeply. But if you want to learn
about Git Free Code Camp, of
course, has a video on Git and
GitHub for beginners. So we're
going to create this new branch
with git init dash b main, now
your Visual Studio code might
automatically start formatting
some stuff. And if it does,
that's great. And if it doesn't,
don't worry about it. But what
you'll see here on the left is
you'll see some stuff is green,
and some stuff is gray, open
back up that dot Git ignore,
you'll see that all the gray
stuff is the stuff that we have
in this dot Git ignore this is
intentional, this is what we
want. This is just some some
highlighting saying, hey, this
green stuff is what you're
working with on GitHub. And this
gray stuff is what you're not
working with and GitHub. And
that's what we want. You don't
need to push artifacts, or cash
or coverage or node modules,
people can install and compile
on their own machines, we
definitely don't want to push up
our Dotty and V if we're using a
Dotty and V. And we don't really
need to push up coverage dot
JSON, either the rest of this we
do. So now what's next, after we
initialize our main branch, you
now should be able to run git
status in your terminal and see
this huge red output of all
these things that are untracked,
and we don't have any commits
for, what we can do now is we
can stage all of our code with
git add period, and then commit
it with Git commit, we're going
to run these one at a time
instead of together. Before I
run git add, I'm going to add
deployments to this list too,
because GitHub doesn't really
need to know about all the
different deployments I make,
especially when I make a ton of
deployments to my local hosts,
they don't need to know. So
we're going to add that to, then
we're going to run git add dot.
And if we do a git status, now,
we can see all of our code has
been staged for being committed
for being a part of this history
of our code. And then take a
quick look at all these files
and make sure your dot E and V
file is not and never in here.
So now we're going to run git
commit dash m and then this
message for our commit, okay, so
we'll run git commit dash m, we
can say, initial commit, or
whatever you want in this
message here, first commit,
initial commit, who cares, and
it's gonna say, create mode,
blah, blah, blah, for all of
these files. And if we do git
status, now, it's blank on
branch main, nothing to commit.
And then you might get something
like this. If you've never
worked with Git before your name
and email were added
automatically. We're a little
bit confused here. We'll talk
about this in just a second. So
next, what we can do is we're
actually going to copy the URL
of our GitHub repo. So you can
grab that just by copying here
or right at the top, that URL
right there. And what we're
going to do is we're going to
add this as a remote repo. To do
that. We'll do git remote add,
and we'll give this remote repo
a name. For us. We'll say origin
and then we'll paste that URL
there. We're now saying the the
origin remote repo is good.
Gonna be at this URL, we run git
remote dash v, we can see that
the origin repo for fetching is
at this branch. And the origin
repo for pushing is also at this
branch. So when we want to get
new code, a fetch code will
fetch it from here. And if we
want to push code up, we want to
give code to the GitHub. We'll
also get it from here. So now
we've set the new remote with
that remote URL. Now we're going
to actually push the changes to
github.com. And the way we do
that is with Git push, and we
pick which remote we want to
push to, and we're going to push
the origin. And then which
branch we want to push to which
we're going to push to Maine,
it'll probably prompt you for
your username and your password,
and maybe your email and
everything. Now, if
authentication doesn't work for
you, for some reason, you can
come over to Settings. Or if you
scroll down to developer
settings, Personal Access Tokens
and create generate new token,
some token,
give yourself repo access, write
access, and hit Generate token.
And try to use this token as
your password. Instead, be sure
to use the GitHub documentation
and the GitHub discussion
associated with this course, if
you get lost or if something
doesn't work, as shown here. But
once it's done, once you add all
that information in correctly,
you come back to your get up and
you will have your first GitHub
repo with all the code and
everything in it like this. And
once you complete this step,
once you do this, you should
absolutely celebrate. If you
like, you can shoot a tweet web
three community in the
blockchain community is
absolutely this collaborative
space. So Twitter crypto is
where a lot of these people
congregate to share ideas. So
definitely be sure to celebrate
and share this and be really,
really excited. And shoot a
tweet out like this. Give your
friends a high five, share it on
Twitter, share it on Discord
shared on Reddit, be excited for
how far you've gotten, we've got
a lot more to go. But by
completing this part, you have
done fantastically, and I'm so
excited for you to start the
next section. Now, we're not
going to go over the TypeScript
addition to this because there's
nothing really new here.
However, again, if you want to
see TypeScript, feel free to
jump into the GitHub repository
associated with this course.
Alright, awesome. You've just
completed Lesson Seven, the
heart had fun me. And now it's
time to move on to lesson eight,
which is going to be our HTML
slash JavaScript to fund me, you
can find all the code for what
we're about to go through, of
course, on my GitHub repo. And
for this section, we're now
going to start to see some of
the differences between Node js
between that back end
JavaScript, and JavaScript in
the browser or front end
JavaScript. And if you come to
the GitHub repo associated with
this lesson, our main version
we'll be using what's considered
better front end JavaScript. But
we'll also have a no JS
addition, as well, if some of
the front end JavaScript is
really confusing, and you'll see
what I mean with some of those
differences very soon. Now,
people can programmatically
interact with our smart
contracts at any time. However,
most of our users are not
compete developers. So we need
to create a website, we need to
create a user interface for them
to interact with our smart
contracts and interact with our
protocols. And that's what this
section is going to teach us,
it's going to be an introduction
to building these fullstack.
building these front ends on top
of our smart contracts. Now, I
wanted to show you what this is
actually going to look like when
we finish it. Because here,
we're actually going to make our
first front end our first
website using the blockchain
using web three. And it's going
to be an incredibly minimalistic
website. As you can see right
here, we're not going to have
any styling, we're just going to
show you how to get the
functionality. And additionally,
we're going to do a couple of
things that aren't really
recommended and are definitely
not best practices. The reason
we're going to do it like this
is the same reason that in math
class, before you learn the
tricks for derivatives, you
learn what a derivative actually
is. We're teaching it like this
first, so that you can
understand what's going on on
the websites when you interact
with them. And when you work
with them. We saw already with
Foston, touching the link where
we can connect our wallets and
we can work with the faucets.
All decentralized applications
have this website and have this
setup where you connect your
wallet and then you interact by
clicking buttons, which make
these function calls to the
blockchain. And here's going to
be our minimalistic website that
does exactly that. So this
section is just going to teach
you what's going on under the
hood. So you can really
understand how to build these
applications at a professional
level. So for this section, if
you don't want to code along
with me, you definitely don't
have to however, coding along
with me will definitely ingrain
everything in your memory here.
So here's what an application is
going to look like. We have our
website here, which is connected
to our hard hat, our local
blockchain, but it's gonna run
exactly the same as if it was on
a real test net, the first thing
you'll notice is in our meta
mask, we are not connected. And
we'll go ahead and hit Connect,
and meta masks will pop up
asking us if we want to connect,
we'll go ahead and connect to
it. And now we'll be able to
interact with our heart at
Funmi. You'll notice two buttons
here are functions that we're
familiar with, we have our
withdrawal function, which is
going to be our withdrawal
function that we just created.
And then of course, we also have
our fund function here where we
push or we send Aetherium or
Matic or whatever, native
blockchain token to our smart
contract. So we can do it
through this user interface. So
once we're connected, if we want
to see the balance, we can
actually right click, hit
Inspect, come over to our
console. And we'll print out to
the JavaScript console, the
current balance of our smart
contract. So nobody has funded
this yet, we can come down, we
can choose an amount we want to
fund. So for example, maybe 0.1,
eath, we'll go ahead, we'll hit
fund, meta masks will pop up,
we'll get a little council
saying funding with 0.1. And
it'll give us all the
transaction details that we need
to send 0.1 eath, to our smart
contract, we can go ahead and
hit Confirm. And after it's been
confirmed after it's been mined
on our local blockchain, we had
get balance, we now see that
it's 0.1. We could call fund
again, we could have multiple
funders, we could switch between
different accounts and fund with
different amounts. And we can
see that funding amount
increase, then we can call the
withdrawal function. As long as
we're the owner, we can confirm
and we can pull out all the
money out of our funding
contract. And we'll get balance.
Now we'll see the balance is
reset to zero. So this is what
we're going to be building. Are
you ready? I sure am.
Let's get into it. This is the
introduction to building
websites with web three. All the
information here is available in
our GitHub repo, so feel free to
follow along there. Alright, so
if you're in your heart head
Funmi dash Free Code Camp repo,
we're still going to want to
have this open as well. But
we're also going to want to
create a new Visual Studio code
for working with our new repo.
So let's go ahead and CD down a
directory. We'll type MK dir,
we'll call this HTML, Fund Me
Free Code Camp. We'll cd into
that. And we'll open this up by
typing code period. You can also
do File Open Folder, but we just
want to open this up in a new
Visual Studio Code. New VS code
will pop up but before we flip
over to that, we do want to CD
down CD back into hard hat fun
we Free Code Camp because we are
still going to use everything in
here. We're still going to
deploy In a smart contract using
this folder and using this repo,
when you're building daps, or
websites that are connected to
the blockchain, you'll usually
have two repositories or repos.
One is going to be for the smart
contracts, like what we see
here. This is our repo that has
all the code for our smart
contracts. And then you'll also
have one for the front end slash
website. And it's going to be
the combination of these two
repos, which makes up the full
stack. So when people are
talking about full stack,
they're talking about the smart
contracts, which is going to be
our back end, plus, plus our
HTML slash JavaScript slash
website stuff, which is going to
be our front end. So smart
contracts are the back end, HTML
slash JavaScript slash website
stuff is going to be our front
end. So we have our back end
already. And now we're going to
build our front end, we want to
keep this up because we're going
to need it to test and interact
with our front end. Awesome. So
we have this new folder now,
HTML Funmi, Free Code Camp. Now
this course is not a how to
learn front end course, we are
going to teach you a number of
front end concepts. But if you
want to learn a full traditional
front end course, once again,
you can check out Free Code
Camp, they've got a ton of
fantastic tutorials, I'm
teaching you front end, if you
go ahead and follow along with
me, though, you'll definitely
get a basic understanding of
front end as well as front ends
and how it relates to our smart
contracts. Additionally, you
don't have to do the front end
parts or the full stack parts.
If you only want to take this
course, to learn back end and to
learn JavaScript, and to learn
solidity and learn how to do
these smart contracts
programmatically, then you can
absolutely skip these front end
parts. However, if you want to
learn to build exciting
websites, and you want to have
other people other than
developers interact with your
protocols, you definitely want
to watch this part. Now before
we actually jump in here and
start writing our code. We need
to understand what exactly is
going on when work with one of
these websites that use the
blockchain. So I actually made a
video about this recently. So
let's watch a segment from that
really quick, just so that we
can get up to speed with with
exactly what's going on behind
the scenes of these websites
that interact with the
blockchain. All right. So here
we are, with a website or a
front end on top of some smart
contracts that we've deployed,
doesn't really matter what it is
right now. This is typically the
interface that you'll see boiled
down to a really, really
minimalistic level. Typically,
you'll see something like
connect function, right, and
Metamask, or some other wallet
connector thing will pop up,
we'll hit Next we'll connect
here might even say something
like connected. And we can also
execute functions, we can
interact with our smart
contracts, we can confirm, etc.
Right? This is something you
might see something like Avi
right, I'll hit Connect on the
application, it'll say, hey, how
would you like to connect? I'll
choose Metamask. I'm going to
change my Metamask to main net,
but you get the picture, right?
This is a simple example of what
that would look like. So what is
actually going on in the browser
when we connect what is actually
going on? And what do we
actually need to do, we're going
to right click, hit Inspect. And
on the right side, we're gonna
see our debugger here. Now if we
go over to sources, on the top
of our browser, you'll see a few
things. If you look down over
here, right, we'll see this URL,
right, which right now is going
to be my localhost. And we'll
also see meta mask and Phantom
and a whole bunch of other
stuff. These other things that
we see here are going to be
what's injected from our browser
extensions. The reason we see
this meta mask thing here is
because I've meta mask
installed, right? The reason I
see Phantom here is because I
have the Phantom app installed.
Meta masks, of course, being an
EVM, wallet and Phantom being a
Solana based wallet. Now what
happens when we have these
extensions installed is they
automatically get injected into
a window object in JavaScript,
and in fact, we scroll down
to here in the console, again,
you can find console, you can
click here and click anything up
there. And we type in window.
We'll see we have this big
window object with all this
stuff, right? This window object
represents this our window
basically right? Now if we
scroll all the way to the bottom
and we do window dot Aetherium.
We also see an object here. Now
this window dot Aetherium object
only exists if you have a meta
mask or meta mask like browser
or if you want to look at some
other web three wallet you do
window dot Solana. So Alana
right and we see this window dot
Solana. Now let's look at a
browser that doesn't have
Metamask or phantom installed.
What do you think is going to
happen in the window now let's
go ahead and right click hit
Inspect. We'll go to the
console. Now let's see what's
going on in here. If we go to
sources, we first off we don't
see that Metamask or that Solana
source here. And if we go to
console, we still see window if
I let me zoom in a little bit.
We still see window here. But if
I do window dot Aetherium If we
get nothing, or if I do window
dot Solana, we also get nothing.
So in order for our browsers to
know that there's a Metamask, or
that there's a phantom, those
extensions automatically add
these to our window objects, and
that's something that we can
check for in our JavaScript. The
reason these wallets are so
important is built into them
underneath the hood, they have a
blockchain node connected to
them. And in order to interact
with the blockchain, we always
need a note. And you might have
seen URLs from alchemy, or in
FIRA because you need them to
interact with the blockchain,
Alchemy, and infura are examples
of third party blockchains that
you can interact with and
basically rent, right. But you
need them to create a provider,
or a node to send your
transactions to. So you could do
it in JavaScript, like something
like this is the alchemy
documentation where you take
that alchemy URL, you stick it
into some object and use that to
send your transaction. This is a
way that you could do it in the
back end. But on the front end,
what you normally want to use is
you just want to use the user's
Metamask, or their Solana or
their wallet as the main wallet.
Now, there are a ton of other
different types of wallets to
connect, like ledger, mu,
Coinbase, wallet, connect, etc.
And there are different ways to
set those up. But they all do
the same thing where they expose
some URL, they expose some node
under the hood, they give us
that URL. They give us that
provider. The way metamath Does
it is with window dot Aetherium.
Boom, this is now our URL. This
is now our connection. In fact,
if you go up to your Metamask,
hit the little three dots,
expand view. hit Add Network,
and then just hit the X so we
can get to networks. You can see
all of these blockchains that I
have in here all have an RPC
URL, this the HTTP RPC URL
connection of the blockchain No,
that's running. I happen to have
one running locally right now.
All of these also have a node
RPC URL and you can actually see
them right in your meta mask
right. This is connected to in
Fira, these are all connected to
in Fira. It's all the exact same
thing. Meta mask just has a
really nice way of taking that
URL, sticking it in the browser
for us in this window dot
Aetherium or window dot Solana
you know or whatever. So this is
the main thing that we need to
know we need. We always need a
connection with the blockchain.
And these browser wallets are an
easy way to do that. Make sense?
Great. Let's take this knowledge
now. And let's
apply it. So in here, let's make
a quick readme.md. Just so we
can talk about what we're going
to be making here. So in this
section, we're gonna be using
raw HTML slash JavaScript in
conjunction with our smart
contracts to build this website.
Later on. We will use next Jas
slash react, which is a more
modern stack to build our
websites here. But learning
understanding how to do
everything with HTML and
JavaScript first, is going to
make our lives a lot easier come
later on down the road. But as
we know, all websites use HTML
as kind of their scaffolding for
what they look like. So let's go
ahead and create our HTML for
our website, we'll call it index
dot HTML. And this is going to
be the basic scaffolding or the
basic bones of what our website
is going to look like. Now, in
VS code, if you go ahead and
just type exclamation mark index
dot HTML, and you click the
first thing that pops up, it'll
automatically populate your code
your file here with some basic
HTML setup. If it doesn't do
this for you, feel free to copy
paste the basic setup from the
GitHub repository associated
with this course, we have our
doctype. HTML, we have some HTML
tags telling us that everything
in between here is going to be
an HTML, which is great.
However, for simplicity, we
don't need most of this. So
we're going to make this a
little bit easier. We're going
to delete this line, this line
and this line. And we're just
going to change the title to
fund me app. And then inside of
our body, we can do something
like or Hello. And now we have
the bare bones to create a
website just with this. Now to
show this on a website, we can
do one of two things. If you are
using Visual Studio code, I'm
going to recommend you install
the extension live server. And
it looks like this. And I'll
have the extension ID for this
extension in the GitHub
repository associated with this
course, this is going to allow
us to easily spin up an HTML
website. So we'll go ahead and
install this. And if you're not
using Visual Studio Code, I'll
show you a different way in just
a second. Once this is
installed, you should have this
little go live button at the
bottom. And if you don't, you
can always open up your command
palette, which again, you can
open up by hitting View command
palette, and you can type in
live server and just say open
with live server but we're going
to just click this go live
button. And it's going to say
starting and it's actually going
to open up your browser with our
index dot HTML. We can actually
see our website is being called
Save on 120 7.0 point 0.1. This
is known as the loopback, or
local host endpoint, we're on
port 5501. If you're not
familiar with the ports, don't
worry about that for now, we
have our index dot HTML here.
And if we change this to
something like what's good, we
hit save. If it doesn't
automatically refresh, we'd come
over here and refresh. And we'd
see that being reflected here.
If you've never created a
website before, you've
essentially just done it,
congratulations, you might get
this.vs code folder. a.vs code
folder allows you to make
settings specifically for the
repo that you're working with,
for your code editor for VS
code, but we're going to mostly
ignore it for now. Now, if
you're not using Visual Studio
Code, what you can do is you can
just run this in the browser. So
one thing you could do is you
could right click it, and I'm
using a Mac. So I'm going to hit
Reveal in Finder, aka reveal
where it's located. And you can
just double click it, and boom,
now it's running right in your
browser. Instead of pointing to
your localhost, it's going to be
pointing directly to your local
file path. Now one final version
that we could do that I'm going
to highly recommend you don't
do. But it's another option,
we're actually going to download
a package for you using no Jas,
which allows us to serve up
HTTP. And we're gonna install it
the exact same way we've
installed our other packages, we
can do yarn, add dash dash dev
HTTP hyphen server. And you may
still want to add it anyways.
But now, we'll get some node
modules for this HTTP server
package, we'll get a package
json, and of course, a yarn dot
lock as well. And what we can do
is we can stop this down here,
stop that live server. And if we
go back to our website, refresh,
it'll now be blank. And we can
run yarn HTTP server. And this
will do the exact same thing.
And we get, and if we come over,
and we refresh, we'll see what's
good. Now this one is a little
bit more finicky. And after you
make a change, like, Hey, what's
good, you might have to close
it, and then reopen it and then
refresh. So I do recommend that
if you're on Visual Studio code,
you definitely just use this
little go live button, because
it'll reflect your changes a lot
nicer.
So let's go ahead and hit the Go
Live button. Hey, what's good
pops up. Okay, cool. Our HTML is
working perfectly.
So the title, of course, is
going to be the Funmi app, which
we see up here in the title
section. So let's update this
HTML, so that it has those
buttons, and it can actually
connect and work with our
blockchain and work with any
blockchain. Something else that
you can do in HTML is you can
actually write JavaScript inside
your HTML. And the way we can do
that is by doing this script
tag, and then we'll do a closing
script tag. And anything inside
here inside of our script tags
is going to be JavaScript. So I
could do something like console
dot log, hi, with a bunch of
exclamation marks, I'm going to
save it. We'll go back to our
front end, we're going to right
click, we'll hit Inspect, we'll
go to the console. And we can
see that Hi prints it out, we
refresh, we can see the hi
consistently printed out hi from
script tag, we'll save it, we'll
move back, we see hi from script
tag printed out. I know it's a
little bit small. So let me zoom
in. Alright, great. So we can
type our JavaScript in here,
it's inside the script tag is
where we're going to write our
JavaScript to write the
functions that our front end is
going to interact with. Now, as
we saw before, in this little
console, we can check for window
dot Etherium, to see if Metamask
or is installed. And again, a
lot of what we're working with
is actually right in the
Metamask documentation. If you
go to their basic section, they
talk a little bit about the
provider, which is this window
dot Aetherium, you can read how
to actually interact directly
with meta mask in the meta mask
documentation as well. Now using
window dot Aetherium is just one
of the ways we're actually going
to connect to the blockchain,
there's actually multiple ways
because there's multiple
different kinds of wallets out
there. But for now, we're just
going to pretend that window dot
Aetherium and meta mask is the
only extension out there. So
what we want to do is we want to
check to see if this wind of
that Aetherium exists. This is
the first thing that we should
be doing. Because if this
doesn't exist, this means that
they can't connect to the
blockchain, one of the first
things that we're going to want
to do is we're going to want to
check to see if that exists. So
we can do something like if we
can say type of window that
Aetherium does not equal,
undefined. Then we'll do console
dot log, I see a meta mask. So
now if we save, we come back to
our front end, we do see I see a
Metamask. I've got a Google
Chrome up without Metamask that
if we look in the console, and
we hit refresh it the same URL
where our live server is
running. We don't see that I see
a meta mask because it doesn't
see a meta mask. We can do else.
console dot log, no Metamask
refresh, we still see ICD a meta
mask where we have a meta mask.
You don't have to open up a
browser without one but we see
no meta mask for Chrome because
it doesn't see a meta mask. Now
what we could do is We can
automatically try to connect to
meta mask if we see that there
is a meta mask, right? Remember
how before, when we hit that
connect button meta mask popped
up and said, Are you sure you
want to connect? So what we can
do is, and you can, again, you
can find this in the meta mask
docs, we can run this eath
request accounts method, which
is basically going to be how we
connect our Metamask. Now, this
is specified by a new EIP and an
older documentations. And in
older tutorials, you might see
Aetherium dot enable, which
essentially does the exact same
thing. So what we could do here
is we could say, a cerium, or
excuse me, window dot Aetherium
dot request. And we could put
method F request accounts. And
we'll save that. Now if we go
back to our browser, we'll
actually see, you'll actually
see Metamask, go ahead and pop
up and say, let's connect so we
can choose an account. And we'll
hit Connect, will automatically
connect our meta mask to our
website. And now if we look at
our meta mask, we can see this
little connected thing. It's
saying that our account one is
now connected to our website.
This means that the website can
now make API calls to our meta
mask, we still have to be the
ones to approve them. But it can
go ahead and connect and try to
run transactions, which is
awesome, which is what we want.
If you want to disconnect, we
can go ahead and click that
little button and hit disconnect
this account. Well that we have
our code currently is anytime we
hit refresh, this is going to
pop up which is going to be
really annoying. So what we're
going to do instead is we're
going to wrap this up into an
asynchronous function, the exact
same as we've been doing, we'll
do we'll create an async
function called Connect. And
we'll wrap it up these curly
braces here. And then we'll just
format this a little bit to make
it look nicer. And now if we
save, we go back to our website,
and we refresh. And we go ahead
and disconnect.
If we refresh Metamask won't
keep asking us Hey, do you want
to connect Hey, do you want to
connect here do you want to
connect, because we need to call
this connect function where we
can do that is we can add a
little button here. So right
underneath our script tag, we're
going to add a button tag. So
this is the opening button tag.
And then here's the closing
button tag. And inside the
opening button tag declaration,
we'll give it an ID, which will
be Connect button. And we'll say
on click equals the Connect
connects function. And we'll
call this button connect in
between these little button
tags, we'll call it connect will
say when we click it will call
the Connect function. So if we
save, and we go back to our
front end, we can now see we
have a little Connect button.
And now if we press Connect,
Metamask is going to pop up,
we'll hit next and connect like
that. And boom, now we are
connected. And we can even do a
little await here so that we
wait for this to finish before
moving on. And then after we
connect, we can say console dot
log connected. So let's actually
go ahead and test this out,
we'll go back to Metamask. we'll
disconnect here, try to never be
on Main net if we don't have to
be. And let's go ahead run
connect, we'll hit Next connect.
And now we see a little console
dot log come out saying
connected. Okay, great. We can
also update our website
accordingly. So that we can let
users know that we're connected.
So we can grab the connect
button element ID and say that
we're connected once we're
connected. So after we await to
be connected, we can go ahead
and do document dot get element
by ID Connect button. And then
we'll say dot inner HTML equals
connected like that. And then
instead of saying no minimize
down here, we'll do just the
opposite. So we'll copy this
line. And instead of connected,
we'll say please install meta
mask. And we'll save we'll go
back to our front end, we'll hit
connect. And now if we're
already connected, it'll just
automatically go to connected.
If we're not connected, it'll
pop up, we'll get connected. And
now we have this button that
says connected, which is great.
So now we already know that
we're connected. So we've
connected our Metamask to our
front end. Now we want to
actually go ahead and do some
functions here. And this is
where we want to create some
more functions and some more
buttons that are going to use
ethers that package that we
become so familiar with. Now, as
we code, our script section is
going to get bigger and bigger
and bigger. So oftentimes, we
actually want to put our code in
a JavaScript file itself. So
we're gonna go ahead, come over
here, we're going to create a
new file, and we'll call it
index dot j s. And instead of
putting our JavaScript in these
script tags, we're going to put
it in this index and then import
this index file into our HTML.
And the way that we're going to
do that is we're actually just
going to grab this function.
We're going to copy it, delete
everything for now. We're going
to paste it into our end ext dot
j s, and then in our index dot
HTML, we're just going to tell
our script tag to use index.js.
So we're just going to say the
source is going to be equal to
dot slash index dot j s. And
then we're going to say, the
type of this is going to be text
slash JavaScript. Now if we save
that, and we save our index dot
HTML, we come back to our front
end, we do a little refresh. And
we make sure that we go ahead
and disconnect. And we do
another refresh, we can see that
even with our index.js in a
different file, because we're
doing src equals index.js, and
we're importing it into our
HTML, when we hit Connect, it
still calls our Connect
function. That's how we can kind
of separate our JavaScript into
its own js file that we're a
little bit more familiar with.
Now, if you look in the GitHub
repo associated with this
course, and you look in the
index dot j s, you'll see our
Connect function, we've added
some quality of life stuff,
we've added some try catches
just to make handling errors a
little bit better, you can go
ahead and add those try catches
in yourself if you'd like. But
I'm not going to demo them in
this video
here. Now we want to create our
fun function. And then later on,
we're going to create our
withdrawal function. And this is
where front end JavaScript code.
And no Gs are a little bit
different. In no JS, we've been
using this require keyword to
import dependencies in front end
JavaScript, you can't use
require, and it won't exactly
work. Now later on, we're going
to use the Import keyword, which
is really the better way to do
this. And this is where our
first differences going to be
using the Import keyword for
front end is much better than
the require keyword, especially
since the require keyword
doesn't actually work. And for
those you who might struggle
with this disconnect in this
change. Once again, in the
GitHub repo associated with
this, we do have a Node js
edition of this, where you can
use the require keyword, you
just have to go through the
readme and download some
packages and run some scripts
that basically transform your
code that uses require into code
that works with imports. But
we're going to teach you the way
to work with your front end code
here using imports. Now you'll
see when we get to next Jas that
we will still download code from
node modules and using a yarn
lock and a package json etc. So
summary in future seconds, we
are still going to do yarn add.
But outside of a framework when
we're using this raw JavaScript,
this raw HTML setup, like what
we're working with here, we're
not going to be doing yarn, add
node modules will add node
modules for framework like next
react. But for raw JavaScript,
we'll be using a different
syntax, which I'll show you
soon. So let's go ahead and
start building our fund function
here. To make our fun functions,
what would we normally do? Well,
we'd create an async function
called fund. And in this
function, we probably would want
to take some ether mount as a
parameter, because we're going
to want to fund it with some
amount of Aetherium. When we
call this function, we might
want to run console dot log will
do a little string interpolation
here. Funding with eth amount,
dot dot dot, these semicolons
are going to drive me absolutely
insane. So I'm going to add a
our dot prettier dot our rc file
into this, and I'm going to go
ahead and add prettier in here.
Otherwise, I'm going to lose my
mind. So we're gonna do yarn add
dash dash Dev, prettier, just so
we can format our JavaScript
with prettier come back to
index.js. I'm gonna hit command
S, and it looks like it does
indeed, auto format with
prettier now yay, no matter
semicolons, we can call this fun
function the same way we call
connect. So in in our index dot
HTML, maybe we'll create a new
button. Button. We'll give it an
ID of fund will say on click
equals fund. And we'll say fund.
And this will be our button
here, we save it, we're looking
at our front end. Now the fund
button that if we call, we say
funding with undefined because
we're not passing it an amount
here. So back in our index
console dot log funding with and
we'll just want to make sure
that we can actually call that
Funmi function. So we'll copy
this line again and we'll say
type of window dot Aetherium
does not equal undefined. We'll
go ahead and try to fund here to
send a transaction. What are the
things that we absolutely 100%
Always need? Well, we need a
provider slash connection to the
blockchain. And we need a signer
slash wallet, slash someone with
some gas to actually send it and
then And we're probably going to
need the contract that we are
interacting with. And to get
that contract, we're going to
need ABI and address. And with
these all together, we can send
any transaction. So to get our
provider, we're going to
actually go ahead and work with
ethers again. Now, we're going
to do it a little bit
differently, though, before, the
way we worked with ethers is we
said const ethers equals require
ethers, right. And this is how
we pulled ethers. And now like I
just said to you, though,
require doesn't work in the
front end. And we actually don't
want to install ethers with a
node modules package. So what we
can actually do instead is let's
go to the ethers documentation.
If you go to the Getting Started
section, scroll down, they have
a section about importing using
Node js, which uses require or
imports. And then they also have
some documentation for working
with the web browser. So instead
of us doing a node module, what
we'll do is we'll copy the
ethers library to our own
directories and serve it
ourselves. So what we do is we
can come in here, we can copy
this massive file, which is
ethers, but in front end
addition, and come back to our
file. And we'll make a new file
in here.
Called ethers. We'll do 5.6
point esm.min.js. And we'll
paste that massive thing in
here. Now, since I have prettier
when I save it, it's going to
auto format. And it's just this
huge file, which has everything
ethers, but front end defied if
you will. Now what we can do is
we can import this into our
index.js. So instead of using
require in here, we'll say
import ethers from and then
we'll just refer to that file
that we just got ethers dash 5.6
point esm.min.js. Now, we only
need to do this weird copy
pasting of the file import thing
in this HTML JavaScript lesson.
In future lessons with Node js,
we are going to do yarn, add
ethers, kinda like we've
normally seen. The frameworks
like React and next Jas that
we're going to use are going to
automatically convert those yarn
added packages to their front
end to five versions. But for
this section, this is how we're
going to actually import the
ethers package. Now the other
thing we'll have to do is on our
front end, we'll have to change
this from type text slash
JavaScript to type module
changes. The type module allows
us to import modules into our
code, which we're going to be
importing this, and we're going
to import another module as
well. Awesome. And now though,
if we go back to our front end,
do a little refresh with the
connect button, we get Connect
is not defined at HTML
button.on. Click, so instead of
calling our Connect button from
the front end here, we're going
to remove these on clicks from
our index dot HTML, and go into
our index.js and add those
connect buttons in here. So
we'll say const. Connect button
equals document, dot get element
by ID, Connect button. And then
we'll say const. One button
equals Doc, you meant dot get
element by ID. One button, the
idea of the connect button is
Connect button. The idea the fun
button is fun button. And then
we'll say connect button.on
Click equals connect. And one
button.on Click equals fond. We
go back to our front end, do a
little refresh. We'll hit
connect now. And it's actually
working, we'll go to our
Metamask will disconnect,
refresh, hit Connect, and boom,
it's popping up again. This is
just due to that type being
module, if it was text slash
JavaScript, that on click button
adding in here, but since we're
doing module, we're going to add
those on clicks right in our
JavaScript. But now that we've
got ethers in here, what we can
do is we can even do like a
little console dot log, just
paste ethers in here, or
actually better yet. We'll add
it right above the Connect
button. Go back to our front
end, we'll do a refresh and we
see the entire ethers object
right in our front end which is
perfect, which is exactly what
we want here. And since we've
got these two variables here, we
might as well update this to
just say connect button dot
innerHTML equals connected and
here as well. Connects button
dot innerHTML equals please
install meta mask because now
connect button is going to be
the same as running this
document dot get element by ID
right
here. and great. Let's go back
to continuing our font function.
So we'll say const provider
equals new ethers dot providers
dot web three provider, window
dot Aetherium. Web three
provider is an object in ethers
that allows us to basically wrap
around stuff like Metamask is
web three provider is really
similar to that JSON RPC
provider, which we use before,
which is where we put in exactly
that endpoint, our alchemy
endpoint, or when we're working
with Metamask. Here, whatever
endpoint that we have in our
network section is web three
provider takes that HTTP
endpoint and automatically
sticks it in ethers for us. So
this line of code basically
looks at our Metamask and goes,
Ah, okay, I found the HTTP
endpoint inside there, Metamask.
That's going to be what we're
going to use as our provider
here. Since our provider is
connected to our Metamask. Here,
we can get a signer or we can
get a wallet just by running
const signer equals provider,
dot get signer, this is going to
return whichever wallet is
connected from the provider,
which again, our provider is our
Metamask. So if we're connected
with with account one, it's
going to return account one as
the signer connected with
account two, it'll return
account two, etc. Now, I'm going
to add console dot log signer
here, and then flip to the front
end now and show you what
happens when we hit the fund
button. You can see in here we
have our JSON RPC signer, the
signer is going to be the
account that we've connected to
our front end. Now we have our
provider, we have our signer.
Now, we're going to need our
contract by getting the API and
the address. So we're gonna need
to say const. Contract equals
what? How are we going to get
our contract? Well, this is
where we're going to need to
know the ABI and the address of
a working with typically, what
you'll see a lot of projects do