since once a contract is
deployed, the addresses are
going to change is they're going
to have some type of constants
file. So they'll create a new
file called constants, dot j s.
And in here, they'll add the
addresses and any API's and
anything like that for us to use
in our fund piece here. Now, as
we're developing, and as we're
building, this, the backend and
the front end team are gonna
have to interact a little bit,
or if it's just you doing the
full stack, you're gonna have to
interact with their back end. So
this is why it's so important to
have both your front end and
your back end code nearby. So if
we go back to our Hardhead, fund
me project that we just made, we
can find the ABI in here. Once
again, if we go to artifacts, go
to contracts, we can go to fund
me dot soul, fund me dot JSON,
we can find the ABI right here,
it's going to be this massive
thing right here. So you can go
ahead, you can even copy this
whole thing in this little non
squiggly bracket and this little
bracket here, we can copy that.
And then we can come back to our
constant.js. And we can just
save it as variable, we'll say
Export const, Avi, e equals and
paste that in there. And then
back in our index dot j s, we
can import it with import
API from constants. Oops. Okay,
great. So we have the API. Well,
what about the address, since
we're going to be running this
locally, we want to get the
contract address of this locally
run contract, we can do that a
couple of ways. One way is you
can just have two windows open
one with your front end code,
one with your back end code, and
the one with your back end code,
you can run yarn, hard hat node,
which will spin up our
blockchain node for us, and give
us the address in here. Or what
we can do. And this will
probably be a little bit easier
is in your window with your
front end code and create a new
terminal. And now we'll have two
terminals running. And then this
second one, we're going to CD
down CD dot dot, and then CD,
hard hat on Me Free Code Camp.
And in here, we're going to run
yarn, art head node. And this is
going to spin up our local
blockchain in this second
terminal in here, where we have
deploying fund me deploy that
address, blah, blah, blah, right
here. And just a reminder, if I
hit this x, it just hides the
terminal. I can always pull it
back up with terminal new
terminal, and I can always hide
it, but this is still running
inside of my terminal. So I'm
going to hide it. And what I can
do is I can come back over to
our constants folder, and at the
top, we can do export const
contract address. equals, we'll
pull the terminal back up. And
we'll go grab, where it says,
pulling fund me deployed at
right here. We'll copy that
address, put some quotes, and
we'll paste it in. And now we're
also exporting the contract
address, then in our index.js
will import the contract address
with comma, contract address.
And now we have both the ABI and
the contract address. So what we
can do, we can say const
contract equals new ethers dot
contract of, we'll pass the
contract address, pass the API,
and we'll pass it the signer.
Now we have an ethers contract
object that's connected to our
signer, and we have the contract
address, and we have the
contract abi, now that we have a
contract object, we can go ahead
and start making transactions
the exact same way we've made
transactions before we can just
run const transaction response
equals a weight contract dot
fund. And then we'll pass a
value of ethers dot utils dot
parse, ether ether mount. So
this is going to be how we're
going to go ahead and create our
transaction. And if you take
this right now, and we go to our
front, we give it a little
refresh, make sure we're
connected and we hit fund, we're
gonna get this error value must
be a string. That's because at
the mount right now is being
passed in as nothing. Now
normally, we'll pass parameters
directly to our functions. But
what we're going to do is for
now is we're just going to hard
code this. So we'll say const.
At the mount equals, we'll do
like 77, or something we had
fun. Now, what do you think's
gonna happen? Well, we get this
other air, insufficient funds
for intrinsic transaction cost,
or you might get some other
error, but you're gonna get a
weird error here. And that's
because we're not actually
connected to our local hard head
node right now. Well, if we look
at our Metamask, we're currently
not connected to the right
blockchain, we're connected to
rink B, or main net or whatever,
we need to get connected to our
local host. If you look in your
networks, you'll actually have a
local host object here already.
But let's just be super
specific. And we'll add a new
network here, we're going to add
something called our hard hat,
local host. And we'll hit Add
Network and we'll add Hardhead.
Local host in here, the RPC URL,
we can find from our node area,
which we scroll to where our
node is running, we can copy
this URL and paste it into new
RPC URL, chain ID is going to be
31337 currency symbol is going
to be go or ether. Even though
this pop up says it might have a
different currency symbol go,
we're just going to put eath in
here. And there is no block
explorer, right? Because this is
a local blockchain, we're not
going to have a block Explorer.
So we'll go ahead and hit Save.
And now we have an account here,
which is great. We're connected
to our local blockchain. And if
we switch our meta mask, we can
see we're on the local hard hat.
And we are connected. Awesome.
Let's refresh. Let's run fund
one more time. And we'll see a
transaction does indeed pop up.
This is great. But our account
here doesn't have any money we
have, we're broke, we don't have
any local Hardhead Aetherium. So
we're actually going to need to
import one of our accounts from
hard hat into our meta mask,
which we can do so and you can
actually do this for any account
with a private key so hard that
gives us these accounts. And
we're going to import the
private key of Count zero into
our meta mask. So we're going to
copy the private key, we're
going to come back to our front
end, click on our meta mask,
we're gonna hit this big button,
we're gonna hit import account.
It's like type private key, and
we're gonna paste our private
key here. A quick note, if you
choose json file, remember how
back in that ether section, we
encrypted our key into a JSON
file with a password, you can
actually import accounts with
that JSON file with the
password. So if you encrypt a
key and you want to add it to
meta mask, you can go ahead and
add it in just like this. But
for now, we're going to use
private key, we'll paste the
private key in and we'll hit
import. And we can see we now
have an account, a new account
and account three, with a ton of
eath from our local blockchain.
So we'll refresh one more time,
we'll go ahead and connect,
we'll make sure that our account
three is connected. And if it's
not, we'll go ahead and hit this
Connect button. So that now our
account three is what's
connected here. And we'll go
ahead and hit fund. And we now
see that we can fund this
contract, we can go ahead and
hit Confirm. And if we look and
nothing's going to happen on our
front end, because we didn't
tell our front end to do
anything once we confirm, but if
we go to our blockchain, we can
see our fun function was called
we've just made our first
transaction on a blockchain from
our own front end, this is
awesome, great work. But it's
probably a little confusing to
the user. If nothing happens
here, they're going to hit the
fun function. And it's going to
be like, Oh, okay, cool. What,
what happens? Now, we probably
want to make it a little bit
more obvious that something just
happened. And one more thing I
want to show you, you don't have
to follow along here, if I hit
fund, and then I hit reject,
it's gonna freak out on us and
be like, hey, like, you hit
reject, I don't know what to do
now. So we're going to make our
code a little bit more robust by
adding a try catch. So we'll
tell JavaScript to try running
this transaction. And then if it
catches an error, just to
console dot log, that error. So
now, if I hit fund, and I hit
reject, it's gonna, it'll still
be a little bit mad, but at
least we're catching it and it's
not going to break and destroy
everything. Okay, cool. We've
got a transaction response here.
And when we hit fund, our front
end goes great. You've funded me
I'm I'm super confused. Oh, one
other point, something that
you'll probably run into
multiple times. As we're doing
this. If you get an error that
looks like this eath. JS query
while formatting outputs from
RPC, nonce to high expected not
to be too but got form, you will
definitely see this a whole lot.
Here's what you do to fix this.
The reason this happens is
because you've closed your
hardhat node and then restarted
it, and your heart had node
goes, Okay, well, I'm starting
fresh, I'm starting from zero.
But Metamask isn't smart enough
to know that, what we want to do
is we want to come to our
Metamask, we'll hit this big
button, we'll go down to
settings, we'll go to Advanced,
and we'll go to reset account.
And yes, we're going to reset
it. This isn't something ideally
that you'd like to do with an
actual account with actual money
on a local network, this is
fine. Now if you reset the
account, and you reset the node,
we can go ahead and hit Confirm.
And it doesn't give us that
error anymore. So that's kind of
the tip there, you want to reset
the nuts so that our Metamask
and our blockchain are in sync
with that nonce number.
So we have this transaction
response. And we probably want
our front end to give the user
some indication, hey, the
transaction went through. So
what we want to do is we want to
listen to the blockchain for
this to finish. So we can either
listen for the TX to be mined.
Or we can listen for an event.
We haven't learned about events
yet. But we will. So for now,
since we haven't learned about
events yet, we're just going to
listen for the TX to be mined.
Or to listen for the transaction
to be mined, we're actually
going to create a new function
called function, listen, or
transaction mine in this is
going to take as input a
transaction response, and a
provider. Now you'll notice this
isn't an async function. For
this section. This is
intentional, we don't want this
to be an async function. And
you'll see why in a second.
We're going to be using
JavaScript promise JavaScript
async functionality to its
massive advantage. And this is
why JavaScript actually works so
well on the front end is because
of how it's asynchronous. So
we're going to create this
function listen for transaction
to be mined, we're going to
await in our fund function. And
we're going to have this return
a promise. Let's go ahead, and
let's learn how to build this.
So we're gonna say console dot
log, string interpolation, we'll
say mining. And then in here,
we'll say transaction, response
dot hash. All of our transaction
response objects have a hash,
which just represent that hash.
And we'll do a couple of data
dot, we'll put in our console
here, we're waiting for the
transaction to be mined, then
what we're going to do is we're
going to return a new promise.
And the reason we're going to
return a promise is because we
need to create a listener for
the blockchain. We want to
listen for this event to happen.
But we want to tell JavaScript,
hey, wait for this thing to
finish looking, wait for this
thing to finish looking. Now
here's where this gets a little
bit tricky. In our fund
function. After we create the
transaction, we basically want
to tell JavaScript Hey, wait for
this TX to finish. So our code
is going to look as simple as
await listen for transaction
mine. And we're going to pass it
the trans action response
and our provider. So we're
saying hey, listen for this
transaction finish. And we're
using this await keyword,
because again, the await keyword
says okay, we're gonna stop
right here. We're gonna stop
until this function is
completely done. Now in this
listen for transaction in mind,
we have to define how we're
actually going to listen for
this. So we're going to say
listen for this transaction to
finish. Ethers actually comes
with a way for us to listen for
transactions and listen for
events, which again, we haven't
learned About, but don't worry
about that yet. So we can go to
the ethers docs. And we can look
up once. Contract dot once.
There's a whole bunch of
listeners that we can use to
listen for events and listen for
different things to happen, we
can do this thing called
provider dot once where we
listen for some event. And once
that event fires, we call some
other function that we've
defined. Now, we haven't talked
about events yet. And again,
don't worry about this quite
yet. One of the events that we
can wait for is we can just wait
for the transaction receipt to
finish, right, because once we
get a transaction receipt, that
means that the transaction has
actually finished going through.
So we're going to use this
provider dot once syntax to wait
for the transaction receipt,
which is going to be our event,
which isn't really an event, but
don't worry about that yet. And
then we're going to call some
listener function that we
defined, you can also do
provider.on, which will trigger
anytime your event fires
provider once just triggers one
time, we only care about this
transaction going through one
time. So we're passing our
provider object. So we're gonna
say provider dot once our event
which is just going to be
transaction response, hash,
provided on transaction response
dot hash. So once we get this
hash, which will pretty much get
right away, we're going to call
our listener function. Now we
can create a function listener
like this, and then just pass
listener in here. But we're
going to do an anonymous
function here, because that's
typically what we see as the
syntax for these loops. And so
far, we're doing provider dot
once to do this anonymous
function, we're going to do just
two little parentheses here. And
this arrow notation. So this by
itself represents an anonymous
function. So we're saying, hey,
there's some function, it
doesn't take any parameters, and
it doesn't have any code, this
arrow function, this whole thing
is saying this is an anonymous
function. So we're saying
provided at once transaction
hash happens, here's the
function that you want to
execute. It doesn't do anything
right now. But let's have a do
something. So once this
transaction dot response
finishes, we're going to take a
trans transaction received as an
input parameter, or our our
callback function, or our
listener function. And all we're
going to do is we're gonna say
console dot log, completed with
a little string interpolation,
transaction receipt, that
confirmations, confirmations,
and then completed with
transaction receipt,
confirmations, confirmations. So
once this provider dot once sees
that there's a transaction hash,
it's going to give as an input
rammer to our listener function,
the transaction receipt, kind of
that same syntax that we've been
seeing this whole time, once a
transaction response finishes,
we get the transaction receipt,
and we can do stuff with it. And
we see how many block
confirmations it has. For us,
this pretty much should always
be one. Now if we save this, go
back to our front end, and we
hit fund, it's going to work,
we're going to give the user
some indication that it worked,
which is great. But it's not
really going to work the way
that we want it to work. We have
this console dot log done right
after we do the await, listen
for transaction mine, and we
come back and we hit fund, we
hit confirm, it actually doesn't
go in the order that we want it
to go, it goes mining this thing
that it says Done. And then it
says completed with one trip
confirmation what what's going
on here, we should write
completed before we write done,
because that's the order that we
have this in. But it looks like
it's words, it's going out of
order. What what's going on
here, what's going to happen is
when we call listen for
transaction mine, or listen for
transaction, mine function is
going to kick off, but it's
going to kick off provided on
once as its own process. So
await listen for transaction,
mine will kick off the listener,
but it doesn't wait for this
listener to find the transaction
response. So this function will
actually finish before provider
dot once finishes. So after it
kicks off the listener, it'll
run to the next line of our
code, which is console dot log
and done. Our front end we'll go
oh, oh, you kicked off a
listener earlier. Let me go back
down and let me recheck to see
if it's finished. And if it has
finished, I'll go do what it
told me to do. And this is where
what's known as the event loop
kicks in.
We don't actually wait for this
provider that wants to finish,
we add this provided at once
onto this queue called the event
loop. And our front end is going
to periodically check back to it
to see if it's finished. So we
want to adjust our code. So we
wait for the listener to finish
listening, which is where we're
going to get into promises here.
So what we want to do is we want
to adjust this function to now
return a promise. And we're
going to use this syntax a
couple of times in the future.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to say hey, we want
to wait for the listener To
finish listening, we're going to
wrap this whole thing into a
promise. And we're going to say
return, new promise. And a
promise takes a function itself
as an input parameter. So again,
we'll use kind of this anonymous
function notation. And it will
take two input parameters
resolve and reject. So resolve
says, hey, if this promise works
correctly, call this resolve
function. And for us, this
promise is going to be done when
the listener finishes listening.
And then we would reject if
there was some type of timeout,
we're not going to write the
reject function. But in the
future, if you were to do this
for production, you'd add some
timeout as the reject parameter.
Basically, you're saying, hey,
once the listener finishes
listening, we're going to
resolve and if it takes too
long, we're gonna say ask for
you, you took too long, and
instead of closing it off, here,
we're going to close it off
around this provider thing. So
we're gonna say return new
promise, resolve, reject. And
only once this transaction gets
fired, are we going to resolve
this promise, like so. So what
is happening here, so we're
going to put the resolve inside
of this provider at once. So
we're saying, once this
transaction hash is found, then
we're going to call this
function, we're gonna say
console dot log, and then we're
going to resolve so this promise
only returns once a resolve or
reject is called. And we're
telling it only resolve only
finish this function once.
Transaction response dot hash is
found, because it's going to be
inside of these little squiggly
parentheses for provider dot
once, the promise right now only
resolves after it's fired. It's
event here. If this was really
confusing, just copy paste this
and move on, we're getting a
little bit deeper into front end
stuff here. So hopefully, this
was clear, if not definitely
jump in to the GitHub
discussions to start asking
about this stuff. But now that
we've updated this, we can come
back to our front end, we can
hit the fund button. And
hopefully this time, everything
will go in order. We'll hit
confirm, we see mining
completed, and then we see done.
And the reason for this is
because again, our await keyword
is now waiting, it says oh,
you're returning a promise, I
need to await I need to wait for
it to resolve or reject. And we
only resolve the promise once
our provider finds this
transaction hash and this
transaction receipt, this is
this listen for transaction
mine. In future sections, all of
this is going to be abstracted
away for us. So life is going to
be much easier, but it is
important to understand what's
actually going on here. Awesome.
So now we're giving the front
end some indication of what's
going on. Our fun function is
done well, no, not really. Why
not? Well, because right now
we're hard coding the eath
amount to 0.1. And on the front
end, we probably don't want to
hard code it, we probably want
to allow users to fund as much
or as little as they want. So we
actually need to change this
from just a button to a input
form. So to do this, we're gonna
go back over into our HTML. So
we'll go back to index dot HTML.
And we're going to change this
fun section here, we're going to
add some form information. So
we're going to keep this button
as it is, or we're going to add
like a little text box to input
as much eath as they want. So
I'm going to create a label,
we're gonna say it's for, it's
going to be fund and this label
we're gonna say, is eath amount,
and then we're gonna close
label, this is basically just
going to create a label. And if
we go back to our front end, we
now just have this Etham out
label that isn't labeling
anything. Now we're going to
create an input, and we're going
to give it an ID of eath amount.
And we're going to give it a
placeholder
of 0.1. And then we're gonna
close the input. So now if we
flip to our front end, we have
eath amount, labeling this
little text box with a
placeholder of 0.1. And we can
add stuff in here, you know,
blah, blah, whatever. And one
more thing, if you have some
tags, but you don't put anything
in between them, you can
actually shorten it by just
putting the little closing thing
at the back of it like this. So
if you don't have anything
between your tags, you can just
close them like this, these two
are equivalent, boom, boom,
boom, boom, those are the same
thing. Great. When we called
fund right now we're calling
fund and we're not passing any
parameters. Let's update our
fund to no longer be hardcoding
eath amount in here, and we'll
have and we'll have our fund
function populated by whatever
we put in this eath amount input
box in our fund function,
instead of saying const eath
amount equals 0.1. We'll grab it
from this eath amount ID and
we'll say document dot get
element by ID eath amount, dot
value. So we're going to grab
whatever value In this input box
here, now, in our index.js, we
have console dot log funding
with eath amount, if in our
front end, we do 1.7. And we hit
fund, we now see in our console
dot log, it says funding with
1.7. And we'll get 1.7. And our
little fun section confirm, it
will mine it, it'll complete it,
and then say, done. Awesome. So
now we've added a little text
box here. So people can fund as
much or as little as they want.
Perfect, this whole thing can
kind of be considered a form.
There's also a form tag, but
we're going to just use this for
now. All right, great. We're
doing a lot of funding right,
and we keep funding our contract
with more and more Ethan, we
keep adding more and more stuff,
we probably want a button to
keep track of how much is
actually in here. So let's just
add a really simple balance
button. And let me actually just
move this down to the bottom
here, much better. So we'll say
button, id equals balance
button. We'll call it get
balance. Now we have a get
balanced button. And it's not
going to do anything because we
don't have a get balanced
function. So let's go back to
our index.js. And we'll create a
get bounced function async
function get bounce. And we'll
just do what we've been doing so
far. If type of window dot
Aetherium does not equal,
undefined, then we're going to
do const provider equals new
ethers, ethers, dot providers
dot web three provider of
window, that Aetherium then will
do const balance equals awaits
provider dot get balance,
contract address, which again,
we're importing way up at the
top, and then we'll just do
console dot log ethers dot utils
dot format, ether, bounce this
format ether function ethers
utils, which you can find in the
documentation to make reading
ethers, formatted numbers much
easier to read. Then same as
what we've been doing before,
we're going to go up, we're
going to copy this fun button
line, paste it will say balance
button equals document dot get
element by ID, balance button.
And then we'll say balance
button on click equals get
balance, we're gonna come back
to our front end, we'll do a
quick refresh, we'll do get
balance. And now we can see the
balance in the console, we can
fund with more like 1.8, we'll
hit fund metamath pops up, we'll
go ahead and confirm mining
completed done, we hit get
balanced, and now we're at 3.8.
Fantastic. Alright, let's keep
it going. What do we need to do
next, we're gonna go ahead and
eat our withdrawal function
here. So let's create that this
is gonna look really similar to
everything we've done so far. So
on our index dot HTML, let's
create a new button that we can
do by copying this whole line,
paste it underneath, call this
withdraw button, we'll call
withdraw. And we'll call this
withdraw. And then in our index,
do the same thing, we'll copy
this, paste it below. So with
drop button was document get
element by ID, withdraw button,
withdraw button.on Click equals
withdraw. So let's make a
withdrawal function down at the
bottom. We'll go ahead, say
async. Function withdraw,
will do the exact same that
we've done above. And I can even
just copy everything from the
get balance and just remove the
balance section. If type of
window dot Aetherium does not
equal to undefined, then we'll
grab the provider here. And same
as the fund contract, we'll grab
the signer and the contract. So
let's just grab those two lines.
Paste them down here called
signer equals provider dot get
signer. Contract equals new
contract, blah, blah, blah.
Okay, cool. Now we're gonna do
the exact same here as we did
with the fun function. So we're
gonna do a little try, catch,
and then we'll even add the
catch here, catch error, console
dot log error. And inside of our
try, we'll do const transaction
response equals await, contracts
dot withdraw. We don't need to
put any parameters in here. Oh,
then actually, let's do a little
console dot log, withdrawing,
and then we'll get this
transaction response. And then
we'll listen for this
transaction to get mined as
well. By running a Wait, listen
for transaction mine transaction
response comma, provider And
that's it, since we can reuse
the functionality from our
listen for transaction mine. So
now we'll refresh, we'll make
sure we're connected, check the
current balance, which is 3.8.
Now we'll go ahead and withdraw.
We see our little withdrawing
console dot log, we'll hit
Confirm. And it looks like we've
completed it, if we look in our
Metamask, our bounced will have
been increased by the amount
that was added here. And now if
we hit balance, we do indeed see
zero, we can even double check
that this is actually working,
we can see our balance is 9.99.
Let's go ahead and even fund
this with 99 eath. Good confirm,
looks like it's completed. Our
meta mask now shows 99.00. And
if we go ahead and withdraw,
confirm, that withdrawal has
gone through, we can see our
balance is back up to 9999. And
now let's just go back and
change. Hey, what's good. We'll
refresh our front end. And now
we can see you've done it, we've
created a minimalistic website
that allows us to connect to the
blockchain and call functions
from a front end. And from a
website, this is absolutely
massive, you should be
incredibly proud and incredibly
excited with yourself. Now, this
is definitely a minimalistic
version. And we're going to work
with more powerful and more
modern front end frameworks. But
this will give you an idea of
exactly what's going on behind
the scenes when we're working
with those more advanced front
ends, and we'll style them up.
So they look a little bit better
than this. But with that being
said, you've just learned the
basics of how these front ends
work. And now that you know how
to push things up to get, I
highly recommend you start
pushing all of these projects up
to your GitHub, they will be a
record that you've actually done
the work and you've built these
smart contracts. And if you're
looking to get an internship
down the line, if you're looking
to help other GitHub projects,
this will be a record of hey, I
can do this, what I can build
look at what I know how to do so
congratulations on your first
full stack or your first front
end application. Before we move
on, let's do a quick refresher
of everything we've learned
here. So number one, typically,
you want the repository or your
code base. For your back end for
your smart contracts to be a
different repository than your
front end, your front end code
is going to be a combination of
HTML and JavaScript. When we
have a wallet like meta mask,
we're injecting these browser
based wallets into the window
object of our browsers like
window dot Aetherium. Each
browser will have a different
extension here, reason we do
this, we want to connect to the
RPC URL that's built into our
meta masks. And in this way,
we're making the same API calls
to an RPC URL as we do in hard
hat as we do in remix as we do
in ethers, etc, we created our
first promise based function
where we had a listener kickoff,
and we wrapped it in a promise
to say, hey, we want to wait for
our listener to finish since
this is a promise based
function, we set a weight listen
for transaction mind and we
waited for this transaction to
finish so that on our front end,
once our transaction finished
going through, we can tell the
user it's finished going through
and we can continue doing other
stuff. Give yourself that round
of applause and let's move on to
the next section.
All right, welcome to the next
section. We are now on Lesson
Nine, our hardhat smart contract
lottery, which again, all the
code for this section is going
to be available in the GitHub
repo associated with this
course. Alright, so let me show
you what we're about to build.
I'm going to show you the front
end login, you don't have to do
the front end, if you don't
want. But the front end does
give us a nice way to visualize
the lottery that we're building.
Here, we're building an
application that allows users
completely decentralized to
allow us to engage in a fair, a
verifiably random lottery. This
is the application that would
actually fix the McDonald's
issue that we talked about much
earlier. So first, we got this
Kinect Wallet button that we're
going to click to connect to
meta mask. And here, we're
actually going to show you how
to connect to more than just
Metamask wallet connect to trust
wallet, math, wallet, any of
these wallets, and we'll show
you how to customize even more.
So we're going to connect to
Metamask. Here, we'll choose our
account that we imported in from
Hardhead, we choose Next we're
gonna choose Connect. And
remember, for our front end bit,
we're gonna go to Settings
Advanced reset account, if we're
working with a brand new hard
hat blockchain. Now, the front
end doesn't look super nice, but
we have an enter raffle button.
And we have a little bit of UI
talking about the current number
of players and then the most
previous winner of a raffle. So
we can go ahead and enter the
raffle and allow anybody to pay
0.1 eath. To enter our smart
contract, we get a little
transaction saying transaction
complete, and we get the current
number of players is one, we can
continue to enter the raffle and
anybody can enter this raffle.
And this, the smart contract
will keep track of all the
players in here, we're going to
run this on a timer, the lottery
is going to automatically
trigger somebody to win. And to
do this, to get a pure
verifiable random number, we're
going to be using chain link VRF
to get a pure verifiably random
number. And then we're gonna use
chain link keepers to trigger
the automation to automatically
have one of these winners get
picked every time one of those
time intervals is up. Once the
keepers kick it off, they will
pick a winner, our decentralized
lottery will say the most
previous winner is so and so.
And they will get all the money
from this lottery making a
perfectly fair decentralized
lottery, we're going to call our
contract, raffle dot soul but
you can call it lottery dot soul
or really whatever you want. And
we're going to make it look
really, really nice. So now
we're back in our Visual Studio
code. This is going to be the
project. If you learn this, you
have the skills to learn all the
rest of the smart contract
concepts, and you are going to
be able to do great things in
the space. This is going to be
your flagship project, this is
going to be the one that you can
be the most excited and the most
proud about for this tutorial.
So let's go ahead and let's
create a new folder. So we're
gonna do MK dir, hardhat, smart
contract lottery, FCC or smart
contract, raffle, whatever you
want to call it, then we're
going to cd into our hard hat,
smart contract lottery Free Code
Camp. And we're going to type
code period, or we're going to
open this up in a new folder,
however we choose to do. So now
that we're in our new folder,
we're going to create our new
hard hat project. So we're going
to do yarn, add dash dash dev
hard hat. And we'll get our node
modules are package dot JSON and
our yarn dot lock. Now we'll do
yarn hardhat. To get started
with a new project, and we're
just going to select create an
empty hard hat dot config dot j
s because we know what a basic
project looks like. And we're
gonna give this project the
customizations that we want to
see, we're going to create an
empty hard hat dot config. And
now in here we have a blank
hardhead.config.js with almost
nothing in here. So we're
starting completely from
scratch. Now we're going to add
all of our dependencies in here.
And oftentimes, you'll add these
sequentially as you build but
we're just going to add them all
in one line, and there are a lot
of them. So we've left a copy,
paste the whole section of the
full blockchain solidity course,
J S, for you to just copy,
paste, so you can install
everything in one go. So grab
that line, and it's going to
have everything that we've been
talking about. And we'll just
hit enter, and we'll install all
of these.
And as you create more and more
projects, you'll get the feel of
what you like for your
dependencies and what tools that
you like to use. Remember, at
the end of the day, the tool
that's best for you and best for
the job is the tool that you
like the most. There never
really is a one tool fits all,
there's almost always going to
be trade offs. Alright, now that
we have all those dependencies
installed, if we look at our
package, JSON will have this
massive dev dependencies, we'll
have everything in Node modules
will have everything in yarn dot
lock. And of course, as we know,
in order for any of these to
actually work, we need to add
them into our Hardhead config.
Now, there's a lot of stuff to
add in here as well. So like
once again, if you want to come
to the heart at smart contract,
lottery, FCC, and go to the
Hardhead config, you can just
copy paste everything and place
it into your project so that you
don't have to always type
everything out yourself. Meclabs
Hardhead waffle anomic labs
started ether scan harder to
deploy slitted coverage, or had
gas reporter heart had contract
sizer, which we haven't talked
about yet. But we will Don't
worry. And then require dot env
dot config. And as you all know,
all these little semicolons are
popping up and those are going
to drive me absolutely crazy. So
once again, we can create a dot
prettier, RC. And if you want to
copy this as well, from one of
your previous projects are free
to do so. One thing that I added
in here was a print width of
100. This just changes how long
a line can be before it goes on
to a new line. That's the only
difference here. Now if we go to
our config and hit save, they go
away, thank goodness. Now if we
look at our solidity version,
we're currently using zero point
7.3. Let's go ahead and update
that to 8.8 or 8.7, or whatever
you want to use. Now that we
have all the basic setup, we can
begin coding our smart
contracts. So we first need to
create a new folder called
contracts where we're going to
store all of our contracts. And
let's go ahead and create a new
file called lottery dot soul or
raffle dot soul or whatever you
want to call it. I'm going to
call mine raffle dot soul. And
you might see this indexing
thing happened from time to
time. It's our hard hat,
solidity extension, indexing all
of our node modules. So it knows
how to highlight things and
knows how to work with
everything in our solidity
files. So that's what happens
when that pops up. Now before we
jump in and create it, let's
figure out what we're going to
do. So we're going to create our
raffle contract. And what do we
want people able to do? Well, we
probably want people be able to
enter the lottery, you know,
paying some amount, we're
probably going to want to be
able to pick a random winner.
But we want this to be
verifiably random, we want this
to be untampered with a bowl.
And we also want winner to be
selected every X minutes or
years or months, aka we want
this to be completely automated.
So we want to deploy the smart
contract and almost have no
maintenance almost have nobody
ever have to touch it again. And
it'll just automatically run
forever. This is the power of
smart contracts. As we know,
since we're picking a random
number, and we have some event
driven execution, we know that
we're going to need to use a
chain link Oracle, since we're
going to need to get the
randomness from outside the
blockchain. And we're going to
need to have that automated
execution. Because a smart
contract can execute itself, we
need somebody to automatically
trigger these. So to trigger
selecting a winner, we're gonna
have to use the chain link
keepers. And that's pretty much
going to be our entire code.
Now, I usually like to do this
before I start any project. And
the reason that I do a little
bit of brainstorming is because
we don't want to just jump in
and really do anything, we want
to have a good idea of what
we're trying to build so that we
can write tests for it, so that
we can know if we're going in
the right direction, etc. Now
that we have a good idea of
where we're going, let's build
it. So per usual, let's do spdx
license identifier. And my team
will do pragma solidity little
caret here, zero point 8.7, even
zoom out, just a hair will trash
that and we'll say contract,
raffle, we can even make sure
that we're not going crazy by
doing a little yarn Hardhead
compile and compiled
successfully, we want it to be
able to enter the lottery want
us to be able to enter it. So
maybe we'll create a function
called enter raffle. What else
do we want to do, we want to be
able to pick a random winner. So
maybe we'll create a function
called pick a random winner, and
boom. So let's comment out pick
random winner for now. And let's
just work on this enter raffle
thing. In the past, we've
created projects like Funmi,
where people can send ether to
our contracts or send whatever
native blockchain token to our
smart contracts using the
message dot value based off of
some USD value. For this one,
we're just going to have the
entrance fee instead be USD
based, it's just going to be
that native asset. So for our
enter raffle, we don't have to
set a USD price, we can just set
a minimum eath price. So up at
the top, let's pick our minimum
price. So we'll do a un 256
entrance fee. And now some of
our learnings from our last
section should come in here, we
now know that this entrance fee
is going to be a what, it's
going to be a storage variable.
So let's prepend it with s
underscore let's make a private
variable because we always want
to set our visibility. But let's
have the entrance fee be
configurable. Well, let's create
a constructor now. And we'll
have this entrance fee be
settable in our constructor, so
our constructor will take a UNT
two to the sixth entrance fee, s
underscore entrance fee equals
entrance fee. Well, if we're
gonna only set this one time, we
might as well make this a
constant or an immutable
variable. So let's make this an
immutable variable so that we
save some gas we'll change this
from S to I and now we're saying
you interviewed six private
immutable I entrance fee equals
entrance fee. Now we probably
are going to want other users to
see the entrance fee. So down
below, we can create function
get entrance fee, and this will
be a public view function which
will returns a UN to the set
Next, and we'll just say return
entrance fee. Now we have a
function that users can call to
get the entrance fee. But we, as
developers can use this AI
entrance fee to know this is an
immutable variable. This is
pretty cheap gas wise for us to
read from in our enter raffle,
we've done a ton of these
before, all we need to do is we
just need to require the message
dot value is greater than that I
underscore entrance fee, what
we've learned before about those
error codes, so we could use
require message dot value, or we
could do one of these customers,
which is going to be a lot more
gas efficient, because instead
of storing this string, we're
just going to store an error
code in our smart contract. So
let's do that. Instead, we'll
say if the message dot value is
less than our eye entrance fee,
then we're just going to revert
the whole transaction with some
error code. And we'll use a best
practice naming raffle
underscore underscore not enough
eath entered. And we'll grab
this arrow code. And we'll have
if the user doesn't send enough
value will revert with not
enough eath entered now that we
know they're calling into raffle
with enough value, we're
probably going to want to keep
track of all the users who
actually enter our raffle. That
way, when we pick a winner, we
know who's in the running. So
let's create an array of players
at the top error here. And then
just to make this look even
nicer, we'll do a little comment
here. And we'll say state
variables. And we'll combine
both our storage and are not
storage variables just in this
state variable section. So we'll
do address array players. Now
players, of course, is going to
have to be in storage, because
we're going to modify this a
lot, we're going to be adding
and subtracting players all the
time. So we're going to do s
players will make this private
as well. And we're going to make
this address payable players
because one of these players
wins, we're going to need to
have to pay them. So we'll make
this address payable private as
players. And since we're going
to make this private, and it's
probably good that we know who's
in the players array, we'll even
do function it player. This will
be a public view that returns an
address of one of these players.
And we'll just return s players
of index will have this
function, take a un 256 index as
an input parameter, we know that
players is going to be a storage
variable. And we're going to add
it to our enter raffle Oh, and
we definitely want our Inter
raffle to be public and to be
payable. Since we're having
people send message dot value,
and we want anyone to be able to
enter our raffle. So it'll be
public, it'll be payable, it'll
be perfect. Now that we have our
array, and someone's entered the
raffle, we'll do s players dot
push message dot sender. Now,
this doesn't actually work
because message dot sender isn't
a payable address. So we'll need
to typecast it as a payable
address just by wrapping it in
payable. So now we have a way to
keep track of all the players
that are entering
a raffle. Now one of the
concepts that we haven't gone
over yet is actually going to be
events. And events are really
important to our smart
contracts. Whenever we update a
dynamic object, like an array or
a mapping, we always want to
omit an event when we get to
less than 10. And then
especially less than 15 with the
next Jas and if T marketplace,
these events will make a ton of
sense, especially for front end
developers. So right now events
might be a little bit of a weird
thing for you as we explain it.
But as we continue on, they'll
start to make more and more
sense. So we're going to start
adding events to our smart
contracts. Whenever we update
one of these dynamically sized
data structures. And to learn
more about events and how to use
them. We're gonna watch another
video that explains all about
events. You can actually follow
along with this video as a side
project. But let's learn all
about events. Now, if you've
worked with solidity, you've
probably seen these things
called events before or maybe
you haven't seen something like
events. But you've always
wondered how chain link or the
graph or some of these other off
chain protocols work under the
hood. And in this video, we're
gonna learn about logging and
events in solidity, viewing
those events on ether scan, and
then working with them in hard
hat. Now it's the Ethereum
virtual machine, or EVM. That
makes a lot of these block
chains tick, like Aetherium. And
the EVM has this functionality
called a logging functionality.
When things happen on a
blockchain, the EVM writes these
things to a specific data
structure called its log, we can
actually read these logs from
our blockchain nodes that we
run. In fact, if you run a node
or you connect to a node, you
can make a F get logs call to
get the logs. Now inside these
logs is an important piece of
logging called events. And this
is the main piece that we're
gonna be talking about today.
events allow you to print
information to this logging
structure in a way that's more
gas efficient than actually
saving it to something like a
storage variable. These events
and logs live in this special
data structure that isn't
accessible to smart contracts.
That's why it's cheaper because
smart contracts can access them
so that If the trade off here,
we can still print some
information that's important to
us without having to save it in
a storage variable, which is
going to take up much more gas.
Each one of these events is tied
to the smart contract or account
address that emitted this event
in these transactions. listening
for these events is incredibly
helpful. Let's say for example,
you want to do something every
time somebody calls a transfer
function. Instead of always
reading all the variables and
looking for something to flip
and switch, all you have to do
is say, listen for event. So a
transaction happened, an event
is emitted. And we can listen
for these events. This is how a
lot of off chain infrastructure
works. When you're on a website,
and that website reloads when a
transaction completes, it
actually was listening for that
transaction to finish listening
for that event to be emitted, so
that it could reload or it could
do something else. It's
incredibly important for front
ends. It's also incredibly
important for things like chain
link, and the graph in the chain
link network. A chain link node
is actually listening for
request data events for to get a
random number, make an API call,
or etc. Sometimes there are way
too many events. And you need to
index them in a way that makes
sense that you can query all
these events that happen at a
later date. The graph listens
for these events and stores them
in the graph so that they're
easy to query later on. So
events are incredibly powerful.
And they have a wide range of
uses. They're also good for
testing and some other stuff,
but you get the picture. They're
really sick. Now that we know
what events are, let's look at
what they look like how we can
use them and how we might use
them in our smart contract
development suite. Now here's
what an event is going to look
like. We have an event here
called stored number. So we have
basically a new type of event
called stored number. We're
saying, hey, solidity, hey,
smart contract, we have this new
event thing, we're going to be
omitting things of typed stored
number in the future. When we
emit this event, it's going to
have these four parameters, it's
going to have a unique 256. For
called old number. Are you
interested? Is it called new
number are you intimidated six
called add a number and an
address called center. Now for
the astute people here, you
might have noticed that there
was another keyword in here, the
index to keyword and this is a
really important keyword. When
we omit one of these events,
there are two kinds of
parameters, there are the index
parameters and the non indexed
parameters, you can have up to
three index parameters. And
they're also known as topics. So
if you see a topic, you know
that that's going to be an
indexed parameter. Index
parameters are parameters that
are much easier to search for,
and much easier to query than
the non index parameters. In
fact, we recommend F get logs
function, it even has a
parameter allows us to search
for specific topics. So it's
much more searchable than the
non indexed ones. The non
indexed ones are harder to
search because they get ABI
encoded, and you have to know
the API in order to decode them.
Now, this is told our smart
contract that there is a new
type of stored number, a new
kind of event here, we need to
actually emit that event in
order to store that data into
the logging data structure of
the EVM. To do that, we need to
do something that looks like
this. This is what it looks like
when we emit an event, it looks
very similar to calling a
function. So you call a mitt and
then the name of the event. And
then you add all the parameters
in there that you like. Here's
the full example of a smart
contract that has an event and
is going to be the example that
we walked through in hard hat.
Now in this smart contract,
whenever anybody calls the store
function, we're going to omit
this event. Here's an example of
a transaction where we call the
store function with a value of
one, let's look into the logs to
see what this event actually is
going to look like an event is
going to be broken down like so
the address of the contract or
account, the event is emitted
from the topics or the index
parameters of the event data.
This is the ABI encoded non
index parameters of the event.
What does this mean? This means
that we took those parameters
that were non indexed, we match
them together with their API or
application binary interface,
pumped them through an encoding
algorithm, and boom, this is
what we got. If you have the
API, they're very easy to
decode. If you don't have the
ABI they are very hard to decode
these non indexed parameters
cost less gas to pump into the
logs. Now in this particular
contract, since we have verified
the code, we verified the
contract ether scan knows what
the ABI is, and we can view this
in Deke or decoded mode. Hex
mode is obviously the non
decoded mode, or in its raw, hex
or hexadecimal or encoded mode.
You can read more about the
layout of these events in the
solidity docs. Now, so that's
the basic introduction of
events. And for those of you who
want to watch the rest of that
video, and who wants to actually
practice using events yourself,
there's a link to these videos
and the code repository
associated with that video, if
you want to play with it, and if
you want to learn more, so feel
free Ready to refer back to the
full blockchain solidity course,
Jas, if you want to go deeper
into events now that we're back,
and we've learned a little bit
more about events, let's add
some events to this contract.
Remember, these events get
emitted to a data storage
outside of this smart contract.
Let's create an event called
raffle enter a good syntax for
naming events, name events, with
the function name reversed. So
for enter raffle, we're gonna
say raffle entered. So up at the
top below our state variables,
but above our constructor, we'll
create a new section called
events. And we'll create our
first event. So we'll do event,
raffle, Enter. And we'll just
have this raffle enter take one
index parameter, it'll be an
address indexed player. So in
our Inter raffle, we're going to
say omit raffle enter. And we're
just going to pass it message
dot sender. I'm going to remove
these comments for now. But feel
free to leave them in as you
code along. Now in this part of
my raffle coding or my lottery
coding process, I probably would
start already writing some tests
and already writing some deploy
scripts. The reason that we do
this is it's good to test our
functionality as we progress.
And oftentimes, when I'm writing
smart contracts, I'm constantly
flipping back and forth between
my deploy scripts, my contracts
and my tests to make sure
everything is doing exactly what
I want it to do for the purpose
of this course. And just to make
it easy for you to learn and
follow along, we're not going to
do that. And we're just going to
keep writing our smart contract
almost to complete and then move
to our deploy scripts and tests.
So in its minimalistic sense, we
essentially have a way for
people to enter our raffle. Now
we need a way to pick the random
winner. And this is where we're
going to need chain link VRF and
chain link keepers. So let's
again, watch some sub lessons
about learning about chain link
VRF. And learning about chain
link keepers. We've made some
videos about these before. So
we're just going to play these
videos. So you can learn about
how taling VRF version two
works, and also how chain link
keepers works, then we're going
to come back and we're going to
add them into our contracts
here. If you're already
familiar, and you already played
with them, feel free to skip
those sections. And we'll just
get to building them here.
Hi, my name is Steven fluid. And
today we're going to be taking a
look at chain links VRF. version
two, version two has a few
different mental models that we
should be aware of. And I want
to show you what it feels like
to be using it. The big
important thing to know about
Vera version two is that instead
of the Vera one model where
you'd be funding your contract
with Link, instead, you're going
to be funding a subscription,
which is basically an account
that allows you to fund and
maintain balance for multiple
consumer contracts. Let's dive
into the docs and see what using
Vera fie two looks and feels
like. In order to show this off
a little bit. I'm going to dive
right into the get a random
number guide in the chain link
documentation. And so it's going
to go through a few the
requirements of some of the
technology we're going to use
today. And the first thing it's
going to ask us to do is to make
sure that we are on the Rinkeby
test net. So let's go ahead and
jump over to Rinkeby. Make sure
my meta mask is unlocked here.
And now that I'm on Rinkeby,
great, I should be able to use
the VIP version to test net. Now
we're going to jump over to
subscription manager. And the
subscription manager is where
we're going to manage our
subscription account. Basically,
this is the place that you put
the funds in order to be able to
use it across a bunch of
different chains. So we're going
to go ahead and connect our
wallet here in order to use the
subscription app. And then we're
going to go ahead and create a
new subscription. So we'll just
use my address as the
subscription address here. I'll
approve the creation. And as
soon as that transaction is
confirmed, our subscription
should be created. Alright, now
we have a subscription.
Basically, this is the account
where we're going to fund it.
And then we can use that account
for all of our random Miss
requests. So I'm gonna go ahead
and just put in 10 link here,
you can put in however much you
want. The price and link of
every random number you request,
it's going to be based on the
current gas rates on a given
chain, as well as the gasoline
that you've chosen. On our funds
have been added, let's go ahead
and add a consumer contract. So
it's asking us for consumer
address, we don't actually have
a consumer address yet. So let's
go ahead and jump over to the
documentation and create a
contract that is going to
request a number. So if you
scroll down, you're going to see
this Vera fee to consumer that
soul contract that we can open
it in remix, let's just jump
right there. We're gonna notice
a few different things in this
contract at the top, we've got
some input. So now you've got
VRF, consumer base version two,
we've got an interface for the
VRF coordinator, and then also a
reference to the link token
interface. So all of those are
specified for you on the Rinkeby
network here in the example
code. And then you can refer to
the documentation for whatever
chain you're going to be
deploying to. And then you're
going to see a few new options
here. So the key hash option is
the way that you specify that
gasoline that was described in
the documentation. So depending
on the key hash you choose for
the given chain you're on the
gas limit will be set
differently for your random
number requests. So for example,
on a theory main net, we have a
200 way key hash 500 Wiki hash
and 1000 graykey hash. You can
also see in our contract Hear
that we have a callback estimate
that you're in charge of. So
depending on how much gas you're
willing to spend in the fulfill
random number, you should set
this value appropriately. Next
up is request confirmations. So
this was something in verify
would be one that you could not
control. But here now, depending
on the chain you're on,
depending on the request and the
type nature of the request you
want to make, you can actually
change this number. And then one
of the most important and useful
features that gives you a lot
more flexibility and control of
your VRF is you can actually
specify the number of random
numbers you want. And so you
specify the number words, and
then that will specify how many
random you went to 56 as you get
back from the network. All right
here in the constructor, we're
gonna see a address for the
coordinator and address for the
link token. And then you'll see
that the subscription ID is
going to be created as we deploy
the contract. And so I'm gonna
go ahead and get that. So if you
remember when we created the
subscription after we found it,
and we see this subscription ID,
and now when I deploy this, I'm
going to use that subscription
ID. And we've got two methods
that should look very familiar,
we've got fulfill randomness
method that takes in randomness
is going to be fulfilled by the
Bureau of Oracle, as well as you
got request random words, which
is how we're actually going to
initiate the request to the
Oracle. So I think we're
actually are already ready to go
ahead and deploy this. So let's
jump to the deploy screen here
and select the right contract,
which in our case, is your FB to
consumer. And I'm going to make
sure that I am on injected web
three so that we can actually
deploy to the Rinkeby network.
And I'm going to paste in the
subscription ID here. And I'm
going to deploy, let's go ahead
and pay for that transaction.
And as soon as that is confirmed
by the network will show up
here, and we'll be able to copy
this address, and then add that
as a consumer and authorize this
contract to use my subscription
account. So let's go ahead and
authorize this with them another
Metamask transaction.
Alright, we can have your
subscription, we can see how
much link we funded it with. And
we can see our consumer
contract. So now by doing this,
we've authorized our consumer
contract to make requests for
randomness. So let's go ahead
and make a request for
randomness here. So we're gonna
go back to our contract that we
deployed here. And we're just
gonna use the remix interface
here to keep things simple. And
I'm going to request some
randomness. So obviously, this
is going to use all of the
configuration that I specified
in my contract, just kind of
hard coded here. So we're gonna
get to words of random is here.
So we're gonna hit request
randomness, confirm the Rigby
transaction. And then as soon as
that transaction comes back, we
should notice that we actually
have a request. And then what
we'll be doing is we'll be
waiting for the Oracle to call
fulfill random words on our
contract. And then we'll be
storing all of those random
words in this s random words,
storage variable. Let's go ahead
and check to see if our random
numbers come back from the
Oracle. So I'll go in here into
random words. And let's request
the zeroeth item of the array
looks like we've got a random
number there. And because we
requested two random numbers, we
should also have an item in
index one. All right, we we've