got our randomness there. And if
we go back to the subscription
manager app, you're going to see
that there's actually an event
history item here, we'll see
that we spent about point three,
three link to get those two
random numbers, we've just taken
a journey to see what it looks
like and feels like to use Veera
version two,
now that we've learned a little
bit more about chainlink VRF, I
hope that you took some time to
go to doxa chain link and play
around with it a little bit so
that you understand what's
really going on, we're going to
use this sample contract in here
to create our function that's
going to pick our random winner.
This is an on chain contract
that coordinates with a
verifiably random chain link
node to give us a random number,
you could look at the code
directly on chain, or you can
come right to the chain link
GitHub and look at all the code
for how this is actually
happening provably and randomly.
And we'll have a link to this in
the GitHub repo associated with
this course. So we're going to
create our function here called
pick a random winner, this
function is going to be called
by the chain link keepers
network so that this can
automatically run without us
having to interact with it. And
actually, while we're updating
this, I want to add some some
stars here saying view slash
pure functions. Now our pick
random winner function, we're
actually not going to make
public we're going to make
external, external functions are
a little bit cheaper than public
functions. Because solidity
knows that our own contract can
call this, we're actually going
to change the name of this
function, as well, very soon,
but we'll get to that in a
little bit. So in order for us
to pick a random winner, we
actually have to do two things,
we first have to request the
random number. And then once we
get it, do something with it. So
chainlink VRF is a two
transaction process. And this is
actually intentional. Having
random numbers in two
transactions is actually also
much better than having it in
one. If it's just one
transaction, then people could
just brute force tries
simulating calling this
transaction and we'll learn how
to simulate calls soon simulate
calling these transactions to
see what they can manipulate to
make sure that they are the
winner. We want to make sure
that this is absolutely fair.
Nobody can manipulate our smart
contract into having them be the
winner of the lottery, this
function is actually going to
request it. And then in a second
func the random number is going
to be returned. And in the
transaction that we actually get
the random number from the chain
link network, that's when we're
going to actually send the money
to the winner. And if we go to
the chain link documentation,
the function that the chain link
node calls is this function
called fulfill random words,
this is going to be the
requesting one, which we could
even change this to request
random winner to make it more
clear, and then we'll make a
function fulfill random words.
And this is going to be an
internal override, which we'll
explain in a little bit, now
fulfill fulfill random words
basically means we're fulfilling
random numbers. The word comes
from a computer science
terminology, but you can
basically just think of this as
fulfill random numbers, because
we can get multiple random
numbers. Now in order to make
our raffle contract VRF a bowl,
we have to import the chain link
code, we can go back to the
documentation, and we're just
going to grab this bottom line
and we'll grab the top line in a
second. So we're going to do
import, I'm going to write it
out. But if you want to copy
paste, you can at chain link
slash contracts slash SRC slash
V 0.8, slash V RF, consumer
base, b two dot Sol. And since
we're importing at chainlink,
slash contracts, we're gonna
need to add that in by running
yarn, add dash dash dev at
chainlink slash contracts. And
now that we have this in here,
we should be able to import like
so. And we're going to need to
make our raffle VRF consumer
base double, we're gonna need to
inherit VRF consumer base go
into our node modules at chain
link src, V 08 VRF, consumer
base V two, it comes with this
function fulfill random words.
And you can see it's an internal
virtual function, virtual means
it's expecting to be
overwritten, the reason that
it's in the sphere of consumer
base V two is so that the VRF
coordinator, which we'll use in
a bit knows that it can call
this fulfill random words
function. And this is the
function that we're overriding.
So back in our raffle dot salt,
we're going to inherit it by
doing is VRF consumer base V
two. And now if we scroll down
to fulfill random words, we can
add in the input parameters
fulfilled pill random words,
which are going to be un 256,
Request ID and un 256, a memory
array random words. And if we
hit Save Our linter will now
notice, okay, this is what I'm
expecting, I'm expecting us to
override the Fill random words,
which takes these parameters.
Now if we look in our docs in
our constructor, we need to pass
the VRF consumer base V TOS
constructor and pass that VRF
coordinator. Again, this V RF
coordinator is the address of
the contract that does the
random number verification. So
right next to our constructor
will add the VRF consumer base V
to constructor and we need to
pass the VRF coordinator v2
address. So in our main
constructor, we'll add that as a
parameter as well. So we'll say
address
VRF core to Nate Torre v two,
and then we'll pass this as a
parameter for the VRF consumer
basically till now that we have
that we shouldn't see that
little underscore anymore. And
we should be able to run yarn
aren't had compiled. Awesome.
And we can see compiled two
files successfully and our code
is working great. Now something
that I often do is I actually
hate running yarn hard hat all
the time, because that's too
many keys for my little brain to
work with. I would prefer to
write as little keys as possible
hard hat also would like us to
write as little keys as
possible. So hard hat comes with
a shorthand and autocomplete
hard hat shorthand is an NPM
package that installs a globally
accessible binary called H H,
that runs the project's locally
installed hard hat and supports
shell auto completion for tasks.
So what we can do is we're going
to start with NPM, like this,
but we're gonna install it with
yarn, we're going to run yarn,
global, add hardhat shorthand.
And what this is going to do, we
can see here installed hard hat
shorthand with binaries H, H,
and Hardhead completion. Now
instead of running yarn,
Hardhead compile, which we can
still run, we can just run h h
compile, running h h is going to
be the same thing as if we had
just run the Hardhead command
for our local directory. So now
we need to actually have our
request random winner function
requests a random winner. So
let's go back to the
documentation. And we'll see how
to do that. We can look at this
function request random words
and see exactly how it works. On
the Vera of coordinator address.
We go ahead and call this
request random words function,
we're going to need to call this
function on the coordinator
contract to get the coordinator
contract. We're going to use the
Vera v2 coordinator interface
and the Vir of coordinator
address. So we're going to want
to keep track of those. We can
do that once again in Arkansas.
factor, we have the address
being passed to our Bureau of
consumer base. Let's also keep
it as a state variable for us.
First, let's get the interface
so we can interact with that
contract, we can import that
from chain link as well by doing
import at chain link slash
contracts, slash SRC slash fees
0.8, slash inter faces slash VRF
cord to mentor V to interface
dot Sol. And now that we import
this interface, same as we did
with price feeds, we can do VRF,
coordinator v2, interface VRF
coordinator. And then we can
save the sphere of coordinator
using the address so we can say
VRF coordinator equals this
address VRF coordinator veto.
And we're just going to wrap
that address around the
interface so that now we can
work with this VRF coordinator
contract. Now we're only going
to set our VRF coordinator one
time right in our constructor.
So what's the best thing that we
can do here, private, immutable,
you Gosh, darn. Right, let's do
private, immutable, you have
coordinator and we'll change the
name to I underscore the ref
coordinator so that we know that
your coordinator is indeed an
immutable variable. In order to
request the random word, we need
to give it a number of
parameters, I'm gonna go ahead
and copy this line into our
contract just so that we can
talk about exactly what's going
on with it. And we don't need
the AES Request ID. And instead
of coordinator we're going to do
I underscore fear of
coordinator. So we're going to
call request random words on
that VRF coordinator contract,
and we need to pass it the key
hash or the gasoline, I prefer
calling it the gas lane, we go
to the chain link, Doc's go to
contract addresses. And we
scroll down we can see different
gas lanes a different
configuration parameters for
different networks is key hash
is going to be the gasoline of
the key hash, which tells the
chain link node the maximum
price you're willing to pay for
your guests and way if for
example, gas prices skyrocket,
and it's going to cost you a ton
of money to get that random
number setting a ceiling, we'll
make it so that random number
doesn't come back. For us to
pick a gas lane, we're probably
going to want to have this gas
lane or this key hash stored
somewhere. So let's go ahead and
make that a parameter of our
constructor as well. And we'll
save that as a state variable.
So we'll do comma bytes 32,
gasoline or key hash or whatever
you want to call it. And then
we'll make a new state variable.
And we're only going to set this
once. So we'll make this a
private, immutable. I underscore
gasoline, and then we'll say
gasoline equals gasoline.
So now, we can just swap this
out, or I underscore gasoline.
Okay, what's next, we need a
subscription ID, the
subscription ID is going to be
the subscription that we need
for funding our requests.
There's actually a contract on
chain, which we can use to fund
any subscription for any of
these external data or external
computation bits. And in this
contract, there's a list of
these subscriptions for people
to make requests to. So we need
the ID of the subscription that
we're using to request our
random numbers and pay the link
Oracle gas, the subscription ID
is probably also going to be
something we're going to pass as
a parameter to our lottery. So
once again, let's scroll up to
our constructor, we'll add a new
parameter. And our subscription
ID actually doesn't need to be a
un 256, it can actually be a
little bit smaller with a un 64.
So we'll pass a un 64 sub
scription ID, we'll make a UNT
64. Since we're only going to
set this once we'll make this a
private, immutable. I underscore
sub scription ID down here and
we'll say I subscription ID
equals sub subscription ID.
Alright, awesome. So now we can
change this to our subscription
ID. Okay, what's next? Request
confirmations request
confirmations is a un 16, which
says how many confirmations the
chain link node should wait
before responding. So if you
make a request, and there's only
one block confirmation, maybe
you don't actually send it
because you don't you're afraid
of some type of blockchain
reorganization or something,
we're not going to worry too
much about this. And we're
actually just going to make this
a constant of three. So we're
not even going to have this be
per amortizable we're gonna have
this one be a constant. So we'll
say a you int 16 Private
constant request, confirmations
equals three, and we're using
the capslock and underscores for
our constant variables here. And
now we'll grab request
confirmations and stick it in
right here. What's next callback
gas limit callback gas limit is
going to be the limit for how
much gas to use for the callback
request your contracts fulfill
random words, this sets a limit
for how much computation are
fulfilled random words can be
this is a good way to protect
ourselves from spending way too
much gas. If, for example, we
accidentally code our contract
in a way where fulfill random
words is incredibly gas
expensive. It'll block the
random number from responding.
We are going to make this
parameter sizable because we
want to change it depending on
how we code our fulfill random
word. So in our constructor,
let's add one more, we'll add
you int 32. Since the size of
this is a un 32, callback, gas
limit, and we'll save the sub
top as a UNT 32, private,
immutable, I underscore call
back. Yes limit. And we'll save
this. I call back gas limit
equals call back Yes, limit. And
then we'll take this, and we'll
stick it here. All right, we got
one more number of words, this
is going to be how many random
numbers that we want to get, we
only want one. So we're gonna go
back up to the top, we're going
to create a you int 32. And
we'll make this also a private
constant. Num words equals one,
because we only want one random
number. And then that'll be the
last thing we need to add for
our IVF coordinator dot request
random words. Now this request
random words function returns a
request ID a un 256 Request ID a
unique ID that defines who's
requesting this and all this
other information. If we want to
save it, we can do u and 256.
Request ID IVF coordinator
requests random words. Now for
now, we are going to emit an
event with this request ID. And
we'll go over why we're going to
do that a little bit later,
create a new event at the top.
And we're not going to follow
the naming convention here.
Because we're going to change
the name of our functions a
little bit, we're going to call
this requested raffle winner.
And we're going to take a un 256
indexed Request ID. Down here,
we're gonna do omit requested
raffle winner Request ID. And
now we have a function that we
can use to request a random
winner using chain link VRF. Now
again, we're going to set this
up so that the chain link
keepers call this on an
interval, but we'll do that in a
little bit. For now, let's
figure out what to do once we
get that
random number. Once we get that
random number, we're going to
want to pick a random winner
from our array of players up
here. So what do we do? Well,
let's go in here. And let's pick
a random winner using something
called the module function. Now
we're gonna get an array back of
random words, or random numbers,
if you will, since we're only
requesting one random word, this
random words array is going to
be of size one with one random
word in it. Now this random word
is a un 256. So this random word
could be something like this.
Well, obviously without the
hyphens, but it could be
something absolutely massive
like that our players array is
only going to be so big. So how
do we get a random winner from
this potentially massive random
number, we can use something
called the modulo function, the
module operation, a mod N
yields, the remainder are after
the division of an operand a by
the blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah. So what does this mean?
Well, we can use the mod
function to get a random number
out of our players array. So
let's say our players array or
excuse me, our s players array
is of size 10. And a random
number is 200. So how do we pick
a random person out of this
players array, or, let's say our
random number is 202. If we do
202, which is our random number,
mod 10, we're gonna basically do
202 divided by 10. But instead
of having the decimals, we're
just going to say, Okay, how
many times is 10 evenly divide
into 202. And what's the
remainder, what doesn't divide
evenly into 202? Well, 20 times
10 equals 200, with two
leftover, so two doesn't evenly
divide, or multiply into 200. So
that means 202 mod 10 is going
to equal to two. So that's how
the module function works. And
we can use that so we're always
going to get a number between.
So we're always going to get a
number here between zero and
nine, which works out perfectly
because that which works out
perfectly, because those are the
indexes of the 10 people in our
array. So let's use that here.
We'll say a un 256 index of
winner is going to be equal to
random words, at index zero,
because we're only getting one
random word module, the S
underscore players dot length.
So this will give us the index
of our random winner to get that
address of the winner will do
address payable, recent winner
equals s players at this index
of winner so awesome. So now
we'll have the address of the
person that got this random
number, the person's that's
going to be our verifiably
random winner. Now, it might be
kind of cool to brag to people
that you're the recent winner.
So let's go ahead to the top and
we'll create a new state
variable for our most recent
winner make this state variable
in a new section called lottery
variables. We'll say address
private s underscore recent
winner and it'll start out as
nobody but as we get winners
update it with s recent winner
equals recent winner and we'll
probably want people to know who
this is winter is so down below,
we can do function get recent
winner, it's going to be a
public view that's going to
return that address. And then
we'll just say return s
underscore recent winner, since
again, the recent winner is
going to be a storage variable.
So now that we have a recent
winner, what else are we gonna
do? Well, we're probably going
to want to send them the money
in this contract. So we're going
to do exactly what we did before
with sending the money, we're
going to do that bull success,
comma, blank equals recent
winner, call, I'm gonna say
value, it's going to be address
of this dot balance, we're going
to send all the money in this
contract, and we're going to
pass it no data. And now we
could say require, you know,
success, whatever, we're going
to be a little bit more gas
efficient here. And we're just
gonna say, if not success, then
we're going to revert a new
transfer failed error. So we're
gonna go to the top, or say,
error name of the contract is
raffle, underscore, underscore,
transfer failed, like that, then
go back down, and we can now do
revert, raffle transfer failed
like that. And now that we've
picked a winner, right now, we
don't have a way to actually
keep track of the list of
previous winners. So we're just
going to omit an event. So
there's always going to be that
easily query double history of
event winners. So we're going to
create a new event in the events
section called the event winner
picked. And this is going to be
an address indexed winner. And
we'll scroll down and we'll do
MIT winner picked the address of
the recent winner. This looks
pretty good.
This looks pretty good here. Now
you'll notice our request ID as
this little underscore here and
saying, hey, it's an unused
function parameter, since we
don't use this, but we still
need fulfill random words to
take a request ID and a random
words array. But we don't use
Request ID, we can just comment
out just the request ID part
like this, this tells our
function, hey, yes, we know that
you need a un 256. But we're not
going to use the request ID. So
we'll leave it in here. But
we'll leave it blank. Now let's
run a little compile here. We'll
use yarn, hard hat, compile, or
hh compile, we'll see if we're
coding things correctly. And
indeed, we don't see any errors.
So perfect, we can continue. So
we've added the chain link VRF,
where we have a way to
verifiably get a random winner.
This is fantastic. Now let's
update this contract so that not
only can it pick a verifiable
winner, but it can also do this
all programmatically and
automatically trigger picking a
random winner based off of some
time interval without us having
to interact with it. And in a
decentralized context. In order
for us to automatically trigger
smart contracts based off of
some parameter be a time
parameter, maybe the price of
some asset is some number, maybe
there's a certain amount of
money in the liquidity pool or
really whatever trigger that you
want, we can use chain link
keepers. To do this. Steven
fluid has done once again, an
amazing introduction to chain
the keepers. So we're going to
follow along with another sub
video section of Steven
explaining chain link keeper
sauce, he's going to be using
the COVID test net, but be sure
to use whatever test net is in
the documentation. When you play
with this and you try this.
My name is Steven foon. Today, I
want to show you how to use the
chain link keeper network in
order to automate your contracts
and give them access to off
chain computation. Let's go
ahead and dive in. So what we're
going to look at today is we're
going to start on the chain link
documentation webpage. And if
you just scroll down a little
bit, you're going to find using
chain link keepers. Now there's
really two parts to building a
chain link keeper up kept smart
contract. So the first thing is
you need to write a smart
contract that's compatible by
implementing these two methods.
And then second, you want to
register that smart contract for
upkeep with the channeling
keeper network. So let's go
ahead and do both of those
things. So let's start off just
by copying and deploying this
sample code that we've got. With
this one click to remix, what
we're gonna see here is a very,
very simple contract. That is
just a simple counter. So we can
see it's got a counter here. So
it's got just a simple number.
And then you're able to specify
when you create the contract and
update interval, and then the
contract is going to verify Hey,
has enough time passed. And if
it has, let's update the
counter. And you're going to
notice that chinley compatible
or timekeeper network compatible
contracts use two really
important methods that are part
of this keeper compatible
interface. The first is check
upkeep, and check upkeep is
special because this is where
the off chain computation
happens. So this is a method
that's not actually run on
chain. This is run off chain by
a node from the channeling
keeper network. And so what's
really nice about this is that
the gas used here isn't actually
gas, it's on chains. This is
just being run by a chain link
node. And then what happens is
if your check upkeep method
returns, the upkeep is needed.
Then it's going to go ahead and
perform upkeep. On chain, so you
can actually generate data off
chain, and then pass that in.
That's called the check data.
And then that becomes the
performed data that's passed
into perform upkeep. And so the
PErforM upkeep method is where
you're going to want to verify
that things are correct. And
that things actually should be
modified and run on chain, and
then actually make the state
change. And so let's go ahead
and compile this contract and
deploy it to the COVID network.
So let's go ahead and within
remix, we can do this
compilation. And we're going to
compile and deploy directly to
COVID. So the zookeeper network
is currently as of the filming
of this, available on both COVID
as well as the theory of main
net. And let's go ahead and play
the counter contract. And let's
see what's not updating more
than every 30 seconds. And so
let's go ahead and deploy. So
meta masks can ask for a little
bit of payment, in order for me
to deploy this contract to the
COVID network. And it looks like
that is live. So now what I'm
going to do is I'm going to be
able to take this keeper
contract, and copy its address.
And now we're going to register
that contract for upkeep. So
we're going to jump over to the
application that powers the
champion keeper network, there's
a few different ways you can
use, you can interact directly
with the registry contract. But
there's a very, very nice
interface that lets you do this.
So let's go ahead and register a
new upkeep and it's giving me an
error that says you need to
connect your wallet. So let's go
ahead and do that. So I'm going
to just connect wallet here, and
I'm gonna give it access to my
account. And then from there, we
should actually be able to
register. So I'm going to use an
email address here. I'll give my
contract a simple name. I'll
paste in that address from the
deployed contract, and then I'll
give it a gas limit. And then
check data is this special thing
where you can actually register
multiple upkeeps On the same
contract in passing data to
specify how you want checkup
keep to be run of, we're just
going to ignore that that is an
optional one. And then we'll
give it a starting balance of
around 10 link, it's gonna go
ahead and use Metamask again to
register that transaction on the
network. And once it's
confirmed, my upkeep should be
registered with the network and
funded with 10 Link To kick
things off. Alright, if we go
ahead and view the upkeep, we
can see it's registered. And as
soon as the next round of the
keeper nodes executes, which
should be roughly about every
block, we should see that the
check upkeep method is going to
return that hey, upkeep is
actually needed because the
timestamp is more than 30
seconds ago. And then we should
go ahead and perform upkeep. So
as soon as I take a look at this
in remix, I can actually make
this bigger here, we're going to
be able to see from the methods
of the contract, if we check the
counter, it's going to start at
zero. And as soon as that 30
seconds has passed, we'll be
able to hit the counter again,
we'll see that the channeling
keeper network has performed
upkeep on my contract. Alright,
we just refresh and we see the
balance of the upkeep has been
decreased by about point 01
link. And we should also see
within our contract that our
counter has now updated via
proof that perform upkeep method
call. And now our counter is at
one showing us that our contract
is being approved by the
chainlink keeper network. And
everything is working exactly as
we expect. So as you can see, it
is very, very easy to create a
contract that is compatible with
the keeper network. And it's
very easy to register that
upkeep and start seeing that
your contract automation and
option computation are working
flawlessly.
Now that we've learned a little
bit more about how chainlink
keepers work if you want to take
some time to go through the
documentation and open up way
down below this open and remix
button. So you can actually work
with one of these and see these
in action for yourself on a test
net, feel free to do so we're
gonna be using a setup very
similar to this keepers counter
setup in the chain link
documentation. So now let's
update our code so that this
request random numbers
automatically happens using
chain link keepers. And if we
look at the example contract can
actually read more about what's
really important for this to
work. And we need a check upkeep
and a perform upkeep function in
our code. So instead of request
random winner, this is going to
be the PErforM upkeep that we're
going to change. But first let's
make this check upkeep checkup
keep function is basically going
to be checking to see is it time
for us to get a random number to
update the recent winner and to
send them all the funds. So
let's go ahead and make that
function. I'm going to add some
notes here, just so that it's
clear what's going on. And maybe
I'll even do natspec To tell
developers what's going on with
this function. So we're going to
create this function check
upkeep. And if we look at what
this needs, it needs to be
external override external
override. And if we see this
override keyword, this means
that okay, there's probably a
perform upkeep somewhere else.
And if we scroll to the top, and
we're going to import this
keeper compatible interface, so
that we make sure that we
implement both check upkeep and
perform upkeep in our code here.
If you want you can just import
keeper compatible in here or
just the keeper compatible
interface in our code. We're
going to do import at chain link
slash contracts slash SRC slash
V 0.8 point two interfaces slash
keeper compatible interface that
soul and now we're just gonna
say contract raffle is Veera of
consumer base V two and keeper
compatible interface and this
keeper compatible interface
inheritance just make sure that
we add checkup keep and perform
upkeep, which we're going to add
in a little bit. And if we look
back at the docs we can see
checkup keep takes a bytes
called Data check data as an
input parameter. So we'll do
bytes called data. Check data as
a parameter. Now this check
upkeep bytes call data allows us
to specify really anything that
we want when we call this check
upkeep function. Having this
check data be of type bytes
means that we can even specify
this to call other functions,
there's a lot of advanced things
you can do by just having an
input parameter as type of bytes
for us though, we're going to
keep it a little bit simple. And
we're actually not going to use
this check data piece. So
similar to how below we're not
using Request ID, we can just
comment it out. However, we
still need to make sure that
this parameter is type of bytes
called data. Now anyways, let's
go ahead and annotate this check
upkeep function, we'll say this
is the function that the chain
link keeper nodes call they look
for the to return true. Look
back at the documentation, we
can see that this check upkeep
returns both and upkeep needed
and to perform data, which
again, we're going to ignore
this upkeep needed is going to
be true or false. If it's true,
that means it's time to get a
new random number following
should be true in order to
return true. So in order for it
to be time to request a random
winner, what should happen, our
time interval should have
passed, which we haven't defined
yet. But we will lottery should
have at least one player and
have some eath. And then our
subscription is funded with Link
similar to how with channeling
Vir f your subscription needs to
be funded with Link, the same
thing needs to happen for check
upkeep and keepers to run your
subscription needs to be funded
with link. Now we're going to
add one more additional piece
here, we're going to say for the
lottery should be in an open
state, something that we want to
avoid when we're waiting for a
random number to return. And
when we've requested a random
winner. We're technically in
this weird limbo state where
we're waiting for a random
number to be returned. And we
really shouldn't allow any new
players to join. So what we
actually want to do is create
some state variable telling us
whether the lottery is open or
not. And while we're waiting for
our random number to get back,
we'll be in a closed or a
calculating state.
Now what we could do at the top
of our contract, we can just say
Boolean, private, s underscore
is open. And we can just set
this to true if we're open
otherwise false. Well, what if
we have a ton of different
states? What if we want it to be
like pending, open, closed,
calculating, etc? What do we
have a ton of different states?
Well, we could make this a U and
256. Private s underscore state.
And we could just keep track of
the state having like zero b
pending a one reopen to be
closed, three, be calculating,
etc. But this can be a little
tricky to keep track of. So a
better way to actually keep
track of all this in our code is
to use an enum enums, can be
used to create custom types with
a finite set of constant values.
So we can create, for example, a
state created locked inactive,
and it's basically a new type
for a smart contract for us,
we're going to create a new
type. And if we go back to the
layout of variables, and our
smart contract types should
actually be first thing in our
contract. So we're going to
create an E new called raffle
state. And for now, and we're
just going to have it be open,
we're just gonna have to be open
or calculating. Now when we
create an enum like this, we're
kind of secretly creating a un
256, where zero equals open, and
one equals calculating. However,
this is much more explicit that
we know what each one of these
numbers actually means. Now that
we've created this new type
called raffle state, we can
create a new lottery state
variable of type raffle state.
So the exact same way we declare
any other variable, we'll name
its type, which is going to be
raffle state. And this is going
to be a storage variable. So
we'll go ahead and do private s
underscore raffle state in our
constructor, right when we
launched this contract, we
should open up this raffle. So
we'll say s, raffle state equals
and we could use a un 256.
Wrapped in type raffle state
like so. Or we can be more
explicit and say raffle state
DOT open. Now we know that the
raffle state is in an open state
and we only want checkup keep to
work is if the lottery is
actually open. Additionally, we
probably only want people to be
able to enter if the law
battery's open. So let's go
ahead and create another if
statement and revert if the
lottery isn't open. So we can
say if s underscore raffle state
does not equal raffle state DOT
open, then we're going to revert
with a new error, we're going to
create raffle underscore
underscore, not open. And of
course, at the top will create
error, raffle not open. Now
additionally, let's go down when
we're requesting a random word.
Let's update the state to be
calculating so other people
can't jump in here. So right
above our VRF coordinator dot
request, random words will do s
underscore raffle state equals
raffle state DOT calculating so
that nobody can enter our
lottery and nobody can trigger a
new update. And then once we
fulfill after we pick our
winner, we'll say s raffle state
equals raffle state DOT open
again. Something else that we
forgot to do was after we pick a
winner from s players, we need
to reset our players array. So
let's add that in here as well
as players equals new address
payable. array of size zero. So
we'll reset the raffle state.
And we'll reset our players
array. Alright, great. So now
that we've learned about enum,
let's add it to our checkup keep
here, we're going to check these
four things. And if they all
pass checkup keys will be true
and will trigger the chain the
keepers to request a new random
winner. So first, we'll say bool
is open. It's going to be equal
to raffle state. That open
equals equals s underscore
raffle state. So you can think
of that as this boolean is open
is going to be true if raffle
state is in an open state, and
it will be false if raffle state
is in any other state. So great.
We haven't is open Boolean that
we can check later on. What else
do we need? Well, we need to
check to make sure our time
interval is past well, we don't
have a time interval yet. So
let's create a time interval. In
order to check the time we can
use another one a solidity is
globally available variables
with block dot timestamp block
that timestamp returns the
current timestamp of the
blockchain to get the current
timestamp, we're gonna need
block dot timestamp. But to get
if enough time has passed, we're
going to need to get the current
block dot timestamp minus the
last block timestamp, which we
don't have yet. Let's go ahead
and create a state variable to
keep track of the previous block
timestamp. So this is going to
be a new state variable that
we're going to make. I'm gonna
say u and 256. Private s
underscore last timestamp.
And right when we deploy this
contract, we'll update this with
the current timestamp s last
timestamp equals block dot
timestamp. Alright, awesome. Now
we have a last block timestamp.
But we're going to need to check
that the difference between the
current timestamp and the last
timestamp is greater than some
interval. So we also need to
create an interval. And this is
going to be some interval, this
is going to be some number in
seconds of how long we want to
wait between lottery runs. So
let's go ahead and add this to
our constructor as well. And do
a comma here. And we'll do u and
256. Interval. And we're going
to create another global
variable u and 256 Private s
underscore interval. And in our
constructor and we'll say s
interval equals interval. Now
interval isn't going to change
after we set it. So instead of
making a storage variable, let's
make it an immutable variable to
save some gas. Okay, perfect.
Now that we have all this, I'm
actually create a boolean to
check to see if enough time has
passed. So we'll say Boolean
time passed equals the current
block that timestamp minus s
underscore last timestamp. And
we should check to see that this
is actually greater than I
underscore interval. So we have
a Boolean check to see if we're
open. It'll be true if we're
open and we'll have a boolean to
see if enough time has passed.
This will be true if enough time
has passed. What else should we
check? While we should check to
see if we have enough players.
So we'll do Boolean has players
equals and we'll check to see if
s underscore players dot length
is greater than zero. If s
players dot length is greater
than zero as players will be
true, otherwise it'll be false.
And we'll also see if we have a
balance so we'll do Boolean has
balance equals address. This dot
balance is greater than zero.
Then finally, we're going to
take all these booleans and turn
them into the return variable
that we're looking for. We're
gonna say Boolean up keep
needed. Equals is open and time
passed. And as players and as
balance, like that, so all these
combined is gonna be this
Boolean upkeep needed. And if
this returns true, it's time to
request a new random number and
it's time to end the lottery. If
this is false, it's not time
yet, it's not time to end the
lottery up. Now again, if we go
to the chainlink, documentation
upkeep needed, actually needs to
return that Boolean upkeep
needed and some bytes memory
perform data. So we need to
update we need to update our
function here. And say returns
full upkeep needed, comma, bytes
memory, perform data star slash.
And since we've initialized
Boolean up, keep needed up here,
we don't need to say what type
of upkeep needed is down here.
Since this will automatically
get returned performed data is
something that we can use. If we
want to have checkup, keep do
some other stuff. Depending on
how this checkup keep went. We
don't really need it to do
anything else. So we can just
leave it as such. Right. So now
we have a check upkeep, we have
a way to check to see if it's
time to trigger picking our
random winner of our lottery
or our raffle. Now that we
learned how to actually do this
trigger, let's write the
function that gets executed
after this returns true. This is
going to be our perform upkeep
function, which we can see an
example again in the chainlink
documentation. Now when it's
time to pick a random winner,
actually, what we're going to do
is just we're just going to call
this request random winner
function. So instead of having
this extra function, let's just
transform our request random
winner function into this
perform upkeep. Since once check
upkeep returns true, the chain
link nodes will automatically
call this perform upkeep
function. So in function request
random winner, let's rename this
to perform upkeep. And we'll
have it take the input parameter
bytes called Data perform data
bytes, called data, perform
data. In our checkup, keep we
had to perform data, we would
automatically pass it to our
performance keep, we're not
going to pass anything to
perform upkeep, we can leave it
commented out like this. Since
perform upkeep is actually
identified in the keeper
compatible interface, this is
now going to have to override
that function. Now we want to do
a little bit of validation
before we continue here. Because
right now anybody can call our
perform upkeep function. So we
want to make sure that it only
gets called when checkup keep is
true. An easy way for us to do
that is to actually call our own
checkup, keep function. Now
right now, checkup keep it's an
external. So we actually can't
call our own checkup keep
function. So let's change it to
public so that even our own
smart contracts can call this
checkup keep function. Now that
we've made it public in perform
upkeep, we can call checkup,
keep passing nothing, and then
return the upkeep needed and
perform data which we don't
really care about. So we'll get
we'll get that ball up keep
needed. And then we don't care
about perform data. So we'll
leave that blank equals check up
keep. And we'll pass it a blank
called data. Now, we want to
make sure that this is true in
order to keep going with the
function. So we could write a
require here, but we're going to
do if not up keep needed, then
we're going to revert with a new
error that we create raffle.
upkeep not needed. And we're
going to pass some variables to
this error
so that whoever was running into
this bug can hopefully see why
they're getting this error. So
we'll pass the balance of this
contract just in case there's no
ether in here. We'll add the
players dot length, just in case
there's no players. And we'll
add a un 256 s underscore raffle
state. Make sure that the
raffles actually open. And then
of course, we'll need to create
this air at the top air, raffle
upkeep not needed, which is
going to take a un 256 current
balance un 256 non players and
you went to fit six raffle
state. Our code is starting to
look really professional. This
is awesome. Now something that
we forgot to do back in the
fulfill random words because we
actually forgot to reset
timestamp every time a winner is
picked. We want to reset the
timestamp as well so that we can
wait another interval and let
people participate in the
lottery for that interval. So
we'll scroll down into fulfill
random words. And right after we
reset players will also reset
the timestamp. Okay great and I
think we're just about done
here. Let's add a little bit of
natspec to make this look even
more professional and and give
people who are reading our
contract even more information.
So let's add title here at title
and we'll say a sample raffle
contract will say an author is
going to be me Patrick Collins
or you can put your own name
there as well at notice. This
contract is for creating and
untampered orrible decentralized
smart contract. And then we'll
do add Dev, this implements
chain link VRF v two, and chain
link keepers. Alright, awesome.
We've got our type declarations,
we've got our state variables,
we've got lottery variables,
which are still state variables,
we've got our events. Now it's
time for our functions.
Afterwards, we've done a little
bit of natspec, at least on our
check upkeep. If you want to add
some more natspec on things like
enter, raffle, perform upkeep,
etc, you can absolutely do so.
And then down at the bottom, we
have our views slash pure getter
functions. Let's see, do we want
any other getter functions here?
Well, we probably want to give
people the chance to get a
raffle state. So we'll do
function, get raffle state, this
will be a public, you returns a
raffle state. We'll say return s
underscore raffle state, we
probably want to give people the
chance to get the number of
words. And this is going to be a
little bit interesting here
running. So if we do function,
get num words, public view
returns, you went to the six
return num words, you'll see
something interesting happened
here. We pull up our compiler
and run hh compile. Hopefully
everything works here. Oh, and
everything doesn't work because
I didn't import this correctly.
Let's fix that. Let's try again.
Oh, there's a couple things I
missed. Let's fix es players.
This is why it's good to compile
as you code as players dot
length. Let's try again. And I
spelt interval wrong. I
underscore inter vol strike to
compile again, see how many more
spelling mistakes I made. And
there it is. I underscore in
error go to paste that and we do
get another error here. Invalid
type for argument in a function
call invalid implicit conversion
from literal string to bytes
called data requested. Since
we're passing this empty string
here. And checkup keep needs a
call data called data actually
doesn't work with strings. So we
need to make this bytes memory
instead. And our compiler is now
happy with us. And I spell it
the timestamp wrong. That's a
lowercase s so and you might see
some squiggles here on Check
upkeep, we could make this a
view function since we're not
actually modifying any state.
But I want to keep it public for
reasons I'll show you a little
bit later. But finally we get
the the yellow squiggly that I
was looking for here. And if we
run hh compile, we should see a
warning in our compiler as well.
Okay, so we see all those yellow
squigglies here. Unnamed return
variable can remain unassigned.
We need this bytes memory in
here because that's what the
keepers are looking for. Morning
function state mutability can be
restricted to view for our
function checkup key. You can
make a view if you want, but I'm
going to keep it public for
reasons I'll show you a little
bit later. And finally, function
state mutability can be
restricted to pure this is what
I wanted to show you since num
words is actually in the
bytecode, since it's a constant
variable technically isn't
reading from storage, and
therefore this can be a pure
function. Returning num words
doesn't actually read in
storage, it literally will go
and read the number one. So
doing get num words in solidity
with num words being a constant
variable, it's going to
literally be the exact same as
saying get one and we would
return one here, we might also
want to get the number of
players. So we'll create a
function get number of players.
And this will be a public view,
returns a un 256. Turn s
underscore players dot length.
We're also probably going to
want the latest timestamp. So
we'll do function get latest
timestamp. public view returns
you in 256. And we're just going
to return s underscore last
timestamp. And maybe we'll want
to do request confirmation. So
we'll do function GET request
confirmations. Public pure since
request confirmations is also a
constant function returns you
went to you went to 56 Turn
request confirmations. All
right, we've got some wonderful
getters here. Some views slash
pure functions, we have a way to
get a random number we have a
way in a decentralized context.
Automatic automatically execute.
picking a random winner we have
a way for people to enter our
raffle to enter this lottery.
And we have a bullet proof way
to solve creating a truly fair
decentralized lottery. Oh my
goodness. Let's do one more
compile for good measure H H
compile. And these are just
warnings. So we're good to go
here. Our code is compiling
successfully. Like I said
Normally, this definitely isn't
going to be the way that you're
going to write your smart
contracts, it's almost
impossible to write a full smart
contract without making any
mistakes. And without flipping
back and forth between
documentation, I have already
written this contract many times
myself, and I still made a whole
bunch of mistakes. So it is
totally reasonable and totally
rational for anybody and
everybody to make mistakes going
through this. And to use
resources and to write tests
along the way. Now that we have
our raffle dot Seoul created,
it's time to add everything
else. So we're going to come
over here, we're gonna create a
new folder, and add our deploy
folder per usual.
And we're going to do exactly
what we've already done a couple
of times, we're going to create
some scripts to deploy our
raffle contract. Now with our
raffle contract, there's a
couple of things in here that we
want to make note of first thing
is that our constructor right
now is absolutely massive. There
are a ton of parameters in here
that we need to account for.
Let's take a look at our
constructors and see if there's
any contracts that we're already
interacting with. Okay, VRF,
coordinator v2. This is a
contract address, entrance fee,
no gasline, no subscription ID
no callback, guestimate No, and
interval. No. So knowing that
this is an address should be a
tip that Ah, okay, we're
probably going to need to deploy
some mocks. For this, since
we're going to need to interact
with a VRF coordinator contract
that's outside of our project.
But let's go ahead and start
working on our raffle deployment
script first, and we know we're
going to have to deploy some
mocks. So we'll just keep that
in mind. So let's create a new
file. Oh, one, deploy raffle.js.
And let's get started deploying
our raffle contract. Now, this
is going to look really similar
to what we've done before. And
we're going to do it again here.
If you want to use your previous
deploy scripts as a reference, I
absolutely recommend you do so.
But let's get started with
module that exports equals an
async function. That's going to
take get named accounts and
deployments. As input
parameters, then we're going to
do const. Deploy log equals
deployments, then we're gonna
say const, Deployer, equals
await, get named accounts. Let's
go to our config and update
module that exports to to have
this I'm just going to copy
paste, so that employer is going
to be defaulted to account zero
and player is going to be
defaulted to account one, if you
want to go ahead and write this
out, feel free to pause and
write out your name accounts.
Right now, there's gonna be a
lot of boilerplate in our heart
hat.config.js. So feel free to
have the GitHub repo for this
lesson up with you or your
previous scripts that you've
already written as a reference
named accounts Deployer. And
we're also going to have a
player named account so that we
can separate different users or
different players who are
interacting with our contracts.
But for now, we're gonna grab
our Deployer. And we're gonna
get started. Now similar to last
time, we would just do const,
raffle equals await ploy,
raffle, comma, and then add all
of our stuff in here, right? So
this would be from Deployer.
args, we're going to have a ton
of args. So we're going to come
back to this. And then log is
going to be true. And then we're
going to have wait
confirmations, there's a little
bit more boilerplate we need to
work with here in our Hardhead
config, we don't have a network
here. So let's add our network
information. So we can get those
block confirmations will be
specific in here, as well. And
we'll say default network is
going to be hard hat. And then
we'll say
networks, and we'll add our
network information that's going
to be working with heart hub,
which has a chain ID of 31337
miles, we'll put that in here as
well. And block confirmations
were just set to one lot this
column here, we're also gonna be
running some staging tests on
the Rinkeby network. So we'll
add rink B in here with a chain
ID of four, block confirmations
of six, and we need to add a URL
and then also some accounts for
our URL. We've done this 100
times. We'll do const. rinky
dink could be RPC URL equals
process study and v dot rake,
the RPC URL, that's private key,
blah, blah, blah, we're going to
add all these same variables
from our last projects. So I'm
going to ask you to pause here
and just copy paste all those
variables from our last project.
Boom, like so since running
rink, prpc, URL, private key
corn market cap and ether scan,
we're also going to want to make
sure you folder, excuse me, new
file, dot env. And we're going
to drop all of our information
in here our rink, prpc, URL,
private key, ether scan API key,
and then our coin market cap API
key as well. Now that we have
our private key or ring prpc URL
down in URL, B RPC URL, and for
accounts, we're just going to
add that single private key. Now
for weight confirmations is
going to equal For network
config dot block con formations,
or one, we're gonna have to
import network from Hardhead,
which looks like my VS code
automatically did for me. Thanks
VS code. So this is how we're
going to deploy a raffle.
Obviously, we have a ton of
arguments that we need to
account for. So let's get to it.
Let's look at our raffle
constructor to see what we need
to get. Okay, well, the first
thing that we need to get via of
coordinator v2, we're gonna use
the same strategy we used in our
Funmi project with using mocks,
if we're on a development chain,
and using the actual contract
address if we're on a test net,
or a live network, so let's get
to it. So let's go ahead,
recreate that helper, hard hat
config dot j s and create that
const. Network. Config, say it
equals for hard hat, we're going
to use a mock. So we don't need
to put that in here for now. But
for rink B, let's go ahead, but
a foreign here, so the name is
going to be Rinkeby. And we're
going to need to go to the chain
link documentation, the VRF
contracts, and we're going to
need to grab the RF coordinator
for the Rinkeby. Test net, we're
going to grab this address here,
plop it in here, we'll say V RF
core did an eight tour v two,
bam, right like that. So back in
our deploy raffle, we're gonna
have to pick whether or not to
use the V RF coordinator v two
in the network config or some
mock that we deployed, which of
course, leads us to us having to
deploy a mock, let's create the
new file 00. Deploy marks.js. So
same thing module that exports
equals async function where it's
taking, get named accounts, and
deployments, as its input
variables from the heart at
runtime environment, or do const
deploy COMM A log equals
deployments. And then const,
Deployer equals await, get named
accounts, Excel, and then we're
going to grab the chain ID as
well as we're going to only
wants to deploy this on a
development chain. So we'll do
const chain ID equals network
dot config dot chain ID. Now
we're going to only want to
deploy mocks, if we're on a
development chain. So once
again, we're going to go to our
helper config, we're going to
add those development chains in
here. We'll say const,
development chains equals hard
hat, and localhost. And then
we're gonna want to export both
of these. So module, dot
exports, equals network config,
and development chance. Now in
our deploy mocks, we're gonna
want to grab those are saying
const development chains, equals
require dot dot slash helper
helper hardhat config. Now we
can check to see if development
chains dot includes the network
dot name that we're currently
on. If we're in a development
chain, we're gonna go ahead and
log local network, the
protected, deploying box. And
now we'll have to deploy a mock
VRF coordinator, where do we get
a mock VRF to coordinator Well,
let's go ahead and create one of
those.
We go to the chainlink. GitHub
again, we go to contracts. So C
0.8, actually have a mocks
folder with VF coordinator v2
Mach dot Sol, and we're just
going to use this as our mock.
So in our contracts folder,
we're gonna create a new file
called test new file called V RF
core, in a core, the two mock
dot Sol, and we're just going to
import this mock and have it be
our mock. So we'll do spdx.
We'll do pragma, solidity,
carrot zero, point 8.0, or seven
or whatever we want to do, we'll
do import at chainlink slash
contracts slash SRC slash v 0.8.
Slash, mocks, slash VRF. Pour
did a tour B to mock that soul.
And we'll just check to see if
it compiles with Hardhead
compile, and it looks like it's
compiling as well. Awesome. So
now that we have our mock
contract, we can actually go
ahead and deploy it. So we'll do
a weight loi, the RF core de ne
Tor V to Mach
comma, and then we'll give it
our parameters in here. We'll
say from Deployer. Log is going
to be true, and then we're going
to do our arguments. Now, what
are the arguments of this VRF
coordinator, v2 Mk. Well, if we
open the VRF coordinator v2
Mock, right in our VS code, or
on GitHub, we can actually see
We will roll over to the
constructor that it takes two
things. It takes a base fee and
a gas price link. What are these
first one? Well, the first one
is this const base fee. If we go
back to the documentation, we
can see that there's this
premium section of 0.25 Link
rink B, this means that for each
request, there's a base fee of
0.25 link for every request. So
anytime we want to request a
random number on Rinckey, it's
going to cost us 0.25. Link, or
you can think of it as 0.25
Oracle gas to make this request.
So back in our deploy mocks, we
can say base V equals, we could
resemble Rinckey here and do 25,
blah, blah, blah, or we could do
ethers dot utils dot parse eath,
of 0.25. And I'll even put a
little comment here, say 0.25 is
the premium, it costs 0.25 Link
per request. And remember, the
reason that this cost 0.25 Link
per request versus the price
feeds didn't cost anything is
because the price feeds. If we
look back at a chain that link,
each one of these price feeds is
being sponsored by a group of
protocols who are paying for all
these requests already, since
there isn't a sponsor for this,
we are the only ones requesting
the randomness, we get to be the
ones to actually sponsor getting
this random number, then the
second thing here is going to be
the gas price link. So let's
create another const here to
const. gas price link. But what
this is, is actually a
calculated value is a calculated
value based on the gas price of
the chain. Here's an example if
we were to request a random
number on Aetherium, and the
eath price skyrocketed up to
like to like a billion dollars,
gas would be incredibly,
incredibly expensive. Now when
chain link nodes respond chain
link nodes pay the gas fees, who
give us randomness, and do
external execution, the chain
link nodes are actually the ones
that pay the gas when returning
randomness or executing an
upkeep or etc. If we go to our
raffle dot soul, and scroll down
to perform upkeep, or fulfill
random words, it's actually the
chain link nodes that are
calling these two functions and
paying the gas for it, they get
paid in Oracle gas to offset
those costs. But if the price of
eath, or any native blockchain
skyrocketed the chain that nodes
itself to pay the gas fee. So
the chain link nodes have a
calculated price have a
calculated variable called the
gas price per link, which
fluctuates based off the price
of the actual chain, so that
they never go bankrupt.
Basically, the price of a
request changes based off the
price of gas for that
blockchain, you can kind of
think of this as the link per
gas, if you will, for now we can
kind of just set it to whatever
we want. And we'll just set it
to one e nine, which is going to
be equivalent to 1123456789. So
now that we have the base fee,
and the gas price link, we'll
grab this base fee, we'll have
these be the arguments for our
VR chord, enter V to mock, so
we'll say and actually we can
delete that will say const, args
equals base fee, and gas price
link, then we can take this args
variable and just plop it in
here. Now we can do log mocks
deployed, then we can do log
that a little line like this to
let people know that this deploy
script is done, then we'll just
do a module that exports dot
tags equals all and mocks. So
now that we have a view of
coordinator v2 Mock deployed,
we'll come back over to our
raffle and make some code around
it. Similar to what we just did
with our deploy mocks. We can
say if development chains that
includes network dot name, we'll
do some stuff. And we need to
import development chains from
our helper Hardhead config. And
we need to import network from
hard hat. My VS code
automatically added them Wow,
thanks VS code. Let's even just
do const args and make this
variable down here. Stick it in
args. Our first argument is
going to need to be this Vera fi
to coordinator so let's make a
variable we'll say let VRF core
need torby to address and if
we're on a development chain,
we're going to grab that mock
contract. So we'll say const
PRF, Cor de ATAR V to mock
equals await ethers dot get
contract, the RF cord the cord
to NATO Tor v two MK, and then
we can set the RF coordinator v
two address equals VRF core
denater V two mach dot
address. Cool. We have that
address here. Else if we're not
on a local network, the VRF v2
coordinator address is simply
going to be derived from our
network config. So let's import
the network config as well from
our helper Hardhead config and
we'll say else VRF coordinator
v2 address equals network config
of our chain ID. Let's which
actually sorry, we do need the