chain ID cons chain ID equals
network dot config dot chain ID,
chain ID of VR coordinator V to
chain ID. You're a coordinator
v2. Alright, perfect. We've got
the setup to work with our VRF
coordinator v2 address. What
else do we need from our raffle?
Well, we need an entrance fee,
we probably want to change the
entrance fee depending on what
chain we're on, we're on a more
expensive chain, we might want
to make this higher than others.
So let's go ahead back to our
helper Hardhead config and make
an entrance fee based off of the
blockchain, so for NP, maybe we
want to make it 0.01 eath. So we
could say ethers dot utils,
parse ether of 0.01. And once
again, thank you VS code for
automatically dropping that in
for me. And we're also going to
want an entrance fee for our
heart app, we can also set a
default in here, but let's just
be a little more explicit. So
we'll say 31337. The name of
this is Art app, we don't need
to give it a veneer of
coordinator v2 address because
we're going to deploy a mock.
But we do want an entrance fee.
And let's just give it the exact
same entrance fee here. So we'll
say ethers dot utils dot parse
ether 0.01 E. Alright, great. So
on our deploy here, we can just
say const entrance fee equals
network config. Chain ID of
entrance fee. Let's start
populating our arcs here. So the
first one is going to be your Fe
two coordinator address. Next
one is going to be our entrance
fee. Got it? Got it. Now we need
our gas lane. On Rigby and other
networks, there are different
gas lanes that we can choose
from, let's grab the only gas
Lane from Rinckey, the 30, gray
key hash, let's drop this, of
course into our network config
as gasoline, pop it in here,
we're hard hat, our mock
actually doesn't care what gas
line we're working on, because
we're going to be mocking the
gasoline anyways. So we can just
say gas lane, we can just go
ahead and use the same one or
really anything here, it doesn't
really matter. Now here we'll
say const, gasoline equals
network config.
Chain ID, gasoline, and we'll
grab the gas lane. And we'll
stick it into our argument
array, we've got this one, we've
got this one, we've got this
one. Now it's time for the
subscription ID. Now if you
haven't run through docstoc
chain link for the chain link
VRF, I highly recommend you do
so so that you can understand
what this subscription ID is we
know that we can actually make a
subscription ID using that front
end using that website VRF dot
chain dot link, which is great
and all but what if we're on all
local chains, we can get a
subscription ID no problem in
here. But it's a little bit
harder on a local network. Now
I'm actually going to teach you
how to create and fund
subscription it is completely
programmatically. So you don't
even need to use the UI if you
don't want to. However, for the
purpose of this course, we're
still going to use the user
interface, we're still going to
use that website for us to get
our own subscription IDs. But
you could 100% automate the
process of creating a
subscription ID and funding a
subscription ID. Because when
you create and fund subscription
IDs, you're just calling create
subscription and fund
subscription on that smart
contract. So on our development
chain, we have our V RF
coordinator v2 Mock, and what
we're going to do and on our
development chain, we're going
to create that subscription. So
we're gonna say const,
transaction, response equals
await VRF coordinator v2 Mock
dot create sub scription. And
then we'll run const transaction
receipt equals weight trends
action response, dot Wait, wait
one block confirmation. And
inside this transaction receipt,
there's actually an event that's
emitted with our subscription
that we can get this is another
place where emitting events is
incredibly helpful. So in fact,
if we open back up a Vera v2
coordinator mark, and we look
for create subscription, we see
we emit subscription created
with the subscription ID, we can
actually get this event emitted
from our transaction receipt.
Now to assign it, let's go ahead
and create a sub subscription ID
up here. And then we'll say
subscription ID equals
transaction receipt that events
of zero dot args dot sub ID. And
again, be sure to watch that
events video if you want to
learn more about how to work
with events in hardware. Now
that we have a subscription, we
need to fund the subscription on
a real network, you'd need the
link token to actually fund the
subscription. The current
iteration of the mock allows you
to fund a subscription without
the link token. So what we can
do is we can just run a wait
your F corps inator Mark, if
coordinator B to Mach dot fund
subscription, and we'll give it
the subscription ID and we'll
need to do some fundamental
this, we can just create some
variable, we'll say const VRF,
subscription fund amount equals
ethers dot utils, dot parse
ether, of, we'll say 30 VRF
subscription, fundament. We'll
just paste that down here. We
could do this as well for a real
test net or live networks. But
just so that we become familiar
with the user interface, we're
not going to do a test net
programmatically. And for a test
net, we're just going to use
exactly what we've been doing so
far. Or we can put a
subscription ID and our helper
config. So we'll say
subscription ID, we'll put
something in here right now,
we'll just leave it as zero. But
later on, when we actually
create a subscription, we'll
update our subscription ID. And
so we'll say subscription ID
equals network config. Change ID
of subscription ID. Perfect. Now
we can add this to our arguments
array. What else do we need
subscription ID, we need a
callback gas limit or callback,
gas limit is going to vary
network to network. So once
again, we're gonna go into our
helper configure callback gas
limit. And for us, we'll set a
pretty high limit of 500,000
gas. So we'll say call a gas
limit of 5.123 500,000. Gas. And
for hard hat, we'll do the same
thing. So we can say const,
callback, gas limit equals
network config, chain ID,
callback, gas limit, grab this,
put it into our argument array.
What else do we need? All we
need now is the interval. So we
can change this network to
network as well. Rigby will say,
interval will ever just be 30
seconds for both hard hat and
for Rigby. So we'll do the same
thing here. Say const.
Interval equals network config.
Chain ID, interval, and we'll
grab this, pop it in the end of
our array. All right, awesome.
Now we have an argument array
and drop it right in here and
perfect. Everything in our
constructor for our raffle
contract. Great. This is looking
fantastic. We've got wait
confirmations we got logging
arguments Deployer. Okay, well,
what next? Well, let's go ahead
and add that verification piece.
So once again, create a new
folder utils, new file
verify.js. We can either copy
paste this from our last
project, or we can grab this
from the GitHub repo associated
with this course, once we have
our verify script in here, we're
going to import it by saying
const. Verify equals require dot
dot slash helper Hardhead
config. And then we can add that
same bit of code down here to
verify our contract, we'll say
if we're not on a development
chain. And we have process
studying v dot ether scan API
key, then we're going to log
verifying dot dot and then await
verify raffle dot address and
the arcs. Now we'll just do a
log of a whole bunch of hyphens
say that this script is done
module dot exports dot tags
equals say this will be all and
raffle. All right, so let's test
this out. We'll do hardhat
deploy, or yarn, hard hat deploy
and see if this script works
correctly. Looks like we ran
into an error network config not
defined. So let's spell this
right. Network config. There we
go. And that looks much better.
Let's try this again. It looks
like our deploy scripts are
working well. local networks
protected, deploying mocks
deployed VRF coordinator v2 Mock
mocks deployed and then we went
ahead and deployed our raffle.
Awesome, this is massive. Now
we're not going to test the
deploying this to a test net
quite yet, because well, we
don't have any unit tests yet.
We need to write unit tests
before we want to ever test
running this on a test net. So
we have our deploy script, we
have our contracts, that means
it's time for us to write some
tests. We'll come over here
we'll create a new folder called
test. And for now, we'll just
make our unit tests. So unit
tests, and in here we create a
new file called raffle.test.js.
And let's write some unit tests.
Now for these unit tests, we are
going to be a little bit verbose
here, we're going to make our
coverage really, really good
here. It's not gonna be perfect,
but this is going to be pretty
verbose. So I'm gonna go pretty
quickly here. So you can feel
free to pause, slow me down,
speed me up whatever you need to
learn this section. It is really
good muscle memory to go through
writing these tests and
understand what you should be
thinking about when you're
writing these tests. So feel
free to speed up the parts You
already know and slow down the
new parts. Because we are going
to go over some new information
here. writing tests may seem
like a tedious process. But I
promise as you get better at
writing these tests, you'll
realize that these are the
things that you can rely on when
stuff doesn't work. And when
you're not sure how to code,
something, getting this muscle
memory down, writing these tests
is going to make you a fantastic
engineer. So let's go through
and we'll write some of these
verbose tests here to try to
make this really good and have
this have really good coverage.
And if you want to go back later
on, and see if you can give it
even more coverage, and even
better tests, please feel free
to do so. But let's get started.
Let's write some tests. So we're
going to start out pretty much
the same way we've been starting
everything out, we're going to
grab our development chains, so
that we only run our unit tests
on a development chain. So we'll
do const development chains,
equals require dot dot slash dot
dot slash helper, RD, hard hat
config, and then we'll say not
development chains, that
includes network dot name, and
describe that skip. Otherwise,
we'll do describe, so this first
describe is going to be our
raffle unit tests. And this is
going to be an async. function.
So raffle unit tests so that it
comes on the next line, it looks
a little bit better. Alright,
great. Now, what are some of the
main things that we're going to
need to deploy? Well, we're
gonna need to deploy a raffle,
we're probably going to want a
VRF core to a tour be to mock
graded before each, that's going
to be an async function, where
we go ahead and we get these
will say const. Employer equals
await, get named accounts.
So we're gonna need to import
get named accounts or require
get name accounts from hard hat,
then we're going to want to
deploy these using our fixtures.
So we can say await deployments.
And then we're going to import
deployments as well from hardhat
dot fixture, and we're going to
call all, we're going to deploy
everything. And again, if we
look at our one, our raffle has
the alt tag, and our Oh, our
mocks also have the alt tag,
okay, perfect. Once we deploy
everything, we can say raffle
equals await ethers dot get to
contract. And we got to import
ethers from hard hat, like so.
And we'll say it will get the
raffle contract and we'll
connect it to our Deployer. And
then we're going to do the same
thing with VRF coordinator v2
Mock equals await ethers dot get
contract, the RF coordinator, B
to MK connect this to deployer
as well. Alright, great, our
first set of tests describe,
they're going to be the
constructor. And this is going
to be an async function. And
let's do this. Let's create an
IT initial initializes the
raffle correctly, this is going
to be an async function. Now I
just want to make a note,
because ideally, we make our
tests have just one assert, or
it just keep that in mind is
that ideally, we want to have
just one assert for it. But
we're going to have a bunch
because like I said, we're being
a little bit loose here. So we
want to just make sure that our
raffle is initialized correctly.
So we'll say const raffle state,
and we'll get that raffle state
because we want to make sure
that we start in an open raffle
state. So we'll say const,
raffle state equals await raffle
dot get raffle state. And then
we want to say assert dot equal
ope and then we need to import
assert from Chai. So assert
equals require Chai assert dot
equal raffle state.to string
because again, raffle state is
going to be a big number. And
even though a raffle state is of
type raffle state, it'll return
a zero if it's open and a one if
it's calculating. So this gets
transformed just into a un 256.
When we call it like this, a
raffle state variable here will
be a big number. So we want to
just to string a file. So assert
dot equal raffle state DOT two
string zero. We'll also make
sure our interval gets set
correctly. So we'll do const
interval equals await raffle dot
get interval. And I don't know
if we have one of those it's
actually C inter ball see if we
have one of those. We don't have
a good interval let's go ahead
and add again interval function
so we'll do function get in
trouble. We have public view
returns you went to six return I
underscore interval will have
good interval will say raffle
dot get interval and will also
say assert dot equal interval.to
string. It should equal one Ever
is in our helper config, right?
Because we're using the interval
and helper config. So we say
interval.to string should equal.
So we'll import that as well.
Network config. And we'll say
the interval should equal
network config. Of let's also
make, get our chain ID up here,
chain ID, say const. Chain ID
equals network dot config, a
chain ID, network config of the
chain ID of interval. Alright,
cool. So let's test this so far,
HH test or yarn, hard hat test.
And cool looks like it passed.
And we have our little gas
output here. Awesome. Let's go
to our Hardhead config, just so
that it doesn't always print out
at gas, but there for now. So
I'm going to copy paste the gas
reporter section from our last
project, like so. And we're
going to have enabled gas be
false for now. So now if we run
a Hardhead test, again, we
shouldn't have that gas bid
printed out, we should just see
the tests and perfect, that's
what we see. And our constructor
test passes. Yay, what's next,
got our constructor. And we
probably could have written more
tests for the rest of these. But
let's just move on. Alright,
enter raffle, that's going to be
our next describe block. So it
will do describe,
enter, raffle. And this is going
to be an async function. And
we'll say it reverts when you
don't pay enough, right, because
one of the first things that we
check is that they're paying
enough. So we want to make sure
that this actually reverts if
they don't pay enough. So this
will be an async function. Where
we're going to do that same
expect await thing. So we're
going to import expect from
Chai, which comes from those
waffle matchers. And we're gonna
say await, expect raffle dot
enter a raffle. And we're not
going to pass any value here,
we're going to expect it to dot
b dot reverted with. And if we
look here, we want it to be
reverted with this raffle not
enough eath entered. So we can
put that in quotes raffle not
enough eath entered. Now we can
try this out. Make sure that it
actually works. Ah ah test dash
dash grep. Put this in quotes
that you don't pay enough. And
awesome. We're passing there.
What else do we want to test?
Well, we want to test that if
the raffle isn't open, we also
revert but we'll test that in a
little bit. As we kind of test
the rest of the functionality.
We want to see that it records
players when they enter. So this
will be an async function. And
now we'll enter the raffle.
First we're going to need that
raffle entrance fee. Let's go
ahead and save that at the top.
So we'll say let raffle VRF
coordinator be to mock raffle
entrance fee and then our before
each will say raffle entrance
fee equals a weight ethers dot
get entrance fee. This should be
raffle dot get entrance fee. So
now we have this raffle entrance
fee, you can use it to enter the
raffle we'll say a weight raffle
dot enter raffle with a value of
raffle entrance fee. And we can
make sure that our Deployer here
has been correctly recorded. So
since right now we're connected
to the Deployer. We'll just make
sure that that deployer actually
is in our contract. So we'll say
const player from contract
equals await raffle dot get
player of zero, because we
record them in our players array
and we have our get players
function which pulls them out.
And then we'll say assert dot
equal player, player from
contract should be the Deployer.
So now we can grep for this in
our hard head test. Make sure
this works. HH test dash dash
grep. Deployer is not defined.
We've got it up here. But we
actually didn't save it
globally. So we got to do let
common Deployer. And we'll say
deployer equals await get named
accounts. And we'll wrap it like
this to get the deployer
Awesome. Let's try this again.
And awesome. What else should
this do? Well, it's also
emitting an event. So let's make
sure it emits an event. So we'll
say it emits event on enter.
This will be an async function
as well. And this will be the
first time that we're testing to
make sure a function emits an
event and the syntax is going to
look really similar to what we
test for when we check to see if
an error is fired. So we're
gonna say await expect raffle
dot enter raffle with value of
raffle entrance fee dot two dot
omit and this.to dot emit we get
from During woful, these chime
matches for emitting events we
can do a wait expect to emit,
and then the event that we're
expecting to emit. So we're
saying to omit the raffle
contract to emit a raffle enter
event. We can copy this, try to
test this in our terminal. So
we'll say hard hat. Test dash
dash grep. Just put this in
quotes. And that passes as well.
Great. Let's now go ahead and
test to make sure that we can't
enter the raffle whenever this
raffle is not open or it's
calculating. So we'll say it
doesn't allow entrance, when
raffle is Cal cumulating. And
this will be an async function.
And first we'll enter will say
await raffle dot enter raffle
value is raffle entrance fee.
Now what we want to do we want
to get this raffle into a closed
state. So we want to get it out
of its open state. Well, how do
we move this raffle from raffle
dot open to raffle dot closed in
perform upkeep, remove the
raffle from raffle that open to
raffle dot calculating but
perform upkeep can only be
called if check upkeep returns
true. Otherwise, it'll revert
with raffle upkeep not needed.
So what we need to do is we need
to make check upkeep return
true. And we will pretend to be
the channeling keeper network to
keep calling checkup keep
waiting for it to be true. And
once we make it true, then we'll
pretend to be the channeling
keepers and call perform upkeep
to put this contract in a state
of calculating. Now how do we
actually do that? Well, in order
for checkup keep to be true, we
first need to see that we are
indeed open, which we are. The
next thing that we need to do
though, is we need to do this
time passed bit. We need to
actually wait that 30 seconds
for time to pass. Now, that kind
of sounds awful. Do we have to
wait 30 seconds for all of our
tests? What if our interval was
10 days when we have to wait 10
days to run our tests? It sounds
ridiculous. Well, hard hat
actually comes built in with a
ton of functions for us to
manipulate our blockchain to do
literally whatever we want it to
do. In the hard hat
documentation. There's a section
called Hard Hat Network
reference inside the Hard Hat
Network section. And in here,
there's a ton of information
about how the hard hat network
actually works and different
configs that we can do with it.
If we scroll down low enough, we
can see the JSON RPC methods
that we can use on this
blockchain, we can do eath
accounts block number call
chinetti. We can do all these
RPC methods that a normal
blockchain has. Additionally, we
can do even more than that, we
can use these things called Hard
Hat Network methods. Since this
is our local Hard Hat Network.
And we're using this for
testing, we want to be able to
test any scenario. And it's
these methods that give us the
ability to do that, you can go
through this and play around and
see all the different things you
can do. One of them in
particular is going to be set
storage set where you can set
storage at any place, which is
really fun. But some of the
special testing debugging
methods are going to be EVM
increase time, and EVM. Mine
increased time allows us to
automatically increase the time
of our blockchain and EVM. Mine
allows us to mine or create new
blocks, because if we increase
the time, it doesn't do anything
unless there's a new block
mined. So what we can do is we
can run a wait network, and
we'll import network from Hard
Hat Network await network dot
provider that send EVM in crease
time, comma, we can send a list
of parameters to send with it,
which for us are just going to
be our interval.to number. And
then we'll do plus one. Now
right now, our interval isn't
stored globally, so we're
probably going to want to do
that. So let's go ahead and do
interval. And then in our before
each, we'll do interval equals
await, raffle dot raffle dot get
interval, I'm just going to copy
this and we're going to delete
this whole line. Wait raffle dot
get interval. Since now we're
just going to call it interval
at a global level, since we're
going to use it a lot. Now we're
gonna say interval that to
number plus one. So we want to
increase the time by whatever
our interval is to make sure
that we can actually get that
checkup keep to return true. So
additionally, we're going to
want to do a weight network dot
provider. Dot send EVM mine with
an empty array just because we
just want to mine it one extra
block. You can also do network
dot provider that request with
an await here, these two would
be basically the same, but this
one's a little quicker, right?
So we've increased the time of
our blockchain. We've mined a
block to move forward. It should
be open time has passed. Do we
have a player? We do indeed,
because we've entered the
raffle. We should have a balance
because we've entered the right
Apple, check upkeep should now
return true. So we should be
able to call perform upkeep and
pretend to be a chain lock
keeper. So we're going to
pretend to be a chain the keeper
and call await raffle dot
perform upkeep. And we're going
to pass this some empty call
data just by passing a blank
array like that. And now this
should be in a calculating
state. So now that it's in a
calculating state, we can say
our enter raffle reverts
correctly if the raffle isn't
open. So now we'll say await,
expect raffle dot enter, raffle.
And we'll send it value of
raffle entrance fee. We're
expecting this.to dot b dot
reverted with that raffle
underscore underscore not open
error. Okay, let's try just this
in our tests now. So we'll run
Hardhead test dash dash grep.
Put this in quotes. And perfect
that passes as well.
Now if we run Hardhead test,
let's just test everything
together right now. And
everything is passing. Oh, this
is wonderful. Awesome. Let's
keep it going. And if we run
Hardhead coverage, we'll see our
coverage is bumping up, we are
already drastically better than
where we were before. Let's keep
going well, let's go ahead and
test our check upkeep now. So
we'll do describe, check upkeep.
And this will be an async
function,
where we'll say it returns
false. If people have been sent
an E, E, it's been a sync
function.
So we'll have everything in here
be true except for the fact that
nobody's entered yet. So we'll
do a weight network dot provider
dot send EVM increase time,
comma interval.to number plus
one
will do a weight network dot
provider. That send UVM mine. No
parameters. Now we're going to
call check upkeep. Now here's
the thing, check. upkeep is a
public function.
So if we just run await, raffle
dot check upkeep, and we pass
nothing in this is going to kick
off a transaction, because hard
had knows Oh, okay, it's a
public function, they're clearly
trying to send a transaction
here. If this was a public view
function, it wouldn't, it would
return that view. But the thing
is, I don't really want to send
a transaction. But I want to
simulate sending this
transaction and seeing what this
upkeep needed would return.
Well, I can actually get that by
using something called call
static, I can simulate calling
this transaction and seeing what
it will respond. So instead of
raffle dot, check upkeep, I can
do raffle dot cost static, that
check upkeep. And this will give
me the return of upkeep needed
and the bytes perform data, I
can extrapolate just the upkeep
needed out of this return or
writing const upkeep needed
equals this, and then I can do
assert not upkeep needed,
because right now upkeep needed
to return false. So we'll say
assert, not false, which is
true. If upkeep needed was true,
then this would be false. And
this would break. So that's what
we want to do. So let's go
ahead, we'll run this, see if it
worked. Our hat test, dash dash
grep. And we're in passing, we
are in business. Awesome. So
this is working perfectly. Well,
and let's also test that it
returns false. If raffle isn't
open. This will be an async
function. And we'll do
everything except and we'll do
everything in here. But we'll
make the raffle in the
calculating state. So do a
weight, raffle dot enter, raffle
value, raffle entrance fee await
network dot provider that send
and I'm just going to copy these
two lines here. Because we're
going to go ahead and do those.
We're also going to do a weight,
raffle dot perform upkeep. And
another way to send a blank
bytes object is to do a string
like 0x hardhat is smart enough
to know that this should be
transformed into just kind of a
blank bytes object. So either
one of these should work. Now
we're do const, raffle state
equals await, raffle dot get
raffle state and we'll Get
upkeep needed. So we'll say
const. upkeep needed, we'll do
exactly what we did above raffle
dot call static dot check
upkeep. Let's say excuse me a
weight, raffle dot call static.
Now we can do assert dot equal,
say raffle state is going to be,
or excuse me raffle state.to
string, it's going to be
calculating, and I started dot
equal upkeep needed, it's going
to be false. Let's run a GREP on
that. And perfect. That's also
working correctly. Great. Now
I'm going to skip over these
next two tests, because we
haven't really learned anything
from them. So I'm just going to
copy paste them from the GitHub,
we're going to return false if
enough time hasn't passed. And
we're going to return true. If
enough time has passed, we have
players Eve and is open. So
we're just asserting true down
here. And we're starting not
true up here, you want to pause
the video and copy paste these
and write these out, you
absolutely can copy paste them
from the GitHub repo, you
absolutely can't like I said,
going through this and making
yourself write these and making
yourself understand these tests
is going to make you a
substantially better coder. And
let's just test that it all
looks good with hh test. Now, as
I was recording this, I just
realized that for all of our
describe blocks, I've been
making them async functions
describe blocks actually don't
realize and can't recognize and
can't work with promises. So
having the be async actually
doesn't do anything. So in your
describe block, we want to get
rid of the async word because
it's actually not helping us at
all. In fact, it's just an extra
word, and it looks kind of
gross. So now all of our
describe blocks, we're gonna get
rid of that async keyword, and
just have them be functions. Of
course, all of our it's, though,
are going to be using
asynchronous functions, which is
what we want. So we've written
some tests for a checkup keep.
Now let's go ahead to perform
upkeep.
Let's create a new describe,
block, ascribe or perform
upkeep. This is going to be a
regular function. And in here,
we're going to start and say it
can only run if check upkeep is
true. And this will be an async
function. Because we only want
to perform keep to work if
checkup keep is indeed true. So
we'll say await raffle dot
enter. raffle we'll send it some
value, raffle entrance fee, I'm
sorry, there should be curly
braces instead. And we'll do a
weight network dot provider that
send EVM increase time inter
vol.to number plus one await
network dot provider that send
UVM mine an empty array there to
the reason that we're moving
time forward and moving our
block forward, of course is
gonna be the same thing as
above, we want our check upkeep
to return true. And then we're
gonna say const X or transaction
equals await raffel dot perform
upkeep. We can either do a blank
array, or we could do 0x Doesn't
matter. And we can assert the X.
Now if TX doesn't work, or this
error is out or something, this
will fail. Right. So that's how
we know that this actually can
work. So let's test this out. We
want this only to work if
checkup keep is true. And we
made checkup keep true by all
the stuff that we did above. So
now we'll do yarn hardhat test
dash dash grep with our IT block
here. And I spelled perform
upkeep wrong perform upkeep.
Let's try spelling things
correctly. And let's run that
test again. And great. That's
working. I will What else do we
want to do? We want it to revert
with raffel. upkeep not needed
if checkup keep is false. So in
here we're gonna say it reverts.
When check up keep is false.
This will be an async function.
And we're going to do that same
syntax await expect raffle dot
perform upkeep empty bytes
object that to.be reverted with.
And what do we want it to be
reverted with? Or hoping it's
reverted with this with that, we
can run this test here Hardhead
test dash dash grep paste that
in. And we see that is indeed
passing now something that
you'll notice here is that our
revert actually goes ahead and
reverts with all this extra
stuff as well. Our test is smart
enough to know that if all we do
is put the name of the error
that is getting reverted with
then it's good enough. If we
want to be super specific, we
can actually go ahead and make
this a string interpolation and
add all of these in here. So we
can add the balance that we
expect we can add the players
that we expect. And we can add
the raffle statement for now
we're just going to keep it as
we're expecting this but if you
want to be super specific you
can have your tests expect for
exactly the specific values that
you're looking for. But alright,
what is the last thing we should
expect form? Well, we should
check to see that this actually
gets called the raffle state
gets changed. And we admit this
event. So let's go ahead and add
that. We'll say it updates the
raffle state admits an event and
calls the VRF coordinator to be
an async function as well. Let's
do this. So let's go ahead and
let's make checkup keep true,
I'm just going to copy paste
these first three lines, since
it's going to be exactly the
same. We're going to enter the
raffle we're going to increase
the time we're going to mind a
new block, then we're going to
call perform upkeep. So we're
going to say const, TX response
equals await raffle dot perform
upkeep with an empty bytes
object, and we're going to do
const TX receipt equals await TX
response dot wait for one block.
From this receipt, we're gonna
get the request ID, we're gonna
say const Request ID equals, we
can get the request ID. From
this omitted event. However, we
should look at our VRF
coordinator mock again, when we
call request random words, both
in the mock and then in the
actual contract, you'll notice
that it also emits an event with
random words requested. And if
you look in here, the second
parameter that it has is indeed
the request ID. So in reality,
US omitting the request ID is
redundant, we can just use the
admitted Request ID from the VRF
coordinator for the purpose of
this course and showing you what
an event looks like. We're going
to leave it in there. But if you
want to go back and refactor
this, you would definitely want
to remove this omit. But for
this test, let's do TX receipt
dot events. And this is going to
be the first event instead of
the zero with event because
before this event gets emitted,
this function is going to emit
an event. So instead of the zero
with event, this is the first
event that gets emitted after
this one. So tax receipts dot
events of one dot args dot
request, ID, and then we're
gonna say cert request id.to
number is greater than zero. And
then we'll also assert that the
raffle state equals equals one.
So we're gonna do const, raffle
state equals await, raffle dot
get raffle state. And this
should actually be raffle
state.to Number, or to string
and then you know, do whatever
we want to do. And this is a
very big it, but we're going to
copy the whole thing anyways. HH
test, dash dash grep, paste that
in there, we run it, excuse
me.to string equals equals one,
transformer time and perfect, we
are passing Great, now it's time
for fulfill random words. And
this is where we're going to
learn a lot of fantastic stuff
here. So we're gonna make a new
describe block zoomed out a
little bit here. And this is
going to be our fulfill random
words. It's going to be a
function, of course. And in
here, we're actually going to
add another before each want to
have somebody have entered the
raffle before we run any tests
in here. So we're going to do a
before each, which will be an
async. function. And we're just
going to run await, raffle that
enter raffle with a value of
raffle entrance fee. And then
we're going to do a wait network
dot provider dot send EVM
increase time of interval, that
to number plus one, and then a
wait network dot provider dot
send EVM mine. Comma. Before
we've tried to do any testing of
or fulfilled random words, we're
gonna have somebody enter the
lottery. And we're going to have
increased the time and mined a
new block. Okay, cool. So the
first thing we want to do is
want to see that fulfill random
words can only be called so long
as there's a request in flight,
so long as there's a requested
as long as request random words
has been called. So we can
actually check that by running
it can only be called after
perform. This will be an async
function. And in here, we're
going to revert on some requests
that don't exist. So we'll do
await, expect the RF core didn't
a tour be to mock dot fulfill
random words. And if we look at
our V RF, coordinator v2 Mark in
here has the fulfill random
words function, which is what
the chain link node actually
calls and inside Add this
function in the actual contract
calls another contract that does
the random number verification.
So we're basically checking this
part right here. If the request
doesn't exist, we're going to
get this non existent request
here. And as you can see, it
needs a request ID and a
consumer address. So we're going
to guess zero. And the consumer
addresses, of course, it's gonna
be raffled out at address, we're
going to expect this to be
reverted, with non existent
request. And then we're going to
do this exact same thing with a
different Request ID or request
ID one. And hopefully, we're
also going to get non existent
requests. Now ideally, no
request here would ever allow
this fulfill random words to go
through. Now, it obviously would
be really hard for us to test
every single possible Request
ID, we're going to see a way in
the future to actually test for
a ton of these variables with
something called fuzz testing.
But we'll get to that in the
future. And I spelt the scribe
wrong, let's let's actually
spelled the scribe correctly, go
ahead and run this hh test dash
dash grep.
And great it passed. Now I'm
going to make just one more test
here, that's gonna be way too
big. But right now the test that
we're about to write is going to
be it's going to be a really big
test. And we probably want to
split it up into different
sections, but actually figured
that this was actually the best
way to show this section. And
it's going to be exactly what
we're going to do. When we get
to our staging test, we're going
to write this test literally
almost exactly the same. So
let's write it, this is
basically going to be the test
that puts everything together.
So we're going to test that this
indeed, so winner resets the
lottery, and sends money, which
is kind of a lot for a single
it, we probably would want to
split those into their own
pieces. But for this, we're just
going to put them all into one,
and it's going to be an async
function. Now we are going to
learn a couple of new tricks
here. So definitely be sure to
follow along. Now for this one,
we're also going to add in some
additional entrances additional
people who are entering this
lottery. So we'll say const,
additional, and trance equals
great. We're gonna have some
more of those fake accounts from
ethers enter our lottery here.
So we're gonna say const.
Starting account, index equals
to, since deployer equals zero,
excuse me equals one, since the
player is zero, so we're going
to have new accounts start from
index one. And we're going to do
a little for loop or let i
equals starting count index, i
is less than the starting count,
index, plus additional and trend
sees there's gonna be entrance.
i plus plus, we're gonna do a
little loop and connect our
raffle contract to these new
accounts. And then we're going
to have these new accounts,
enter our raffle contest. Count,
connected raffle equals raffle
dot connect accounts of i and do
we have accounts defined
somewhere we don't. So let's get
accounts to find somewhere.
We'll say const accounts equals
await ethers dot get signers.
And then we're going to do a
weight account connected raffle
dot enter. raffle with a value
of course of raffle entrance
fee,
we're going to connect three
additional entrance to our
raffle. So we're going to have a
total of four people connect
into this raffle. Now that we
have them in here, we're going
to keep note of our starting
timestamp. So we're gonna do
const starting timestamp equals
await, raffle dot get last
timestamp. And here's where
we're going to get a little bit
tricky. What we want to do is a
couple of things we want to we
want to perform upkeep, which is
going to mock being chainlink
keepers, which will kick off the
chain link, which will kick off
calling fulfill random words.
And we're going to mock doing
that as well. Mock being the
chain link VRF. Once we do that,
we can of course just check to
see okay, did the recent winner
get recorded the raffle get
reset just play as we said as
the timestamp is everything
reset. But we want to do this in
a specific way. If we're doing
this on a test net after we call
fulfill random words, we will
have to wait for the fulfill
random words to be called. Now
since we're working with a
hardhat local chain, we don't
really need to wait for
anything, right because we can
just say okay, boom, snap our
fingers and adjust our
blockchain to do whatever we
want. But we're going to
simulate that we do need to wait
for that event to be called. So
in order for us to simulate
waiting for that event, we once
again need to set up a listener.
Now if we set up a listener we
don't want this to Just to
finish before the listener has
is done listening, so we need to
once again create a new promise.
And this is going to be
incredibly important, especially
for our staging tests. So we're
going to do await, new promise.
And this is going to be exactly
the same as we set it up before,
it's going to be an async
function that's going to take
resolve and reject as
parameters. And we're going to
use this little arrow syntax
here saying, this is an async
function, basically, and we're
going to set up once again, that
once syntax, we're gonna say
raffle that once, what's the
event name, winner picked. So
we're gonna say, Listen, for
this winner picked event, we're
gonna say raffle dot once winner
picks happens, do some stuff.
And again, this is just an
anonymous function. So we're
gonna say raffle dot once the
winner picked event gets
emitted, do some stuff. So we're
setting this up. Now it's in
this function, we're going to
add all of our certs and
everything because we want to
wait for winter to get picked.
Now before the event gets fired,
though, we of course, need to
actually call perform and call
fulfill random words. So this is
going to seem like it's a little
bit backwards. But that's
because we want to set up our
listeners so that when we do
fire, the methods that will fire
the event, our listener is
activated and is waiting for it.
So we're going to put all of our
code inside of this promise.
Now, because we put it outside
of the promise, we put all the
code outside of the promise,
this promise will never get
resolved, because the listener
will never fire into vent. So if
down here, you know we call
fulfill random words with
something, you know which the
spelling is bad. But let's say
we call the down here, this
piece of code will never reach
this fulfill random words,
because it's always going to be
waiting for this wants to get
resolved. So we need to add all
of our code inside the promise.
But outside this raffle dot once
now we don't want to wait
forever, right? Maybe there is
an issue here. And we want to be
able to reject this, if there's
an issue. Now what we can do is
in our heart hat dot config, we
can add a timeout. So we can add
this mocha section, we can give
ourselves a timeout of 200,000
milliseconds, which is going to
be 200 seconds max, if this
event doesn't get fired in 200
seconds, this will be considered
a failure and this test will
fail, which is what we want. And
I typically like to just wrap
this in a try catch because if
something fails, it'll cause you
a whole bunch of headache catch
E. And if anything fails, we'll
also reject, there's an issue
with us calling some function,
we'll just say, Hey, okay,
that's a failure. But you fail,
that way, our promise can get
resolved in a timely manner,
we're going to add this code in
a little bit. But let's keep
going. Let's keep going. And
excuse me, the trycatch should
be in the ones, the ones above
the results, excuse me, because
this is the listener. So sorry,
we want the trycatch to be
inside the ones if this takes
too long, we want to just go
ahead and throw an error.
Otherwise, we're going to
resolve now outside the
listener, but inside of the
promise, we're going to do this
bit here, where we go const TX
equals await raffle dot perform
upkeep, and we'll pass it the
empty bytes object, we'll get
const TX receipt equals await TX
dot weight of one block.
And then we're going to do a
weight VRF core didn't a tour be
to mock dot fulfill random
words, CX receipt dot events of
one dot args dot Request ID come
a raffle that address. So then
the final thing that we're going
to do is we're going to get this
veer off coordinator be to mock
we're going to have it call
fulfill random words, which
takes the request ID and the
consumer address. So we're going
to mock it, give it the request
ID which we get from the
transaction receipt, and the
consumer address here. All
inside this promise, we're
setting up a listener for this
winner picked event. And then
we're mocking the channeling
keepers and then we're mocking
the chainlink VRF. And once this
function gets called this
function should emit a winner
picked event. So this raffle
that was set up that was
listening for this to get
emitted will pick up and go Ah
okay, I found it I found the
winner picked event. Now we can
go ahead and do some stuff. So
once the winner picked event
gets fired, we'll do a little
console dot log found the event
like this and we'll jump into
our try catch and this trycatch
is going to be basically us
doing all these asserts in here.
So first we want to say const
recent winner equals await
raffle dot get recent winner and
we're going to be checking just
everything in this raffle right
we're gonna be checking that the
recent winners right that that
the raffle state's been reset
the players have reversed, you
know, players has been reset,
etc, etc. So we'll say const
raffle state equals awaits
raffle dot get raffle state
we'll say const. Ending
timestamp equals await, raffle
dot get last timestamp. And
let's start doing some asserts.
So first we should assert that
this es players array has been
reset to zero. So if we call get
number of players it should be
zero. So we can do const num
players equals await raffle dot
get number of players like so.
And we can do assert dot equal
nine players.to string is going
to be zero. What else can we
assert? Well, we can assert dot
equal raffle state should be
back to being open. So raffle
state.to string should be zero,
we should assert that the ending
timestamp is now greater than
the starting timestamp. Because
the last timestamp should have
been updated. We also want to
make sure our recent winner is
correct. But we'll do console
dot log recent winner. Now we
can go to the VRF coordinator
mock. And we could simulate this
and try to figure out who the
random winner is to console dot
log accounts to. And then just
to show a bunch of them, we'll
do 01 and three a raffle dot
once this needs to be an async
function, not just a regular
function. Let's try that one
more time, get latest timestamp
is the correct function. So
let's update this with the
correct latest. Let's put latest
in there. Because I'm spelling
something's wrong. I sure am
looks like we're printing out
recent winner here when we
haven't even initialized it. So
let's move it up. And then we'll
do console dot log recent
winner. So I know this is a
massive test here. But let's
give it a try and see if
everything kind of does what we
think it should do. And it's
slowing down here, which is good
because we're doing a lot of
stuff. And uh huh, we finally
get this passing thing to come
out. And we did a ton of console
dot logging so so there's a lot
of stuff in here of the signers
are getting printed out. So
let's just make this a little
easier to read. We'll add dot
address to all these, we can see
who the winner is. So it looks
like the winner is going to be
account number one, which is
great. So what we can do now
that we know account number one
is going to be the winner, we
can get that winners starting
balance way down here before we
call fulfill random words. So
we'll say const winner, starting
balance equals await accounts
one dot get balance, yes, you
can just call get balance right
like that. And now that we have
the winner starting balance back
in our tests, we can say const
winner, ending balance equals
await ounce one dot get balance.
And we can make sure that this
winner got paid what they need.
So now we're going to do a big
assert with some money stuff,
just trust me, this is what the
math is. So we're going to do
assert dot equal winner
balance.to string,
excuse me winter ending
balance.to string should equal
the winner starting balance dot
add the raffle entrance fee that
multiplied by the additional and
trance that add the raffle
entrance fee that we paid.to
string. So this math is
basically saying the winner
should end with a balance of all
of the money that everybody else
added to this contract. And
that's it. So we can run this
test one more time. And Gosh,
darn it, it passed. Okay, so
there was a lot of code here.
And this might have been one of
the hardest pieces of this
entire course is going to be
this part right here. So if you
struggled a little bit with
this, don't let that bog you
down. This is probably one of
the more difficult sections of
this course, let's do a quick
refresher of just this test that
we're doing. And then we'll see
in an action when we do it. In
our staging test. What we did is
we're picking a winner resetting
the lottery and we're sending
money. Basically what we're
doing is we're testing that this
fulfill random words thing does
what we want it to do a random
winner wins and they get the
money. So how do we actually do
that? Well, we first started off
by having a bunch of random
people enter the lottery. Great.
Sounds good. Now what we wanted
to do was we want to call
perform upkeep and fulfill
random words, we want to pretend
that the random number was
drawn. And that's what this code
down here does is it calls that
random number but and what we
could have done was we could
have had all these assert and
checked all the variables. After
we did this, right. We could
have totally done that. However,
on a test net where we don't
always know exactly when a
transaction is going to finish.
We have to wait If we have to
listen for an event to be fired,
before, we could call the
transactions that would end this
whole thing, we needed to set
something up to listen for that
event to be fired. And we said,
hey, only once this event is
fired only once this transaction
is called, can we do our testing
now for our local network, we
are mocking the VRF
coordinators, we have control,
we know exactly when this is
going to run. But on a test net,
we don't. So you'll see in our
staging tests, we won't have any
of this here. And we'll have to
rely on setting up a listener to
listen for the channeling VRF
and the keepers to fire their
events. And that's why the
staging test is going to be so
important to make sure that
we're doing everything correct.
And that's why we set up our
local tests like this, so that
it mimics what we're going to be
doing on our statement test what
we're going to be doing on a
real network here. And again,
we're setting up this listener
and we're saying, Ah, once we do
here, this event, then we're
going to try to actually check
all of the balances and check
that everything is working as
intended. And if we don't see
it, we're going to reject. And
if there's a timeout, if it
takes more than 200 seconds,
we're going to say okay,
something went wrong, we're
going to cancel it. And
actually, I'm going to bump this
up to 300 seconds, because I
think 200 seconds is not going
to be enough. And depending on
how quick the rink B test that
is, you might have to bump this
up even bigger. So just keep
that in mind. But who, okay, we
have just built some fantastic
tests. Let's go ahead, and let's
just run h h test to see if all
of our tests are going to pass.
And well, 14 passing, everything
is passing here we are looking
good.
This is fantastic. Alright, so
now that we have our unit tests,
let's go ahead and create a
staging test. Our staging test
is going to look really similar
to that massive test that we
just created down here. And the
reason we set up our unit test
to do this a weight promise
thing with the raffle dot once
was because this is actually how
we're going to need to wait on a
test net or main net for a
winner to be picked. We cannot
on an actual test net, pretend
to be the chain link V REF, we
can pretend to be the chain link
keepers if we want. But we're
not going to make sure that the
10 the keepers is actually
working. But we are going to be
doing this because we want to
listen for that event to be
fired, we want to listen for the
chain link VRF to respond with
the winner. So let's create a
staging test. And this is a test
that we're going to run on an
actual test net here. Okay, so
we're going to create a new test
called raffle dot staging dot
test dot Jas and this is where
we're going to put our staging
test. Now we can actually code
this pretty quickly because most
of our staging tests is gonna
look real similar to our raffle
test here. So for now, let's
just grab this whole first part,
and then we'll adjust it as we
need. And then we'll close it
off. Because we're definitely
gonna need a raffle, we're not
going to need a VRF coordinator
mock because again, we're not
going to be using a mock. Since
we're on an actual test net, we
will need the raffle entrance
fee, we will need Deployer, we
will need a Deployer. And we
might need the interval. But
let's delete it for now we
probably won't need the chain
ID. So let's delete that as
well. Awesome. Something that we
want to keep in mind is that
when it comes to our staging
tests, we only want our steam
test to run when we're on a
test. Net, we don't need to run
our unit tests because our unit
tests aren't checking that
compatibility with a test net,
we want our unit tests to only
run on a local network. And we
want our staging tests to only
run on a test network. This is
where again, in our test, we're
going to check to make sure what
type of chain we're on. And
oops, it looks like I already
imported the development changes
here. So we're actually in our
staging tests, we're going to
check before we run any test
what kind of network we're on.
So we're gonna say, if our
development chains that includes
network dot name, we're gonna
say if our development chains
includes network to name, so if
the chain we're on is in the
development chains, and again,
we're going to use this ternary
operator where we say, if we're
on a development chain, do
something. And then if we're not
something else. If we are on a
development chain, what are we
going to do? Well want to skip
this and we can actually skip
this by putting in this describe
dot skip. And this will skip
this whole section here. And
then we can say, if we are the
development chain, go ahead and
do our thing. So this is some
really nice syntax that allows
us to skip our staging tests if
we're on a local network. And
additionally, we can grab this
syntax, go into our raffle dot
test dot j s where we have our
unit tests and add the bang
operator, which is the knot and
hit Save. And now we're saying
if we're not on a development
chain, skip it and only run this
if we aren't in development
chain. So this says run this
only on a test net or main net.
And then this has run this only
on a local network. Great. So we
have a deployer which we're
going to need. We are not going
to need to deploy any fixtures
because we're going to run our
deploy script and our contracts
should already be deployed. We
will need a raffle we won't need
a VRF coordinator mocks we can
delete that We will need the
entrance fee, and we probably
won't need the interval. So we
can go ahead and delete that
too. Alright, awesome. So we
have our describe, we have our
before each, let's make our
tests. And I'm just going to
make one giant test to test kind
of everything end to end. And
you can add more tests later on
yourself, if you want to our
staging test is going to be
really similar to this massive
test that we made down here. And
in fact, we're going to use most
of this code here as our
boilerplate. So let's create a
describe. And we'll say, and
we'll actually just copy this
describe the four random words
and paste it in here. Because
again, we're going to be using a
lot of the same code in our
staging tests here. Great. So
now we'll say it works with live
chain link keepers and chain
link VRF, we get a random
winner, acing function. So this
is going to be our test in here.
So in this test, we of course,
we want to enter the raffle. And
we shouldn't have to do anything
else except for enter this
raffle. Because the chain the
keepers and the only VRF are
going to be the ones to actually
kick off this lottery for us,
we'll do a quick grabbing of the
starting timestamp to have it
before all this kicks off. So
we'll say const starting
timestamp equals await raffle
dot get last to me get latest
timestamp, get latest timestamp,
we're gonna grab this because
later on, we're going to test to
see if the timestamp has indeed
moved forward, we want to enter
the lottery, right, we want to
run the command we've been
running over here all the time,
we want to do you know await
raffle dot enter raffle, but we
don't want to call it yet.
Because same as what we did over
here, we want to set up our
listener first. Now in here, we
probably should have set up our
listener before we entered the
raffle. However, we controlled
the blockchain. So putting it in
that order was is was okay. But
we want to set up the listener
before we enter the raffle just
in case the blockchain moves
really fast. And we're going to
set up the listener the exact
same way, we did it over here.
So we're gonna say await new
promise. And it's going to be an
async function that takes a
resolve and a reject. And we're
going to use a little arrow
notation here. And in here,
we're going to set up the
listener, we're gonna say raffle
dot once, once that winner is
picked, we're going to do
another async function using
that Arrow.
Arrow function syntax, we'll say
console dot log winner picked
the event fired. And only once
we get this winner picked, can
we start doing our asserts in
here, can we start making sure
that there's a winner, there's a
verifiably random winner, it's
been picked, the money has been
moved, etc. This is where we'll
do our try catch. And if there's
any error, we're just going to
automatically reject, we're
going to reject the promise. And
if all goes well, of course,
we're going to resolve the
promise. So our listener has
been set up here. We haven't
added our asserts here. But we
will, let's just go ahead and
write the rest of the test. And
then we'll go back and we'll
update this listener so so our
listener has been added. And
inside here is actually where
we're going to enter the raffle.
So inside here, await, raffle
dot enter raffle value is going
to be raffle entrance fee. And
really that's it. Right? So
we're setting up the listener,
setting up the listener, then
entering the raffle. And this
code won't complete until our
listener has finished listening
because again, this whole SEC is
in a wait. So we're gonna say
okay, cool setup, the listener,
wait for this to finish. And
then when it gets here, it goes
out okay, this is the end of the
code Are we all done executing
Oh, no resolve or reject hasn't
been called yet. And that's
because we're still waiting for
the listener to finish
listening. Now, once we get this
winner picked event emitted in
here, we're going to get that
recent winner so we'll say const
recent winner equals await
raffle dot get recent winner
will get the raffle state we'll
say const. raffle state equals
await raffle dot get raffle
state, we'll get the winners
balance. So we'll say const.
Winner balance equals await
recent winner. And since we're
only entering with our Deployer
we should check to see the
deployers balance at the end and
we can't do it right with this
deployer object here. So we'll
have to do the player account
equals await ethers dot get
signers, no wrap this actually
actually will just say this is
accounts here like that. And
then we'll just do a count of
zero because it counts as zero
is going to be our Deployer. So
our winner balance is going to
be accounts a zero dot get
balance. And then we're going to
do const ending timestamp equals
a weight raffle dot get latest
To timestamp, and we should also
get the starting balance. So
we'll say winner ending balance,
we should also get the starting
balance right after we enter. So
we'll say const. Winner,
starting balance equals await
accounts. Zero dot get balance,
so that now we can do some
comparisons. All right, great.
Let's do the comparisons now. So
we should first expect the
raffle to be reset. So we can do
this a few different ways. Down
here. We did number of players.
We can also say, await, expect
raffle dot get player 0.2 dot v
dot reverted, right because Get
Player zero should get reverted
because there's not even going
to be an object at zero. So
that's another way we can check
to see if our players array has
been reset. Next, we can do
assert dot equal recent
winner.to string, this should
equal our account zero dot
address. Okay, our Deployer What
else can we do? We will assert
dot equal raffle state to zero.
We want this email to go back to
open after we're done. And then
we finally want to make sure
that the money has been
transferred correctly. So we'll