do assert dot equal, this should
be a winner ending balance. That
to string should be equal to
winner starting balance, add
raffle entrance fee.to string.
So if we look down here, they
enter the raffle we check their
starting balance right after
they enter. And they basically
should just get that raffle
entrance fee back right because
they are the only ones who have
entered this raffle. And then we
can do one more assert, do
assert that the ending timestamp
is greater than the starting
timestamp. And then we'll of
course, say resolve. So this all
goes well, we resolve. If
there's an issue with any of
these asserts, we're going to
catch those errors and we're
going to reject and this is
going to be false. And this
whole test is gonna go ah, there
was an issue, we now have a
staging test that looks really
good here. Let's try
this out. Let's try our staging
test out from start to finish.
So now in order for us to test
this staging test, from end to
end, you first going to need to
get our sub ID for the
channeling fear F then we're
going to need to deploy our
contract using the sub ID, we're
going to need to register the
contract with chain link VRF.
And it's somebody we're going to
then need to register it with
chain link keepers. And then of
course, we're going to run the
staging tests. So let's do it.
So first thing we're going to
need to do is what? Get our sub
ID for chain link VRF. Okay,
great. So we're going to come
over to VRF dot chain dot link.
And we're going to need to
create a new subscription. If we
don't have enough rink B eath.
Let's we want to head over to
the full blockchain solidity
course, here, we're going to
scroll down. And we're going to
look for the recommended test
and here, which is ranked v. And
we're going to use the faucets
link to get some Rigby link, run
Fosses dot chain dot link, let's
switch over from COVID to a
cerium. Rigby, we know we're
going to need some link and some
eath. So let's just go ahead and
get both. Alright, great now
that our transaction has gone
through, let's just double check
our wallet here. And it looks
like we do indeed have Ethereum
here. And if you don't see the
link, you can head over to link
token contracts, Link token
contracts in the chain link
documentation. We'll scroll down
to Rigby, we'll grab this
contract address import tokens
and we'll paste it in here. Add
Custom tokens, import tokens.
Great. Now I can see my eath and
my link here, perfect. We have
some eath we have some link,
let's head over to V REF
subscription management. And
we're going to create a new
subscription. Again, we could
totally do this
programmatically, because the
user interface here is only
helping us facilitate call
contracts to the registration
contract that's completely
decentralized and on chain. So
let's go ahead and create
subscription will create
subscription will confirm the
transaction and Metamask on the
Rinkeby network will do a little
bit of wading in great once it's
gone through, you can go ahead
and click the add funds button.
I'm going to show you what it
looks like if you accidentally
refresh and jump off though. So
if you refresh and you go back
to veer off the chain dot link,
you should have a new active
subscription. And you'll see
this number here. If you click
on it, this is your subscription
ID great. So we can actually
take this, come back to our code
into our helper Hardhead config.
And we can paste our
subscription ID under
subscription ID for our Rinkeby
network here. Awesome. Now that
we have a subscription we can
see it's not funded with any
link. So we don't have any
Oracle gas here. And we don't
have any consumers. Right our
consumer is going to be a raffle
or a lottery contract. So let's
add some funds first and we
don't need to add A whole lot
because we're only going to be
testing once. So let's go just
go ahead and add to link here,
this number might change
depending on different costs of
the test nets and how much link
token there's available. So if
you're actually working on a
main net, be sure to head over
Doc's touching that link EVM
chains contract addresses, you
can read more about the costs
some of these different chains,
so you can figure out exactly
how much to put in here. And if
you go to the full blockchain
solidity course, Jas, we can
scroll down to Lesson Nine,
there's a recommended link
amounts or rinky saving tests
for chain link VRF. For now
we're going to put two for
keepers, we're going to put
eight, but feel free to refer to
here so you know how much to put
in. So let's go ahead and
confirm, we're going to approve
adding funds here, go ahead and
confirm. And we're now funding
our subscription to so we can
pay that Oracle gas to get our
random numbers. Great. And once
we're funded, we can close it,
we'll do a little refresh. And
we can see the balance is now to
link when we don't have any
consumers perfect. So we've got
our sub ID, we funded it. Now
let's go ahead and deploy our
contract. And we already know
that we should be all good for
deploying our contract, we go to
our Dotty and V will need to add
all of those same parameters
from our previous projects,
we'll need to shrink the RPC
URL, we'll need our private key.
If we want to verify we'll need
our ether scan API key. And if
we want to do gas output, we'll
need our coin market cap API
key. So let's make sure we have
all that. And we'll look at our
deploy script. Once again, just
real quick look at our helper
hardcat config just real quick,
and it looks like we do indeed
have everything in here. And we
should just be able to deploy it
in one command.
So we should be able to do yarn,
hard hat or just h h again,
ploy, dash dash network Rinkeby.
Let's go try this out. All
right, it looks like we've
compiled successfully, we've
deployed it successfully. And
we've even verified it, we can
go and open it up on Rinku ether
scan. And we can see our code
here has been verified. And it's
looking beautiful. We can read
from it, which is great. We can
see all these commands here now
that it's verified. And if we
look at the Git raffle state, we
should indeed see that it's
open, right, and it's going to
stay open until somebody ends
the raffle and updates the
amount of eath that the contract
actually has. Now that we've
deployed a contract using that
sub ID, we need to register the
contract with chain link V REF.
And with chain link keepers. So
we need to add this consumer
does tell chinley VRF. Hey, this
is the contract that you're
looking for now. So we're gonna
go back to V REF dot chain dot
link, and we're going to grab
this contract address, and we're
going to add it as a consumer,
your subscription is ready, you
can now add consumers we're
gonna add consumer. And again,
this website is just here to
help facilitate us interacting
with the contract. So we're
going to approve that user,
we'll go ahead and confirm and
the transaction is going
through. While we wait for this
to go through, we can go to
keepers dot chain dot link, and
do the same thing work with the
user interface to register a new
upkeep. So we'll go ahead and
add our email Hardhead free code
camp@gmail.com. We'll call this
raffle upkeep. We'll paste our
upkeep address in here we have
our admin address, and you can
ignore this bit right here. For
gas limit, this is going to be
the gas limit of the PErforM
upkeep function. If we did our
gas estimator, we could just
check to see how much that
perform upkeep costs. But for
now, I'm just going to put
500,000 That's probably
overkill, but that's fine. Check
data, we're going to keep blank
because again, our checkup keep
doesn't take anything. And then
starting balance, we're going to
put as eight. And if you forget
to put a starting balance here,
you can always find it later. So
let's go ahead and register,
we're gonna get a Metamask pop
up, we're gonna go ahead and hit
Confirm. And we can go back to
our VRF and see that it's indeed
been added and awesome, we now
have a consumer on our VRF. So
now let's just wait for our
keepers to go through upkeep
registration requests submitted
successfully on domain net, you
might actually have to wait a
little bit for your request to
go through, but I'll test that
it should automatically go
through. Now if we go back to
keepers dot chain dot link, we
should now see we now if we
scroll down to my upkeeps We
have a raffle upkeep here and I
have to because I accidentally
use the same account that I
tested on, you can ignore the
two you'll have one but this is
the one that we just created.
And we can actually see what our
balances and then what the
minimum balance for this
actually is. So it looks like
eight Link was a little bit too
low. So let's go back to Fosses
dot chain dot link slash rinky.
Now that we have some more link,
we can come back to our raffle
upkeep. And we go ahead and hit
add funds. And we'll add just
three. And we'll go ahead and
confirm we first need to give
permission to spend. We approved
our link transfer now let's
actually transfer the link to
the contract and alright funds
added successfully. So now let's
do a little refresh. Now we no
longer see that message saying
that it's underfunded and we
have our balance and we can see
that it's more than the minimum
balance. We have See the history
that we just funded this twice.
Once this actually kicks off,
we'll see activity type will be
like perform upkeep or something
got our sub ID, we've deployed
the contract, we've registered
with chain link V REF, we've
registered it with chain link
keepers. Now all we need to do
is run the staging tests. Now
running our staging test is
essentially going to be the same
as us calling this enter script,
right, because all we're doing
in our staging test is entering
the lottery. And then we just
have a whole bunch of validators
that we're running to make sure
that things are doing as we
expect, since our contract is
actually verified, what we could
do on Rigby ether scan is we can
actually go to this right
contract section of the
contract. And we could even
connect our wallets to it. And
once this turns from red to
green, after a little refresh,
we'll now see that it's green,
it's connected, we can even call
functions on this contract
ourself, so we could enter the
raffle ourself, we would add,
you know, however much eath to
enter the raffle, and that would
kick off the keepers in the VRF,
as well. So we could call it via
ether scan, we could obviously
call it via our staging tests
here, we could call it via our
scripts, we could call it via
the console, there's a ton of
ways to actually do this. But
moment of truth here, we're
gonna run our staging tests,
which is going to have us enter
the lottery, and set up a
listener to make sure that
everything works correctly. And
additionally, we'll see on our
raffle upkeep history, we'll see
a transaction go through, and
then we'll see a transaction on
our chain like VRF as well. Are
you ready? I sure am.
Let's do this. So we'll do h h,
test, dash dash network, rink B.
And that should be all we need
to do. In our state and tests,
we probably should have added
some console dot logs in here to
tell us hey, to tell us what
steps that we're on with each.
But we forgot to. So if you
follow along with the repo
associated with this, we've
added the console dot logs in
the test there. But all right,
if we go to the ether scan for
this contract, we go back to the
rink the ether scan for this, we
paste in that address, the first
step that we're doing in this
test, of course, while we're
setting up this listener, the
first transaction is going to be
entering the raffle that's going
to kick everything off. Right.
So if we refresh a little bit on
ether scan, we do indeed see
we've entered the raffle. And
we've updated the balance of the
raffle. Okay, awesome. So raffle
has been entered. Now then what
happens? Well, if the raffle has
been entered, if we go to raffle
dot soul, if it's open, if
enough time has passed, if
there's players and it has a
balance, which we just checked
does, this will get kicked off
by the keepers. So if we go to
the keepers, and we do a little
refresh here, after a little
bit, we do indeed see checkup
key passed and we see a perform
upkeep having gone through
great, what does perform upkeep
to well perform upkeep calls the
chainlink VRF. So now if we go
over to chainlink, VRF, we do a
refresh here, go down to
history, we do indeed see one of
the transactions has gone
through we can see the
transaction hash, the link
spent, etc. And now if we go
back to our tests, we do indeed
see raffle unit tests for friend
fulfill random request winner
pick event fired. And this means
that we just went through this
entire process of having a
perfectly truly decentralized
raffle work on an actual
Testament with our integration
tests working correctly.
Absolutely massive, huge
congratulations if you've made
it this far. And if you just
walk through the integration
test with me now bounce over
contract has now been reset to
zero because our wallet address
just won the lottery right and
got the money back. Now you
might be wondering, Hey, I see
the Create raffle function. And
I see enter raffle but I don't
see didn't the chain link nodes
just call perform upkeep and
fulfill random words, I'll come
no matter how often I refresh, I
don't see those transactions
here. Well, those are actually
going to be considered internal
transactions fulfill random
words, it's actually called
through the VRF coordinator and
the VRF coordinator contract
then calls for full randomness.
So we can go to internal
transactions. And one of these
transactions is going to be the
transaction to the VRF
coordinator contract, which
calls our contract. Same thing
with perform upkeep. Perform
upkeep, the chain link nodes
actually call through the
registry contract and then the
registry contract calls perform
upkeep. That's what we see here.
And if we go through the
internal transactions, we'll see
him there. Now let's look at
this enter raffle as well. And
since we've learned about events
and logs, we can actually go to
the logs section now. And we can
see our log or event being
emitted here we can see the name
raffle, enter, we can see the
topic zero which is going to
identify this entire event. And
then we also see this number
here which is what which is
index topic, one address player
and then there's no data
associated with this right
because we only have index
parameters which again show up
as topics so this is absolutely
phenomenal. Wow, absolutely
massive and we can rerun a unit
test Just by hh test in this
will only run our unit tests.
And we can see that these are
all passing as well, things are
looking fantastic here. And we
have just successfully created a
verifiably random, autonomous,
decentralized, raffle and or
lottery deployed on the
blockchain, you should be so
excited right now. Now, I'm not
going to show you how to push
this up to GitHub. However, if
you want to push this up to get
up, and again, tweet at me,
tweet at chainlink tweet at Free
Code Camp, please feel free to
do so because you just did an
amazing job getting this far.
And if you're gonna want to push
this up to GitHub, remember,
we're going to want to put a dot
Git ignore. In here, we add a
ton of stuff like that VS code
artifacts, cash deployments,
known modules, etc. Type chain
types, all this stuff, you can
find a sample dot Git ignore, of
course, in the GitHub repo
associated with this, this is an
advanced project, we did a lot
of really advanced things here.
And this is the section of the
course, where I think at this
point, you've got most of the
fundamentals down. And now we're
going to move into more front
end. And we're going to move
into more industry specific and
more advanced topics that are
really going to supercharge you
and make you one of the masters
of the blockchain in the smart
contract realm. So huge
congratulations, one more time,
definitely go celebrate,
definitely go for that walk,
take a quick break, let
everything we just learned
settling your brain and get
ready for the next one.
Alright, now we're gonna go over
the TypeScript edition of this
lesson, we're gonna go a little
bit quickly here, because we're
not learning too much new stuff
for this TypeScript edition. So
if you want to just follow
along, you can open up the repo
here and use the TypeScript
branch. One thing to note that
is a little bit different is
when we do our promise in our
tests, we're doing a weight
promise void, because we're not
going to be returning anything
with our promise here. But the
rest is going to be exactly the
same. We're going to have a hard
hat dot config to TypeScript
that's going to use imports.
Once again, everything else is
pretty much the same. We're
going to export the config like
we did last time. In our package
dot JSON. Of course, we're going
to have all of our TypeScript
dependencies as well. And then
our deploy scripts are going to
follow that same functionality
that we've used before. So now
our deploy scripts use a type
deploy function on our variables
that we export at the bottom.
And we also import the hard hat
runtime environment type, which
where we pull the deployments
get named account and networks
from in our tests. Of course,
we're still importing the types
of these contracts from type
chain slash types, like you see
here, like for example, raffle
is going to be signed to raffle
VRF coordinator V to mock is
going to be signed to type VRF
coordinator V to MK and if we
wanted to deploy with these
contract factories, we could as
well. So those are going to be
the main differences with
TypeScript. There's not anything
really new there. But again, if
you want to follow along with
TypeScript, and you want to code
everything in TypeScript, and
example is here for you
All right, welcome back. I hope
your break was absolutely
fantastic because now we are
getting into more advanced full
stack slash front end
development. We've done the back
end development, we've created
smart contracts, we created our
lottery. In our last section, we
have all this wonderful code
that allows us to work with our
own provably decentralized
lottery. In order for regular
everyday people to use our
lottery, we're going to need to
build a front end. Now
previously, we learned to build
a front end with raw HTML
JavaScript, with our Funmi
project, we created a front end
with just pure HTML and
JavaScript, just creating
applications with HTML and
JavaScript is great. And if
that's what you want to do, you
absolutely can. But doing it
with those vanilla protocols has
some limitations. And working
with a framework, like what
we're going to be working with
in this section is going to make
our lives a lot easier, we're
going to be able to develop
quicker, have more
functionality, and do more in
less time. As you remember back
to the project wasn't really a
fleshed out project, if you
remember, it was just a bunch of
buttons. And that was really it.
So working with a framework is
really going to enable us to put
more features and add more
styling to our applications
really easy. Once again, the
code for this entire section is
located in our lesson and is
located in this GitHub
repository associated with the
course. Now I have to put an
asterisk here, as I've said many
times, the front end sections of
this course are not required,
we're not going to learn
anything new about the back end
in this front end section. So if
you don't care about building
websites, all you want to do is
learn the smart contract aspect
of this course, you can skip
these sections. But if you do
want to learn how to build these
front end applications, if you
do want to give users and non
developers the abilities to
interact with our smart
contracts, then please continue
to watch. Now I also have to put
an asterix here, because if you
haven't worked with some of
these frameworks before, the
learning curve can seem a little
bit steep. And as I've said many
times, this isn't going to be a
front end course that would take
several more hours than what we
want to do for this video. So if
you've never done front end
before, this is one of the
sections where I do recommend
you follow along with one of
these optional sub lessons,
we're not going to play them
here. But if you follow along
with one of these sub lessons,
that will definitely be
incredibly helpful. One of the
videos that I have for the sub
lessons is this video right
here, how to connect your smart
contracts to Metamask. And it
shows a number of ways
connecting your smart contracts
and building kind of these these
front ends. It does start with a
raw HTML and JavaScript edition.
So you can really get some more
practice in here with HTML and
JavaScript. And then it moves to
index js ethers and a few other
next Jas based applications.
Doing it a few different ways
will install a new some more
insight on what you should be
thinking about when you're
approaching these. So this is
absolutely a video to watch if
you're new to front end
development. Additionally, for
this section, like I said, we're
going to be using a framework.
And in particular, we're going
to be using the next Jas
framework. Now. Next, Jas is a
react based framework. React is
a framework for building front
end and full stack applications.
Next, Jas is a framework on top
of the React framework. So if
you already know react, most of
this is going to come very
naturally to the reason that
we're using React in next Jas is
because React is easily as of
right now one of the most
popular frameworks and languages
out there. And it's no surprise
why we've got a little article
in the GitHub repo titled Why
you should use React js for web
development, which we'll go into
a little bit more. Some of the
biggest applications like
Facebook and Instagram use React
js and a number of other Fortune
500 companies and React js
especially in the blockchain
space is easily the most popular
with protocols like uniswap, and
Avi also using React Jas. Now
the reason we're using this next
Jas on top of React Jas is that
next Jas, I think makes working
with react much easier. And I
want us to work with the easiest
and most powerful framework out
there. Next, Jas is also getting
a ton of steam has some really
advanced but in my mind easier
to use features than just raw
react. Now, like I said, if
you've never worked with React
before, if you've never worked
with next Jas before, and you
want to do a little brush up,
definitely watch my video six
ways to connect your depth to a
wallet. And if you find yourself
struggling with with this
section, because the front end
stuff doesn't really make sense.
We also have a next Jas crash
course in the GitHub repo
associated with this course.
It's about an hour long and it
is absolutely phenomenal. Free
Code Camp also has some next Jas
crash courses. So if you're
struggling with the front of it,
go take it next Jas course, and
then come back to this section
or skip the front end sections
all together, do the rest of the
course of just the back end, and
then come back and do these
front end sections. We're going
to show you the cutting edge
ways to interact and work with
your front end and then also
deploy them. And if you follow
along correctly, by the end of
this, you'll have a website
deployed that you can show off
and you can send a link of it to
your friends. And now I know we
already showed you what this
looks like but I'm going to show
you it one more time just so we
can walk through and see exactly
what we're doing. So we're going
to have this decentralized
lottery where we can go ahead
with can connect our wallet if
not already connected. And we
can switch, we can switch around
between networks. And our app
will actually recognize it and
say, hey, the only supported
chains that we're working with
here are going to be 31337,
which is localhost, or four,
which is ring feed. And we'll
learn how to add this validation
into our application so that our
app only works when we're on a
chain that we want, then we can
go ahead and interact with it.
Normally, we can click a button
Metamask will pop up, we can go
ahead and confirm we'll get a
little transaction notification
saying that transaction is
complete. And we'll get our
front end updated. And then on
the back end, we'll be able to
see the chain link nodes and the
Chinuch V REF do their work. And
once they actually pick a
winner, after a refresh, we'll
be able to see that the back end
node was updated, we do indeed
have a previous winner. Awesome.
Now, not only that, we're going
to show you how to build this,
but also, we're going to show
you how to host it on an actual
site. So you'll be able to push
it up to your own blockchain.
And additionally, we're gonna
host it in a decentralized
context. So this site that we
have here is it's going to be
hosted on a technology that
allows us to host websites in
decentralized contexts as well
swore backends. And even our
front ends can be hosted in
decentralized context. So So I
hope you're incredibly excited
for this because we're going to
be showing you the cutting edge
tools that many of the top
blockchain projects use. And
let's just jump right into it.
Now, I'm currently in the
Hardhead smart contract lottery
project, the project that we
just did, we did this hard hat
smart contract lottery, which is
great. What we're going to do
now is we're going to create a
new folder, although we are
going to be coming back to this
folder from time to time to make
a couple of updates. So if you
want to keep it open, you
absolutely can. But for me, I'm
gonna go ahead and CD download
directory to kind of my main
directory for this whole course.
And we're going to create a new
directory called next Jas. smart
contract. Lottery, FCC, then
we're going to cd into next Jas
smart contract lottery FCC, and
go ahead and hit code period.
And like I said, if you want to
keep that one up and have this
new folder up, you absolutely
can. But basically, again, we're
just opening up our VS code in
this next Jas smart contract
lottery folder. Now for this
front end stuff, in particular,
if you want to be absolutely
sure you're using the same
versions as I am, what you can
do is you can git clone this
repo, and then copy the yarn dot
lock and package dot JSON, and
then run yarn, this will make
sure you're always using the
exact same packages that I'm
using, and you'll never run into
any weird issues. So if you do
run into an issue, one of the
first things to do, especially
for these front end parts is to
go back, make sure you have the
exact same yarn dot lock and
package that JSON that I do in
my examples here, and go from
there. Now we're here in our
front end project. And we're
going to create a website, we're
gonna create a front end for
application, like I said, we're
gonna be using next Jas, if you
want to follow along with the
next Jas documentation here,
they do have a great getting
started and walking through
this. So for us, we're going to
do yarn, create next app, and
then put a little period saying
we want our next app in this
directory. If you don't put this
period, it'll create it in a new
folder, and you'll have double
folders. Okay, awesome. So and
once we do this, in our little
files explorer section, we now
can see all the different files
that come boilerplate with this.
Now, let me just do a quick
walkthrough of what's going on
here. Again, we also go through
this in those two videos that I
recommended, but it doesn't hurt
to go over it twice. So node
modules, of course, is going to
be the package in the
installations pages is going to
be the different pages on our
site. Let me let me show you
what I mean by this. To run this
whole thing. Actually, we can
just run yarn, run Dev, and
we'll get started server on
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
you can command click it or copy
paste it into your browser. And
now you'll see on localhost
3000, we have our page up here.
Now what we can do, actually, so
index.js is going to be our
default page, which is, you
know, considered this slash
here. But what we can do is we
can create new pages. So I could
do new file, you know, dog dot
Jas. And then you know, just
copy paste index into dog to
Jas, paste it, delete everything
inside the div, you don't have
to follow along here and just go
Hi, save this, go back here. I
can now put in dog and get this.
So pages is going to be all kind
of these different routes to
these different spots on our
website. And index is going to
be our default, kind of like our
homepage. So I'm going to delete
Dardo. And inside these files is
going to be something called
react syntax or JSX. They come
as Jas but they're basically
reacts in text. Next, Jas is
based on React, you'll see these
pages are this weird combination
of both JavaScript and HTML. We
see some import stuff at this at
the top, which reminds us of
JavaScript and again, you'll see
some important stuff at the top
and then down here, you'll See,
like div head main h1 P, you'll
see all these like HTML tags
react index js allow us to do
this combination of JavaScript
and HTML. And it actually makes
life a lot easier. Now, you'll
also notice we're doing imports
in here. Remember, I told you
all this earlier, imports work
with our front end require does
not. So that's some of the
difference between node does not
equal JavaScript, right? This is
where the differences can start
getting a little bit confusing.
But the way that I usually like
to think about it is I just say,
no JS, excuse me, I'll just say
back end. I can J S is a little
different from front end. Yes.
So back end, Jas and front end
Jas are a little bit different.
That's kind of the way I like to
think about it. app.js is going
to be our entry point for
everything the way react and
next Jas work is everything is
what's called component based in
all of our files here, you're
gonna see this export default
function home or something along
those lines. What react and next
Jas do is they say, Hey, this
huge clump of HTML stuff that
has a hodgepodge of JavaScript
inside of it is considered a
component. And so all of our
pages get wrapped through this
underscore app.js page. So this
is a page but it's kind of like
the main entry point. And they
get stuck into this component
section of our app that Jas so
you can think of this on this
graph. The GS is kind of the
whole application or whole front
end. And on this homepage, this
component, we're sticking index
dot j s right in here, we're
swapping out component for index
dot J. S. Now API is what we
wanted to do if we wanted to do
like some HTTP, GET HTTP POST
requests, but we're not going to
do any of that. So we're going
to pretty much ignore API for
now public is just going to be
some public images like a
favicon or Versaille, that SVG
styles is going to be the CSS
for our project. CSS stands for
Cascading Style Sheets. And it's
basically a way to style your
HTML, we're going to change the
way we do styling and a little
bit, but that's basically what
these both do the ESLint I'm
dumping this right now we have
our dot Git ignore which we know
what it does. We have our next
dot config dot J. S. This is a
configuration file or next. Jas,
of course, we have our package
json, we have a readme, and we
have our yarn dot lock. So most
of what we're going to do is
actually going to be inside this
Pages folder. And we're also
going to create a couple other
folders that are going to be our
main stuff now, because I'm me,
and like I said, I love working
with prettier, I'm going to
automatically dump a prettier
RC, and a prettier ignore in
here, just so that I can format
my code a little bit nicer, you
can grab your prettier RC from
our last projects, you can grab
your prettier ignore as well. Or
you can just pause me right now
copy, paste them from the GitHub
repo associated with this
lesson, paste them in, and then
we'll do yarn, add dash dash
Dev, prettier, so that we can
auto format all of our code for
come back over to here, we can
save and boom, stuff gets auto
formatted. Now, again, we're
going to be using the multi
terminal feature. So right now I
have one running my front end.
So if I come back to the front
end, I hit refresh. It's still
running. And then I have one to
do, you know my scripts and
stuff. We have yarn run dev
running right now. And if we go
to our package, JSON, running
yarn, run dev just runs next
Dev. And actually, let me cancel
it and just do yarn dev yarn is
actually smart enough that don't
need to do run Dev, but it just
runs next Dev. And this next
command comes built in once we
installed next, which we did
when we did yarn create next
app. So next Jas comes with
these scripts already built in
for us, we want to build our
front end to enable people to
interact with our lottery in a
fair way, and connect with the
smart contract that's running.
Let's create some simple front
end pieces for this. So first
thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna go to Pages, and we're
going to go to index.js. All
this stuff in here is cute and
nice. And thank you next, Jas,
but we're going to delete it all
and delete everything except for
that headpiece, we're gonna
leave that up, we're just going
to change the name. But this way
down here, we're going to change
the name from Crate next app to
smart contract lottery or raffle
or whatever we want to do.
description will be our smart
contract, lottery. And then
right below the head, we're
going to write hello, blue, and
save. And if we look at our
front end, we now see that it
says smart contract lottery and
the top and I'm going to move
this all the way over here,
smart contract lottery and the
top and we see Hello, so smart
contract lottery. Hello, the
description here, we're not
going to see this is going to be
something that web scrapers and
stuff we're going to find.
Now one of the first things that
we're going to need to do is
we're going to need to create
that connect button. We've done
this in the past with raw
JavaScript, but now we're going
to do it with next js and react.
The one that we made previously
was pretty minimalistic. In
fact, we bring it back up it
checked to see if there was
windows that Aetherium and then
went and requested and connected
and said okay, cool. You're
connected. Now what did didn't
do was a lot of things that we
would want an application to do.
When we change networks, our
application didn't detect that
when we change users or
it was really stringent in the
functionality that it actually
had for connecting to a wallet.
So we're going to make our
wallet connect button,
incredibly powerful, so that you
can connect with the button, you
can switch networks, you can
switch accounts, you can pretty
much do anything in our
application will know our
application will be responsive.
So that's gonna be one of the
first things that we're going to
do, we're going to create a
header and connect button nav
bar one a little navbar here,
saying, hey, you know, you can
connect with this button. So
that's gonna be the first thing
that we're going to do. Now we
can build our whole connect
button in this index dot j s and
stick it in here. But instead,
what we're going to do is we're
going to make it a what's called
a component. So we're going to
create a new folder called
components. And we're going to
create a new file in here called
header.js. And you might also
see a lot of people do
header.js x.js and.js x do
literally the exact same thing,
you can do either one, I'm going
to do dot JSX, just to remind me
that this is a React file that
we're creating. This is a
component that we're creating.
But yeah, you can do J S JSX. If
you want to learn a little bit
more about components, we've got
a link to learning about
components. They're basically
independent and reusable bits of
code. They serve the same
purpose as JavaScript functions,
but work in isolation and return
HTML. So basically, we're going
to create like a little chunk of
HTML that we're going to export
into our index such as like what
we've done in the past, this
just helps modularize and reuse
this header component, you know,
across our project. Now, we're
only going to be using our
header in one area. However,
it's still nice to modularize
the project regardless. And to
get start, this is going to be
what's called a functional base
component. So we're going to
create basically a function
called home write really pretty
much exactly like what we see in
JavaScript, except it's going to
return some HTML. So we can do
like a little div. And my VS
code auto created the closing
div here. And in here, I'm going
to be like hi from header. This
is going to be a real
minimalistic component like this
is a valid component here. Now
we have this function that
returns HTML. And to give other
applications, the ability to use
this component will do export
default function home. And then
in our index.js, we can import
it with imports. Home actually,
excuse me, I'm not going to call
it home, we're going to call it
header, header, excuse me,
export default function header,
and then import header from the
down directory components slash
header, like so. So now we've
imported our header in index
such as if we go back to our
front end, which is still
running, we don't see it in
here, right? Remember,
everything goes through our app.
And when we're on the slash
page, that's going to go to our
index.js. index js is importing
our header, but it's not
returning our header, right, we
see. And here, we see it
returns. And this is the HTML
that it's returning. And as you
can see, there's clearly no
header in here. So now that
we've imported our header, we
need to actually add our header
in here. So we'll do header, and
then adds the closing tag right
here. If you don't add any
stuff, you know, in between two
tags, you can go ahead and just
do this one liner here, with a
backslash at the end saying,
Hey, this is an open and closed
tag here. Now that we've
imported it, what do you think
we'll see on the front end, now
that we've added it to our index
js, you're right, we see hi from
header, because we added our
header here. And then we see
Hello. So high from header,
hello, boom. Now, anything that
we do, obviously now in our
header.js, will see reflected on
our front end. So we can do hi
from header, blah, blah, blah,
you know, just a bunch of
dribbles, and we'll see it on
our front end. So this is going
to be our section where we're
going to make our header or a
navbar or all the functionality
for the Connect button. Now I'm
going to tell you something, and
some of you are going to love
this summer, you're going to
hate this. I'm going to show
you. I'm going to show you the
hard way first, then the easy
way. Why am I going to show you
the hard way first? Well,
because I want you to become
familiar with what's actually
going on behind the scenes and
what's actually going on with
some of these components because
it is really helpful when
building these front ends to
understand, Okay, here's what's
going on. If you don't
understand what's going on
behind the scenes, you're gonna
go to try to build more advanced
applications, and you're gonna
have no idea what to do because
you've just learned the
shortcut. I like to think of it
as like calculus, like we're
going to learn how to calculate
a derivative first, and then
we're going to learn the
shortcut to quickly getting
derivatives. So don't skip this
part, because this is going to
help you well and beyond down
the line. Okay, we're going to
learn this the harder way to set
everything up in our HTML Funmi.
We just use raw ethers to kind
of do everything and you
absolutely can use raw ethers to
do everything. However, there
are some packages especially for
React that make life developing
a front end substantially better
and in our full blockchain
solidity course, Jas. We have a
number of other packages that
you can use will stack
development and other libraries.
And if you watch this six ways
to connect your depth to a
wallet, you'll actually
understand some of the
differences. So if you haven't
watched that video, go back,
watch that video. But there's a
whole bunch of libraries that we
can use that are going to make
our lives a lot easier. We've
listed some of them here. React
Morales is the one that we're
going to be using today, they
have some additional plugins,
and they have probably my
favorite thing on the planet,
which I'm going to show you how
to do very soon. But these are
also open source, Ross also
comes with some optional
functionality to hook into your
own back end to give your app
even more features and even more
functionality. And that's the
other reason that we're doing
it. So and we're gonna go over
that later. And if you want to
use pure ethers, you absolutely
still can. A lot of these
packages that we're using do
rely on ethers, but we're not
going to use just ether. So we
go to the React Morales page.
And to get started, we can just
do this bit right here. So we're
literally going to copy this and
bring it into our project. And
if you go to our package that
JSON, we actually already have
react and react DOM. So we can
just do yarn, add Morales, and
react oralis. Now you'll notice
I'm not doing these as dev
dependencies, I didn't do yarn,
add dash dash dev here. The
reason is, because for our
production builds, when we
actually create the website
here, you will need Morales and
you will need react Morales we
don't need prettier to create a
website prettier is a tool that
we're using as developers. So in
all of our projects, so far,
we've been using just dev
dependencies. That's because
we've only been building our
projects for developers, our
GitHub repos, they haven't been
made to build a website, they've
only been to do things on the
back end, for our website, we're
actually going to be building a
front end. So we need to put
this in the dependencies
section, because we need to say,
Hey, these are the ones that we
need to bundle up together for
the front end, and you can
ignore these ones. And if it's
just like a tool to make our
lives better, it's gonna go in
dev dependencies. So we're
adding Morales and react
Morales. And a lot of the syntax
that we're going to do for our
header is actually going to be
really similar to what we've
been seeing so far. So let's do
this. And then actually, we're
just going to change this name
to manual header, manual header
update imports for manual
header, you can go ahead and hit
yes to man you all header here,
we're gonna copy manual header,
make sure it's in our index.js
it we're gonna change header to
manual header, and we're gonna
change how to manual header
here. And the reason we're doing
this is because like I said,
we're going to create a much
simpler header after we create
this kind of harder one. And
we're going to want to create
that connect button, which
again, we made in HTML Funmi. By
calling eath request accounts,
what we can do actually with
Morales is we can just do this
thing called Enable Web three.
So at the top, we're going to
import, use mirallas.
From react ralis. And if you go
to the React Morales page here
or to their GitHub, you'll learn
how to set all this up too and
learn more about the
documentation. So we're going to
import use Morales from react
Morales, and inside our function
here, but outside of our return,
we're going to say const, Enable
Web three equals use mirallas.
Now use Morales is what's known
as a hook as a React hook. And
it's a way to keep track of
state in our application. Now,
in order to use mirallas, our
entire application needs to be
wrapped around what's called a
Morales provider, which is going
to be a context provider for us.
And I'll explain what that means
in a minute. But basically, what
we need to do is we need to add
this Morales provider to our
app.js. So in here, we're going
to import oralis provider from
react oralis. And we're going to
wrap our entire app around this
Morales provided so we're going
to do some little parentheses
here. New Line, we're going to
paste morass provider like this,
it's going to give us the
closing tag, copy it, paste it
like this and save. And then in
here, we're going to write in
the sheet allies on Mount equals
false. This initialize on Mount
piece here is the optionality to
hook into a server to add some
more features to our website. We
don't want to hook into a server
for this application, we want
everything just to be open
source, and we don't need any of
this additional functionality.
So we're just going to do
initialize on Mount equals
false. Now that the whole thing
is wrapped in this Morales
provider, we go to the front end
we should be able to refresh
everything looks pretty much the
same. And we can start using
these hooks. Now this use
Morales is what's known as a
hook and hooks can be a little
bit confusing to understand at
first glance, but they're
incredibly powerful and they are
the de facto way for us to build
react projects. And if you're
familiar with class components,
we're not gonna be using class
components because hooks are
much better hooks allow function
components to have access to
state and other react feature
ers state being probably one of
the biggest ones and the most
popular ones, we want our
application to be different if
we're connected to Metamask,
versus if we're not, right, if
we go back, if we go back to our
example website here, right, if
we're not connected, we want to
say, Please connect to a wallet.
And then when we are connected,
we want to go ahead and be
connected. If I have, let's say,
I have some variable like, and I
don't have this hook here, I
have like, let connected equals
false, right, or enable Web
three, or is web three enabled,
let's say I've led connected
equals false. And then I have,
you know, let's say have some
button that connects us and
changes connected to be true,
changing connected to be true is
great and all but it won't
rerender our application, you
see, when I disconnect and I
reconnect here, our application
actually changes based off of
whether or not we're connected.
And this is what we want, we
want our front end to rerender.
When we're connected, if I just
use a variable like this inside
of our component, our front end
isn't going to rerender. Or even
worse, if I use it outside, our
component doesn't even know
anything about this changing. So
hooks are a way for us to
actually work with state
especially and automatically
rerender when something changes
and enable Web three is going to
be a function that we get from
this use Morales hook to do
that. So for a lot of our
components, instead of just
saying like, let web three
enabled equals true, like we did
in normal JavaScript, we're
going to be doing a lot of this,
these hooks. For the most part,
we usually want our website to
change based off of if some
variable has changed and enabled
web three is a function that we
get from this hook that says,
Okay, go ahead and connect
Enable Web three is basically
the equivalent of saying try
await Aetherium dot request,
like this. Now enable Web three,
the way we're going to use it
here only works on Metamask. But
we will show you how to get this
kind of this cool little module
up where we can choose between
different ways to connect our
app.
We have our enabled web three,
let's go ahead and create a
button, that's going to do the
same as what we did in our HTML
Funmi in our return, but here,
instead of hi friend header,
we're going to add a new
component, or we're going to add
a new tag, we're gonna add the
button tag, and for me it
automatically close to, and I'm
just gonna call it connect, I'm
gonna go ahead and save. Now we
see a little button that says
connect. And obviously, it
doesn't do anything, we're gonna
give this some functionality,
we're gonna say on click now
since again, this is a JSX
component. This isn't raw HTML,
in raw HTML, we can't just kind
of stick JavaScript wherever we
want. But in JSX files, we can
stick JavaScript kind of
wherever we want. So inside of
this, inside of this block of
HTML, we can actually stick
JavaScript in here by adding
these little brackets. So adding
these little brackets in our
jobs can return. But here, we
can add JavaScript. And what we
want to do is we want to have
our On Click Call Enable Web
three, we're going to call an
async function, we're going to
use the arrow syntax here, one
click, we're gonna call this
async function, which is just
going to be await, Enable Web
three, await Enable Web three,
let's add the little parentheses
here. And essentially, with just
this, we've done pretty much
everything that we had back in
this big connect function here.
Now if we go back to our front
end, do a little refresh, we can
see that right now, we can see
that I'm actually connected, I'm
gonna go ahead and disconnect.
I'm still connected from some of
the last applications I was
doing, we can hit Connect, and
now we see metamath does indeed
pop up, we'll hit Next connect,
and boom. And that's all we need
to do. Now, if we look at our
Metamask, it says connected.
Great. Okay, cool. So now we
have a way to actually connect
here, let's add some
functionality and make our
application smart enough to have
the connect button if we're
connected. And if we're not
connected, not have that button.
So what we'll do now is use
Morales comes with another hook
called is web three, enabled,
which is just a variable part of
our hook that keeps track of
whether or not our Metamask is
connected. But we can actually
do one better, we can actually
check to see if there's an
account because maybe web three
is connected. But but they
didn't connect it to an account.
So let's go ahead and we'll
import count from us. Morales
will check to see if there's an
account. So what we'll do is
inside of our div tags, we'll do
a little JavaScript, we'll do
that ternary operator again,
we'll put a count here with a
question mark. And we'll do that
that same syntax that we've seen
before, we'll say account, if
account exists, do this. If
there's no account, do this. And
if there's no account, we want
to add this Connect button. So
we'll go ahead and we'll stick
this in here. If there is an
account, we'll just show that
account, right. So we'll do div
backslash div in here, we'll
just say connected, like that.
Now if we go back to our front
end, we see connected. If we do
a little refresh, it'll go away.
So we'll we'll re hit Connect,
and now we're connected, which
is great. Let's make it even
smarter. We'll have it show our
account here. So instead of just
saying connected, we'll say
connected to I'll put some
JavaScript, we'll put some
JavaScript inside of our
JavaScript. But since this is
that HTML stuff, we got to use
these brackets to say JavaScript
again. So we'll put JavaScript
inside of the JavaScript, we'll
say connected to, we can just
say account. Now go back to our
front end, we see connected to
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
you'll notice if you hit
refresh, you'll have to
reconnect, we'll get to that in
a minute, what a lot of people
do is they'll do a count dot
slice, zero, comma six. And then
outside of the brackets, they'll
do dot that dot, another set of
brackets account, that slice,
count dot length minus four,
close that off like that, we
have our account, when we hit
Connect, now it says connected
to blah, blah, blah, hello. And
because of these hooks, when I
switch accounts, and I connect
with these new accounts, it even
automatically re renders
switching accounts. So these
hooks are really good for re
rendering our websites whenever
some value changes. For example,
if I said like, let count number
equals seven, and we had a
button, that updated account
number, our front end wouldn't
rerender unless we told it
specifically to rerender, which
gets really annoying. So hooks
kind of help us a lot with doing
that. And it allows us to keep
track of states between renders.
Now, here's something that right
now it doesn't do, if I hit
refresh, I have to re hit this
connect button, even though my
Metamask says, Hey, we're
connected. But if I refresh, I
have to re hit this Connect
button. Why is this happening.
Or when I hit refresh, our
website doesn't know that we've
hit enable Web three already,
right, because we basically go
back to blank when I refresh,
and then I have to hit Connect,
which is really obnoxious and
really annoying. So we want to
add some functionality, so that
automatically the instant we
render, we go ahead and we check
to see if we're already
connected. And if we're
connected to show this. Now to
do that, we can use another hook
called use effect. And this is a
core react hook. So we'll do
import use effect from react
like this. This is a core hook
directly from react. And it's
one of the most popular out
there along with use state. And
we've left some links to
learning more about the effect
hook in the GitHub repo
associated with this course, I'm
gonna give you my summary of
basically what this use effect
does, we basically have this
function called use effect,
which takes two parameters, it
takes a function as its first
parameter, and then second, it
optionally takes a dependency
array. And what this use effect
is going to do is it's going to
keep checking the values in this
dependency array. And if
anything in this dependency rate
changes, it's going to call some
function, and then rerender, the
front end. So for example, using
Morales comes with this function
called is web three enabled or
this variable called is what
three enabled. If we add this to
our dependency array, what we
can do in our use effect is do
console dot log, hi. And then we
can do console dot log is web
three enabled, what this use
effect is going to be doing is
it's going to constantly be
running, this is running all the
time. And it's going to be
listening to see if is web three
enabled changes, right? And
anytime we run Enable Web three
is web three enabled becomes
true. So so now if we go to the
front end, we do a little
refresh, we see high false, high
false. Now why do we see this
twice is web three enabled only
changed once? Well, this is
because of how use effect works,
it will automatically run on
load or right or the first time
it does and then it'll run
checking the value. So we're
basically seeing this run twice,
it runs the first time we load
it, and then it'll check the
value and run again. So we see
go twice, even though it's
really just once. But if we go
back here, sorry, let me just do
a quick reload again. We hit
Connect, we now see Hi is now
true, because it saw is what
three enabled change to true
because enabled web three made
is what enabled return true. And
it ran this again, right. So
that's how that actually works.
And there's a couple of
different ways to think about
this. Actually, we actually
don't even need to give this an
array. And what happens if we
don't give this an array? Well,
let's refresh. We'll hit
Connect, and we'll see it's
still ran a couple of times. So
if we don't give it array, no
dependency array, it'll run any
time something re renders. And
you need to be careful with
this. Because then you can get
circular renders, if you have
some use effect that changes
some value. And you have another
use effect that re renders when
that value changes while they're
both just going to keep changing
back and back and forth. So no
dependency array like this. It
will run anytime something re
renders we'll give it a blank
dependency array. It'll just run
once on load, just run one time.
So now like we have a blank
dependency right in here, we
reload. Right? We see that it
runs twice. That's actually
because we're basically re
rendering once in the
background. So it really is just
running Once but there's
something else going on in the
background. So it looks like
it's running twice. Now if we
just add is web three enabled,
do a little refresh, it'll do
the exact same thing, it'll run
the same amount as if this was
blank. But when we connect,
it'll add here. If this was a
blank array, when we refresh,
we'll see kick out twice, which
should be ones. But like I said,
there's something going on in
the background. If we hit
connect. Now, we don't see
anything here, because the blank
dependency array says, Hey, I'm
only going to run one time on
load. Now, if there's our stuff
in this array, like is web three
enabled, it's going to run
anytime something in this array
changes, right. So again, we'll
refresh will connect, we see it
ran again, after a hit Connect
will refresh. Hi, hi connected,
ran one more time. So so that's
kind of the cheat sheet here. If
we give it no dependency array,
it's going to run any time
anything in this project re
renders, if we give it a blank
dependency array, it's just
going to run one time, or like
we saw, it ran twice. But that's
because there's something else
we render in the background. And
if we give it dependencies in
this array, it's going to run
anytime something in this array
changes. And this is really
helpful, because oftentimes,
we're going to want our front
ends to rerender, this use
effect will say, oh, cool, some
value changed, I'm going to run
this function, and then I'm
going to rerender, your front
end.
And now we're going to use this
use effect thing to make sure
that when we refresh, it
remembers that we're actually
connected. So how do we do that
inside here, we are going to use
this is web three enabled thing.
And the first thing that we want
to just do is we want to say if
is what three enabled, then
we'll just return. Because if
we're already connected to web
three, then we don't need to do
anything. Now, if we're not
connected to web three, and we
don't have an account, we'll
want to go ahead and call Enable
Web three, right want to
automatically enable Web three.
So now if I go back, you'll see
with just this code, I'm just
always automatically calling
Enable Web three. But this can
get really annoying. Because if
I disconnect, right, let's go
disconnect everything. Now
refresh, it's going to always
call Enable Web three, right,
every time we refresh, it's
going to automatically call
enabled through without us even
hitting the Connect button. So
that's no good to we want to
actually see if we're connected.
So the way we do this, like I
said, we want to use our local
storage, again, application, or
these little, this little thing
here go to Application, we want
our we want our application to
remember that somebody hit this
connect button, and they went
and connected to us. So what
we're going to do is in our
little onClick function down
here, we're not just going to
call await Enable Web three,
we're also going to store a
little remembrance here saying,
Hey, we actually did connect
recently. So below this, we're
going to run window, dot local
storage, dot set item,
connected, comma injected. I'm
actually going to comment this
out for now, because my friend
is just going to keep popping up
like that. So what this does is
we're saying, okay, in our
window, because again, if you go
back to the window, you go to
console, a type window, you're
actually going to see this giant
window thing here, right, which
we showed you before, there's
always this window object in
here. And we're going to do
window dot local storage, which
relates to if we go to this
application section, this local
storage section here, that set
item connected to inject it. So
we're going to set a new key
value in here, we're doing it
like this because in the future,
maybe you want to do you know
connect it to Wallet connect or
connected to Coinbase wallet or
something, right, but we're just
gonna say injected, meaning
we're connected to that meta
mask. And in some versions of
next, Jas next, Jas has a hard
time knowing about this window
variable. So we can just do if
type of window does not equal
equal, undefined, then we're
going to do this. So we're just
making sure that window doesn't
equal undefined that there is a
window. So now if I go back to
the front end, and I hit
Connect, and we go ahead, and we
connect here, we'll see now in
our application, local storage,
we'll see we've added this
connected injected bit here,
we're storing in the browser
that we are indeed connected to
this. Now that we've added this
into our browser, we can roll
back up to our use effect here
and say, Okay, if they're
already connected, great, we'll
be done. But before we do
anything, let's check to see if
they have this here. And if they
already are connected, let's