just run that connect bit. So
we'll say if type of window does
not equal, undefined, right,
because we want to check for
that window object. Again, we'll
say if window dot local storage
dot get item connected,
connected, so if that connected
key exists, then we'll just run
Enable Web three. So now We have
some functionality in here,
which even when we refresh, it
will automatically run enable of
three for us. So now if I go
ahead and refresh the front end,
we don't have to press that
connect button anymore, because
it goes, Oh, I see that locally,
we stored this connected key
whenever you refresh. Now, it
checks for this first it sees it
and then runs enabled web three.
Now on the other side, though,
if we're in here, and now we
disconnect, and then we refresh.
This will show up, which is
really annoying. And every time
we refresh, it'll keep showing
up, which we don't want. We want
it to be that when we
disconnect, we tell it hey,
we've we've gone ahead and
disconnected here. So back in
our application, we can add
another use effect to check to
see if we've disconnected. So
let's create another use effect.
That's going to costly just look
for us being connected, we'll
say use effect, do a little
arrow bracket thing here. And
we're going to do this anytime.
And oh my goodness, anytime I
save, it's going to keep popping
up. So I'm just going to just
going to comment that out for
now. So in here, we want to say
okay, whatever, there's a
rerender we want to run if any
account has changed. And Morales
has some functionality for us to
do this as well. So from user
morass, we're going to import
more Alice, and then down here
in our use effect. Inside the
little function, we're gonna say
mirallas.on account, changed
of account, we're gonna do some
stuff. So on account changed,
takes a function as an input
parameter. So we'll say console
dot log, account, change to
account. And what we can do is
we can check to see if this
account is not. And we can say
if account equals equals no,
then if the account is null, we
can assume they've disconnected.
So we can say window dot local
storage, dot remove item,
connected, we'll also run a
deactivate web three function.
So from Ross, deactivate, web
three will also run, deactivate
web three, which is going to set
is web three enabled to false.
So we're going to disconnect the
web three, and then we're going
to say console dot log.
No
count found. So let's try this
out. Now. Let's go back to our
front end, we'll do a little
refresh here. So right now it
says we're connected. Even
though in my meta mask, we're
not connected, right? And to
start from scratch here, you can
go ahead and disconnect it. But
but my browser says, Hey, we're
connected, right? So now we'll
connect. And we'll actually be
connected right, next connect,
and it and it just overrode
connected, you know, with
inject, let's, let's make this
injected. And then we'll remove
Yep, okay, injected, we'll
refresh, like, connect, and now
it says injected. Okay, cool. So
now we're connected here. If in
here, if I just switch accounts,
right, let's go to Account
three, I'll connect. If we go
back to our console real quick,
we'll say account change to
blah, blah, blah, I can change
back, right, we'll go change
account change to blah, blah,
blah. Now, if we go back to our
application, go in here. And we
disconnect. Now let's disconnect
both of these disconnect. And
disconnect. We'll see it's now
been removed from local storage.
And if we go to our console,
it'll say, no account, change
the No, no account found and
removed it. Now if I hit
refresh, nothing happens here, I
can go ahead and connect. Right
next connect, I can refresh.
Oops, I need to go back in here
and re enable this. So sorry,
let's add this back in here. But
now it can refresh. Let's go
ahead and disconnect here. Let's
connect. Let's go back to the
console, we can connect thing
will pop up next connect, I can
refresh. It stays connected for
me, I can switch accounts, I can
go ahead and here, I can switch
accounts, I can even disconnect.
And it will automatically update
for me, which is what we want.
So now we've essentially made a
way more robust connect button,
where it goes back and forth
with when we're connected now.
Now one more thing that we might
want to do, or application is
when we hit Connect, we want to
maybe disable this button,
right? We don't want it to allow
it to be able to be pressed. So
I'm gonna hit Cancel, we're just
gonna add one more bit of
functionality here, we're going
to add this is web three enable
loading. And what this does is
it just checks to see if
Metamask has popped up. And so
what our button after the on
click section, we can add
disabled. Equals is web three
enable loading, so it'll be
disabled if we're loading here.
So let's go ahead and we'll
disconnect disconnect. Now we'll
hit Connect, and you'll see the
button can be clicked. So that
just makes it a little bit nice.
Turn, Next connect Bada bing,
bada boom, awesome, we have just
made a way more robust front end
than what we had before this
connect button is super slick.
And it allows us to kind of flip
back and forth. And our
application is incredibly
powerful and knows how to handle
all these different changes. Now
that we've learned how to do it
the manual way, let me give you
the Chiti way, in our
components, we're gonna create a
new file header dot j s, and
what we're going to do is we're
going to install this web three
UI kit, it's a front end kit,
and it has a whole bunch of
these components already built
for us. So we can build like a
header component and a connect
button component just by using
this. So to install, install it,
we're gonna come back here,
we're gonna stop our front end.
And we're just going to run
yarn, add web three UI kit, like
that. And again, we don't want
this to be a dev dependency,
because it is going to be a part
of our website, and then we'll
do in our header.js, we'll do
import connect button from web
three UI kit. And then we'll do
export default function header.
And then all we'll do is return
do like a div. And then inside
this div, we'll do next button.
With a little backslash here, we
aren't going to need this for
this project. But if we want to
be super explicit, we'll say
Morales off equals false. Just
again, to reiterate, hey, we're
not trying to connect to a
server here just to make that
super explicit. But this connect
button does everything, this
manual header thing that we just
created, does. So back in our
index.js, we can comment or
delete this line will do import
header from dot dot slash
components slash header. And
then instead of manual header,
we'll just do header. We start
our app back up with yarn dev
again,
we go back to the page, we do a
little refresh here, we now see
we have this connect Wallet
button. And it's even looks a
lot nicer. It's got some nice
styling to it as well, we can
hit Connect wallet. And it'll
give us this little ngModel
asking us which wallet we want
to connect to. So asking us
which wall we want to connect to
is kind of similar in our manual
header to this or set item
connected, injected, right or
wallet connect, it would do
connected wallet Connect for
trust wallet, it would it would
set item as connected wallet
connect, etc. So it allows us to
connect in different ways. And
we if we hit Metamask, we go
ahead and connect like so even
had some nice styling here where
it gives us our wallet address
here. But it also gives us our
wallet balance as well. And
again, if we go ahead and
disconnect, we'll see it
automatically disconnect. We
connect like so we can reconnect
like so boom, boom. If we switch
accounts, it's smart enough to
know that we're switching
accounts. So I know I showed you
kind of the hard way. But I
wanted to show you kind of
what's going on. It's setting
this local storage in the
background so that it knows
which where it's actually
connected. But for headers
moving forward, this is all you
need. And your life will be
drastically drastically easier.
And let's just add a centralized
lottery or decentralized raffle
or whatever you want to our
header as well. So it says
decentralized lottery, you know
the button Hello. Now that we
have that, what else do we need?
Well, well, the main thing that
this app needs to do is just
have a big button that says
enter the lottery. And then
ideally, you know, show how many
people are in the lottery and
then the recent winner as well.
So let's go ahead, we'll create
a new component called lottery
entrance. And we'll grab that
component similar to like what
we did with our header, we'll
drop this component right here.
And then our app will pretty
much be done. So let's create
this lottery entrance component,
lottery entrance, that Jas,
right and again, in the reason
we're putting these in
components, we could 100% Stick
it all, you know all our code in
here to make it more modular so
that we in the future, if we
want to have more pages or do
other stuff, I'm going to zoom
out a little bit just so that we
can see all of our code a little
bit easier. This is our whole
index j s. This is our whole
header. Let's create a new
lottery entrance app just for
the boilerplate code here we're
going to export default lottery
entrance, excuse me, export
default function, lottery
entrance, and this is just going
to be you know, another
component where we're going to
return some that JSX HTML stuff,
right? So we're gonna do div and
do like hi from lottery
entrance, Excel. And now that we
do that, we can go back to our
index.js. We can do import
lottery entrance from dot dot
slash components. Slash lottery
entrance, will stick it right
underneath the header like that.
And if we go back to our
website, we see high from
lottery entrance so our lottery
entrance is going to be right
underneath the header would
Here's what we want. And then
we'll delete this line that
says, Hello. So lottery
entrance, what is the what is
the first thing that we really
need to do in here? Well, we're
going to want to have a function
to call the lottery to enter the
lottery. Let's go ahead and do
this. Now let's go back to how
we did this with HTML fund me
recall that old fun function
like this, but doing it like
this won't rerender. And there's
a whole lot of other
functionality that doing it like
this won't give us so we're
going to use Morales to actually
call some of these functions,
because mirallas has in React
mirallas. Again, they have hooks
for us to do pretty much
anything we want to do. And one
of these hooks is called use web
three contract. And what this
does is it gives us a hook that
will give us the data returned
from a function called an error
returned, a little function that
we can use to call any function.
And then we also have these
really helpful is fetching in is
loading. So if we want everyone
to have our UI or our website,
do something while it's fetching
or while it's loading the
transaction, we can use these
two variables to do that. And
then all we need to do is we
just need to pass it the
contract information, which
similar to ethers is going to be
the ABI contract address, we'll
pass the function name, and then
any parameters for that
function. So we're going to use
this syntax here to make that
transaction to the blockchain.
And to call these functions. So
what we're going to do is we're
going to import us web three
contract
from react mirallas. And inside
our function, but before I
return, of course, we're going
to say const. And then we'll do
kind of exactly what we see in
here. For now, let's just get
the function, let's just get
this run contract function,
because this is going to be the
function that we can call to
actually enter the lottery. So
we'll say const, run contract
function, and we're actually
going to call this enter raffle.
And we'll say equals, use web
three contract, and we need to
pass the ABI, we're gonna need
to pass the contract address,
we're gonna need to give it the
function name, we'll need to
give it the params, which
actually we do know it's going
to be blank. But then finally,
we will need the message value.
Because if we remember back into
raffle doesn't take any
parameters, all it takes is this
message dot value bit. So that's
all we're going to need to pass.
So how do we get all this stuff,
and I'm going to leave this in
here. But we're going to comment
it out for now, because this is
what we need to do. But we need
to get all of this stuff into
our code here. So how do we
actually get all that stuff?
Well, ABI is easy, right? Abi
isn't going to change at all, no
matter what network or on ABI is
always going to stay the same.
Now if you've already deployed
your smart contracts, and you
know exactly what address it is,
because you've deployed to a
main net, or you've deployed to
a test net, all this stuff isn't
really going to change. And we
can just hard code it all right
into here. Or we can do what a
lot of people do is they'll
create a constants folder. And
in here, they'll add like an API
dot JSON, maybe they'll add a
contract addresses dot JSON. And
then they'll add maybe like an
index dot j s or something,
we're gonna build our
application in a way we can
actually test locally using our
own Hard Hat Network, and then
compare it to what it looks like
on the actual test net as well.
So we're going to make it
network agnostic. So the front
end works exactly the same no
matter what network that we're
on. And we can go back, download
a directory back into our CD,
hard hat smart contract lottery
Free Code Camp, and spin up our
node here, right with hh node or
yarn hard hat node. And we'll
use this as the blockchain that
we're going to connect to. The
thing is, if I go back here, and
I'm building the front end, and
I go, ah, like this would be
better if we did X, Y, or Z. And
maybe I changed the name of some
functions, you know, blah, blah,
blah, something else, I want
that change to be reflected on
my front end. And I want to be
able to code my front end as
such. So since we are the only
developer right now, we kind of
have the ability of where we
both know, the back end code and
the front end code. So something
that I like to do to make my
life a little bit easier is I
like to create an update front
end deploy script. So after we
deploy stuff, we run a little
script that will create this
constants folder for us with a
whole bunch of stuff, right?
It'll give an ABI, it'll give
contract addresses and anything
else we might need in our front
end from our back end. So what I
like to do is I like to come
back to my original code and an
update this for a new script. So
I'll come in here in this deploy
script, I'll create a new file,
and I'll call it oh two or even
like 9999, up, date, front, and
dot Jas. And the reason I do 99,
obviously, is because we want
this to be always the last
script in our deploy folder. And
then we can just write a little
script that's connected. We just
write a little script that's
connected to our front end here
so that whenever we deploy
contracts, no matter what chain,
we can update that constants
folder on our front end. So
let's go ahead and create that
script right now we'll do module
dot exports, equals async
function. And we'll add all our
stuff in here, we don't really
need to deploy any contracts,
because we're just updating the
front end. So we can just leave
the parameters of this one
blank. And the other thing I
like to do, because sometimes I
don't care about the front end,
what I'll do is I'll only update
the front end if we've specified
a dot env variable. So I'll
create a dot env variable called
up date, front end. And then
I'll set this to true. And now
in our script here, we can say
if process dot E and V dot
update, front end. And we can
just say like console dot log,
updating front end. And now back
in here, right, if a mat if I'm
in the correct directory in
here, if our own hard hit
Deploy,
you know, get this little
updating front end. And now we
can update front end. So let's
do it. So I'm actually going to
create one function called
Update contract addresses. And
this is going to be our function
that we're going to use to
update contract addresses, then
I'm going to make one called
Update API, where we just update
the API's and the front end so
so we're going to call this
update contract addresses. So
I'm going to create a new
function async function, update
contract addresses. And first,
we're going to get that raffle
contract since we're going to
need to get its address. So
we're gonna say const, raffle
equals await. And we're gonna do
the same thing we've been doing
ethers dot get contract, raffle,
and then my VS code auto
imported, it doesn't const
ethers equals require Hardhead,
like so. So we have raffle in
here. And we're gonna want to
pass this raffle address to our
front end, since this is going
to be a variable that we might
use a lot of places, we can just
add it like const, front end
location, addresses file,
equals, and we're going to give
it the relative path to where we
are now, which is going to be
you know, if we see the download
directory to next year's smart
contract lottery, FCC, I can
even just copy this, paste that
in here. And then it's in the
constants folder, and it's going
to be contract addresses dot
JSON. And let's get the ABI
file, we'll say const. Front and
a bi file is going to equal and
this is going to be nearly the
same thing. So we can just copy
paste that. And then we'll do
slash API dot JSON. And now in
our update contract addresses
function, we can say const,
current addresses, equals and we
can read again, in our front
end, we can read from this file.
So I'll usually start out with
just two brackets. So that's
like JSON compatible in both of
these files. And so to read it,
we're gonna say JSON dot parse,
FS dot read file sync, we're
gonna have to import, say const.
FS equals require, I know we've
used Fs extra in the past, but
this one, we're just gonna use
Fs, which is going to be our
front and addresses file, we're
going to read it in with UTF
eight encoding. So now this is
going to be our current
addresses. And we're going to
update the list of current
addresses with some new
addresses. Because our contract
addresses we want this to be
chain agnostic, we would do
something like for you know, and
then the addresses on rink B, we
could do 31337, and then the
addresses on our local host,
right, we want to be able to
keep track of all the different
addresses across all the
different chains. So back in our
function here, then we'll say if
if network, dot config dot chain
id.to string in contract
addresses that were config ideas
in there, then we're just gonna
go ahead and add this new
contract address in there. But
before we add this new address
in there, let's just check to
make sure it's not are already
in there. So we're just gonna
say if contract addresses of
network dot config dot chain
id.to string, this is so long, I
don't want to keep writing that
I'm gonna say const chain ID
equals network, config that
chain id.to string, and we're
just gonna use chain ID. If
chain ID and contract address
then if we don't already have
that includes raffle dot
address. We're gonna go ahead
and add this new address and
then if the chain ID doesn't
even exist, we're gonna go ahead
and do contract addresses
current addresses, equals or
assuming current addresses of
chain ID equals and then we'll
just create a new array, raffled
that out address. So we're
saying if the chain ID doesn't
exist in current addresses,
we're just going to add this new
array in there. And then
finally, now that we've updated
its object, we're gonna write it
back to this file, we'll say Fs
dot write, file sync, front and
addresses file. And then we're
gonna do JSON dot string of
five. So we're going to
Stringify this JSON object, so
we're just gonna go ahead and
write it back. And then bottom
module that exports that tags
equals all and then front end. I
cool. So we have a function to
update the contract addresses,
but we also need the ABI. So
we're gonna do date API, and
we're gonna create another
function async function, update
API. And in here, we're gonna do
the exact same thing on raffle
equals await ethers that
contract,
raffle FX dot right file, sync,
front and abi. It's just going
to copy paste it front end, AVI
file. And then to pass just the
ABI, we can actually get it
directly from this raffle
object, we can actually just do
raffle dot interface that format
ethers dot utils, dot format
types, dot JSON. If you look in
the ethers, Docs, ethers has
this contract dot interface
thing which returns an interface
which is different from a
solidity interface. But it
allows us basically just to get
the API with this one line of
code. So in our back end code
here, now if you run h h deploy
or H H node, we should
automatically update our
contract addresses in our API
dot JSON. So let's go and try
this. So we'll run h h node. So
we'll start a node, right in
this terminal over here, we'll
flip back to the front end. And
if we open ABI to JSON, we do
indeed, now see, we have the
raffle API in this file. And if
we go to contract addresses, we
see on network 31337, here's our
first address, right. And if we
deploy to different chains, this
will get populated with
different network IDs, and then
a list of addresses associated
with them. So it helps make our
front ends a lot easier to
maintain, and bounce around and
kind of test and work with. Now
that we've done all this, we can
actually close our hardhat smart
contract lottery Free Code Camp,
the hard hat project for this,
and we're just going to have all
of our terminals be in here. So
what we're gonna do is we're
gonna go down and directory CD
dot dot, and we're going to cd
into Oh, sorry, we're actually
we're already in their CDs, hard
hat, smart contract, lottery
Free Code Camp. And then in this
one, we're going to run hh node
or yarn hardhat node. Now we'll
have a local blockchain running
so we can test everything that
we're doing in the front end,
actually, I'm gonna move this up
one. So now in our first area,
here, we have our front end code
running, then we have our
blockchain running. And then in
this one, we're just going to
add, you know, whatever we want
to add. Now, we can actually go
ahead and hit this little X
button here to close the panel.
So that's just hiding the panel,
these are all still out, they
only get trashed when you
actually hit the little
trashcan. So we're just going to
close the panel. But all those
terminals are still running, I
promise back. So where were we?
Okay, back to our function here.
So we just automated the process
of updating our API's and then
updating our contracts as well.
And now we can import these into
our files. Now we can import
them one at a time, it'd be like
import API, from dot dot slash
constants, slash API, or we
could do something a little bit
clever is we could export these
in the same file. So if we
create a new file, a new
index.js, in here, we can import
them and then export them in
this one file. We can say const,
contract editor says equals
require dot slash contract
editor dot JSON, and then const
API equals require dot slash API
dot JSON. And then we'll do
module dot exports equals API
and contract addresses. So now
once we export them like this
back in our lottery entrance, we
can import them just in one
line. So we'll say import API
comma contract addresses from
dot dot slash constants. So we
can just specify the folder
instead of each individual
files, because we have this
index dot j s here, which
basically represents this whole
folder. Back in here, what do we
have now? Let's uncomment this
abi. Okay, great. We have the
ABI we're importing it from our
constants, folder, contract
addresses, we have our contract
addresses. And we're going to
need to specify the network ID
in just a second here. We have
the function name here, which is
going to be what enter the
raffle. There are no params. So
all we need to do so how do we
get both the chain ID and then
Also the message dot value will
change, it is something that we
can get really easily with
Morales, let's comment this
whole section out one more time,
just so I can show you something
we can do import. Once again,
we're going to get that use
Morales book from react Morales.
And what we can do is we can say
const.
Chain ID equals use ralis. Now,
the reason morality knows about
what chain we're on is because
back in our header component,
the header actually passes up
all the information about the
Metamask to the Morales
provider. And then the Morales
provider passes it down to all
the components inside those
Morales provided tags
concentrated equals use Morales.
And I'm just gonna do a little
console log chain ID because I
want to show you what it looks
like. So if we do a little
refresh, and we're in the
console here, we can ignore some
of these warnings here, but we
see the chain ID is actually 0x
Five, well, because I'm on the
rink B chain or the Grilley
chain excuse me, if I switch
back to hard hat localhost,
which you should know how to do
from a SEMA fun we bet if you
don't have hard hat localhost
and your Metamask go back to
that HTML font we bit follow
that along. Okay, great. Now
it's going to print this Oh x
bla bla bla bla bla. So that
might be a little bit confusing.
But this is the hex version of
our chain ID. Right. So let's
switch to Etherium main net. Now
we pronounce Oh x one, right?
Oh, x one is the hex version of
the number one. So chain ID
gives us the hex addition of the
chain ID. So I don't want the
hex addition, I want the actual
number. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say Okay, chain
ID, your name is actually going
to be chain ID hex. And we can
do console dot log chain ID hex,
but I want the number. So what
we can do is parse a built in
JavaScript parse int, CIN ID hex
like that. Now if I go back,
we'll do a little refresh here.
Scroll away from the warning, we
can see the one here. Now let's
switch to hard hat, localhost.
We'll scroll down we see 31337.
So use Morales chain ID returns
the hex we parse it with Parson
to get the actual number. Okay,
great. So we can stick the chain
ID into here. Now this raffle
address is something that we're
actually going to use a lot, we
might as well have it be at the
top of our code here, we aren't
going to be changing the raffle
address. So we don't need to put
it in a hook. We are going to
technically be changing the
address when we change networks.
But our header app takes care of
re rendering and dealing with
all that. So we can just make
this a constant variable. So we
can say const, raffle address
equals, first let's check the
chain ID hex and if there's a
chain ID hex and if there's not
a chain ID hex we're gonna do
something else. Excuse me, we're
gonna say chain ID hex in
contract addresses. And
actually, there's never gonna be
a chain ID hex. So we'll do
const chain ID equals Gen ID hex
parsed, Parsons, chinati hex,
and you might be thinking, hey,
this, these are both the same
name. Well, what we're doing up
here in use Morales is we're
saying hey, pull out the chin ID
object, and then rename it to
chain ID hex and down here,
we're saying, Hey, we're going
to create a new variable called
Chain ID. So we'll say contract
addresses of chain ID at zero.
So in here, we're saying this
network ID and this address,
otherwise, we'll just say no.
Okay, we're getting there. Let's
uncomment this, now we have the
raffle address, and we can just
stick it in here. All we do now
is the message dot value. If we
remember back to our raffle, we
actually set that fee
dynamically. So we have in here
we do entrance fee equals
entrance fee, which is the
parameter in the constructor. So
we want to call this get
entrance fee function. This is
one of the ways we can send a
transaction. And we can also
send functions, one of the ways
that we're going to do it right
when our lottery entrance loads,
we're going to run a function to
read that entrance fee value. So
how do we do that? Well, we can
use one of our hooks again,
right use effect use effect can
run right when something
changes, we're only going to
want to try to get that raffle
entrance fee if web three is
enabled. So what we can do is
back up in here and use Morales
will pull in that is web three
enabled. And we'll have our use
effect in our function, we'll
just say if this is web three
enabled, then we'll try to read.
So we can go ahead and use this
use web three, contract Wagan.
Let's go ahead and just copy
paste this. And we'll use the
same setup here. Except instead
of enter raffle, of course,
we're going to be doing get
entrance fee. So we're going to
get entrance fee. We need the
API we got it raffle address got
it. This is going to be the
function name is going to be get
entrance fee params nothing
message that value, nothing.
We're going to be calling this
get entrance fee function. And
now I finally show you how to
actually call one of these in
our contracts here. Use web
three contract, download our use
effect, we're actually going to
call get entrance fee. Now if we
just call get entrance fee like
this, and we say like, you know,
const something equals get
entrance fee and then console
dot log something, what do you
think's going to happen? And
oops, I need to import, I need
to import use effect from react.
There we go. We look or logs, I
don't see console dot log,
something won't get entrance fee
is going to be an async
function. Once again, we need to
wait we would need to do a wait
get into T, right? There's an
issue we can't call await in our
use effect. So what can we do?
Well, we can actually make an
async function, call it update
UI. And then we can stick this
inside of the async function
here. And we can call update UI
right outside of it like this.
So now we go back to our front
end, we do a little refresh. And
if we scroll up, we still see
nothing. Well, is web three
enabled actually changes. So the
first time that this runs, is
web three enabled probably is
false. But when it turns to
true, we want to we want to run
this section in our little
dependency array. We're going to
add this in here, right? And the
reason that it's false to start
with is because of exactly what
we showed in that manual header,
right? What does it do? Well,
first, we check to see after we
do a refresh, if window dot
local storage get item is
connected, then we call Enable
Web three, which will make this
enabled. So in our lottery
entrance, is what they're
enabled starts off as false when
we do a refresh. And then the
browser checks the local storage
says, oh, web three should be
enabled, let's enable it and
turn to true. So now if we hit
save, and we do a little refresh
in our console, we can now see
the logged out entrance fee. So
then we'll switch this to
entrance fee from contract. Now,
we also probably want to show
this entrance fee on our UI, if
we do let entrance fee, we'll
say equals blank. And we'll take
this and we'll update, you know,
and we'll update this just
saying entrance fee equals await
entrance fee. Cool. Now we have
this as kind of a global
variable, we can add it in here.
And then let's even do a weight
entrance fee. But this whole
thing in parentheses, and then
do.to string, and we can even
console dot log entrance fee.
Now we're adding in a new
browser. But there's still an
issue here. Let's see if you can
spot it, we'll do a little
refresh.
We don't see the entrance fee in
the UI here. But we do see it
good console dot log out, right.
And again, this is going to be
in a way here, what is going on
here will use effect is going to
rerender our browser, right? And
that's what we want is what
three enable goes from false to
true, our browser re renders
watch, once we get our entrance
fee, does our browser rerender?
No, it does not because entrance
fee is just one of these normal
variables, right. So we want to
actually change this from being
just a normal variable to being
a hook because entrance fee does
get updated, but it's not
triggering a rerender. So we
actually want to change this to
being what's called a use state
hook. So you can read some more
on the documentation about the
using the state hook, it's kind
of the same as doing let
entrance fee, you know, equals
blah, blah, blah, and setting it
below. But it also will trigger
a rerender for us. And to do it,
we actually do const entrance
fee, comma, set entrance fee
equals use state zero import use
state from react as well. So
basically, entrance fee is going
to be our value, right, so if we
do console dot log entrance fee,
it's going to print out the
entrance fee entrance fee is
going to be the variable we call
to get the entrance fee, the
entrance fee is going to be the
function we call to update or
set that entrance fee. And
whatever that this entrance fee
variable is set, we trigger a
rerender. From the front end, we
have the state or the actual
variable in the function to
update it. And then in the use
state here, we just give it its
starting values we're saying
entrance fee is going to start
out as zero. So now that we know
that, let's go back down here,
and instead of saying entrance
fee equals this, we can say
const entrance fee from call
equals away entrance fee.to
string and then we can say set
entrance fee to this entrance
fee from call. And now when we
set the use state, we're going
to trigger a rerender. So
entrance fee will actually be
populated. Now if we go to our
browser, do a little refresh
here. We can see that the
entrance fee has indeed been re
rendered here and we can
actually see it here. We see the
console dot log of zero here
even though we're doing console
dot log entrance fee because
this set entrance to function
hasn't finished running it
basically. So we're just gonna
get rid of that line will
refresh and Bada bing bada boom,
this huge number is kind of
gross. We might even want to
update it so that it looks a
little bit nicer. So once again,
we can import ethers, ethers
from ethers. And down below,
we'll do a little ethers dot
utils dot format units. And
we'll do entrance fee from call
and we'll do a comma and type
in. And if we refresh on the
front end, now we can see,
entrance fee is 0.1. So we can
even label this we'll say
entrance fee, blah, blah, blah.
Now if we do a little refresh on
the front end, entrance fee 0.1
E.
Finally, we have the entrance
fee, and now uses finally on our
function to enter the lottery.
So let's finally uncomment this
out. And for message value,
we're going to want to use this
entrance fee. And I'm realizing
it's actually better to store
this in its raw to string
format. So we're going to undo
this part that we just did.
We're going to add it down here.
So we're going to ethers, that
format units, entrance fee,
comma, ether, like that. So that
like that, and let's comment
this back out real quick. So
that at least in the UI, it
shows up at 0.1. But on the back
end, we're actually going to
save it as its raw, and have way
value. So we're saying that we
have this entrance fee and what
we can do uncomment, this, we
can just grab this entrance fee,
and plop it in here. So we need
to make a button that's gonna do
that. Now again, we want to make
our code that all this works,
even if we're connected to a
supported chain, though. So
before we even add this, right,
if we switch from hard hat to
like, Aetherium main net, do a
little refresh. We're getting
kind of get an error here,
because we're calling get
entrance fee.to string on an
address that doesn't exist,
right? So it's gonna get really
confused and be like, hey, what,
what are you doing here? Let's
add a little button here so that
we can actually enter the
raffle. Before we actually do
that, let's make sure that we
can only call the function so
long as there actually is a
raffle address. So we'll do
raffle address. And we'll do
this ternary operator once
again. So that only if this
raffle address is valid, right?
And it's not, no, we'll add all
this code here, right. So we'll
say if the raffle address
exists, we're going to do some
stuff. And for now, we can
actually just copy paste this
line, stick it in here. And then
otherwise, we'll say div.
Excellence div, close it off.
We'll save reformat, great.
We'll say no raffle address,
detected. Now we'll just do all
of our code in this section up
here. So we have this little div
here, which is great. Inside of
this div, let's add a button.
Button button, we'll save it got
a little button here, we'll have
it say, enter raffle. And we'll
say on click, well, we're going
to do some JavaScript. So let's
do some JavaScript, we want to
call an async function async
function. So I know the double
brackets is going to be
confusing, right. But these
brackets allow us to do
JavaScript in our HTML, or JSX,
or whatever. And these brackets
represent this function, it's
going to an async function. And
we're gonna say, await, enter
raffle. And that's it. So let's
go back to the front end. Now we
have a little enter raffle
function. If we do refresh,
let's just make sure our account
is reset here. So we're gonna go
down to settings, advanced,
reset accounts, yes. I hit ENTER
raffle. metamath does indeed pop
up. And we can go ahead and
confirm. Awesome, okay, we can
now enter our raffle. We're
doing incredibly well with this.
As you saw, we just got that pop
up. And that was pretty much it,
right? It's not very helpful for
the users who are following
along with this to look at this
and go, Okay, did it go through?
Or we did it fail, like, what,
what just happened? So what we
want to do is create what's
called notifications, right? We
want a little pop up saying,
Hey, you sent your transaction,
great job, we're going to use a
library. Again, we're going to
use the web through UI Kit,
which comes with some
notifications that we can go
ahead and use. So if you come to
this little interactive thing,
which is right in their GitHub,
there's a whole bunch of stuff
in here. And you can actually
click around and play with
different buttons and different
things. And you can actually go
ahead and even go to docs for
each one of these. And you can
go show code. And you can
literally like copy paste code
into your project, like whatever
you want to do styling and
everything for us. So back in
our app dot j s, we're going to
add import, no to vacations
provider from web three UI kit
and inside of the Morales
provider, but outside of the
components, we're gonna do
notification provider
notification provide Add it like
this. So it goes Morales
provider notification provider
component. So wrapping our
component in this notifications
thing, and that's notification
provider not notifications. And
this is going to allow us to
actually make notifications back
in our lottery entrance. Back in
our lottery entrance, we're
gonna scroll up to the top,
we're going to import a hook
those notifications called us
know, to the occasion from web
three UI kit. And this use
notification gives us this thing
back called a dispatch. So I'm
gonna say const, dispatch,
equals use notification. So use
notification returns this
dispatch, and this dispatch is
like a little pop up that will
give us so down here, when we
call this enter raffle, we're
gonna give it a little some
parameters in here, we're gonna
say on success, these functions
come with onsuccess, they come
with onComplete, they come with
an error, all this stuff. And
when this function is
successful, we'll do handle
success, we'll create a new
handle success function that
will handle the success. And
this is Patrick from the future
coming back to show one
additional point. I know I
mentioned it, but it is really
good to add this on error, colon
error console dot log error for
any run contract functions, even
the reads, If any of your run
contract functions break, you
won't know. So definitely want
to add this on error error
console dot log error to all of
your run contract functions. So
up here, before the return,
we'll create a new const handle
success. We'll say this is an
async function async function
that takes the transaction as
input parameters. And remember,
you can turn functions into
constant variables. And we'll
say await TX dot Wait, one, so
we'll wait for that transaction
to go through. And then we'll
create another function called
handle new notification, dx. And
you'll see why I'm doing it like
this in a minute. And we'll say
const and Linoone notification,
this is just going to be a
synchronous function because we
don't need it to be async. And
we're just going to call this
dispatch, we're going to set up
this notification basically. So
we'll say notify, or dispatch,
and then we'll add the
parameters in here. So it takes
an object as a parameter, we'll
say type info. Message, it's
going to be transaction
complete, the title is going to
be TX notification. Jose, Shawn,
we're going to say, top are and
then icon, we're going to say a
little bell.
And you can find all this stuff
right in here, type icon
position, you can read all about
the different parameters you can
kind of set this up with so
handle new notification handle
success. So we're saying, enter
raffle once this transaction is
successful, call this handle
success function, which is going
to call handle new notification.
Okay. And you'll see why we
split this into two instead of
just having handle success. Also
do the dispatch. When we press
our enter raffle button, we're
going to call enter raffle is
successful, we're going to call
handle success. We're going to
wait for that transaction to
finish Yes, it passes a
parameter to our handle success
function. And then all we're
going to do is we're going to
call handle new notification.
And we're going to dispatch
we're going to launch one of
these notifications. So back
here, let's hit enter raffle.
metamath pops up will confirm.
And after it completes, we get
this wonderful transaction
notification transaction
complete, right. So we've let
the user know, great job, you've
submitted a transaction. Great
work. So this is great. We're
giving our users some helpful
pieces here. Now let's add a
little bit more here so that the
users know what else is going on
with this lottery. But we need
to display a little bit more
data, right, let's display how
many people are in this lottery.
How many people are in this
game. And we can do that. Of
course, because we have a number
players command. We also
probably want to get the recent
winner. And we can do that as
well. Up here, we're going to
copy this get entrance fee,
we're going to create another
one called Get num players. And
this is going to call go back to
raffle dot soul. It's going to
call get number of players
actually so let's just call it
call it the same thing. Get
number of players and we're
going to call and get number of
players. And to store this
value. Once again up at the top.
We're going to copy this line,
paste it right and we'll do non
players. And then we'll do set
num players. And then we'll copy
this line again. A recent winner
so we'll do recent Winner.
Winner will do Set, recent
winner, then we'll copy this
again, instead of getting number
players will do get get recent
winner. So we'll call it get
recent winner get recent winner
in our use effect, let's do more
than just get the entrance fee,
let's get everything. So we can
say const num players, from call
equals, we'll do a weight, get
number of players.to string, and
then we'll do set set num
players do like that. So we'll
do set num players, num players
from call. And then we'll also
do const recent winner from call
this is going to be await get
recent winner. And we might need
to wrap this to string but I
think I don't think we need to.
So we'll do set recent winner
paste that in here. So now we've
had a number of players, we've
added a recent winner. Let's
come back down here. We have an
entrance fee. Let's go ahead and
do number of players. And we'll
add number of players or what
did we call it? Oh my god, we
called setting employers twice
oops, it's called non players,
scroll down players gonna be non
players, and then we'll do
recent winner.
And then we'll add in the recent
winner. Awesome. Okay, entrance
fees 0.1 eath number of players
to recent winner is nobody here.
And if we go ahead and we enter
the raffle metamath pops up.
We'll go ahead and confirm. Once
a transaction goes through,
we'll get transaction complete.
And if we do a refresh, we see
the number of players has
updated. But we had to refresh
which is kind of annoying,
right, let's enter the raffle
again, we'll go confirm
transaction complete. But this
didn't rerender. Right. So we
want to set something up so that
we automatically rerender. And
guess what's going to do that
the handle success that we were
talking about before. That's
right, all of this update UI
stuff, we can actually pull out
of the use effect. So we're
going to copy it all deleted
there. And we're going to have
it be its own standalone
function like this. And then in
our handle success, whenever
this successful transaction goes
through, we're going to update
the UI, right? So handle success
handled new notification, and
we're going to update the white.
So now if we go back here, let's
enter the lottery. Let's
confirm, we see we get the five
and we get transaction
Notification. Now we want to
test getting a recent winner
here. So what we can do,
actually back in our hard hat
project is we want to create a
new script. And I actually
already created it for you,
that's going to mock the
channeling VRF. And that's going
to mock being a keepers. So all
this is really doing is pretty
much exactly what our tests were
doing. If you want to pause
right now and look through this
yourself, pause here and add
this mock off chain, which is
both keepers and VRF. Or you can
just go to the GitHub repo here.
Just go to the GitHub repo for
Lesson Nine. It's already in
scripts go down to scripts
Markov chain, you can just copy
paste it here. Because I want to
test that that recent winner. So
in my hard hat, smart contract
lottery, so we'll do yarn,
hardhats run scripts, slash mock
off chain dash test network
local host, we're going to mock
you know, basically picking a
winner from an upkeep with
Request ID one, we're on a local
network. Okay, let's pretend the
recent winner was so and so. And
what we can do is we can do a
little refresh here, we can see
we have a winner updated. Boom.
Now we're gonna clean up the UI.
But I want to talk about a
couple of things. Before we do
that, because we're almost done
with this section. Something I
want to make really clear
because it confused me a little
bit is that this onsuccess isn't
checking that the transaction
has a block confirmation, it's
just checking to see that the
transaction was successfully
sent to Metamask. So onsuccess
checks to see a transaction is
successfully sent the Metamask.
And that's why up in that other
function, we do TX dot wait one
because that's the piece that
actually waits for the
transaction to be confirmed.
Right now we're using Morales to
make once we call that mocking
script, I had to refresh the
browser to see the winner here,
right and number of players
obviously got reset to zero,
which is great. That's not
ideal. Ideally, we want our UI
to just automatically update
when some event gets fired. In
our raffle contract, we get this
event emitted. Instead of in our
code doing this await success
here. What we could do is we
could set up a portion to listen
for that event being emitted and
update the front end
accordingly. With that knowledge
we can also listen for the
winner event being emitted. We
could update our front end
instead of having to refresh
it's your cue Yes, and you want
to see if you can add to this
right now, I highly recommend
you do. So
we've pretty much finished all
the functionality. And wow,
you've learned a ton in this
little bit, right? We've learned
about use effects use Morales,
all these hooks, all this stuff,
and we've got a front end that
very nicely handles interacting
with our smart contract. The
only thing is, is it looks
really ugly. This is kind of
gross. So let's make this look
at least a little bit nicer.
There's two things to think
about when it comes to building
these front ends. There's
component libraries, like web
three UI Kit, which we're using,
which gives us kind of like
components that give us, you
know, blocks of code, like this
connect button that are already
formatted for us. And then
there's CSS libraries that
actually will help us format the
rest of our stuff here. So we're
using one of these component
libraries. We're also going to
use one of these formatting
libraries, and the library that
we're going to use is tailwind.
And the reason that we're going
to use tailwind CSS is because
it's really popular. If you want
to learn CSS, there's some
wonderful resources that you can
use to learn CSS web three
schools is one that I've used a
ton. So there's going to be a
link to that in the GitHub repo
associated with this course so
that you can make your websites
look pretty when formatting
stuff but we are actually going
to work with tailwind because
it's going to make us doing CSS
stuff a lot easier. Since we're
using tailwind with next Jas.
There's actually a wonderful
little guide here for installing
tailwind with next Jas. And
we're gonna go basically go
ahead and follow along with
this. This link is available in
the GitHub repo associated with
this course with this lesson. So
we've already created our
project we've seeded into our
project. Now we're gonna go
ahead and install tailwind npm
install dash D instead, since
we're using yarn, we're going to
do yarn or pop this open, green
new yarn, add dash dash Dev,
paste those three in tailwind
CSS, post CSS and then
autoprefixer and it's the three
of these that are going to
basically make up tailwind with
next Jas. Once we have those
we're going to basically init
tailwind and make a config file
for tailwind. So we're gonna do
yarn tailwind CSS and it does p
yarn tailwind CSS init dash P
will run that. This is going to
give us this post CSS dot config
dot j s and this tailwind dot
config dot j s and what we're
going to want to do is literally
just hit this copy button, and
we're going to update our
tailwind.config.js tailwind Jas
so that it says okay, all of
this stuff, anything in Pages
anything with.js.ts dot JSX or
TSX. And anything in these
components, anything in those
two folders is going to be
considered tailwind double. We
want to use tailwind on these
two folders. Then we're going to
add the tailwind directives to
our global CSS files. So if we
go back, we're going to styles
Global's we're going to
overwrite everything in here
with ADD tailwind base and add
tailwind components at tailwind
utilities. And this makes it so
that our global CSS file uses
tailwind. Now, you'll see like
unknown rule at tailwind, what
we can do is we can go to
components, what we can do is we
can look up this post CSS
language support extension,
paste that in here, boom, let's
go ahead and install this. And
now we get those little
underscores to go away, which is
really nice. Now, per usual, we
can just do NPM, run Dev and
start adding tailwind to our
divs. Now what tailwind does is
allows us in our divs to set
everything as a class name, and
then just set some real
minimalistic text in these class
names here. So let's look at our
smart contract lottery here.
We've just tailwind did it. So
it already has been updated a
little bit. Let's update our
header here. Well, let's see. We
want to give our header a border
from the tailwind. We'll do a
quick search. Look a border we
can see all this border stuff
like border width border this
border that say we want a border
on the bottom, we can see we can
get a border on the bottom with
something like this. Let's do
border on the bottom with a
width of two pixels. We just do
border b two. So I'm going to
copy border B to do border b
two, I'm going to save it and
what we need to do for our CSS
and everything to take effect.
Go ahead and kill the front end.
And then we'll rerun it with
yarn Dev. Go back to our front
end now. Give it a little
refresh and Okay, cool. Now we
have a little border here. So
we're starting to add some stuff
and it's just not a whole lot
yet. Oh, and then we can also
add tailwind to me go to
Extensions. We can also look up
tailwind. There's a tailwind
extension here. So I'm just
going to add a whole bunch of
stuff in here. We're gonna do
flex, flex row.
We're gonna make our
decentralized lottery and h one
which stands for like header
one. Do class name equals, we'll
do the y dash force. We'll give
it padding the top of form the X
padding on the x axis of four.
We'll make it bold font and
we'll make the text three XL
size. So we'll make everything
bigger. Cool. Then we'll do one
more, we'll wrap our Connect
button in a div. So we'll say
div class name equals, and we'll
give it a an automatic left
margin. We'll do py too. So some
y padding, some x padding. See
what we have done. Okay. Now if
we zoom out a little bit, we can
see, if we close this too, we
can see now our Connect button
is on the side here. And they're
kind of separated like that. And
I think that looks nice. So
we're going to keep that now
we're going to go back to our
lottery entrance, we're going to
change this up just a hair,
we'll say div class name equals
P. Five, we'll make our button
look really nice. We'll say
class name equals background
blue 500. When we hover over, it
will say, background blue 700.
So now if I just say that, and
when we hover over it, it looks
a little different, that's
really nice. We'll say text is
white, we'll say the font is
bold, we'll give it some white
padding, I'll give it some x
padding, we'll have the bunbee
rounded, and we'll give it a
margin left auto, now looks a
lot better, right? That's a lot
prettier. We're just going to be
doing some basic CSS here just
to make it look a little bit
nicer, right, but just that by
itself already made this lottery
button look a lot cooler. Now
some functionality that we
didn't add here. So we need to
add a disabled, kind of like
what we did before. And in our
enter a raffle it comes with,
like I said, is loading and it
is fetching. None of our
transaction is loading or
fetching, we'll just make this
disabled. So we'll say is
loading or is fetching this will
be disabled. Right? Now, if we
go back to the front, we hit
enter raffle, go ahead and hit
confirm, we can add a CSS for
it. But when a transaction is
loading, they will not be able
to click that button anymore,
which that's something else
pretty that we want to do
speaking of is loading and is
fetching. When it's loading or
fetching, we probably want it to
have that like little spinny
thing right when we hit it right
now. And mash is pops up. And we
can confirm but it would be cool
if it had like a little spinny
thing here, right. So you can
usually just Google like how to
add spinny thing or stuff like
that, and you'll get something.
But you can again, you can just
copy paste this from my code,
I'm going to show you what I
ended up doing for this section.
And we're gonna say is, if is
loading or is fetching. And
we're going to use that ternary
operator all the time, then in
here, we're going to do a little
div. And otherwise, we're going
to do a different div for
loading or for fetching, we're
going to add like a little
spinny thing in here. So we're
going to add class name equals.
If we're loading, we're going to
add this little spinny thing,
which I'll show you what it
looks like in a second. And if
we're not loading, we're just
gonna do enter, raffle like
that. So we'll come back to the
front end, see answer raffle,
we'll click the button. Now we
get this cute little spinny
thing, confirm transaction goes
through. So anything goes away.
Nice. Well, let's put these on
different lines. So we'll just
do
so those will be on different
lines. Now boom, entrance fee,
number players recent winner,
once a lottery now will confirm
transaction complete number of
players has gone up and we have
done it. Now this looks a lot
nicer. It's clearly not perfect,
but it's much easier to read
than kind of that lump that we
had before. And the reason I
wanted to show you this was
really just kind of giving you
your footholds for making these
look a little bit nicer. This
definitely isn't a CSS course.
Oh, wow. Okay, this is
phenomenal. We have an app that
we really like. And we're like,
you know what, we want to deploy
this bad, Larry, let's talk
about how we can deploy this,
this section is going to be
optional, okay, because I'm
going to deploy something to
rank B and deploying to test
sets can take a long time. So
we're going to deploy our
contracts to rink B. And then
website to a hosting provider.
So first, let's talk about
hosting providers for a quick
second, if we want to host our
beautiful website that we just
created, there are ways to
deploy it using things like for
cell or Google Cloud, or AWS.
Nettle. Phi is another really
popular one there, all these
different places that we can
deploy our application. Now, the
thing about these though, is
that these are all centralized
deployment places, having a
centralized deployment
application can still be
incredibly important, right? If
we look at ether scan for a
second ether scan is a
centralized application right at
the end of the day, but it's
still one that we've been using
a lot. However, if we want to
have a front end that's
decentralized. Well, that's a
little bit harder. The more
important thing for us is that
our back end, our smart
contracts are decentralized,
right? That's the most important
thing because that will give
users the ability to interact
with our logic in a
decentralized way. But maybe we
also want our front ends
decentralized. Now at some point
we will still use a centralized
service Like VSL to deploy an
application, and I'll show you
why when we get there, there's
some features that right now,
they're really just hard to do
without like a really solid
centralized back end. What's
important to keep in mind is
that our back end, the logic of
our contract is on a
decentralized blockchain. So
even if we host the front end on
a centralized hosting provider,
using some type of centralized
database to make the front end
easier to work with, the logic
of the application is
decentralized. And that's the
most important piece. So I'm
going to give you some tools
later on, and how to introduce
more of these feature richness.
If you choose to do so doing so
will add a centralized component
on your front end. And it's
something to keep in mind,
depending on how you want your
architecture. So when doing that
just be absolutely sure that the
smart contracts on the back end
are deployed are decentralized
on one of these blockchains.
Now, we'll learn about some of
those centralized ways to do
that in a later section. For
now, let's learn how to deploy
this front end in a more
decentralized way.
And the tool that we're going to
use is a tool called IPFS. Now,
let me explain a little bit
about how IPFS works. It's this
distributed decentralized data
structure. That's not exactly a
blockchain. But it's similar to
a blockchain. There's no mining,
though. But there is pinning
data, you can add data to this.
So let me explain how this
actually works. And you can read
how this works on the site,
there's going to be a link to
this and the GitHub repo
associated with this course. But
we give you my basic take on it.
So we have our code, or our
file, or whatever it is, right,
we have some piece of data. Now
as we know, when you really have
anything, you can hash that
thing, you can hash that data,
right, so you can get a unique
output. So and that's actually
the first thing that IPFS does.
It hashes our data to get a
unique hash, that only points to
that data. Yes, a massive code
file a ton of text. Yes, you can
encode all of that into a single
hash function, your IPFS node
does this hashing for you. And
every single IPFS node on the