planet has the exact same
hashing function, kind of like a
blockchain, right, they all kind
of run this same spec, the same
specification. So we can hash
our data on our IPFS node and
get this unique output. What we
can do then is we can pin that
data or pin that code, or pin
that file or pin that whatever,
to our node, we have some data,
we get a unique hash of it, all
it does is host this data and
have these hashes. That's it,
our node is connected to a
network of other IPFS nodes. So
there's a massive network of
people running IPFS nodes,
they're incredibly lightweight,
way lighter weight than any
other blockchain node. And they
all talk to each other. So if I
asked the network, hey, I want
to get this hash. All these
nodes would talk to each other.
And eventually they'd reach up
at our node saying, Oh, I found
a node that has that hash.
Here's the file associated with
it. Now, you might be thinking,
Okay, well, that's kind of
centralized, because we have the
data on one node here, right?
Well, you're right, well, here's
the thing, what other nodes can
do is they can say, oh, that
data looks really cool, I want
to have that persist, what they
can do is they can pin your
hash, they can pin your data,
and they'll get a copy of your
data on their node. And you can
keep doing this. And so you
easily allow an entire network
to easily replicate any code or
any data in a decentralized
sense. And they're incredibly
easy to spin up. And they're
incredibly easy to work with
something about IPFS, that makes
it drastically different than a
blockchain is the can't do smart
contract, there's no execution,
it can really only store it's
just decentralized storage that
IPFS can do. Now, the issue here
is that in order for our data to
really be decentralized, another
node does need to pin our data,
right? Because if we're the only
IPFS node that's got this hash,
it's kind of centralized on our
node, if our node goes down,
that data is gone, and the
network won't be able to access
that data anymore. So we'll talk
about strategies in the future
about having other people pin
your data. But for now, this is
a way we can host data, we can
send code and have it be in a
decentralized context. So unlike
a blockchain, where every single
node in a blockchain is going to
have a copy of the entire
blockchain IPFS nodes get to
optionally choose which data
they want to pin, and they can't
do any execution. So you could
have an IPFS node, half a
megabyte, and you could have an
IPFS node, that several
terabytes, it's up to the node
operators, how much data and
what data they want to pin. Now
that we know about IPFS.
Let's actually deploy our
wonderful application to IPFS so
that anybody can use it and
anybody can connect to it. So
long as our node is up. Are you
ready? Okay, get excited here.
We're first going to do this
kind of the Manuel Wait, because
I'm going to show you how to
install IPFS. And work with
IPFS. Hit get started, there's a
number of ways to install and
work with IPFS, you can get it
with a desktop application, get
a command line. And then we can
also add IPFS to our browser
using something like brave or I
think Firefox to some this IPFS
router is automatically built
it. But if using something like
Chrome, you might have to add a
little companion, because what
we want to do is we can actually
use those little hashes as URLs
for websites, right, and so we
want to be able to put that URL
in our browser and connect to
that node or that piece of code.
So what we're gonna do is we're
gonna have you install the IPFS
desktop, so you're gonna hit
that. And when you do that, you
should be able to open up IPFS.
Now, if you install it, you
might get this little guy, this
little box here in your upper
section. Otherwise, you might be
able to open it up with with
IPFS desktop and see it as a
regular desktop app. Well, once
you install it, you might see
IPFS is running, you can restart
stop, you can do all this stuff,
we're gonna go to the file
section, and we're gonna get a
little pop up that looks like
this. Now, I've got a ton of
stuff in here, because I've been
using IPFS for some time in
here, right now, you might have
no data. So let's just go ahead
and import some file. And maybe
for now we'll just import, you
know, our next dot config dot j
s, right? It doesn't matter,
just import something. And now
in here, we have this next dot
config dot j s or whatever file
you import it. So what we can do
with this is we can actually
copy the CID. And we can view
this in our browser. So if we do
IPFS dot dot slash slash, and we
paste it in, we hit enter, we
can give our browser access to
actually rendering IPFS URLs. If
using brave, you can just do use
a brave local IPFS node or let's
go ahead and download this IPFS
companion. So we'll get IPFS
companion, there's a Firefox
install for Chrome brave, blah,
blah, blah. So I'm gonna go to
the Chrome store to get it for
brave, we're just going to hit
Add to brave add extension. But
once you download it, you'll get
something that looks like this.
Even on a little browser
companion, we can see like
import, we can see stuff about
our node, if we click our node,
we will see a very similar
setup. But now that we have the
companion in our browser, we can
copy that Cid that hash. Now
brave, we can just do use brave
local IPFS node, and will
automatically get dropped into
the file. Now, if IPFS companion
doesn't work for you, and you
can't see the URL inside of
something like Google Chrome or
some other browser, what you can
do is you can use something
called the IPFS gateway. Now
using a gateway, you're not
actually directly requesting the
data through IPFS requesting the
data through another server,
which is requesting it through
IPFS. But if you are having some
trouble accessing these files,
you can use the gateway. So what
you'll do is we'll do HTTPS,
slash IPFS, slash and then paste
the hash code there. And you'll
be able to see your file. Now if
you do it like this, you won't
even need IPFS companion at all.
So we're going to deploy our
website to IPFS. So that anybody
else who wants to pin this can,
and we will now have the ability
to have an incorruptible, in
unputdownable website, which is
just awesome. We're going to
learn how to do this the wrong
way first, and then we're going
to use a tool that's going to
make it a lot easier for us.
Okay, so first, let's go to our
website here. And, and if you
want to deploy to rink B, go
ahead and feel free. Just
remember to make sure that your
contract addresses file updates
accordingly. Okay. Now, next,
Jas has the ability to create
static websites. And that's
going to be an important term to
know we're going to make a
static website. At the moment,
we don't want our website to be
tangled with any server stuff.
And the reason we we don't want
it to be tangled with any server
stuff is because if our website
runs with server stuff, and we
deploy it to IPFS, will IPFS
doesn't have the ability to run
any code, it just hosts code. If
our front end has any server
stuff, it won't work. Now, in
its current state IPFS can't
come to our project and know
what to do, right, it doesn't
know how to do yarn dev can't do
yarn Dev. So we need to put all
of our code into its static
equivalents. So to do that,
we're gonna do yarn build. And
if again, if we look at our
package dot JSON, it comes with
this build, which just runs next
build. And running this build
command is going to build our
code, what's called like a
production build, creating an
optimized production build here.
And we'll get something that
looks like this. And we can see
this point down here. Static,
automatically rendered as static
HTML uses no initial props.
There's some server based
applications that next Jas comes
with that if we use them. Our
static build won't work. And
actually, you'll see when we run
yarn, next export, it'll fail if
you have any that non static
stuff. So let's Go ahead and try
yarn next export. And let's see
if it fails, it didn't fail, we
now have a new folder called
out. And this is our folder,
that's just pure static code and
that we can use on IPFS. In a
later section, I'll show you
what it looks like when you
don't use some of those static
things. Both Morales and next
Jas have the optionality to not
have static code. So we'll just
want to keep that in mind. So
now that we have this out
folder, we can go back to IPFS.
And we can import a folder,
we're going to import that whole
folder in here. So hit that hit
that import button and go to the
folder. Where that is mine is in
next year smart contract lottery
out. So now we're going to
upload this to our IPFS node.
Once it's done, we'll get this
little checkmark. And we can go
through IPFS files and see our
output here. What we can do,
let's go ahead and pin this to
our node, we'll pin it to our
local node here. And now once
it's up, we can copy the CID and
go back to brave or chrome or
whatever. You type in IPFS colon
slash slash, paste that in
there. And we immediately get
dropped into our smart contract
lottery in a browser. And we see
hi from lottery, no raffle
address detected, because right
now the way I set mine up Was it
only works with, you know, our
local hard hats, let's connect
our Metamask we'll hit the
connect button, connect, and
voila, we are right back where
we were. But with our data
stored in IPFS, we can enter
raffle as long as our node is
running a confirm. And we see
exactly what we get in our local
browsers. So this is phenomenal.
Now that I've shown you how to
do this, this is the manual way
of adding our code to IPFS. Let
me show you the easier way of
adding your code to IPFS we're
gonna go to this site called
fleek HQ. Go to fleek.co. And to
get to it, I'm going to turn my
my IPFS companion note off
because of some of the oddities
with working with brave but now
we're here@flickr.co fleek.co
makes it easy to to deploy
websites and apps to the new
open web permissionless,
trustless, censorship resistant,
etc. I like to think about it as
kind of like an auto deployment
for our websites. And
additionally, it does some
things to help out with that
problem. I was talking about how
we want to get other nodes to
pin our data. So it helps us out
with that. So let me show you
what it does. So let's go ahead,
we'll sign up. And why don't you
know, you can sign in with
GitHub. So if you have your
GitHub, definitely want to sign
in with GitHub here. Because
we're going to use GitHub to
actually help us automatically
deploy. So we'll authorize fleet
to work with our GitHub. You've
authorized your GitHub, let's go
ahead and add a new site or add
new site. Now we can use fleet
to just automatically deploy
websites, once we push them to
our GitHub. So we can come to
our GitHub once again. And click
the little plus button, we'll do
a new repository. We'll call
this next Jas smart contract,
lottery Free Code Camp. We'll
make it public create the
repository. Let's push all this
code to GitHub. We did it once
before, let's do it again. We'll
do git add, we'll do a little
dot, then we'll do git commit
minus m, say like initial commit
or whatever. We'll do git
remote, add origin, and then
we'll grab that URL, paste it
right here. And then we'll just
do git push origin, main. Now we
go back to our application we
see it in here we can do is back
in our fleek. We can connect
with GitHub, we're going to say
only select repositories, we're
only going to do this next js
application, this next JS get
we're going to install an
Authorize. Authorize Great. So
now we're going to pick a repo
we've picked a repo, we're going
to choose this application. And
we're going to use IPFS as our
hosting service. And now we're
going to add our information in
here. So we're going to use the
main branch. Here's the repo.
There's gonna be our framework
is gonna be next Jas. So we're
do fleek next. Jas, we're using
yarn. So we're gonna do yarn
install, and yarn, run build,
and then yarn run export. If you
want you could also just do
yarn, yarn build and yarn run
export, those are gonna be the
same thing. Publish directory is
going to be out and then we just
hit Deploy site, yarn, next
export as the last command, not
yarn, run, export. The accident
did the wrong one, you go over
deploys. Click on this, go to
deploy settings and then Edit
Settings and then just change it
to yarn. Next, export save. Then
we'll go back to deploys and
trigger deploy, if you did the
wrong one that was just a
learning opportunity for you to
learn where the settings are
after you deploy. And what this
is going to do is we're going to
do to deploy, it's going to run
those three commands yarn build,
yarn export, it's going to run
everything. And then it's going
to deploy a site for us both on
IPFS. And it's going to give a
regular URL that we can use for
normies, if you will. And while
this deploys, you'll actually
see down here we have this thing
called file coin di D in deal
proposal, Cid IPFS. Like I said,
we need other people to host our
node. File coin is actually a
blockchain that helps you pin
your data and uses decentralized
storage to do so. And fleek
helps you create those deals and
helps you pin your data with
this filecoin Blockchain
filecoin is one definitely to
take a look at. And then after a
while, you might have to wait a
little bit. And once it's done,
get a little deployed website,
we go back to hosting, we click
on our thing we can see we have
like a little website here. And
if we click it, we get a normal
URL for connecting and
interacting with our website,
you might even see this little
IPFS thing which will connect to
your IPFS node. And
additionally, we scroll down in
here we can see current IPFS
hash, so we can just stick that
in, um, and Bada bing, we have
an IP Fs deployed application.
Now what's cool is let's say I
make some changes, you know,
I'll go to lottery entrance. And
I'll do, I'll scroll on the
bottom to recent winner, I'll
make a new div. What a close the
div off, we'll save git add dot
Git commit minus m, add a dot
git push origin mean.
In our GitHub, we'll do a little
refresh, add a.as, the most
recently added one, go back over
to fleek. Go back to hosting
click on the section that we
just made go to deploys, and
you'll see there's a new deploy
going through. So it
automatically deploys your new
site, it'll automatically create
a new IPFS hash for your new
data. However, it'll still be on
this holy bird, you know, or
whatever your URL is here. And
this is kind of just a router
for IPSs. So that people without
IPFS connected can also connect
to this still. And now that my
application is done, pushing
automatically, with fleek, we
can see what's up being post in
my application here. Now, like I
said, filecoin isn't going to be
a technology, we're gonna go too
deep into introduce ourselves.
But like I was just saying IPFS
does have this limitation. It
doesn't have data persistence,
you have to have people pin your
data, in order for it to stay
distributed, and stay
decentralized. File coin is a
blockchain dedicated to keeping
this data, both decentralized
and persistent. And to give us a
better understanding of
filecoin. We actually have Ali
here to give us an overview.
Take it away, Ali. Hello, I'm
Ali, and I'm a developer
advocate here at the filecoin
Foundation, which works closely
with protocol labs and IPFS.
Just a quick note, protocol Labs
is our r&d arm. So it works on
creating tooling and technology
for a truly open and democratic
internet and web. And it's
building out some of the
foundational tooling like IPFS,
and filecoin, which are two
separate projects to enable
that. And hopefully, today,
because you're here to build, I
want to impart on you the
knowledge and tools you need to
get started with both of those
projects. So as anyone that's
kind of played around in this
ecosystem, or tech, in general
would know, data is an
absolutely essential part of our
daily lives. And not
surprisingly, it's also a super
fast growing field in web three,
and one, that's fundamental one,
and it's one of the fundamental
necessities of the decentralized
web stack as well. So the
current model of centralization
that's grown up, and basically
out of a lack of an identity
layer on the internet, is one
where only a few big companies
offer storage, and only a few
entities hold our data for
authorization purposes. And this
is an obvious problem, both in
terms of being an attack vector
for data mining, so without
data, getting leaked through
insecure service to third
parties, and also creating a
data resilience problem. So
whole services go down every
time one of these companies
servers does and we've
definitely seen that. So it
really leads to the question,
why aren't we designing the web
for the autonomy and resilience
we need in the first place? And
how do we store data in a way
that aligns with both the
original vision of the internet
as an open place for knowledge
sharing and collaboration, and,
and, and in a way that agrees
with the web three mission as
well. So these are the core
problems we're solving with IPFS
and file coin. Firstly, IPFS is
a distributed system for storing
and accessing files, folders,
websites, applications and data.
And it's designed to be able to
work even when the networks
between planets, so it's a
distributed by design, it has no
central authority servers, and
it's designed to be offline
first for resilience. And it's
not just a fancy name for
another peer to peer network
either. Because the nice thing
about the IPFS protocol is the
standard it uses for addressing
content on the network. IPFS is
unique because rather than using
traditional methods we might be
with familiar with from the web,
like those are location parts
that point to a particular HTTP
address where your content may
or may not be available and
stored. IPFS uses content
addressing so content addressing
means that each piece of data,
each meme or even full file
system has its own unique
cryptographically verifiable
fingerprint, you might call it.
So if you change even one pixel
of your main image, for example,
then the content ID or Cid
associated with it also changes.
So importantly, this hash
function is also upgradeable. So
let's say quantum computing
breaks out current secure hash
algorithms, we can upgrade the
standard we use. And it means
you will always get the same
content returned by an IPFS. Cid
as what you expect. So this is
fundamentally important, because
when you don't have to care
where the data comes from, you
open up the web to massively
distributed storage systems.
Hello, decentralization. So now
we have a really important and
valuable protocol that enables
distribution at scale. And it
provides verifiability of data
to serve and retrieve content on
the web. And not just for web
three, either, but also for all
web, or tech use cases. The
problem is, and it's one that
the early internet also faced,
who's going to ensure the
persistence and permanence of
all this data on the network. So
unless you're running your own
nodes 24/7, or your content is
really popular or other nodes
decide to altruistically store
your data. Because I think it's
important, then this data can
become unreliable because
they're no longer actively
hosted on any nodes on the
network's. So to avoid this, you
could also turn to a pinning
service that you pay to keep a
copy of your content around.
Unfortunately, the problem with
this though, is that we're
heading back towards
centralization of data. And
we're creating new data silos
with this solution and losing
the trust lessness and
resilience we're looking for.
And these one a bad solution
prior to file coin, and it's why
they sprung up initially, but we
want a better solution. So this
is where file coin comes in. So
far coins architecture, then
designed to leverage a crypto
economic incentive model
together with cryptographic
proofs in order to ensure data
is stored persistently, highly
reliably and verifiably. It uses
these cryptographic proofs to
also enable smart contract based
permanence. And that means that
it's designed to be as permanent
as you, the data owner want it
to be. It's your data, so it's
your choice. It's also designed
to enable internet scale
capacity. It's currently the
largest distributed storage
network in the world with over
18 million terabytes of capacity
available, which is apparently
about 135 copies of the European
Union's nuclear program, CERN's
data which, which is kind of a
fun fact. It's also file coins
also designed to be and stay
hyper competitive on pricing due
to its market economics. And
this comes down to storage
deals. So to make this network
feasible, filecoin uses storage
deals. And these include two
main consensus mechanisms that
ensure both rewards for good
actors in the system, and
penalties for bad actors. So
when you make a deal with one or
more storage providers to store
your important data, the
provider generates a proof of
replication. So this proves that
the storage provider is storing
a unique copy of your original
data over time to make sure that
this data is persisted. These
storage providers must prove
that they still have random
subsets of this client data and
they create proof of space
times. And these proof this
proof of space time is something
that is stored on the
blockchain. So anyone at any
time can also check that this is
true. And it also makes up the
mechanism by which miners are
rewarded or penalized because
you have to stake Phil on the
network in order to become a
storage provider. So when a
storage deal comes to an end, or
user can you can opt to let it
expire or renew the deal. If you
opt for renewal, then the
providers again bid to host this
content. So this creates an
efficient market for pricing a
continual efficient market for
pricing as well. It can even go
negative. So the storage
provider can even pay you to
store your data if it's an
important data set due to some
of the block rewards that are
being offered by the filecoin
Foundation as well. So these
mechanisms are what built in not
just data permanence, but data
timeframes, sovereignty, too so
it's your data, it's your
choice. You can decide you want
to store your data for five
minutes or 500 years. It's also
your choice over how much
resilience you want to have that
data so or how many copies of
that data you want to have and
with what store to providers. So
this allows you to comply with
regulations like GDPR. And
there's a growing number of
tools in the ecosystem like
murmurations bit screen that are
allowing for you to do this
filtering. But it also gives you
some guarantees that your data,
you know, if one storage
provided goes down, you know,
surely not 10 of them are going
to go down. So that's a
guarantee for your resilience
there as well.
And this is why IPFS and
filecoin are great complements
of each other. So IPF s gives
you that benefit of content
addressing file coin gives you
persistent guarantees that even
if your computer or your
favorite IPFS pinning service
where to go away, the content
persists. Just as a quick final
note on these concepts as well,
IPFS and file coin is separate
projects, as I mentioned. So
IPFS is a protocol much like
HTTP, whereas file coin is a
blockchain. So IPFS is also
storage layer agnostic, you can
combine it with the storage
layer of your choice. And while
file coin was specifically
designed to complement it, and
we think is a great choice, you
can also store your IPFS data in
the cloud or an other storage
solutions as well. So hopefully,
you've got a good baseline for
why you'd want to use IPFS, and
filecoin. And for those
engineers out there that like a
challenge, and are interested in
working on the base protocols
and code of IPFS, and file coin,
which isn't always easy for the
average user, I'd encourage you
to go and take a look at the
project docs and get hubs and
some of the associated grants
available for extensions to
these open source projects. And
this is a great site here if you
want to get more information
into the nitty gritty and really
dig into the code behind IPFS
and filecoin. And extend some of
that. For those of you that just
want to build out of the box
though. And this is definitely a
camp that I often fall into. I
want to talk about some of the
dev tooling and storage helpers
that make it easy for you to get
started. So firstly, Flake Flake
is one of my favorite IPFS dev
tools. And projects Flake is a
CI CD tool that you can use to
deploy your apps for free as
simply as easy as you would with
some of the web tools you might
web to tools you might be
familiar with like Netlify
oversell. The big difference,
though, is fleek uses IPFS to
host your site or app. And it
even offers an AES domain
routing on their platform. So if
you're deploying a front end
app, I would encourage you to
use fleek to make it more
distributed instead of some of
the traditional web two tools.
It's just as easy, I promise. So
another one of my favorite tools
is NFT storage, storing your NFT
metadata immutably and
persistently, as you already
probably know, is integral to
keeping the main value
proposition of NF Ts, then on
fungibility. So if you're not
storing this data on chain,
which obviously can become
pretty financially unviable for
large files, then this is
exactly where NF T storage comes
in. So it was specifically
created as a public good to
archive and persist NF T data.
So it's free. And it takes care
of the complexity around firstly
creating an IPFS Cid for this
metadata, and then making
automatic deals with filecoin
storage providers. So it does
this with at least eight storage
providers. So eight times
redundancy and it does it with a
multigenerational timeframe. So
it automatically renews those
deals. Because it's a public
good, it's all free as well. And
it's also super easy to use,
because you just need because
it's a JavaScript service. So
you just need to say import that
as an NPM package or JavaScript
library and then call the API
and NFT dot storage takes care
of the rest. For data that isn't
NF T metadata as well, we built
web three dot storage, web three
storage is designed to give you
those same web two benefits. So
similar to NF T dot storage,
make it super easy for you to
use. And it's got JavaScript and
go client libraries.
While giving you you know the
power of IPFS and filecoin of
decentralized storage and IPFS
content addressing so it's got
one terabyte after terabyte, one
terabyte of free storage with
that. So try that out if you're
not just like trying to store
and obtain metadata. The next
tool is a bit more advanced.
It's called textil Palghat gate,
and it's for you know, more
advanced developers or those
looking for more flexibility to
interact with IPFS live peer to
peer and filecoin. It's a Docker
container wrapped around
filecoin and IPFS nodes. And it
gives you a lot of options to
configure it's a minor
selections and extend
functionality. It also offers
some bridges to several layer
ones which might be of interest
to developers out there. Another
one here and I'll preface this
by saying you need an invite to
this is ESRI tech. So it's for
people looking to store really
meaningful public data. It's
currently in alpha mode and like
I said, it requires an invite
because it's been built as a
public goods specifically to
store important information. If
you are I do have Use case
around this slide, please feel
free to reach out to us on this
project. Other final tool I'll
mention is orbit dB. So many
people coming to the web three
space from web two are often
looking for the same sort of
relational databases that we're
so used to in traditional
computing except in a
decentralized or distributed
format. And this isn't an easy
problem. So Oba to me is
currently in active development.
And because this isn't an easy
problem to solve, this isn't an
ideal solution for those of you
looking for an out of the box
experience. But if you are
looking for something like that,
try out orbit dB. And there's
also several other tools in the
ecosystem leveraging IPFS and
filecoin, including ceramic,
which is similar to textil power
gate, except it uses
decentralized identities.
Lighthouse is file drive, and
there's even Morales has an IPFS
API, so check those out as well.
So storage is really a
fundamental component on one
technology system. So and
there's so many use cases you
could dive into here. And so
hopefully, I've provided you
with some of the knowledge and
tools you need to get started
with IPFS and file Goyt. Coin
and really make powerful
distributed applications. And
there's just one more tool
that's also in active
development now. So if you look
closely at this diagram, you'll
notice probably unfamiliar logo
right at the end of the logic
layer. And that's the logo for
the filecoin virtual machine. So
FBM will be launching at the end
of this year. And we're super
excited about it. And it's going
to allow smart contracts,
contract use combined with like
colocation of storage data,
loads, so computing capabilities
with storage capabilities, and
will also be EVM compatible. So
as I said, we're super excited
for the kinds of use cases that
we're going to see come out of
this project as well. And you
can follow along here on the
website here as well. So
hopefully, I've given you all
the tools you need to get
started with IPFS. And file
coin. If you do need more
resources or want to get
involved, we have proto School,
which is interactive tutorials
on decentralized web protocols.
There's also NFT, school dot
Dev, or join a hackathon, check
out our hackathons.filecoin.io
page for all the latest
hackathons we're involved in.
And if you do really want to dig
deep and build tooling in IPFS,
and file coin or build a cool
project, check out our grants
options as well for that, in the
meantime, all please learn long
build and prosper.
So we've learned a ton in this
section. And that is it. So
let's do a summary of all the
amazing things that we've
learned. And then we'll go into
the TypeScript edition of this
because the TypeScript edition
is definitely a little bit
different. So let's talk.
Alright, so first, we learned
more about next Jas. And we
learned we can have an
application using next Jas. And
it's a framework that's gonna
allow us to build really
powerful front ends and full
stack applications really
easily. We learned about the
layout of our next JS project,
we add components in a
components folder, which are
basically minimalistic blocks of
JavaScript and HTML that we can
use to modularize and create our
website out of these components.
Constants is a folder that we
can put constant variables, Node
modules is node modules. And out
folders. What happens when we
export all of our code to a
static example, pages are going
to be basically the routes or
the different pages of our
website, everything goes through
app.js. Public is just some
public stuff styles is for any
CSS or styling of our
application. And then we have
our basic files here. In our
pages section, we have our app,
which is surrounded by both this
notification provider and our
Morales provider, all of our
components run through this app
on all of our pages run through
this app. So this is kind of
considered the entry point for
our entire application. Having
this Morales provider wrapped
around our notifications in
component means that we don't
have to pass parameters between
our components. And our lottery
will just know what chain ID
that we're on, because our
header is going to pass it up to
Morales provider and the Morales
provider is going to pass it
back down to our lottery
entrance. And we saw with our
manual header, the way that that
connect button works behind the
scenes. So it's doing some local
storage, where we're storing
whether or not we're actually
connected, we learned about use
effect, and you state and these
different hooks in our front
ends were one of the main
reasons we want hooks is we want
we want our websites to
rerender. When stuff changes, we
want our components to be able
to talk about the state of the
blockchain with each other. And
they're incredibly powerful for
building our React applications.
Use effect is one of the most
popular ones where if we don't
have a dependency array, our
function inside of our use
effect will run anytime
something re renders a blank
dependency array means it'll
just run once on load. And if
there are dependencies in the
array, it'll run any time any of
the variables in those change.
We also learned about the use
state hook, which is really
similar to saying like, let
variable equals x. But it also
comes with the RE rendering
ability. And it comes with some
other nice abilities that we
didn't really discuss here, we
learned how to call different
contract functions with
mirallas. Not only sending
transactions, but also calling
data. Morales is smart enough to
know that when it sees get
entrance fee that this is going
to be a view function. And this
is going to be a transaction, it
can tell the difference between
the two. So this one's going to
populate Metamask to pop up. And
this one just going to return
kind of normally like a view
function, what we can actually
use the same syntax between
sending transactions and then
calling view functions on our
contract, we added a button,
calling one of these Morales
pieces and then had an onsuccess
section where when our
transaction completed, we update
the UI and we add a little pop
up for notifications, we learned
how to deploy our code directly
to IPFS. And use that IPFS hash
to interact and see our code, we
also learned about fleek and how
fleek automatically deploys to
IPFS. Whenever we do a git push
to our GitHub repository, and it
makes continuously updating our
websites much easier. It also
gives us a regular canonical URL
as well. And then finally, we
learned about IPFS and
decentralized database storage.
Now you might be asking, Okay,
well, why don't we just store
all the data for this website on
Aetherium, or polygon or
avalanche, etc? And the answer
to that is that can get
incredibly expensive storing
data, storing a ton of data on
the blockchain costs a ton of
gas, whereas this is a much
cheaper alternative. Aetherium
avalanche and the smart contract
platforms aren't really meant to
be data storage layers, they're
meant to be logic layers, right?
Decentralized logic,
decentralized smart contracts,
oftentimes, yes, we're gonna
have to store data in them. But
when it's a ton of data, there
are better solutions. And there
are different solutions out
there for storing our data, like
IPFS and filecoin, you should be
incredibly proud of yourself, if
you've made it this far, because
you've just made a really solid
app, a really solid front end
application. And you've learned
how to really easily add
functionality for interacting
with your smart contracts. So
give yourself a pat on the back,
maybe even tweet this out, share
this really cool application
with your friends and family.
Take a break. And I'll see you
in the next lesson.
All right, welcome to one of the
fastest lessons that we're going
to have here. And in this
lesson, we're going to talk
about the hardhat starter kit.
Really quickly, I'm going to
walk you through it and show you
how to use it. Now we've learned
a lot about projects, we've
learned a lot about different
repos, learnt the basics of
smart contracts. And we've
learned a lot about front end as
well and building front ends for
applications. So this smart
contract kit repo comes packed
with a ton of starter kits that
you can use to start deploying
your projects right away. And as
you can see, that hard hat
starter kit is easily one of the
most popular ones with the most
stars the most forks out there.
The smart contract kit repo
actually comes with a ton of
frameworks, like if you want to
work with SWANA, if you want to
work with Python and Brownie, if
you want to work with foundry,
truffle, really any other
framework out there, you can get
started, clone one of these
repos, work with one of these
repos and build your project and
get started right away, we're
going to show you how to use the
hard hat starter kit. So you can
just grab the repo and go and
already have some boilerplate
code and a boilerplate really
good looking repo to start your
projects with, we come to the
smart contract kit, hard hat
starter kit repo here. And if
you're working with GitHub, you
can just go ahead and use this
template and it will
automatically generate you a new
GitHub repo with the hardest
starter kit. So let's go ahead,
we'll click use this template,
we come up with our own name
here, we'll call it make it
public create repository from
Template. it'll generate our
repository. And now we
automatically have it in our own
repo here. And we can get
started working with it. And we
can get started working with it.
If you don't want to click the
use that template button, we can
also just copy the URL. And in
our code editor, we can just do
git clone and paste that in
there. So for now, I am going to
get clone, but I'm going to get
clone with this repo that we
just created. Come back in with
the git clone, hard hat play FCC
or hard hat starter kit. We're
going to cd into our head play
FCC, and then open that up in a
new code editor. And awesome.
Now you'll see in this repo, it
comes packed with a ton of
contracts, deployments, scripts,
tasks, test, everything, you
name it to really get started in
a professional environment. We
look in the contract section, we
can see we have a couple of
sample contracts. We have a
contract for making an API call
to a chain link node, working
with keepers working with price
feeds, and then working with
chain link Vir Fe two. We've got
some test contracts and we
additionally have this fuzzing
folder, which we'll talk talk
about in a much later section of
this course, we have deployed
scripts where we start with
deploying mocks, then we deploy
each one of those contracts, we
have a sample script to read the
price from one of these
contracts. And we have a whole
bunch of sample tasks. Now at
the time of recording, instead
of scripts, this repo uses
tasks. But again, they're a
little bit interchangeable. And
of course, we have some unit
tests and some staging tests as
well, that you can go through
and take a look at, once we're
in this repo, we can run some
familiar commands here, we'll do
yarn, of course, to install our
all of our packages. And then
everything that we're going to
do, if you get lost, you can
always come back to this repo.
And you can follow along with
getting started and the
Quickstart. So we just did the
git clone. Now we're doing the
yarn, and then we're gonna go
ahead and run yarn hard hat
test. This hard hat starter kit
repo is very consistently up to
date, we did the last push being
just a few days ago, and will
constantly have some best
practices for building our smart
contracts and having a really
professional coding environment.
And it's got this really cute
logo. Once we've installed all
the dependencies, we can run
yarn, art hath test, we can run
all of the tests in the test
folder, which also will show us
how to interact and how to use
all these different contracts in
here. And they each have some
console dot log, so you can see
more about what's actually going
on when these tests actually
run. If we look in the Hardhead
config.js, it's got some really
familiar code in here, we have
all our imports at the top, we
grab a whole bunch of
environment variables, we've got
the ether scan plugin, we've got
the gas reporter, the contract
sizer, which is a plugin that
tells you how big your contracts
are. So named accounts,
different solidity versions, and
then mocha timeout as well. We
can of course, do yarn hard hat
node, which will run through our
deploy scripts, and then spin up
a new note for us, which has
mock chainlink tokens, mock
Oracle's mock aggregators, and
mock up VRF for us to go ahead
and interact with once that's
up, we can then of course, to
hard hat, console, dash dash
network localhost, and begin
interacting with contracts on
localhost. So we can kind of
follow along with price feed,
for example, and do const price
consumer B three equals await
ethers dot get contract, price,
consumer V three.
And then we can do await price
consumer B three dot get latest
price. Let's wrap that in a to
string. And we can see a mock
latest price from a contract
that uses channeling price
feeds. And we can interact with
any of our contracts and work
with any of the mocks as well in
here. If we want to deploy this
to an actual test net like
Rinckey, or main net will just
pop in our dot env file, we'll
close our node terminal, and we
can run yarn hardhat or just hh
deploy. And then we'll add
whatever tags we want to do
here. So let's just deploy our
price feed contract. If we go to
the price feed deploy, we scroll
down, we'll get the tags. Okay,
great, we'll use the feed tag,
dash tags feeds dash to or feed
dash dash network brings beam.
And while we're waiting for this
to deploy, we can go back to the
actual repo. And just make sure
to follow along with the
documentation here and the
Quickstart in all the usage and
everything so that you make sure
that you're working with the
most up to date version. There's
even documentation on running a
local network using a test net
or live network working with
Aetherium. Rigby adding your
private keys and dotting envies
all this stuff that you already
know, forking, which we'll learn
a little bit later, auto funding
your contracts for working with
chain link API running tests,
you can additionally run your
tests in parallel by adding the
dash dash parallel flag to our
tests. We can interact with our
deployed contracts with those
different tasks that we've
created linting code formatting,
estimated gas code coverage
fuzzing, we'll talk about later.
And then contributions. PRs
issues are always welcome here.
And once it's outputted, and
even verified, if you have
verification turned on, you'll
get a little task that we can
run to just go ahead and read
the price feed or interact with
the contract. So we can copy
that task out. Yarn hardhat.
Read price feed since it's a
task here, contract the contract
data which we just deployed
network Rigby. And we'll get
reading data price feed from
consumer contract on network,
Rigby price is here, which of
course, we're saying the price
of Aetherium is $3,033, because
it has eight decimal places. So
if you're ever looking to start
a new project, and you want some
boilerplate code, this hard hat
Starter Kit is a great place to
get started. And of course, you
can open it and get pod if you
want to just test it out and try
it and get pot in a Cloud Shell.
So that's it for this lesson.
Wasn't that fast. This was the
fastest lesson ever. So if you
want to do a little extra
learnings here, I would fork
this I would clone this I would
use this template, try to play
around with the repo a little
bit yourself and see what you
recognize, see what you don't
recognize and keep that prepped
in your mind for later so
Questions in the course. And
then for everyone here who is
TypeScript, there is, of course,
a TypeScript version of this as
well that you can get cloned.
And it has a nice blue logo here
to show that it's a little bit
different. So, that being said,
use the repo, have fun. Let's
get to lesson 12.
Alright, now we're moving on to
the hard hat ERC. 20s are the
section where we're going to
learn how to create our own ERC
20 or EIP 20 Or B E P 20 or AEP
20 any of these tokens on the
blockchain before we can
understand what an ERC 20 is, or
even what one of these tokens
are, we first need to understand
what is an ERC. And then also
what is an EIP in Aetherium, and
avalanche and finance and
polygon. All these blockchains
have what's called improvement
proposals. And for Aetherium,
they're called Aetherium
improvement proposals, or E IPs.
And what people would do is they
come up with these ideas to
improve Aetherium or improve
these layer ones like polygon,
Matic avalanche, etc. And on
some GitHub or some open source
repository, they'll add these
new EIP is they'll add these new
improvement ideas to make these
protocols better. Now, these
improvements can really be
anything, they can be anything
from a core blockchain update to
some standard, that is going to
be a best practice for the
entire community to adopt. Once
an EIP gets enough insight, they
also create an E RC, which
stands for Aetherium request for
comments. So EIP a theory and
improvement proposals ERC a
theory and request for comments.
And again, these can be like BP,
Pep, you know, etc. For all
these different blockchains.
Both the improvement proposals
and the Request for Comments,
all have these different tags,
now they're numbered
chronologically, so something
like an ERC 20 is going to be
the 20th ERC slash EIP, the ERC
is and the EFPs share that same
number. And there are websites
like EIP is that aetherium.org
That keep track of all of these
new Aetherium improvement
proposals, and you can actually
see them real time go through
the process of being adopted by
the community. Now, one of these
e IPs or ERC is, is going to be
the ERC 20 or the token standard
for smart contracts. This is an
improvement proposal that talks
about how to actually create
tokens and create these smart
contract tokens. I made a video
about this recently. So in the
GitHub repo associated with this
course, we're going to have a
sub lesson, and we're going to
watch a quick video that
explains more about these
different tokens. Now first,
let's define even what are ERC
20s So ERC 20s are tokens that
are deployed on a chain using
what's called the ERC 20 token
standard, you can read more
about it in the year 20 token
standard here link in the
description as well. But
basically, it's a smart contract
that actually represents a
token. So it's token or the
smart contract. It's both it's
really cool tether chainlink
unique token and dye are all
examples of ERC 20s Technically,
chain link is in the ERC. 677 as
there are upgrades to the ERC 20
that some tokens take that are
still backwards compatible with
ERC. 20s And so basically, you
can think of them as ERC 20s
with a little additional
functionality. Now why would I
even care to want to make an ERC
20 Well, you can do a lot of
really cool stuff with it. You
can make governance token, you
can secure an underlying
network, you can create some
type of synthetic acid, or
really anything else. In any
case, how do we build one of
these ERC? 20s How do we build
one of these tokens? Well, all
we have to do is build a smart
contract that follows the token
standard, all we have to do is
build a smart contract that has
these functions that has a name
function, symbol function,
decimals function, etc. All
these functions we need to be
able to transfer it, we need to
be able to get the balance of it
etc. And again, if you want to
check out some of the
improvements that are still ERC
20 compatible, like the ERC 677
or the ERC 777. Definitely go
check those out and build one of
those instead. All right,
awesome. Now that we know what
one of these ERC 20s is, we can
go ahead and create our own per
usual in the GitHub repo
associated with this course. We
have all the code available
here. If you want to just get
clone. This is going to be again
another one of our quicker
lessons here. So we're in our
terminal. We're in our VS code
here. We're going to make a new
directory. I'm going to call it
hard hat ERC 20 FCC will cd into
hard hat, your C 20 sec. And
we're going to create a new hard
hat project the exact same way
we've been doing it yarn add
dash dash dev or tab. Let's
actually open it in its own VS
code will do code.or file open
this folder. And okay, we're in
our project now. Let's create a
new hard hat project. We'll do
yarn, art hats.
We'll do create an empty hard
hat dot config dot j s here and
great. We've now got an empty
hard hat dot config dot j s. If
you want to copy paste your hard
hat dot config from a previous
projects you want to copy paste
your heart Have dot config or
your dot EMV file, because you
know we're going to need those
feel free to do so now, I'm just
going to update this to 8.7.
I'll add the rest of my stuff
later. So as we've heard this
EIP 20, or this ERC 20. All it
needs is to have these functions
in its token standard so that we
can transfer tokens, we can do
all the stuff in the ERC 20
contract itself, it really is
just keeping track of how much
of each token people have. So
the smart contract, kind of in a
weird way it keeps track of
itself. To get started, we're
going to do this kind of the
manual way. First, we're going
to create our own manual token
here, or a really minimalistic
one anyways, so let's create a
new folder. contracts will
create a new file called manual
token dot soul. Yes, I'm going
to show you kind of the hard way
to make it and then I'll show
you a much easier way to make
it. So to get started here are
usual we can do pragma, solidity
to carrot zero, point 8.7. And
then we'll even do spdx, license
identifier, MIT do contract,
manual token, and boom, let's
get started. The main reason
this token smart contract works
is that there's some balances
mapping. So we have a mapping of
addresses to you in 256. And
it's usually public called
balance of and all this does is
this mapping is obviously the
key is going to be every single
address on the planet, and then
how much they have. And
basically, when we transfer
tokens, transfer tokens, we're
basically just subtract from
address, amount, and add to to
address. So a really
minimalistic way to implement
this would be to create this
transfer function first. So
we'll create this function, I'm
going to call it underscore
transfer, we can do an address
from address to you into fifth
sixth mount. And now we'd
probably put some requirements,
we probably omit some events,
and let's make this public as
well. And really, at the end of
the day, is we're gonna say
balance of from minus equals
value, which is the same as
saying bounce of from equals
bounce from minus value, or
excuse me, amount, and then
we're gonna say balance of two,
excuse me, plus equals, which is
the same as saying, you know,
balance of two plus. And
technically, that's really all
we need, right, we probably want
to do some asserts ins here,
some requires to make sure all
of our numbers make sense. But
really, at the end of the day,
this is all that this function
is doing. Transfer works when
the caller is sending money
directly into another address.
But what happens if we want to
allow some smart contract to
work with our token, or we want
to allow somebody else to work
with our token, you know, maybe
to deposit it into a protocol,
or do some more functionality
with it, there will be some
approved function that will
approve that contract to do
that. And then we'll have a
function transfer from and this
function will, you know, it'll
just implement taking funds from
user and this will be public as
well. And then at the top will
be some type of allowances
mapping that will tell who's
allowed which address to take
how much token, which sounds a
little confusing, but let me
just add the mapping. So it'll
be a mapping of addresses to a
mapping of addresses to an
amount to a unit tivity sex and
this will be public allowance,
we're gonna say address, Patrick
is going to allow address of
Patrick's brother to use 25
tokens. And that's how this
allowance works. And in our
transfer from transfer from will
check this allowance mapping and
save Hmm. Did Patrick give you
authorization to borrow those
tokens? Oh, yes, you did. Okay,
we'll let you transfer from. And
I'm just, I'm just going to copy
paste an implementation of it,
you can check out the GitHub
repo as well. And it would look
something like this is we check
the allowed amounts, update the
allowance, and then transfer the
tokens. So those are some of the
main functions. So we need an
approved function, obviously, to
update the allowances here. And
usually, you'll have like a un
256 initial supply. And this
will be like how many tokens
there are starting with how many
tokens there are total,
sometimes you'll add a mint
function to add more functions.
But you can basically start to
see this contract ramping up.
One thing we could do is we
could go ahead go through this
spec and just line by line, you
know, build our token ourself.
And after we do that, it might
look something like this. So I'm
just copy pasted the code from
the GitHub repo. If you go to
contracts, manual token, I just
copy paste this code in here.
This is what a contract a token
contract might look like. Okay.
So we have all these functions,
we have all these arrays. We
have all this stuff. And you can
see in the constructor, we're
taking initial supply, and then
a token name and a token symbol.
The name, you know, might be
something like dy token. And
then the symbol might be
something like dy, just so that
it's easily recognizable just by
its name and its token.
coding it all from scratch, like
that is definitely something
that we can do. But as
engineers, we know that that's
probably really annoying. And we
don't actually want to do that.
So what can we do instead? Well,
we can use an open source
library, like open Zeppelin, to
actually get some boilerplate
code work with open Zeppelin is
almost considered kind of the
standard library of solidity.
They have a list of open source
contracts that anybody can use
and import into their contracts
that have a ton of boilerplate,
so that you don't have to
manually write everything out,
we can see all their code in
their GitHub repository, open
Zeppelin slash open Zeppelin
contracts, and we're going to be
using them a lot moving forward.
So for example, you can see kind
of on the left side of their
documentation, they have this
tokens section, and they have an
ERC 20, which is one of those
tokens standards. If you scroll
on here, they even have some
minimalistic examples of how to
create your own ERC 20 token.
And that's what we're going to
be using to build our token.
Because you see how much smaller
this is how much less code this
is to maintain. Let's go ahead
and let's use open Zeppelin for
us to create our token. So let's
create a new file. We'll call
our token dot soul. I'm going to
create our own token here. So
let's do spdx. License
identifier, MIT, we'll do
pragma, solidity carrot zero,
point 8.7, we'll do contract our
token. Now, what we're going to
do, we're going to import
openzeppelin contracts into our
hard hat project. And we're
going to do it the same way we
did with chain link and any
other packages in the future. So
we'll do yarn, add dash dash
Dev, at open Zeppelin slash
contracts. And this is going to
add the open Zeppelin slash
contracts NPM package to our
project. And one of the code
pieces that they have is this
ERC 20 contract that we can use
and we can have our token
inherit all the functions. So
we'll go ahead and import it
with import at openzeppelin.
Slash contracts slash tokens
slash ERC 20 slash ERC 20
ditzel. And just by importing it
like this, all we have to do is
have our token inherited now. So
we'll say contract. Our token is
ERC 20. Boom. And just like that
our token is almost done. Now
you might get this little wiggle
this little red line here saying
our token should be marked
abstract. And that's because if
we look into the ERC 20 dot soul
of openzeppelin We'll see that
it has a constructor. So in
order for us to inherit your C
20 token, we have to use the ERC
20 constructor and we just need
to give our token a name and a
symbol. But we can say in our
constructor, we can leave it
blank. And then right next to
our constructor, we'll add the
ERC 20 constructor and our name
will be our token. And then our
symbol will just be OT and then
this ERC. 20 token also comes
with something called a mint
functionality, which is
essentially a function that
allows us to create tokens,
right because right now we
actually get initialized with
zero tokens, right. So nobody's
actually allowed to have any
tokens. So we want to mint the
initial amount of tokens and
then who owns all those tokens
to start with. So usually what
you'll see is you'll see a mint
function like this, it'll be
passed in message that sender,
so whoever deploys this contract
will own all the tokens to
start. And then we'll give it
like an in their soul supply.
And then we could do like, you
went to 56 initial supply equals
like seven, or whatever. But
instead, a common practice is
just to add it to the
constructor. So you and 256
initial supply like that, as we
know about solidity decimals
don't work so great. So if I say
my initial supply is 50, that 50
is going to be like 50 way, and
there's all these ERC 20s come
with a decimals and decimals
function, which tells us how
many decimals we should expect
with our ERC 20. The default is
18. And we can override this
function if we want a different
amount of decimals. And if we
know the default is 18. And we
want to deploy 50, we might want
to do our initial supply of 50 e
18. Or you can also say like 50
times 10, raise the 18th or
whatever you want there. And in
our code when we deploy this
now, this is actually where
we're going to finish the
project. Because everything else
that we would do here, we've
already done, all we need to do
is make a deploy script and
write some tests. That's really
it. Because right now you have
all the skills that you need to
write a deploy script and then
optionally write some tests for
this project. So I highly
encourage you to pause the video
here and try to write your own
deploy script. And even if you
want to write your own tests,
you can always refer back To the
GitHub repo associated with this
lesson, as we do have a deploy
script in here, we also have a
TypeScript edition in here as
well that we're additionally not
going to go over. And of course,
if you get totally lost, there's
a ton of instructions in here to
help you learn more and help you
work with this specific
repository.
So let's do a quick review of
what we just learned. So ERC 20
tokens, or EIP 20 tokens or or b
p or p p, or any of these dash
20. Improvement proposals are
what's known as the token
standard. And the token
standard, these tokens on chain
actually just tokens that are
smart contracts. Now, these
tokens are obviously different
than the layer one tokens like
Aetherium, or polygon or
Avalanche or arbitration, those
are not going to be smart
contracts, those are going to be
blockchain native tokens, and
you'll hear me refer to it as
blockchain native tokens a lot.
versus these tokens, these ERC
20, these smart contract tokens,
which are just smart contracts.
And they're just kind of a
combination of these functions
that represent how many tokens
each address has, we can create
our own token with all the
specifications added. Or we can
just use openzeppelin to import
a token in now another popular
repo like open Zeppelin is going
to be this one from Rory capital
called soulmate. And they're
both aimed to be standard
libraries for solidity. And one
of the important things to keep
in mind is that these tokens
have this allowance mapping. And
you can allow other addresses to
have access to your tokens and
move your tokens around. This is
important, especially when we
get to later on when working
with defy when we want to give
some smart contract access to
our tokens so that they can
input it into their defy
protocol. It's also a little bit
tricky. And you want to make
sure you're not allowing
malicious contracts to interact
with your tokens. And we'll also
see that when we start to
interact with these tokens more
before any contract can interact
with our tokens, we need to
approve them to interact with
our tokens. And that's it. Now
you're a token wizard, and you
can deploy your own tokens. Take
a break, get that coffee, and
I'll see you in the next one.
All right, welcome to the next
session, we are going to be
learning about defy in this
session and going to be
programmatic, and going to be
programmatically interacting
with the defy protocol. I am
incredibly excited for you for
this session, because defi is
one of the best use cases for
smart contracts. And one of the
use cases that I am specifically
most excited for now, as I've
mentioned, the past defy stands