for decentralized finance, we've
left some links in the GitHub
repository for you to learn more
about Defy. One of the main
reasons we're so excited about
defy is because we move away
from this area of traditional
agreement. And that's what smart
contracts are all about. They're
about removing this centralized
entity, from our financial
world, and especially from these
financial institutions that have
a conflict of interest. They're
in business to make money not to
keep our money safe not to make
us money. And we want to work
with a system where everything
is transparent, especially when
it comes to our financial
services. So we want to move to
this world of smart contracts,
especially when it comes to our
money. And in my mind, defi is
going to be the industry that
affects the masses, the quickest
because of how much fair how
much better decentralized
finance is than centralized
finance. And at the moment, the
rates and the yields and the
interest that you gain in defy
is much better than centralized
finance, because remember, will
go away from these centralized
protocols, saying, hey, trust
us, we'll give you access to the
markets or hate trust us put
your money in us will keep your
money safe to this cryptographic
math base guarantees instead of
having to trust these companies
and these entities, which is
what we want. And additionally,
the more our Oracle networks get
better, and the more Oracle's
networks work with these smart
contract platforms like
Aetherium, like polygon, like
arbitrage them, the more data
and the more complex financial
products that we can do. Now,
one of the other reasons I'm so
crazy excited about defy is if
you look at this little chart
right here, it shows the
different markets by size. Now
this this image is a little bit
outdated, but it still shows you
the relative sizes of all these
different industries defy right
now is a $200 billion market,
there's about $200 billion
locked in the defy industry. And
I'll show you that in a minute.
Cryptocurrency actually, at the
time of recording isn't 360
billion. It's actually like 1.8
trillion. So it's a lot more
than this. But still, it's a
massive subset of all these
other areas like gold is a $10
trillion market. The stock
market is almost $100 trillion
global real estate, almost $300
trillion derivatives as
quadrillion dollars. So the FBI
is a super tiny, tiny, tiny,
tiny subset right now and in my
mind, all of these areas can be
re landscaped with Defy. So
we're ramping up, we're getting
there. So it's gonna be up to us
to make some of these protocols
and make it Much easier for
people to get into the space
where their finances are going
to be more fair, more
accountable and more
transparent. And with better
yield rates, we can actually see
a pretty good summary of what's
going on in defy this site
called defy llama. It shows
total value locked in all these
different decentralized
protocols. And we can see a lot
of these are across multiple
chains, right. And a lot of
these are EVM compatible chains,
Aetherium, Biden, smart chain,
avalanche, Fanta, drawn polygon,
all these are EVM, compatible
blockchains, where we can see
exactly how much money
independent users have put into
these protocols. The time of
recording Ave is the number one
protocol for total value locked.
So there's $22 billion locked in
Ave, which is the protocol that
we're going to be going over
today.
So what is Ave So are they is a
borrowing and lending protocol,
it allows us to borrow and lend
cryptocurrencies. So we can
actually put down a token as
collateral, it's kind of similar
to like putting money in a bank,
and earn yields on other people
borrowing that collateral from
us almost exactly what a bank
does, except for the fact it's
what's called noncustodial. To
the Ave team never touches our
money. Nobody ever touches the
money. It's all just a smart
contract. It's all just this
programmatic code. So we can be
rest assured, no one's going to
run off with our money, no one's
going to do anything bad. And we
also gain these higher yields.
borrowing and lending is a
critical piece for creating
really any interesting financial
applications. If you want to
short sell something, if you
want to leverage up on some
asset if you want to. If you
want to do more complex
financial products, you need
borrowing and lending. Now a lot
of the typical FinTech or
financial technology or finance
terms do apply here. And this
course isn't going to be a deep
dive into exactly how these
financial products work. And
it's also not going to be a
course on finance. If you want
to learn more about finance,
we'll leave a number of links in
our GitHub repo associated with
this course. So you can learn
more about finance and become
what I like to call a defy
quant, quantitative defy
engineer. And I am so excited
for more defi quants to get into
this space. Alright, so here we
are in the Ave application. It's
at testament dot Ave dot
markets, we are in the testament
of Avi now, everything that
we're going to do here is going
to work on Main net as well, but
we're going to use it on their
test net. Now this is actually
obvious older UI, and they have
a new website that looks even
better than this. But we're
going to be going through a lot
of the basic functionality
depositing taking out a loan,
potentially even shorting an
asset, if we want, I don't
recommend going to the site
because it might not work and
COVID the way you'd expect it
to. So for this, just sit back,
relax and watch. In order for us
to actually short sell or margin
trade. The first thing that
we're going to need to do is
actually deposit some
collateral, we need to deposit
some collateral in order to
borrow this way. If we never
repay back the loan that we took
out or the the amount that we
borrowed, Ave, we'll just go
ahead and take the collateral
that we put in here, we'll do
what's called a liquidation
call. And that's why this is
actually a little bit safer than
short selling in traditional
markets. Because if your
collateral is less than how much
you have borrowed, you'll just
immediately get liquidated, but
you still lose a bunch of money
so like don't get liquidated. So
what we want to do now is we're
gonna scroll to Aetherium, we're
going to connect our wallet
here, we're going to move to
COVID test network browser here.
And we're gonna go to this
deposit piece. So it already
shows our balance here we have
point two COVID eath. Let's
deposit 0.1.
We're gonna hit deposit Metamask
can pop up, confirm. But once
this goes through, this means
that we've have it deposited and
we go to our dashboard, we can
see we have some eath here,
point one eath got some API,
this is kind of like that
percentage return that we're
gonna get back for, for
depositing into Ave. And yes, we
can use it as collateral here,
we have this, this marked as yes
here. So that's exactly what
we're going to do. And it says
nothing borrowed. Yep, we can go
ahead and hit this borrow now
button. And we're gonna get
brought to the borrower screen,
and we're going to choose which
asset we want to borrow. Now,
whenever we borrow one of these,
there are these API's, right?
This is the percentage that over
the course of a year that we're
gonna have to pay, in order to
actually borrow this asset. The
stable one means it'll always be
for or variable means it
actually changes depending on
kind of how much liquidity the
protocol has, you can kind of
pick which one you want to do
stable is you're always gonna be
a 4% variable is going to be a
little bit riskier, but you
might get a lower fee. So we're
actually going to borrow some
dye right, because dye is a
stable coin. It's worth $1. In a
way, you could call this taking
out on margin because we're
taking out dye to borrow and
another way we could say we're
shorting dye which is kind of
funny to think about, but you
get to choose how much you want
to borrow here and you'll see
this this thing called Health
factor I'm going to zoom in a
little bit this thing called
Health factor here as we as we
scroll this thing. So this
health factor is how close to
being liquidated you are
remember how I said you can get
liquidated this health factor
represents how close we are to
getting liquidated. This means
means how close we are to always
saying, You know what fu we're
taking your funds. If it goes
below one at any time, somebody
can liquidate you and take a lot
of that deposit that we put in,
there's some math behind
actually what the health factor
actually is, you can head over
to the Ave documentation, which
I will leave a link in the
description to kind of read more
about the health factor. So
we're going to borrow 29 die
we're buying, we're borrowing
basically 30 bucks. Gonna hit
continue, I'm gonna do a
variable, zoom back out,
continue, we're gonna borrow
metamath pops up, confirm
transaction that's pending. And
we're gonna go to the dashboard.
And now we can see kind of our
new balance here, right, we can
see the point one eath,
deposited and 29 die. And we can
see our health factor up here,
you can even click this little
button, saying, hey, it
represents how close you are to
being liquidated, we can see the
value here, our eath is worth
like $200, or die is worth 30
bucks. So we're good. We're
pretty healthy here. In order
for Avi to understand and under
to price the underlying
collateral, so it knows how much
it can lend out. Obviously
another one of these protocols
that uses changing price feeds
to price, the underlying
collateral, many of these
billion dollar defy protocols
use chain link on the back end
to do all their pricing
mechanisms. And that's
essentially it, we could then
repay our debts, we could borrow
more assets, we could swap
assets around. And the interest
return, we get onto pausing our
assets is amazing. So now that
we learned a little bit about
how to use their UI, which is
hosted on IPFS, by the way,
let's go ahead and let's learn
how to do all this and do even
more programmatically so we can
become defy quanta engineers.
Now, like I said, we're going to
be working with the Ave v two
protocol, if you want to try out
the v3, you absolutely can, if
you can go there and play with
it right now, it still has more
money locked in it, which is
great. But the v3 protocol is
obviously the latest addition.
So we're gonna be flipping back
and forth between the
documentation and our code base.
So I recommend that you have the
documentation up as well. And
per usual, all of the code that
we're going to be working with
is in this hard hat defi Free
Code Camp repository. So let's
jump in. I'm in by VS code, I'm
in my folder with this course,
we're going to make a new
folder, we're going to call it
hard hat, defy FCC, we're going
to cd into it. And then we're
going to open it up with code
period. Or you can also do per
usual, File Open and then open
that folder. Now we're in a new
project, we're going to do yarn,
add dash dash Dev, aren't hat.
And we're going to add hard hat
and start up our minimalistic
hard hat project. Once again,
for starting up your
minimalistic hard hat projects,
I usually just copy paste from
another folder, or I just used
that hard hat starter kit that
we saw in the smart contract
code repo. But whatever works
best for you to get your project
started, you can use now that
we've got this, we can run yarn
hardhat. And we'll just create
an empty hardhat.config.js. Now
to save us some boilerplate
time, I am going to copy paste
my hard hat.config.js from a
past project into this one, just
to make it so we don't have to
go through that boilerplate
setup again. And I'm also going
to copy paste this line from our
heart at smart contract lottery.
Again, if you want to use your
package JSON or your yarn dot
lock to install dependencies,
you absolutely can. But I'm just
going to paste that in here and
run it. And then I'm going to
copy paste over my prettier
files, so that all my JavaScript
can be formatted the way I want
it to be. Okay, great. Now we
have a minimalistic project spun
up, let's go ahead and get
started learning how to interact
with the AVI protocol here. So
let's make a quick readme and
talk about what we want to be
able to do. So first, we're
going to want to be able to
learn how to programmatically
deposit collateral. And if we
stopped right there, that might
be enough, we'd be able to
programmatically deposit
collateral, and in doing so we
earn yield, we'd earn that
percentage return just on our
deposited collateral. So
accomplishing this by itself is
already a feat. But let's say we
want to go one step further, we
want to get into these more
interesting financial products.
So after we deposit some
collateral, we're going to learn
how to programmatically borrow
and other asset, the deposited
collateral is going to be eath,
slash wrapped eath, which we'll
talk about in a little bit,
we're going to borrow another
asset, which for this demo is
going to be dye. And the reason
that we're using dye is because
dye is what's known as a stable
coin. So dye is actually a token
on the blockchain created by
this maker Dow where the price
of the dye token is always
pegged to $1. So we're putting
down eath as collateral and
we're borrowing cryptocurrency,
US dollars, sort of, we're
borrowing this token, which
represents a US dollar and then
we'll just repay that I will
repay almost everything back and
you'll see why we don't repay
everything back in a minute. One
other protocol that I want to
talk about quickly is the
uniswap protocol. And the
uniswap protocol has become this
haven for trading. It's a
decentralized application that
allows us to trade assets and
tokens with each other on
something called an automated
market maker. It ends basically
a decentralized Stock Exchange,
but with tokens and again,
tokens aren't exactly stocks,
they're very different. So when
looking to get some of these
assets It's like wrapped
Aetherium or dye or link token.
On a main net, oftentimes,
you're going to use one of these
decentralized exchanges. And
obviously, these decentralized
exchanges are much fairer,
because everything that happens
on them is transparent, much
fairer than centralized finance,
everything that happens on them
is transparent. You can see
everything that's going on on
chain, which is absolutely
phenomenal. So let's go ahead
and get started here. And let's
just create our scripts folder.
Because in this project, we're
actually not going to create any
contracts ourselves, we're just
going to learn how to interact
with these protocols. If you do
want to learn how to build some
of these protocols, at the end
of this session, we will give
you a ton of links. And we'll
have a special guest explain a
few different ways to learn how
to build more of these
decentralized protocols.
Although we've already built one
with our decentralized lottery,
which is fantastic. Let's create
some scripts here. And for all
of these things, deposit
collateral, borrow and repay.
We'll just put this all in a new
script called Ave borrow dot
Jas. So we're gonna do
everything in here. And since
this is a script, it's going to
have the same setup, as we've
seen before, right, so we're
gonna have this main thing
around an async function. Main,
and then we'll have our imports,
of course at the top. Now
something that's important to
note, go to avi, we go to the
protocol, we kind of read
through the docs, and eventually
we would find out the protocol
treats everything as an ERC 20
token. And but we know that
Aetherium or the native
blockchain token that you're
using, isn't an ERC 20 token.
And the reason that treats
everything like an ERC 20 token
is that it's just much easier,
right? If everything's using
this ERC 20 token standard, it's
much easier to send in and
interact with stuff.
On a lot of these protocols,
when we go to deposit Aetherium,
or polygon, or arbitrary marks
cetera, what actually happens is
they send your Aetherium through
like what's called a web
gateway, and swaps it for weath,
which stands for rapt ether. And
it's basically Aetherium. But in
an ERC 20 token contract, so
what we want to do is going to
do that same thing, we're gonna
skip kind of using this web
gateway. And we'll just get the
Web Token ourselves, and we'll
use that as collateral. So in
our script tag, I'm going to
make another file called Get
weath.js. And in here, we're
actually going to go ahead, and
we're going to build a script
that will deposit our token for
web token. Okay, so let's create
the script. And there's a link
to the web token on ether scan,
and on Main net in the GitHub
repo. And the way it works, is
you actually deposit Aetherium.
And in return, it'll give you
the web token on Rigby right
now, by deposit 0.05. Go ahead
and write I'm connected to ether
scan, I'll go ahead and write
this transaction, I'm gonna
drink pee. So I don't really
care if it's if it's the actual
contract or not, because it's
not real money. But I'm going to
deposit 0.05 eath. And after our
transaction goes through, we
copy the contract address, we
add this token to our Metamask
the same way we added link will
import tokens, paste the address
in here, add custom token,
import tokens will now see we
have some wet token in here, I
deposited 0.1 before so 0.1 plus
0.05, which is why it shows 0.15
Because I did it twice, well,
while I wasn't recording. So um,
but this is how you can get this
wet token into your contract.
And then anytime you want, you
can call this withdrawal
function. And you can withdraw
your Aetherium out of this and
do what's called Burn your wet
token. So when you swap back
from weath to Aetherium, you hit
this withdraw and boom, you
basically swap them back because
this contract itself right now
is holding your Aetherium token.
Pretty cool, right? So in our
get wet function, we're not
going to add this main thing
here, we're going to create get
West here just as kind of a
module and we're going to import
it into our Ave borrow. So we're
not going to do this this main
thing that you see here.
Instead, we're going to create
an async function called Get
Wes. And then below, we're going
to export it. So we'll do module
dot exports equals get weath.
And we're going to export it so
our Avi borrow can use this get
West script that we're creating
right now, let's add let's go
ahead and do this. Well, in
order to interact with a
contract, we're going to need an
account. So we can do const
deployer equals await get named
accounts, per usual. We'll do
const get name accounts equals
require hardhat. My VS code
automatically imported that
thank you VS code now. And now
we want to call the deposit
function on the west contract.
How do we call this deposit
function on the west contract?
Well, how do you call any
contract? Well, what do you
need? You need the ABI and then
you need the contract address.
Drill this in. You're always
going to be the API and the
contract address to interact
with the contract. We know that
if we give we know that if we
give our project the whole
contract, it'll get the API but
we also know If we just do the
interface, that's just as good,
it won't give us all the
functionality, but it will tell
it will give us the API, it will
tell our ethers, what functions
it can use. So we're going to
create a new folder, create our
contracts folder. And in here,
we're going to create a new
folder inside of that called
interfaces. And this is where
we're going to create our web
interface. Now a web interface
is going to be really similar to
an ERC 20 interface. So if you
want to go ahead and try to add
it yourself, feel free to do so.
Or what you can just do is you
can come to the GitHub repo
associated with this lesson,
come to iOS and just copy paste,
right, you'll see the functions
in here are exactly the same as
an ERC 20, allowance approved
balance of decimals named blah,
blah, with these additional
deposit and withdrawal
functions. So I'm going to copy
all this, move back over to my
hard hat project, we'll create a
new file, we'll call I left dot
soul. And just to note,
oftentimes, a good best practice
is to have interfaces, start
with eyes so that you know what
to interface and then we'll
paste it in here. Now in order
for this to compile, we'll need
to use 0.4 point 19 version of
solidity. So what we can do is
we can come over to our, our
head.config.js. We have solidity
compilers, version 0.07, or
whatever versions that you have
in here, we can add or just
replace. So I'm going to put a
comma here, version 0.4 point
19. Save. And now in order to
make sure we can get that API,
do yarn, hardhats compile, or hh
compiled, and great, we compile
this interface. So now we have
the ABI to interact with. Now
that we have the ABI, a little
check mark here, let's go ahead
and get the contract address.
But for reasons that we're going
to learn about very soon, we're
actually going to work just with
main net set of getting the
Rinkeby test and address, I'm
going to look up with main net,
we're going to find the web
token on Main net. So I'm going
to copy the address of main net.
And again, you can just grab
this address from the GitHub
repo associated with this lesson
as well. And for now, we're
gonna say check a little check
mark here, and paste the address
there. So now we're have the ABI
compiled from an interface, and
we have the contract address for
main net. But let's go ahead and
create this contract now. So we
can say const, iOS equals await
ethers dot and then we'll need
to import ethers from Hardhead
as well. Ethers dot get contract
at this is another one of these
functions on ethers, it allows
us to get a contract at a
specific address, we'll say get
contract app, we use the iOS ABI
for now, we'll just hard code
this address in here. And then
we'll connect it to the
Deployer. So we're saying let's
get this web contract with the
ABI of iOS at this address
connected to Deployer. So we
could go ahead and run await AI
with dot deposit. And we'll set
value which will be some
amounts. Let's go ahead and at
the top, we'll say const amount
equals let's do ethers dot utils
dot parse, ether, and then we'll
do 0.0 0.02. So we'll deposit
0.02 will say const TX equals
that will do await TX dot wait
one wait for one block to go
through. And then we'll just get
the balance will say const. With
balance equals await I with that
balance of employer. So we're
going to call the balance of
function on our iWeb ERC 20
token. And then we'll just do
console dot log got West
balance.to string.
So we're using the main net
address in here. And we're gonna
say okay, we're going to deposit
some amount, we're going to
wait. And then we're gonna go
ahead and get the balance right,
so we're just depositing our
Aetherium so that we can get
that ERC 20 version of
Aetherium, that West token here.
Now, you might be thinking,
Okay, why are you putting the
main address in here? Let's
Patrick, slow down. Let's go
ahead and let's create a mock
Web Token contract address.
Let's deploy the mocks first,
and then we'll go ahead and use
that same setup that we've been
doing this whole time, why you
why you directly hard coding
this in here. Well, I've been
alluding to this for some time.
But there's another way that we
can run tests in our smart
contracts. And this is with
something called main net
forking, we can actually do
something where we fork the main
net, and run a local hard hat
node. That's pretending to be a
main net node. And all we have
to do is update our hard head
config to do so. So let's talk
about forking for a minute. So
on the left here, we have a
blockchain an example of
blockchain it's going to be
something similar to a test net
or main net like Rinkeby, eath,
main net polygon etc. This is
going to be a blockchain that we
deploy to. Now there are a whole
bunch of blocks in here, right?
We have this huge chain that we
can work with. And all this
information on the blockchain is
public information, like this
block is going to have
transaction transaction
transaction, each one of these
blocks is going to have a whole
bunch of transactions. And all
this information is on this
public blockchain. In addition
to all these transactions, it's
going to have things like price
feed contracts, it's going to
have things like Ave contract,
the Web token, contract, etc.
All this contract information is
public. So hypothetically, if
it's already there, we should be
basically able to copy this to
our local environment and do
some simulations ourselves. And
that's exactly what forking
does. A fork blockchain
literally takes a copy of an
existing blockchain like on the
left here and brings it on our
local computer. We actually have
control over our blockchain
that's running locally, because
it's gonna run on a local
computer, similar to hard hat.
Now, everything we do on this
local forked blockchain is not
going to affect main them,
because it's a simulated
blockchain. It's just running in
our local environment. So we can
actually interact with this
forking this kind of local
blockchain that resembles that
mimics the actual blockchain.
And here's what forking doesn't
do, it doesn't download the
entire blockchain into our local
setup. Anytime we reference an
address. Anytime we reference,
hey, there's something at a
specific address, we make an API
call to our Aetherium node,
which again, we're using alchemy
and say, hey, oh, what's at this
address, and it'll return just
that specific contract for us.
This way, we don't have to
download the whole blockchain.
And it's a lot quicker. And we
can also do this forking to run
our tests to run our scripts to
do everything. And now you might
be thinking, wow, Patrick, this
sounds awesome. Well, why don't
we just do this for everything?
Well, there's some trade offs.
The pros are that it's quick,
it's easy, and a test will
resemble what's on Main net. Now
the cons are that we need an
API, and we can't do everything
locally. Some contracts, some
contracts are complex to work
with, and mocks might just be
better. But using a forked
network might be a good way to
run your tests, it might be a
good alternate to just using
mocks. So it really depends on
what's right for you and right
for your project. But it is a
fantastic tool, especially for
something like Avi, where we
want to quickly test some
things. Now the hard forking
also will give us a bunch of
fake accounts. So we'll still
get a bunch of fake accounts on
Main net that will be given a
theorem. So we'll get fake main
net accounts for this forking.
So for the rest of this, we're
going to be using this forking
to run our scripts and run our
tests. If you want to go back
after this and try this all out
on COVID. We've got a whole
bunch of different addresses for
the COVID network so that you
can run these scripts directly
on COVID. And you can see the
transactions yourself. Just note
that when using COVID, you'll
want to make sure that you're
using the same addresses, as are
in the AVI docs for the COVID
network, because they do change
sometimes. Great, let's go
ahead, we'll go to our RT head
dot config dot j s. And now
we'll go to our networks, which
right now, I don't have
anything, I only have ranking.
And we'll add hard hat in here,
we'll add a little comma down
here. And we'll say, you know,
the chain ID of course is going
to be 31337. We'll add this
forking keyword. And in here,
we'll say the URL for a Forking
is going to be our main net RPC
URL. And this is another reason
why we're using alchemy. Alchemy
is fantastic at these forked
blockchains, and has really good
pieces here. So what we can do
is we can come back to our
alchemy dashboard, we'll create
a new app. This one will be for
Aetherium main net, and we'll
say forking chain. We'll say for
forking, we'll go ahead and
create this on a theory and main
net. Now that we have this
forking chain, we can do the
same thing. We'll grab our API
key, we'll come back to our
project, create this new file,
we'll create our dot env. And
we'll do main net RPC URL equals
and paste that in there. In our
Hardhead config, we are now
going to be forking from mainnet
RPC URL whenever we work with
the heart at blockchain. So now
that we have this in here, let's
go ahead and try to run this get
wet function. Because since
we're forking the blockchain, we
should be able to go ahead and
simulate this. So backing off a
borrow, we'll go ahead we'll do
const, get weath
equals require and then we'll
pull this script that dot dot
scripts slash get weath. And
then, in our main function,
we'll just run await yet. So to
run our script here, we'll do
yarn hard hat, run scripts
avevamo.js. And our default
network is hard hat. So we could
either do dash dash network hard
hat or just run it. And
remember, since in our config,
we're saying, hey, when we run
the hard hat chain, use this
forking, we're going to be
forking, so let's go ahead Run
this ran to air main. Net RPC
URL is undefined. Well, that
makes sense. Let's go ahead and
add this consummated RPC rel
equals process study and v dot
made it RPC URL. Let's try this
again. And we now see we got,
you know, this much weath,
which, again, that much wealth
is gonna be
1-234-567-8910 1234567 0.02
wealth, which is exactly what we
want. So now we have a way to
interact with main net locally,
which sounds kind of crazy. But
he's incredibly powerful for
exactly what we're doing right
here. So we have a way to fork
main that eath and run our
scripts and kind of test to see
and simulate what it would be
like to actually run these
transactions. So we're gonna do
like that, our get with function
looks good. And obviously, we
would still modularize this, we
put this in our helper Hardhead
config, but we're going to skip
doing that for now. So let's go
head back to the AVI borrow. And
let's go ahead and flesh the
rest of this out. Now, let's go
ahead and set up the rest of the
boilerplate here. So we'll do
const Deployer, because we need
an account, obviously equals
await, get named accounts. And
then we'll do const get named
accounts equals require. Now we
want to start interacting with
the ABI protocol, well, what do
we need, we're gonna need the
ABI and the address, nothing
changes, we're gonna need these
two. So what we can do is we can
go to the Ave docs. And again,
we're going to be on V two. And
we can go ahead and find the
contract address in here. Now
the way it works is they
actually have a contract, which
will point us to the correct
contract. The contract that
we're going to be doing all the
lending with is this lending
pool. And there's actually a
contract to get that contract
address. And to get the lending
pool address, we have to go to
the lending pool address
provider. It's this contract
that will tell us what the
address of the lending pullets.
And we can actually see the
deployed contract section, we
can see the address of this
contract. And we can see the
address of all the main ones and
the COVID. Once again, if you
want to play with this on COVID.
But we can see lending pool
address provider is going to be
located right here, we can copy
this address. And we'll just
take notes of this.
And that lending pool, we're
going to get from the lending
pelagics provider. So let's
actually create a function that
will get us the lending pool
address from the lending pool
address provider. So down here,
we'll create async function, get
lending pool. Now in order to
interact with this lending pool
address provider. Same thing,
we're going to need its address
and its API, we have its
address. So let's go ahead and
get its API, you can go ahead to
the GitHub repo associated with
this lesson. And just copy paste
it from the interfaces section.
You could also look directly on
the blockchain to see what this
contract looks I can create your
own interface. Or we can go
ahead and use the interface
right in the documentation. So
we have islanding Palach.
Provider, I'm just going to copy
this from the ABI docs. But
again, you've got a number of
options. And so in our contracts
in our interfaces, let's let's
stick iwth in interfaces here.
Let's create a new file. And
we'll call it I lending pool
address provider, dot soul. And
we'll paste it in here, we just
see we're using 0.6 point 12. So
be sure to in our Hardhead
config to make sure we have that
we don't so we're just create a
new one 0.6 point 12 And then
we'll compile yarn Hardhead
compile and compiles so awesome.
We now have the ABI here, we'll
get this contract by saying
const lending pool address
provider equals await ethers dot
get contract at will say I
lending pool address oops
address as I lending pool
addresses excuse me, I'm going
to update the name I Lenny pull
addresses provider islanding
pool addresses provider, we're
going to pass in that contract
address that we got from the
Ovid docs here. Paste that in.
And then we're going to connect
it to our Deployer. So we're
going to have our get lending
pool, get past that account
variable and then we'll just use
the account here to connect it
and the account that we're going
to pass is of course going to be
our Deployer. In our lending
pool address provider. There's a
function called Get lending pool
which returns the address of the
lining pool and this is going to
be the function that we're going
to call so we're gonna say const
lending pool address equals a
weight lending pool address says
probes address any pool address
says provider dot get lending
pool and that's it we'll have
the lending pool address and
then we'll have this contract
give us the lending pool
contract by doing const lending
pool equals await ethers dot get
contract Add. And we need to do
the same thing, the interface,
the interface, the address, and
then the account. So back in the
docs, we can grab the I lending
pool by copying this like this.
We'll go back to our contracts
interfaces, new file, I lending
pool, that's all. And we'll
paste it in. Now with this one,
if we scroll to the top, we
noticed that we're importing
from some local places that we
actually don't have in our
contracts area, we can once
again go ahead and add the AVI
protocol v2 from NPM. And just
use this as our imports. So
we'll do yarn, add dash dash dev
apt have a slash proto call
hyphen V two. And now that we
have the Add Ave protocol in our
node modules, we can update
these imports to point to our
node modules instead of our
local files. So I'm just gonna
go ahead and tell you that the
islanding pledge provider is
that Ave slash protocol hyphen V
to slash contracts slash
interfaces. And then data types
dot soul is gonna be at of a
protocol hyphen v2 slash
contracts slash, proto call
slash libraries, slash types,
data types, that's all again to
make sure this is right, yarn,
Hardhead compile or hh, compile.
And Cool. Looks like I did that
right? Lending pool equals await
ethers dot get contract at,
we're going to be using lending
pool, I lend the pool here,
we're going to use this lending
pool address got from the
addresses provider. And then the
account, which is going to be
our Deployer. And now we can do
return lending pool. And if we
want, and now that we have this
function get lending pool backup
in our main function, we can say
const lending pool equals a
weight, get lending pool and
then pass the Deployer. And then
we can even do a little console
dot log,
lending pool address and then do
lending pool dot address. And
since we're making it forking,
we can kind of just keep running
this right. So we'll do yarn
hardhat run scripts. Ave Baroda
Jas, there are multiple
artifacts for contract II
lending pool addresses provider.
And this is because in our node
modules, import all this stuff
from contracts and in here, and
there's already in islanding,
pool addresses provider in those
add ons slash contracts. So
actually, we don't even need
this, I lending pool added
service provider, we can go
ahead and delete it. Our time
right now is getting confused.
It's saying Oh, are you
referring to the one that you
downloaded from NPM or the one
that you made, which which one
do you want to use. So we'll
just make it easier for hardhat.
And we'll say okay, well, we'll
delete the one that we created,
we'll use the one that we've
downloaded here. And now we
should be good to run this
again. Because now there's only
one for to pick from, which is
the one we downloaded from NPM.
And perfect, we get our get
weath printout here, and then we
get lending pool address is
here. And this is going to be
the actual lending pool address
on ether Aetherium main net. So
if we go back to ether scan,
copy that address and paste it
and ether scan, we can see it's
even labeled Ave v two, and we
can see a ton of transactions
going through all the time. And
ether scan is having a hard time
keeping up with all the
transactions. So we've got the
lending pool address, we've got
some web token, what do we need
to do? Now we want a deposit of
what do we need in order to
deposit the token? Well, if we
look at the deposit function in
the avec GitHub, we can scroll
in here and we see it eventually
we'll call this safe transfer
from which is basically going to
be this transfer from function,
since we're calling transfer
from it's going to be this
contract, that's actually going
to pull the money out of our
wallet. So in order to give the
Ave contract, the ability to
pull the money out of our
wallet, we need to do what we're
going to need to approve the
contract. So first, before we
can even deposit we're gonna
need to approve it to get our
web token, we're gonna have to
get the Web Token first. So
let's get the Web Token address
we'll say const Web Token
address, equals and this is
where we marginalize it and get
it from our hard head helper
config. But for now, we can just
hard code it, the Web Token
contract address is going to be
the exact same thing as what's
in get web and then want to
approve. So let's write an
approved function because we're
going to use this a couple
times. So we'll make an async
function and approve ERC 20
And we'll take a contract
address a spender address, which
is going to be the contract that
we're going to give the approval
to to spend our token and amount
to spend so exactly how much we
want to prove it. And then an
account to do all this on. So in
here we'll say const ERC 20
token equals await ethers dot
get contract at. And we could
say I WEF but maybe we just want
like a simple ERC 20 token
interface. And we're going to
grab that by cheating a little
bit coin to our hard head defy
FCC. We're going to go to
interfaces and grab this
interface from here. So we're
going to copy this, paste it in
here New File IO ERC 20 dot som
paste and now we have an ABI for
ERC. 20s So we'll do get
contract that ERC 20 Actually
let's change this name to ERC.
20 address so we're going to get
the contract with the ABI of IRC
ERC 20 at contract address ERC
20 address and then we'll
connect it to our account here.
So and once we have the ERC 20
We can do const TX, we're going
to do that approve transaction
we'll do a weight ERC 20 token
dot approve spender address, and
then amount amount to spend.
We'll do we'll do a wait TX dot
wait for one block. And we'll do
a little console dot log saying
approved. Now if you don't run
this function before you try to
deposit you'll just get an error
saying hey, token is not
approved, which is a pretty
common error. So if you ever see
that just know, I forgot to
approve my token. So backup in
our main script, we'll go ahead
and run this function. We'll say
await approve ERC 20 with the
Web Token address lending pool
dot address because we want to
give the len pool the approval
to pull our web token from our
account. And then we'll give it
some amount to actually will
import a mount from get weath as
well. Mount we gotta go back to
get with an export it so we can
actually import it. So get with
exporting that amount that 0.02.
So we'll prove the amount and
then we'll connect we'll have
our Deployer do it obviously
because we're doing everything
with the Deployer. So we'll
approve the ERC 20. And then
once we approve, we can go ahead
and deposit it. So we'll say
console dot log, depositing
that. And then we'll run await
lending pool dot deposit. If we
look at the deposit function, we
can see all the parameters that
the deposit function takes. We
can also see it in the Ave v2
documentation and we just look
forward the posit. And we can
see it takes the address of the
asset that we're going to
deposit how much of that asset
we're going to deposit address
on behalf of we're going to do
it on behalf of ourself and then
a referral code, which right now
is just always going to be zero
because the referral code has
been discontinued. So we're
going to deposit the wet token
address, we're going to deposit
our web token, we're going to
posit 0.02 of that web token.
And then we're going to use a
deployer ash and then referral
code is going to be zero. And
then we'll do a little console
dot log the positive. So let's
try this script. Let's see if it
works. I'm just going to hit up
to go ahead and rerun this
script to rerun this command I
just ran into doing a little
compiling that ERC 20. That song
was compiled one solidity file,
got a bunch of wrapped Aetherium
lending pool address. We
approved it, we deposit we were
depositing it and then we
deposited it. So if we're
looking at our little readme
here, we get a little checkmark.
We've done step one, we've
deposited our collateral.
Awesome. So now we have some
collateral to use to borrow
other assets. Great. So now
we've deposited let's go ahead
and learn how to borrow now
through a couple of new lines,
and we'll say borrowed time. So
in order for us to borrow, we
probably want to know how much
we can borrow. And we want to
know more about our account,
right? We want to know how much
we have borrowed, how much we
have in collateral and how much
we can borrow. So there's a
function that Avi comes with
called Get User account data,
which will return the user's
account data across all
reserves, how much collateral we
have down the total value it in
its eath price, we have the
available borrows and eath
current liquidation threshold,
loan to value etc. Now these are
really important metrics. If we
have one, eath and collateral
that doesn't mean we can borrow
one eath of assets. Each one of
these tokens have some different
values like loan to value. For
example, if you have one eath
you can only borrow zero point
75 for the dye token, this is to
reduce risk of the collateral
and reduce risk of people not
having enough collateral down as
prices fluctuate. There's a
liquidation threshold of 80% if
you have one eath as collateral
and point 81 eath borrowed,
you'll get what's called
liquidated. So what is
liquidation? When you put down
collateral and you borrow, if
the amount that you have
borrowed past this liquidation
threshold is passed that 80% Or,
or depending on different
assets, it's different people
can do what's called liquidate
you. This is when they pay back
some of your loan that you took
out. And they also get to buy
some of your collateral at a
cheaper price. This keeps the
Ave platform solvent, and it
makes it so that there's never
more borrows than there are
collateral in order to borrow
assets, we still need that
collateral down. So basically,
if you borrowed more money than
you've put up, other users can
can take the money that you've
put up in return for them paying
for your loans. So we obviously
don't want this to happen. And
the audit protocol
programmatically doesn't want to
have not enough money to do
this. So they incentivize users
to liquidate, in case of these
failures is the protocols come
with this thing called a health
factor, which if this health
factor is below one, you go
ahead and you get liquidated,
the actual function to liquidate
somebody is called liquidation
call. So you can actually build
a bot and you can liquidate
users who go insolvent and you
can make a fee, you can make a
reward for actually doing this.
These protocols need to stay
solvent, they need to have
enough money to lend out. And
they programmatically enforced
this, which is why it's so
great. You can learn more about
liquidations in the liquidation
documentation. So this get us
account data will tell us how
much we have collateral, how
much we have in debt, and how
much we have available to borrow
based on how much collateral we
have. We can see the current
liquidation threshold we can see
the loan to value and then we
can see our health factor, which
is obviously really important.
If our health factor ever falls
below one, we get liquidated. So
we never want this hell factor
to fall below one when we're
borrowing assets. So let's
create a function that can grab
that first. So let's create a
new function called async.
Function get it borrow user
data, and we'll pass in the
lending pool contract, we'll
pass in the lending pool
contract and the account that we
want to get the data for. So we
can say const. And actually, we
can pull out just the values
that we want, we could pull out
the total collateral eath total
debt eath and the available to
borrow. Let's just pull out the
total collateral eath the total
debt if and the available,
borrows. So this equals await,
lending pool dot get user
account data of account. And now
we'll even just kind of logged
us out we'll say console dot log
you have total collateral eath
worth of eath the positive
console. Log you have total debt
eath worth of eath borrowed and
then console dot log you can
borrow
available borrows eath worth of
eath. And then we'll just return
available to borrow will turn
available borrows eath. And
we'll return or total debt, we
don't really need to return
total collateral we could if we
want we really just want to
print it out here. So now back
in our function, we can do in
our main function, we can run
let, I'm going to do that
because we're going to be
calling this a few times
available borrows eath. And
total debt eath
equals await, get borrow user
data of lending pool and
Deployer. And if we run this,
we'll see how much we can
actually borrow yarn hard hat or
just h h run scripts on a
borrowed.js and work on our
forked blockchain here. And
remember, it is going to be a
little bit slower. And this is
kind of one of the disadvantages
too because it does have to make
API calls whenever we want to
interact with these chains. And
then we got total collateral
eath is not defined. And that's
because I spelt total wrong. So
let's spell total correctly. And
we'll run this again. But okay,
great. So you have this month's
worth of eath deposited, you
have zero worth of eath borrowed
because we haven't borrowed
anything, and you can borrow
this much worth of eath.
Remember, the amount that we can
borrow is always going to be
less than the total amount that
we have as deposited. That's why
we see this lower number here.
So cool. So that's how much we
can borrow. Let's use that to go
and borrow some time. So we have
this total amount we can borrow
an eighth and we're gonna get to
borrow time. I promise we're
gonna get to borrow time, but we
need to figure out What's the
conversion rate of diets? We're
gonna get how much we can borrow
in eath. But we want to borrow
dye. So how much of dye can we
borrow based off of the value of
eath? And to do that, we're
gonna have to get the dye price.
And how are we going to do that?
Well, you guessed it, we're
going to use chain link price
feeds. If you look in the AVI
documentation, you can find
price Oracle, which is a
contract that you could actually
use right directly from Avi. But
the first thing it does is check
from a chain link aggregator,
which we already know how to do.
So we're gonna go ahead and just
call directly from the chain
link aggregator. So let's create
a new function function, we'll
call it get dye price is first
we're going to need to get that
interface, same thing. So you
can either go right to Hardhead
defy and just grab the interface
right from here, we could swap
this out with just an import
from chainlink NPM, as well. But
I'm just going to go ahead and
copy paste a new file, this is
going to be the Ag reg gate, Tor
v3 interface. Dot saw that we've
worked with so many times. Now
that we have this interface,
this will compile, we're
obviously looking for latest
round data, which will give us
this answer here, which is going
to be the price. So let's go
ahead and grab that. So we'll
say const di eath price feed
equals await ethers dot get
contract at and we'll use the
air, Greg a Tor v3 interface
will get the dye eath price feed
right from the chain link Docs.
So we go to docs dot chain dot
link UVM chains will go to
contract addresses on Aetherium.
Or look for di eath on Main net.
And we see di eath is right
here. So we'll grab this and
again, we're just hard coding it
in the GitHub repo associated
with it. With this, we put it in
a little config file, but we can
just go ahead and hard coded in.
And for this one, we don't need
to connect this to the deployer
account. Since we're not going
to be sending any transactions,
we're just going to be reading
from this contract, right. So
reading don't need a signer
sending me to signer. Now we can
say const price equals a weight
dye eath price feed dot latest
round data. Now latest round
data, as we know is going to
return us this huge thing. And
we only want the answer at the
first index. So another way we
could do this, we could just
wrap this whole thing up. And
then once this returns, we're
gonna say okay, just grab that
first index here, which will be
that price. And then we could do
a little console dot log, the dy
eath. Price is in price dot two,
like that, and then return
price. So we can go ahead and
run this as well test this out,
just by hitting up and then
enter. Depositing we deposited
this is how much we can deposit.
Nothing Oh, and I forgot to call
it oh, excuse me, let's go up.
This, let's say const dye price
equals await get dye price. And
tada. The dye youth price is
this big number, which of course
we know is going to be $3,289
which is which of course is
gonna be 3289 di per eath. Now
that we have the dye price, we
can figure out how much dye we
want to borrow. So great, we
have the price. Now let's figure
out the amount that we can
borrow in dye, we have the
amount we can borrow eath, we
need to convert it to die. So
we'll say const amount die to
borrow equals available, be the
available borrows in eath.to
string. And then in JavaScript,
we can do this.to string but
still do math. So times 0.95
times and then we'll do the
reciprocal of that die. So one
divided by die price.to number.
So this will give us the amount
of die that we can borrow. And
then we'll want to get this in
way. So if we print this out
right now, console dot log, you
can borrow.
Run this now, you can borrow
amount die to borrow. Not in way
units, which we need in way
units, but you can borrow 48
Die, which based off the price
looks about right. So to get the
correct units, we'll say const
amount, di to borrow way. That's
going to equal ethers dot utils
dot parse ether, MT di to
borrow.to string. This is just
purely the amount of dye to
borrow right so we get 48.79
die. But again, we want that in
way the die token has 18 decimal
places similar to Aetherium. So
we need that amount in way and
then we can go ahead and start
actually borrowing now. So we'll
create a new function called
borrow die async function,
borrow die will take the die
address. Take the lending pool,
take the amount die to borrow
and weigh in Then of course,
we'll take the account. And all
we'll do is we'll do const.
Borrow TX is going to be a
weight, lending pool dot borrow,
die address, amount die to
borrow. And again, we can go
right to the documentation, if
we want, it takes the address of
the asset, the amount, we want
to borrow the interest rate
mode, which is going to be
variable or stable, the referral
code and then address on behalf
of, we're going to say one for
the interest rate mode, where
one is going to be stable. And
then we're going to do zero or
this referral code because
that's debunked now, and then
we'll do a count, then we'll do
a wait, borrow TX dot Wait, wait
one transaction, and then we'll
do console dot log you've
borrowed. Well, and that's it.
So we now have this borrowed I
function. So back up in our main
function, right, now, we can
finally do the borrow time. So
we'll do a wait, borrow die. And
we'll pass those parameters in
here. So we're going to do
const, die token address, equals
and we're just going to hard
code this from main net. So we
can look up die token address,
main net, we'll grab this
address here, this looks like
this is indeed the DI token, we
check right on the object get
up, we could check right on the
ABI of actual code, since we're
just testing, we're just gonna
go ahead and grab from ether
scan here. So for borrow dye,
we're gonna need the dye token
address, we're gonna need the
lending pool contract the amount
of dye to borrow in way, and
then our Deployer. And then
we'll await borrow dye. And then
we will run this get bar user
data again, just print out the
information about where we are
after we do that. So when we can
run this, again, we should see
the amount that we have
borrowed, updated, our first
call to that function is gonna
say, Hey, you have this much eat
the positive Do you have nothing
borrowed, you can borrow this
much eath, we get the price, we
get how much we borrowed, we
borrow. And now it says you have
this much where the eath
deposited and you have this much
worth of eath borrowed and you
can borrow this much eat. So we
actually now have bought a bunch
of this dye actually borrowed.
And the reason we're doing times
zero point 95, we don't want to
hit that cap of the maximum
amount that we can borrow. So
we're saying hey, let's get 95%
of the amount that we actually
can borrow. So we're not going
to borrow everything, we're just
gonna borrow 95%. And you can
see that the amount of eath we
have deposited is actually
higher. This is because we're
actually gaining interest just
by having this eath deposited.
And now that we have some dye
borrowed, we borrowed 48 dye,
which is equivalent to this much
Aetherium. And then we still
have a little bit more we can
borrow because we only borrowed
95%, which is great.
Awesome, we've taken out a
borrow programmatically, let's
repay at least some of it here.
So we're gonna have to create a
new function that's going to use
the repay function in the
contract. So we're gonna do
async function repay, and this
is going to take the amount that
we want to repay the dye address
that we're going to repay the
lending pool and then the
account now to repay once again,
we're going to have to approve
sending our dye back to Ave So
in here, the first thing we need
to do is we actually need to
call wait prove ERC 20 with the
dye address, lending pool dot
address, mount and then
accounts, right because approve
ERC 20. That's the input
parameters it takes, and we need
to approve sending the dye back
to the contract. So we borrowed
it, and we're gonna send it
back. Now we're actually going
to send it back. So let's say
const, repay TX equals await,
lending, cool that repay the
address, amount, one account.
And then we'll say await repay
TX dot Wait, that will do
console dot log repaid up in our
main function, we're going to do
a weight repay, and we're going
to give it the amount dye to
borrow in way. We're gonna give
it the dye token address, give
it lending pool, and then we'll
give it deployer get you borrow
user data one more time just so
we can print out the final
amounts. Now, you'll notice
something though, we're going to
give back all of the dye that we
borrowed. However, we're still
going to have a dye balance,
you'll see that when I run this
that we're still have a little
bit of Aetherium borrowed,
basically, we'll still have a
dye balance because we'll still
have a little bit of die borrow
and try to figure out why before
I answer it actually. So we have
this tiny, tiny tiny amount of
eath borrowed here and we have a
much larger amount of eath
deposited so Why do we still
have this tiny, tiny amount of
eath borrowed? Well, the reason
is because as we borrow dye, we
actually accrued interest. So we
still owe dye back. Now what we
can do is we can do something
like uniswap, to actually swap
our Aetherium, for dye to repay
the rest of our debt here. And
that's how we could actually
finish repaying all the debt is
to get a little bit more dye to
pay off that interest that we
had accrued. And if you want,
you can go back and you can do
the exact same thing we did here
to grab the uniswap code, place
it in here to programmatically
repay your debt as well. But at
this point, you have just gone
through the entire lifecycle
here. And that is absolutely
massive, huge congratulations.
You've just deposited borrowed
and repaid tokens from the AVI
protocol. Now I'm going to go
briefly show you what some of
these transactions are going to
look like on an actual test net,
on an ether scan, you'll see
that when we deposit our
collateral, we actually get back
what's called an A token, or an
interest bearing token, these
tokens keep track of how much
collateral or in our case how
much web token we have deposited
in the AVI protocol. And when we
want to withdraw our wealth
back, we burn these eight
tokens, we remove these eight
tokens, you can see that our
first transaction is going to be
deposit and I wanted to show you
what it looks like when you
actually deposit one of these
tokens, this transaction
associated with this lending
pool, that deposit right here,
if you look at tokens transfer
down here, you can see we
actually we deposited, you can
see that we actually sent rapt
ether to the ARB a contract. Now
you'll also see this a weath
stuff here. So what is this a
with stuff. So to keep track of
how much you've actually
deposited into Ave, Ave will
give you your own a wealth token
or a token to keep track. And
this is this interest bearing
token, you actually can see up
here a little bit of interest
already for actually depositing
these tokens into the protocol.
And it's this token, that will
keep going up, the more people
borrow and the more people use
the protocol. So you can
actually grab this token
address, interest bearing token
this a token, I can import it
into my meta mask. And I can see
that I have 0.1, which
represents my initial deposit
00517 dot that dot A with and if
you keep this up long enough,
this number will slowly go up as
you get more and more. Because
the interest keep out and you
can see just went went up right
there, the interest will keep
changing and keep going up.
Obviously, we have so little
deposited that the interest
isn't gonna go up very quickly,
but it will go up, the more
people use the protocol. And
since I'm using a test net, the
actual usage of the protocol
isn't very high, but you get the
picture.
Awesome, you've done phenomenal
to get this far. Let's do a
quick recap of everything that
we've learned. And then we'll
head on to the next section. So
first, we learned about the web
token or the wrapped Aetherium
token, it's a way to tokenize
our Aetherium or layer one
blockchain native token. Then we
learned a little bit about the
AVI protocol, and how it's this
defy primitive for borrowing and
lending assets. And we can
actually gain interest by
depositing our tokens and our
assets into Ave we learned a
little bit of also about
uniswap, which is another
incredibly important defy
protocol, which allows us to
swap tokens between each other
in the decentralized context,
then we learned that we can
actually deposit some of our
tokens into the AVI protocol,
which is a decentralized
borrowing and lending platform
and similar to a bank will
actually gain interest on our
deposited tokens. But first, we
have to approve them. Because
anytime you want a contract to
interact with your tokens, you
need to approve the contract to
do so. And then we go ahead and
deposit once we deposited we got
the dye price. And then we
learned that we can actually
borrow dye we can borrow an
asset based off of how much
collateral we put down. And then