we learned how to repay it back.
We learned about forking a
blockchain as opposed to using
our own main blockchain. Another
thing to know if you are using
an RPC URL like something from
alchemy so awesome you've
learned a ton about defy now
defi is an absolutely massive
powerhouse when it comes to the
blockchain. And it is one of the
most important things
blockchains can do. If you want
to learn more about defy and
read more on Defy. I've got some
more links in the GitHub here so
that you can learn more about
defy and one of them in
particular that I want to show
you is this one called speed run
Etherium. Not only does it give
you a ton of defy examples, but
it gives you a whole bunch of
other examples as well. And this
will be a good test of
everything that you've learned
after you pass this course. Or
even right now if you want to or
whenever you want and to talk
about it a little bit more, we
actually have Austin Griffiths
here to talk a little bit more
about speed run Aetherium
himself, I'll pass it over to
Austin.
Hey, what's up, I'm Austin
Griffith, I want to show you
speed run Aetherium. speed run
Aetherium is a great way to get
started in Aetherium. If you are
a developer, it's targeted at
web two developers becoming web
three developers speed run a
theory. m.com is the website. It
takes you through both getting
started and kind of getting
getting an idea for the language
and the syntax. But that's just
the start. Just understanding
the language is just the start,
you feel like you're you can do
anything. And you're on the top
of the world when you finally
get the syntax of solidity
together, and you can jam
through a smart contract. But
really getting context with the
space and figuring out what
works and what doesn't, that's a
whole nother battle. And that's
where speed run aetherium.com
comes in. So let's speed run the
speed run. First, you will get
scaffold e down speedrun
Aetherium kind of revolves
around scaffold eath and uses
scaffold eath as a base, you'll
want to tinker around with some
ideas within solidity. And let
me show you what I mean by that.
So with scaffold eath, you have
a front end and you have your
smart contract. So scaffold eath
comes with hard hat out of the
box. And you will use the
combination of hard hat and
react to build a DAP where
you'll deploy both the smart
contract and the front end. And
this, this ability to edit your
smart contract and have your
front end auto adapt to it is
kind of the key to scaffold
ease. I just added some extra
extra exclamation points. But
we'll see that show up over
here. Once this contract
deploys, there we go, there's
that. So just real quick, again,
if I create like a un 256 public
counter, and we set that equal
to five, and then I build a
function called increment,
that's public that does counter
public, there we go, that does
counter plus, plus, you can
imagine what's going to happen
here. So you, you edit a little
bit of solidity, you deploy your
contract, and then your front
end auto adjust to that. And it
gives you the ability as a
developer to call those
functions tinker with your smart
contract to play around, you can
even have a console log in
there, where it you know, sets
says the count now is there we
go something like this. And
let's go ahead and deploy that.
Notice I'm doing these quick
iterations, I'm making small
changes in solidity, and I'm
seeing those changes show up in
the front end. And I'm tinkering
with those in the front end and
testing my assumptions. Here, if
we go look at our hard hat node,
when I make this increment call,
we should see that nice console
log there, you know, this
address, set the count to eight,
right? Very, very cool. So this
is scaffold eath. This is what
speed run Aetherium is built on
top of, you'll get in here,
you'll edit your smart contract,
then you'll edit your front end,
you'll point your front end at
some particular network, you'll
deploy your smart contract,
you'll deploy your app, it just
gives you the ability to have a
front end along with your smart
contract. And you'll have that
as you're building your smart,
smart contract. So to have this
front end, to tinker with your
smart contract is going to help
you kind of figure out how you
want to write your solidity,
like, is this going to be a
mapping? Is this going to be an
array? How am I going to track
this struct, you can kind of do
this in an iterative process by
just throwing it in here into
your smart contract and
tinkering with it on the front
end and trying it out and seeing
what you need to build. So
that's scaffold eath. And that's
the base that you'll need to get
started with speed run Ethereum.
Once you've you're able to have
this all installed, you'll
you'll have your kind of react
front end here with yarn start,
you'll have yarn chain, which
will run your your hard hat
node, then you'll do yarn
deploy. Once you have that setup
locally, you're ready to go with
speed run Aetherium. And you can
also do this right here and
challenge zero. So challenge
zero, gotta go zero index,
right, we got to be nerdy
challenge zero sets you up with
just getting the environment
setup, you'll you'll quest on
building a simple NFT example.
It's going to come with an NFT
smart contract. And it's going
to come with an NFT front end a
little kind of like minting
view, it'll come with all of
this stuff to do that. And it'll
walk you through basically
challenge the row is going to
hold your hand, it's going to
take you through every step
you'll have to get get you have
to have a certain version of
node E, L some some correct
range of node and yarn
installed. Watch out yarn has an
executable on Linux, make sure
you have the yarn, the package
manager. But after you have get
your node and yarn, you'll run
through cloning down each
challenge. You'll do an install,
you'll fire up the chain and
you'll fire up your front end.
And you'll have a working app
that lets you interface with
your NFT smart contract. You'll
go through here and you'll learn
about wallets. Then you'll start
minting NF Ts and you'll send
those NF T's are Round. And
that's challenge zero, it's just
getting you started. Here even
in challenge zero, you'll deploy
this NFT to Rinkeby. And you'll
also deploy an app and allow
your friends to go to your app
and mint in FTS on Rinkeby. So
that's the first challenge, it
looks like we even like dive
into open see and play around
with some of those mechanics.
The second challenge challenge
number one challenge one of
speed runner theory is like
where it all really starts. This
really shows off the superpower
of Aetherium. It sets it up. So
you need to build an app where a
bunch of people that don't
necessarily trust each other,
can coordinate and stake into a
smart contract. And this is
like, this is the superpower of
Aetherium. The ability for you,
the developer to write a few
simple rules to allow jerks to
coordinate financially, and not
greet each other and steal each
other's money, right? You're
we're building these financial
systems, there's, you know, game
theory and economics and so many
other things going on here. But
you as the developer, you're
writing simple rules, and you're
building a system that allows
people to coordinate. So
challenge one, we'll take you
through how to get set up with
your steak or docile, smart
contract, you'll install
everything exactly the same way,
you'll fire everything up. And
then it's just going to walk you
through the kinds of things that
you will need in your smart
contract. But you'll have to
write the solidity yourself. So
this is this is not going to be
a handheld tutorial, hell thing,
you're going to have to write
the smart contract yourself. And
there's some guidelines and some
rails that kind of help you out,
but it's not going to do it for
you. Okay, so that's, that's
Quest One is or that's
challenge. One is building a
decentralized staking app. Then
challenge two is building a
token vendor this so in
challenge one, you'll learn
things like how to send money
into a contract, how to have a
contract, keep track of
mappings. In challenge two,
you're going to learn contract
to contract interaction, you're
going to learn about ERC 20s,
you're going to learn about
specifically the approved
pattern, which is kind of a
jerk, it's, it's hard, it's a
hard thing to deal with is the
approved pattern, you need to go
to your token contract and
approve the vendor to take some
money, then in a second
transaction, you need to go to
the vendor and have the vendor
grab the money from the token
contract and do something else.
So that's that's challenge two
is learning about tokens and
vendors, and is starting to
really like get you kind of
exposed to the idea of this like
massive multiplayer game that is
Aetherium. And also kind of like
how to build these vending
machines that anybody can get
to, then you'll build a Dex. Now
once you've once you're done
with 01. And two, you're really
kind of you have a license to
learn at this point, you're
you're ready to really like go
do some damage and build some
cool things, maybe go build a
couple other things, but come
back and come come hit challenge
three, challenge three is going
to be a little bit more open
ended, there's going to be a
cohort of other people that are
also building this. And you have
to get through the first three
challenges to even get to
challenge three to even get to
this chat room. But there's a
chat room where other developers
that are also building their own
decks are all there together,
and you can kind of learn with
them and chat with them. But
you're going to build an
exchange. And you're going to
build an exchange that works in
a smart contract in a
decentralized way with no
centralized breaking points. And
what that's going to mean is
you're going to have to have
reserves of both eath and tokens
and you're gonna have to have a
pricing function and LP tokens
and all sorts of other things
that you'll have to learn about
as you get to it. Then challenge
five is a multi SIG wallet. Such
a fundamental important thing
about how to store your eath
safely is going to be in a multi
SIG wallet and how you can have
multiple identities even even
like the the base of like what a
Dow is, is sort of like starting
with a multi SIG wallet. And
you'll need to build one of
those you'll need to understand
call data call data is super
weird and complex. And
everything's a transaction even
when you're just poking a
contract. It's a transaction,
and you have to craft that call
data correctly to say, I would
like to call this specific
function on this specific
contract. So that's multisig
wallets and then it kind of ends
up we've got more challenges in
the pipeline, but it kind of
ends on build an SVG NFT so much
fun to build an NF t that crafts
the actual drawing in the smart
contract and renders it. So
that's the speed run, go speed
run Aetherium checkout scaffold,
eat start building, build
something awesome on Aetherium.
hearts, hearts, hearts, go get
them.
Austin Griffith is one of the
OGS when it comes to helping
engineers get caught up and up
to speed in the blockchain world
so massive thank you to Austin
for all he's done so far.
All right now we're gonna get
into NF T's. Let's do this. Now,
I've already made a number of
videos on what NF T's are and
how to start working with NF
T's. So we're going to watch a
portion of the previous Python
edition of this course where I
explain and a piece from a high
level and then of course, we're
gonna get into the ultimate NFT
tutorial. So let's learn about
NF T's look, NF T's are hot
right now. Nf T's also known as
ERC 720 ones are a token
standard that was created on the
Ethereum platform. Nf T stands
for non fungible token is a
token standard similar to the
ERC 20. Again, ERC 20 is like
link of a maker, all those
goodies that are found on the
Etherium chain. An NF T or a non
fungible token is a token that
is non fungible, this means that
they are starkly unique from
each other. And one token isn't
interchangeable with any other
token of its class. A good way
to think about it is $1 is
interchangeable with any other
dollar $1 is going to have the
same value of another dollar.
Those are fungible tokens that's
like ERC 20s one link is always
going to be equivalent to one
other link, by contrast is going
to be NF T's those of you nerds
out there, we know like a
Pokemon would be a good example
of an NFT you're one Pokemon is
going to have different stats,
different moves, sets, and isn't
interchangeable with any other
Pokemon, or maybe a more
relatable one. It's like a
trading card, or unique piece of
art or the like. So that's what
these NF T's are there non
fungible, non interchangeable
tokens that for the moment are
best represented or thought
about as digital pieces of art
that are incorruptible and have
a permanent history of whose own
them who's deployed them, etc.
Now, like I said, NF T's are
just a token standard. So you
can actually make them do much
more than just be art. You can
give them stats, you can make
them battle, you can do really
unique things with them, you can
do pretty much whatever you want
with them. But right now, the
easiest way to think about it,
and the most popular way to
think about it is by calling
them ah, ah, ah it's odd, or
some type of collectible or just
anything that's unique. Now,
they've been getting a ton of
buzz recently, because we've
been seeing more and more of
these being sold at insane
prices, like we saw x infinity
sell nine plots of their land
nine plots of their unique land
for $1.5 million. We also saw
the original creator of the Nyan
Cat, you know, this cat
sold for like 300 eath. So
apparently people really value
these things. So like I said,
they're just tokens that are
deployed on a smart contract
platform, and you can view them
on different NFT platforms like
open sea or wearable. And these
are the NFT marketplaces that
let people buy and sell them.
You obviously can do that
without these marketplaces,
because it's a decentralized but
they're helping give a good user
interface. Now, like many of you
out there, my initial thought to
NF T's was okay, this sounds
pretty dumb. But I think that
that was dumb. I think art does
have a lot of value. And I think
that artists are not always paid
fairly for what they do. And
this is actually a huge issue
right now in the modern day
world where an artist can make
some type of art people just
copy paste it, you know,
everywhere and, and they never
get attribution for what they
make. So having a really easy
decentralized royalty mechanism,
or some type of mechanism where
these artists can get accurately
comped for what they're doing, I
think, is really important. I
love music. I love movies, those
are pieces of art that I digest.
And I really like and I think
it's fair for them to get comped
appropriately because they are
providing value to my life. I
think NF T's are a great way to
solve this issue as kind of
having these decentralized audit
trails and, and royalty trails
that we can set up and, and see
really transparently without
having to go through some
centralized service. So that's
the basic gist of it. Let's talk
some more about the standards
ERC 721 standard are the NFT
standard. This is the basis of
it all there is another standard
that's semi fungible tokens, the
1155 We're not going to talk
about that here. But you can
check it out the main
differences between a 721 and
the ERC 20 and ERC. 20 is they
have a really simple mapping
between an address and how much
that address holds. 720 ones
have unique token IDs, each
token ID has a unique owner. And
in addition, they have what's
called a token URI, which we'll
talk about in a minute. Each
token is unique. Each token ID
represents a unique asset. So
since these assets are unique,
and we want to be able to
visualize them and show what
they actually look like we need
to define those attributes of
the object. If it's a piece of
art, we needed a way to define
what that art looks like. If
it's some type of character in a
game, we need to wait define
that character stats in the NFT.
This is where metadata and token
URI has come in. So if you know
anything about Aetherium, you
know that sometimes gas prices
getting pretty high, especially
when it comes to storing a lot
of space, it can get really,
really expensive. So one of your
first questions might be Well,
are they storing these images?
And these are pieces on chain?
And the answer is sometimes back
when they were coming up with NF
T's and artists were deploying
stuff, the eath devs and the
artists were like yeah, art,
let's do that art. I'm just
gonna deploy This one megabyte
image onto the Etherium chain.
And Oh god, it's so much gas
expensive, delete button.
Otherwise, it's not, it's not
good. And they realized that if
they put all this art on chain,
it's going to be incredibly
expensive. So to get around
this, what they did is they put
in the standard, what's called
the token URI. This is a
universally unique indicator of
what that asset or what that
token looks like and what the
attributes of the token are, you
can use something like a
centralized API, or IPFS. To
actually get that token URI.
Typical token URI has to return
something in this format like
this, where it has the name, the
image, location, the
description, and then any
attributes below, there is often
this talk of on chain metadata
versus off chain metadata.
Because it is so much easier and
cheaper to store all your
metadata off chain, a lot of
people will use something like
IPFS that is decentralized, but
does take a little bit of
centrality to keep persisting,
but they can also use their own
centralized API. However,
obviously, if that goes down,
then you lose your image, you
lose everything associated with
your NFT. Because of this most
NFT marketplaces actually can't
and won't read off on chain
attributes or on chain metadata,
because they're so used to
looking for the token URI.
Obviously, if you do off chain
metadata, you can't do anything
really cool or really
interesting or have any gains
with your NF T's. For example,
if you wanted to create an on
chain Pokemon game, all your
attributes would need to be on
chain in order for your Pokemon
to interact with each other.
Because if it was off chain,
then that becomes a lot harder
to cryptographically prove. So
if you're new with NF T's and
you're like wait, this is kind
of a lot of information, I'll
make it easy for you. If you're
looking to render an image, I'm
an NFT, add your image to IPFS,
add a metadata file pointing to
that image file on IPFS. And
then grab that token URI and put
it and set it as your NFT. The
chain link DND article does a
great job of walking you through
this and showing you how to do
this. So be sure to read that if
you're looking to learn how to
do that we're not going to cover
that in this video, but we will
be deploying our first NFT with
some on chain attributes. Again,
having your attributes on chain
is really going to allow you to
build really creative NF T's
that build games or have
interesting properties and and
really makes the authenticity of
your NFT guaranteed because
those attributes are always
going to be on chain.
Alright, so now that we know the
basics of approximately what an
NF t is, and similar to the ERC
20 You can see the E IP 721 or
the ERC 721 non fungible token
standard on the Aetherium, ie
IPs. And once again, if you
scroll down, you can see all the
different events and the
different functions that come
with creating this token. And
now everything that we're going
to do is going to be available
at this GitHub repo. This hard
hat NFT FCC, we're going to
actually go through all the code
down to deploying and creating
our own customized NFT. And I've
labeled this the ultimate NFT
repo as part of this course,
because we're going to go
through a lot here, we're gonna
go through a basic NFT, a real
minimalistic NFT and then an
IPFS hosted NFT. That is
dynamic. And it uses randomness
to generate unique NF T's so
that we can have provably rare
and appease or provably rare
cards or provably rare tokens or
stats or whatever you want. And
then we're going to do what's
called an SVG NFT. These are
entities that are 100 percent hosted on
chain, so you don't need an off
chain. So you don't need IPFS,
you don't need an off chain
database. And this one's also
going to be dynamic, where it's
going to use price feeds in
order to fluctuate what the
image of the entity actually
looks like based off the price
of some asset. And here are the
images that we're going to be
using. And we obviously have
these three adorable doggies
here. If you want to follow
along with the Quickstart, you
absolutely can. And I'm going to
do a quick overview of just
running the code to show you
what it's going to look like at
the end. Basically, what we're
going to do is we're going to
have our code, we're going to
run hardhat deploy dash dash
network, rink B, dash dash tags
main. And this is going to
deploy all of our contracts and
everything. And then finally, if
we go to test nets dot open c.io
And we grab the address of one
of these NF T's we should be
able to put it in here see our
actual NFT as a collection with
an item. Or Additionally, we can
just go right to the contract.
We can read the contract, we can
get the token URI, and then we
can copy this token here, I
paste it into our browser or any
IPFS is into our browser, and
then grab the image attribute
and see what this actually looks
like on chain. So with all that
being said, let's learn how to
build this ultimate NFT repo and
build all of these different
customizable NF T's let's jump
in. So once again, we're in our
terminal I'm going to create a
new directory. We're gonna call
it hard hat and a T for FCC.
We're gonna cd into that. And if
T FCC and we're going to open
that up with code.or, you can
hit File, Open Folder At this
point, you'll have gotten pretty
familiar with the setup of our
code bases here, feel free to
copy over or do whatever you
want to do for our setup, we'll
do yarn, add dash dash dev hard
hat. And then while that's
loading, I'm going to copy over
my prettier files. Because I
want to use prettier, I'm going
to copy over my hard
hat.config.js. And I'm also
going to grab my package that
Jason copied over here, I'm
going to delete this old package
dot JSON. And I'm just going to
hit Enter on this and rename the
one I just copied over from
package copy to package json.
And the reason I'm doing this is
so that I can just go ahead and
run yarn and install all this
stuff for me. Or we can just
come back over here and just
grab this lesson nine hard hat,
smart contract lottery, all that
stuff, again, just run that
massive piece as well. Or you
can copy over your package json,
and then just run yarn that will
do the same thing. Now we don't
have to keep doing this
boilerplate over and over and
over again. And then while
that's loading, I'm also going
to grab my Dotty and v file that
we've been using on a past
couple of projects, the
readme.md. And we'll just do
what we're gonna be doing here.
So we're going to make three
different contracts. One is
going to be a basic NFT, using
that ERC 721 standard, then
we're gonna do a random IPFS
hosted NF t. And then finally,
we're going to do a dynamic S V
G NFT. So our random NF T is
going to be random at creation
time, this is going to give some
true scarcity and some true
randomness to our NF T. And it's
gonna be hosted on IPFS. Our
dynamic SVG NFT is going to be
hosted 100 percent on chain, and the
image of it's going to change
based off of some parameters.
That's what makes it a dynamic
SVG NFT.
Let's go ahead and we'll create
a new folder, we'll create our
contracts folder, and we will
create our first NF t this is
going to be our basic NFT. And
I'm going to go a little bit
quick here, because most of what
we're going to be doing is
actually things that we're
already familiar with. So we'll
do basic NF T dot soul in a new
file. And let's go ahead and
let's do it. Let's go ahead and
we'll do spdx license
identifier, it's gonna be MIT.
We'll do pragma, solidity,
carrot zero, point 8.7 pragma,
solidity, and then we'll do
contract, basic NF t. Let me
just basic, get a t.so, like
that. And we'll say contract
basic NF t. And then we'll just
run hard at compile or yarn
hard, hit compile, and it looks
like we're doing well here so
far. Okay, perfect. Based off of
that NFT token standard, we go
back that EIP, we're going to
need a whole bunch of different
functions here, we're going to
need transfer events, we're
going to need owner events
bounce up, we're going to all
these different functions. And
we could 100 percent implement these
and transfer them exactly like
the ERC 20 did, or once again,
so we can use, you guessed it,
we're gonna be using open
Zeppelin contracts for this as
well. So we come back over to
open Zeppelin, we go over to
contracts. And we're gonna go
ahead and add this with yarn,
add dash dash Dev. So yarn, add
dash dash dev at opens up on
contracts, like so. And while
that's going through, we can
look at the ERC 721 of this and
we can see what creating a
minimalist ERC 721 looks like.
Now there's a number of
extensions that come with its
ERC. 721 In this example that
they give us. They're using ERC
721 Uri storage, which we'll
talk about in a little bit. So
we've added it in here. And now
we can actually import that ERC
21 from opens up when in our
contract. So we'll do import at
open Zeppelin slash contracts
slash token slash your C 721
slash ERC. 721 does so they use
a different one in the demo, but
don't worry about that. And same
as the ERC. 20 we're gonna say
our basic NFT is ERC 721. So
we're doing this inheritance,
you find the constructor, we can
see this has a constructor,
where it takes a name and a
symbol. So we're gonna want to
use this constructor and our
contract. So we're gonna say,
construct door.
And our constructor is just
going to be blank. But we'll do
the ERC 721 constructor and
we'll call this a doggie. And
the symbol will be dog just like
that. Our basic NFT we're just
going to have it be this doggy
here, right so it's going to be
an NF T of just a purely this
dog here. The name is going to
be doggy and the symbol is going
to be dog. Now in order to
create new dogs. What we're
going to do is openzeppelin code
comes with something called a
mint function exactly the same
as the ERC 20 So we're going to
create a function called mint
NFT this will be a public file
function that's going to return
you activity six. And we'll use
the safe mint function of this
ERC 20 or underscore safe mint
message dot sender will mint the
token to whoever calls this mint
function. And then we need to
also give this a token ID, if
we're looking back at the code
for the ERC 721. And again, you
can see this on GitHub as well,
we're gonna look at this safe
mint function, it takes an
address to who is going to own
the NFT. And then a token ID,
what is the ID of the token
based off of this address. So if
you have a collection of tokens
on the same smart contract, each
one of them needs their own
unique token ID. So what we're
gonna do is we're gonna create a
un 256, private variable called
S underscore token counter, and
it's gonna get initialized in
our constructor to zero, but
we'll just be explicit and say
es token counter equals zero.
And then in here, we'll just
have the token ID of this new NF
t be that token counter. And
then of course, we'll say s
token counter equals s token
counter plus one. So every time
we meant a new NFT, we up the
token counter, and then we'll
just return, we'll just return
the new tab counter. Right. And
then obviously, at the bottom,
we could do like function, get
token counter, this would be a
public view returns you in 256.
And I'm gonna go a little quick
here, because you've seen this
before, return s underscore
token counter, right, since it's
a private variable up here, the
public function down here to get
that token counter. So this
technically, is it. This is
technically an NF T. But what
does this look like? Well, right
now, this NF T isn't going to
look like anything at all, in
this EIP token standard. It has
this thing called a token URI.
And this is the important
function that tells us exactly
what this token is going to look
like. Like what we said in the
mini lesson here. This token URI
returns some type of URL or
universal resource identifier
that returns some JSON that
looks like this. And in this
JSON, we're going to have this
image part. And this image is
going to be a URL that's going
to point to what this image
actually looks like. Now this
URL can be hosted on chain, it
can be hosted on IPFS, it can be
hosted really wherever. But
ideally, we're not going to use
a centralized server to host it.
If this is hosted on a Google
Cloud or a centralized server or
whatever, and our centralized
server goes down. Well guess
what this MC is gonna look like,
it's not gonna look like
anything. So we want to use some
type of decentralized storage,
to get a URL, or URI to store
what this looks like. To make
this section a little bit easier
for you, I've actually already
gone ahead and hosted an image
to IPFS. For you, it's going to
be at IPFS dot dot slash slash,
it's going to look like this,
this is going to be the image
that we're going to use for our
dog here. If you create just
this image, though, as the token
URI, that's not going to work,
we need a URI that returns this,
with the image inside of it. Now
for this first section, have
already gone ahead and done that
for you as well. And that's
going to be located here. This
is what our token URI function
needs to return. So it's going
to have the name, the
description, the image URI,
which then points to the dog,
and then some attributes, etc,
etc. Now, you'll notice that the
image here is pointing to HTTPS,
dot dot slash slash ipfs.io. The
reason I did this was again,
just in case you didn't have the
IPFS gateway, but this would be
a lot better if this was in its
IPFS form. Because if the
centralized server ipfs.io, goes
ever goes down, this NFT will
show what it'll show nothing. So
it would be much better. If it
was instead of ipfs.io. It was
IPFS, colon slash slash, like
that, instead of ipfs.io. But
for now, this is what we're
going to be using. And you can
just go to the GitHub for this,
just to grab this for this
section. Right? Just go to
contracts, basic NFT, you can
just grab this, this, this top
part, just copy it like that. So
we're going to paste that the
token URI up, up, up at the top,
like so. Oh, it should be
returns, return. There we go.
Okay, cool. So we're just going
to copy paste that in here like
this. Like I said, even though
the token URI here is pointing
directly to IPFS, which is good.
If you actually go to this file,
the file is actually pointing to
http.ipfs.io. Again, for your NF
T's don't do that for this NFT.
I just did that just in case,
but for your NF T's don't do
that. And we're going to make
this a public constant variable.
Why? Well, because this token
you write is never going to
change. We're going to make this
NFT so that everybody who meets
one will have this exact same
adorable little puck here. And
the way we do That now is we
need to identify the actual
token URI function. So I'm going
to do it above get token
counter, we're going to say
function, token URI. And these
always take a UNT 256 token ID,
we're going to make this a
public view, override returns
string memory. And this needs to
return the token URI. Now, this
is going to be the most basic
way to create this, right. And
if we wanted to make this
function a little nicer, we'd
comment out token ID as well,
since we're actually not using
token ID. But we're overriding
in our in the ERC 721 that we're
importing. This has a token ID
function or a token URI
function. And we're overriding
this, right, we're not using
this at all, we're saying, Hey,
we're just going to use our own
here. And that's all we need for
this to work. And now if you
were to deploy this to rink B,
if you were to jump over to open
C test net, and you would deploy
this, this dog, this adorable
little pop would be what shows
up for all the minutes. So let's
go ahead, and let's create a
little deploy function for this.
So we'll do a new folder, deploy
a new file, we'll call this a
one deploy basic NF T dot j s.
And this is going to look real
similar to everything that we've
done before. So I'm going to
move a little bit quicker here.
const network equals require
hard hats, const development
chains, equals require dot dot
slash helper, hard hats config.
And I don't think I added that.
So I'm going to copy paste my
helper Hardhead config from our
last project. And if you get
confused, you can always just
come to the GitHub here, and
just go to the helper Hardhead
config and grab it from here, we
have that const development
chains, or say const verify
equals require dot dot slash
utils. Slash verify. We're also
going to grab our utils, I'm
going to copy paste so utils
folder from alas project, once
again, you can copy paste from
your last project, or you can
just go straight to the repo,
grab the verified dot j s, we're
going to go over these two
functions a little bit later,
but at least grab the verified
for now. And then we're gonna
start the function. So we'll do
module that exports equals async
function. We're gonna get get
named accounts, and deployments.
And we're gonna say const.
Deploy, log equals deployments
against deployer equals await,
get named accounts. So we'll do
a little log here just to get
started to do our basic NFT
doesn't take any constructor
parameters. So we'll say const
args equals a little blank here.
Then we'll do const basic NFT
equals await, deploy basic NF T,
exactly what we've seen before a
number of times at this point,
we'll say from Deployer. args is
going to be args. And then log,
it's going to be true. And then
we'll also do weight
confirmations. It's going to be
network dot config dot block,
confirmations, or one. Then if
we want to verify this, we're
going to once again do if it's
not development chains, dot
includes network dot name, and
process that EMV dot ether scan
API key will say log verifying
dot the dot await, verify basic
NF T dot address arguments which
are going to be blank, grab this
little log here, stick it right
underneath. And then actually in
our basic NF T. This should be
args not arguments. Now we have
a deploy script. Now we have a
basic NFT here in test data
deploy script, or any hh deploy
or yarn Hardhead deploy. And
oops, let's go back to the basic
kind of tea or mint and have tea
needs to return a UNT 256. Try
again. Get token counter also
needs to return a UNT forget you
into anywhere else. Nope. Okay,
looking good. And looks like
we're compiling well compiled,
deploying Well, now if you want
to deploy this to rink B, you
can. I recommend holding off
though, because we're going to
do that at the end. Now that
we've written a deploy script.
We've written the contract, you
already know what's coming next.
Yes, neat. What's next is the
tests now because we're not
actually learning too much more
here. I'm not going to walk you
through writing this test. I'm
going to challenge you now. How
to pause the video and write the
test out yourself and see how
far in this test you can
actually get. Remember, to test
it, you're going to want to run
yarn, hard hat test,
right, let's see if you can
actually write the test
yourself, then come back to the
video, see if your tests were
just as good or not as good as
what we did here. And of course,
you can always go to the GitHub
repo test sections. And if you
get lost, you can look at the
basic nft.test.js To follow
along. All right, welcome back.
Hopefully, you wrote some
awesome tests, taking the time
to actually do some of those
exercises is really going to
make you a much better engineer.
Following along with me, it's
awesome. But tinkering yourself
and trying to do everything
yourself is really what's gonna
make this stick. So I hope you
did pause the video. And hope
you did go ahead and try to
write the test for this
yourself, you've technically
just created a really
minimalistic NFT.
Great job. Let's kick things up
a notch. Let's move now to a
random IPFS hosted NFT where
we're going to do everything
pretty much programmatically. So
let's jump in. In our contracts,
we're going to create a new file
random IPFS, NFT, dot soul. Same
thing. spdx license identifier,
gonna be MIT pragma, solidity
carrot zero, point 8.7, or
whatever version you want to
use, will do contract random
IPFS NF? T, like so. So what is
this one going to do? So instead
of just minting any NFT, when we
meant an NF t, we will trigger a
chainlink VRF call to get us a
random number. Using that
number, we will get get a random
NF t that we're going to decide
on. And the random n of t that
we're going to use, it's going
to be either a pug a Shiva in
you, or a St. Bernard. So
whenever anybody mints NF T,
they're gonna get one of these
random three dogs. And we're
going to make this so that each
one of these dogs have a
different rarity, we're going to
make these dogs rare by
different amounts, say we want
the pug to be super rare, the
Shiva to be sort of rare, and
then the St. Bernard to be
pretty common. So probably it's
gonna be super rare Shiva in us
is gonna be sort of rare, St.
Bernard is going to be pretty
common, right? Or the most
common, if you will. So let's go
ahead and start building this,
we're probably gonna have to
make a function called like
request NF t, because we're
going to know that we're gonna
need to kick off a channeling
VRF request, we're probably
gonna have to make a function
fulfill random words, that's
going to take a un 256 Request
ID and a un 256. Array, memory
random words, as we've seen
before, we've done fulfill
random words in the past. And
let's let's even go one step
further, we'll make it so that
users have to pay to mint an NF
t. So this is going to be they
have to pay a certain amount of
eath to get the NFT and then the
owner of the contract and
withdraw the eath. So we're
basically paying the artists
here, we're paying the artists
to create these NF T's. And then
they can be the ones actually
actually withdraw the payment
for all these NF T's. And we're
also going to need, of course, a
function, token URI, which takes
a un 256. And this is once
again, same as our basic NFT
gonna be what this token
actually looks like. So let's go
ahead and get started creating
this. Now, because these red
lines are going to draw me
crazy. We're going to add some
visibility here, we'll make this
request NFT public fulfill
random words, we actually know
from the past is going to be
internal token URI is going to
be public. Let's build this
request NFT. And again, to
request a random number, go back
to EVM. Chains, we go to using
randomness, we can follow along
with the Dr. chain link again,
to figure out how to get this
random number. So since we know
we're going to be working with
chain link, we want to add at
chain link slash contracts. So
back in in our code base, we'll
add that in yarn add dash dash
dev at chain link slash
contracts, like so which was
perfect. And we can go ahead,
and we're going to import that
VRF consumer base V two and the
VRF coordinator interface into
our code because we know we're
going to use both of these. If
you want to just copy paste from
the docs, you absolutely can go
to pause here. And since we're
going to be using this view of
consumer base, we want to
inherit it. We're going to say
random IPFS and f t is V RF
consumer base V two and this
little, little wiggly line will
show up here saying This seems
to be override. So I'm just
gonna go ahead and add override
here. And this little wiggly
line is gonna stay there for a
little bit until we implement
the rest of the functions. So
let's go ahead and implement the
rest of those functions. Request
NFT, of course, is going to be
public here. And in order for us
to request an NF T, we're going
to need to call the coordinator
dot request random words where
we pass all this stuff in.
Right, so let's go ahead and get
all this stuff for our V REF
coordinator in our constructor,
so let's create a new
constructor. struct door. And
we're going to use the VRF
consumer base, the two
constructor to use to create our
constructor, the VRF consumer
base V two needs an address in
here for the VRF consumer base.
So we'll go ahead and we'll do
address VRF. Or did Nate Torre b
two. And then we'll pass this to
the VRF consumer base
constructor here, just by adding
that that red squiggly line has
gone away from me perfect. And
we want to save that address to
a global variable. So we can
call request random words on it.
So we're gonna go ahead up here,
we're going to say I underscore
var F chord. To me, Tor, we're
going to make this immutable VRF
coordinator. And we're going to
do it by saying VRF v2
interface, it's gonna be
private, immutable, you have
coordinator and then in our
constructor here, we're gonna
say IVF coordinator equals VRF,
coordinator v2 interface wrapped
around this like so. So we know
we're going to need this, we
know we're actually gonna need a
ton of these. So let's just add
all these variables in here,
we're gonna need the
coordinator, we're gonna need a
UNT 64 private, immutable, I
underscore subscription ID,
we're gonna need a bytes 32,
private, immutable,
I underscore gas lane, we're
gonna need a you int 32 private,
mutable, I underscore callback
gas limit, we're gonna need a
UNT 16 Private constants,
request confirmations, we're
gonna say it's gonna be three,
and then a un 32. Private
constant equals num words, which
is going to be one, and we'll
get this red squiggly line
saying it's mad at our our
constructor here. So let's go
ahead and add all of our
immutable variables in our
constructor. So we'll get the
VRF coordinator v2 from our
constructor will get the UNT 64
subscription ID, we'll get the
bytes 32 Gas lane, aka the key
hash, we'll get the un 256.
We'll do a UNT 32 callback gas
limit, then we'll go ahead and
do I subscription ID equals
subscription ID will do I gas
Lane equals gas lane will do I
call back gas limit equals call
back.
Yes limit.
Okay, a lot of variables set up.
But those are the variables that
we're going to need for the
chainlink VRF. Now we have all
these variables down in our
request. And if t we can request
a random number to get for our
random n of t, we're going to
say and our returns a yuan
tivity six Request ID. So in
here, we'll say request, Id this
request ID that we just
initialized I underscore VRF.
Core didn't a Tor dot request.
random words. And this should
look pretty familiar to what we
did in our lottery. I underscore
gas Lane comma, I underscore
subscription ID, comma, request,
con for nations. I underscore
callback gas limit. And then of
course num words and we can just
literally copy paste this from
the documentation or from our
last project, whatever you want
to do. So we are requesting this
random NFT here. Now here's the
thing, though, we want whoever
called this request function it
to be there and have tea, right.
And if we saw in our basic NFT,
when we minted the NFT, we call
this safe mint which needed the
owner and the token counter.
When we request a random number
four are NFT. It's going to
happen in two transactions,
right? We're going to request
and then later on we're going to
fulfill and it's going to be the
chain link node that's calling
fulfill random words. So if it
In the fulfill function, we just
do this safe meant message that
sender, the owner of this NFT is
actually going to be the chain
link node that fulfilled our
random words. So we don't want
that, what we want to do is we
want to create a mapping between
request IDs. And whoever called
this so that when we call
fulfill random words, which
returns with that exact same
request, ID, we can say, Ah,
okay, your request ID X, you
belong to the person who called
this request and of team, we're
going to create a mapping
between people who call this and
their request IDs so that when
we fulfill random words, we can
properly assign the dogs to
them. So up at the top, right
underneath here, I'm going to
call them VRF helpers, we're
going to create a mapping of un
256. To an address, we'll make
this public which we should make
it private, but we'll just make
it public s underscore Request
ID to sender. And then when we
call this request, and F T, will
set the request ID to sender of
Request ID equals to message dot
sender. Now, when the chain link
node responds with fulfill
random words, what we can do is
we can say address dog owner or
the NFT dog owner is going to be
equal to s Request ID to sender
of Request ID. This way, it's
not going to be the chain link
nodes that are going to own the
dog, but it's gonna be whoever
actually called requests. NFT.
Okay, cool. So we have a way to
request a random number for our
random NF t. Now, let's go ahead
and mint this random dog, this
random NF T for this for this
user. So we have the user now
using this mapping, what else do
we need? Well, we're gonna need
the token counter here. Let's go
ahead and we'll create a token
counter variable. So we'll
scroll up and make a new
section. And we'll say, un 256.
And then again, we'll just make
a lot of these public just to
make it easier, but you might
want to make this private and
use that same syntax we were
doing before do s underscore
since this is a stored variable,
token counter. And we'll grab
this token counter. And we'll
say you went to 56. New token ID
equals as token counter, now
that we have the dog owner, and
the token ID, we can go ahead
and mint this MFT. So we'll do
safe mint.
Owner, new token, ID and then
safe man is going to be squiggly
because our code is gonna say,
what is this? What is the safe
mint function? Where did you get
this from? Well, we're gonna
need to get it from open
Zeppelin again. So we're going
to go ahead and do import at
open Zeppelin slash contracts
slash token slash ERC. 721 slash
ERC. 720 one.so We'll say a
random IPFS empty is Vera of
consumer base, and also ERC 721
In our constructor, right after
our V RF consumer base, we're
going to put the ERC 721. And
same thing, we need to give it a
name and a symbol. So we'll call
this random IPFS NF T. Comma,
we'll just do Rin for random
IPFS NF team. Now safe mint
actually works and then it's
gonna be mad at me for this. So
I'm gonna do override just let
it stop getting mad at me.
public view override turns
string memory. Just that
squiggly line goes way. Okay,
cool. So great. So now we can
safe mint to the dog owner this
new token ID Are we done with
this? Absolutely not. Why not?
Well, we don't know what this
token looks like. And what we
set above is we want to actually
make these dogs different
rarities. So how do we actually
create these dogs with different
rarities, all we could do is we
create a chance array an array
to show the different chances of
these different dogs here. So
down below, we're going to
create a function and it's going
to be a public pure function
called get chance array. And
this is going to return you went
to 46 of size three in memory.
And this chance array is going
to represent the different
chances of the different dogs.
So we're gonna say return
10 3100 Or we're gonna say Max
chance value.
And up at the top under empty
variables. We're gonna say you
went to 56 internal constant,
Max chance value equals 100. So
by making this array, we're
saying index Zero has a 10 percent
chance of happening. We're
saying index one has a 20 percent
chance of happening because it's
going to be 30 minus 10. And
then we're saying index two is
going to have a 60 percent chance of
happening, because it's going to
be 10 plus 30. minus this 100.
This array that identified the
percentages of the different
dogs. We're saying the pug is
going to have a 10 percent chance,
Shiva in you a 20 percent chance and
the St. Bernard a 70 percent chance,
we're going to use it to give
this token ID that we just
minted its dog breed. So we're
gonna create a new function
called Get breed from modded
RNG. And the reason we're
calling a get breed from modded
RNG is exactly the same way. In
our lottery. We got a random
number, we're gonna say you went
to 56 modded RNG equals random
words of zero mod Max chance
value, we're going to mod any
number we get by 100. Doing it
like this, we're always going to
get a number between zero and
99. If random words zero mod Max
Chin's value is going to be
seven. That means we're gonna
get a pug. If we get 88. That
means we're gonna get a St.
Bernard, if we get a 45. We're
gonna get a what? That's right,
a St. Bernard, if we got a 12
We're getting a Shiva in you. If
the mod ID number that we get by
modeling this random word is
between zero and 10. It's going
to be pug between 10 and 30.
shiba inu between 30 and 100 St.
Bernard and that's how we get
these randomness values. So now
that we have this modded RNG, we
have this mod ID number that's
going to be between zero and 99.
Okay, this function called Get
breed from modded RNG. And this
is going to take the UN 256 mod
ID RNG will make this a public
pure function, and it's going to
return the breed of the dog. Now
the breed of the dog is going to
be an email similar to raffle
state that we did before. We're
going to do this right at the
top since this is going to be
what a type declaration or say
enum. Read, we're going to say
the zero with number is going to
the pug. The ones number is
going to be the Shiva in you.
And then the second one is going
to be the St. Bernard. So we
have the pug which is zero to
10. Shiva in you 10 to 30 St
Bernard 30 to 100. So get breed
from modded RNG public pure
returns breed. So we're gonna
loop through this we're gonna
say you intuitive six cumulative
sum equals zero, we'll say you
went to 56. size three memory
chance array equals yet chance
array. So we're getting that
chance array. So we're going to
create a little for loop we're
gonna say for you went to 56 i
It's gonna start with zero is
going to be less than the chance
array dot length. i plus plus
ran through that for loop here.
And we're going to say if modded
RNG is greater than or equal to
this cumulative sum and modded
RNG is less than the cumulative
sum plus chance array plus
wherever we are on the chance
array, then return breed of AI.
And then outside of this, we're
gonna say cume cumulative sum
plus equals chance array of I,
let's say moderate orangey
equals 25. And if it's 25, it
should be a Shiva in you,
because that's between 10 and
30. So we're saying if mod RNG,
which is 25 is greater than or
equal to cumulative sum, which
right now is zero, and it's less
than n, the Moto G is less than
the cumulative sum plus the
chance array of I which is going
to be 10 Return breed of I
cumulative sum is currently zero
plus chance of I which is 10 is
going to be 10. And this is not
true because Morarji is 25. So
since this is not true, we're
going to move to the second step
which is just cumulative sum,
plus equals chance right? So
cumulative sum will now be equal
to 10. And then we reached the
end of the for loop. So we'll
restart i is now one, so let's
try this again mod RNG is
greater than or equal to
cumulative sum Okay, that is
true cumulative sum is 10. Mod
RNG is 25. And mod RNG is less
than cumulative sum plus chance
re of AI, which is 30. So we're
saying 25 is less than 10 plus
30, which is 40. Return breed of
AI, this is true. So breed of AI
would be true and AI at the
moment is one. And if we scroll
up, that's indeed the Shiva in
you. So that's how this function
is going to work, it's going to
get us the breed from that
modeling bit. And then if for
some reason, some really wacky
stuff happens here, we want to
just go ahead and add a revert,
right, because we should be
returning a breed. But if we
don't return a breed, we should
just revert. So we're going to
create a new error at the top,
random IPFS NFT underscore
underscore range out of bounds.
The down below, we're just going
to say if for some reason you
don't return anything, just do a
revert random IPFS NFT range out
of bounds. And now we have this
function. Okay, so now we can
get the brief from a modded RNG.
So pack in our fulfill random
words function. Let's go ahead,
and we'll say, we'll uncomment
this will say breed, dog breed,
equals get breed for modded RNG
pass the modded RNG here, and
let's move this safe mint down
below us getting the dog breeder
so we can mint and add the dog
breed at the same time. So we're
gonna go ahead and safe mint
here.
Now we can do a few things to
set this dog breed here, we
create a mapping between the dog
breed and the token URI, and
then have that reflected in this
token URI function. Or what we
could do is we could just call a
function called Set token URI
and the openzeppelin ERC 721 You
have to set this token your eye
function yourself. However,
there is an extension in the
open Zeppelin code called ERC.
721 Uri storage and this version
of the ERC. 721 comes with a
function called Set token URI
where we can just call set token
URI. And this will automatically
update that tokens token URI to
whatever you set it as. So we're
going to use this extension this
set token URI in our contract.
And the way that we do this is
instead of doing token ERC 721
Year C 721 that soul will do
token ERC 721 slash extensions
slash your C 721 Your arise
storage. That's all. And we'll
say random IPFS is ERC 721 your
rice storage. Now what's cool is
that our constructor will still
just use ERC. 721 Because ERC
721 Uri storage is extending ERC
721. And then this contract just
comes with some additional
functions like set token URI. So
right after safe meant, we're
actually going to call set token
URI with this new item ID. And
then we're going to give it that
breeds token URI, we're gonna
give it a string here that
relates to whatever breed that
we just got based off the dog
breed here. Now, to do this,
what we could do is right at the
top and our NFT variables, we
could create a string array,
internal, Alt S dog token, your
eyes, we're gonna make this
constant where it would just be
this array of all these strings
that we created. But maybe in
our code, we want to make this a
little bit more variable. And we
want to parameterize this. And
that's exactly what we're going
to do. So we're going to create
this string array, internal s
underscore dog token, your eyes,
which is just going to be a list
of these URLs are these URLs
that point to stuff like this,
we're going to do that in our
code so that when we upload any
image that we want to IPFS we
can then upload this s dog token
you arise accordingly. In our
constructor, we're actually
going to take in another
parameter called a a string of
size three, memory dog token you
our eyes, we're going to pass as
a constructor parameter, these
different dog token you arise.
So we're going to pass it this
list of dog token arise. Of
course zero is going to be the
token URI of the pug. One is
going to be the Shiva in you and
two, of course is going to be
the St. Bernard. So we're going
to pass it this list of dog
token your eyes, and then down
in set token your eye from that,
that list that we created. We're
going to set the token URI of
this token based off of that
array of the UN 256 version of
that breed are casting this dog
breed back into you and 256 to
get its index. With that we now
have a way to actually,
programmatically get a provably
random NFT with different
randomness for different one of
these NF T's. Now, let's go back
up to our little, our little
comments we made here, limited
NFT, we trigger a chain link or
a VRF. To call random number, we
got the rarities down, we got
the minting down. Awesome. Okay,
we don't have this part, though.
Users have to pay to Minton NF T
and the owner of the contract
can withdraw the eath. Okay,
this is stuff we've already done
before, this should be pretty
familiar here. So back in our
request NF t function, we'll
make this a public payable. And
all we'll need to do is we'll
just say if message dot value is
less than some mint fee, and
actually let's go back to our
constructor, we'll create a mint
fee, you int 256 Mint fee.
And then we'll do you in 256
internal I underscore mint fee,
we'll make this immutable. And
then we'll just say I'm
intervene equals mint fee. If
message of value is less than
mint fee, you already know we're
going to do a revert, need more
eath sent, we'll create a new
air called need more eath sent
and actually we'll do air random
IPFS and ft underscore
underscore need more II sent
like that, copy this, paste it
here and boom. So now just by
adding this line, this is now a
payable function. And people
have to pay some mint fee to
mint their randomized NF t. Now
we're also going to want a way
for owner to withdraw. So we'll
scroll down a little bit. We'll
scroll down to here, CREATE
FUNCTION withdraw, this will be
public. And we only want the
owner to do this. So we could
create our modifier, you know, a
modifier again only owner, or
what we could do is use
openzeppelin. Again,
openzeppelin also comes with
some access code, or one of
them's this ownable code, and in
here, it already has the only
owner modifier for us, we're
just gonna go ahead and import
that as well. We'll do import at
openzeppelin slash contracts
slash access slash ownable dot
som, and we'll say contract
random IPFS. And if t is this,
this come ownable. And then
we'll make our withdrawal
function only owner. And so
whoever deployed this contract
is going to be set to being the
owner, which is what we want.
And when here, same as what
we've done, we'll do u and 256.
amount equals address this dot
balance. And then we'll do bull
success comma equals payable,
message dot sender, but call
value is going to be a mount and
then we're going to call
nothing. And then we're going to
say if not success. And we're
going to revert with transfer
failed, then on top, we're going
to do error transfer failed. I'm
just going to copy this a little
quicker, like so and then come
back down to transfer failed
paste it here. So we're gonna
revert random IPFS. And if T
transfer failed, perfect, so now
we have a withdrawal function
and a way for people to pay for
art here. Now we don't need this
token URI anymore, because when
we call set token URI, this is
going to set the token URI for
us because in the back ERC 721
Uri storage already has that
function laid out. So our
contract will already have the
token URI function and we don't
have to explicitly set it
ourselves. But we do have to
explicitly set some other ones.
We are going to need function
get meant fee will be a public
view turns you went to 36 turn I
meant fee will need function get
dog token your eyes, you went to
36 index, this will be a public
view which will returns the
string memory return s
underscore dog token your eyes
index will need function get
token counter. This will be a
public view turns you into 56
Return s underscore token
counter. Alright, so we just
wrote a ton of code here. And of
course as we taught you before,
we also are going to need some
events. So when we request an NF
T, we're going to emit an event.
So we'll omit NF T requested and
then we'll pass it the request.
ID in the message dot sender. So
up at the top will say event NF
T requested. So pet, take a un
256 index Request ID, and then
an address requester. And then
we're also going to make an
event for NF T minted for when
it's finally minted. And it's
going to take a breed, dog
breed, and an address, mentor.
So write down when we fulfill,
we're going to emit NFT. minted.
And it's going to take that dog
breed and then the dog owner.
Okay, we've just written a lot
of code here. So let's go ahead
and see if we can compile this
with H H compile, or yarn
Hardhead, compile. And Wow,
looks like we went ahead and
compiled it. This is great. So
all of our code now looks good.
Now might be a good time to take
a quick breather, we've just
written a lot of code. And it
might be good to just go over
all the stuff that we just went
through. A lot of this is
familiar, but it's still really
good to redo some of this stuff
and really get that muscle
memory and for these credit, an