NFT contract that when you mint,
one of these NF T's, you're
gonna get a pug a Shiva in you
or St. Bernard, based off of
some rarity, where the pug is
really rare. Ship it in you is
sort of rare in the St. Bernard
is pretty common. The way we do
it is we have this request NF t
function, which people have to
pay to call and it makes a
request to a chain link node to
get a random number. Once our
contract gets that random number
uses a chance array to figure
out which one of the NF T's
we're going to actually use for
this for that minting. And we're
going to set the token URI
accordingly. And we're going to
store the image data for this on
IPFS, which we haven't done yet.
So our deploy function for this
is going to be really the
interesting part of this
contract. But because we just
went over so much, if you want
to take a quick break quick
breather, and then come back, I
encourage you to do so we just
learned a lot. And we wrote a
lot of solidity code. So go take
a quick breather, and I'll see
you in a
minute. So let's go ahead and
get on in here, create a new
deploy, go to ploy, random
ipfs.js. And now this is going
to look really similar once
again, to the lottery contract
that we've already done. And we
can copy some boilerplate from
our code over here, we're gonna
need all this, we'll just copy
that, close it off with a little
curly and boom, we've already
got a boilerplate. Now, since
we're working with chainlink,
here, we are going to be working
with mocks again. So we're gonna
come back new file 00, deploy
mocks dot j s. And if you want,
you can just copy paste from the
earlier section that we did with
the with the raffle slash
lottery. Since we're going to be
doing the exact same thing here,
I'm gonna go ahead and pause and
you can copy paste from your
previous projects. Or if you
want, once again, you can just
come to the GitHub repo
associated with this course,
come over to the deploy. And go
ahead and grab the deploy mocks
right from here. If you grab
from the GitHub repo, we also
are going to be working with a
mock v3 aggregator, but I'm not
going to add that part in quite
yet, because we don't need it
quite yet. So go ahead and pause
the video right now. Copy and
paste the VRF coordinator mock
or pause the video and try to
write the mock code yourself.
Okay, great. So once you've done
that, we're of course gonna need
to concentrate ID network dot
config dot chain ID, because
we're gonna need to decide if
we're actually on a development
chain. So same as what we did
before then we're gonna say if
development chains that includes
network dot name, then we're
gonna say const VRF coordinator,
B to mock goes await ethers dot
get contract VRF. Core. The name
for the to mock similar to the
raffle we're gonna say let VRF
coordinate Tor v two address,
same, the VRF coordinator v two
address equals VRF. coordinator
v two mach mock that address and
then we're going to want to
create a subscription exactly
the same as what we did with our
lottery. So we're gonna say
const, TX equals weight VRF
coordinate tore V to mock dot
create subscription. And then
we'll do const TX receipt equals
weight, TX dot weight one. And
we're gonna get the sub ID from
this exactly the same way we did
it in the lottery section. So
we'll say that we need that sub
ID by saying sub subscription ID
will say subscription ID equals
TX receipt, dot events, zero.
That args got somebody. So
that's what we do if we're on a
development chain, else said the
VRF coordinate tore V to address
equals network config of the
chain ID dot VRF coordinate or B
to that then the subscription ID
equals network config. Chain ID
dot subscription ID. Perfect.
And then we'll just double check
our helper hard hat config. So
that Rigby has both the VRF
coordinator v2. And we're also
going to need a subscription ID.
So right now, I have our
subscription ID from our past
project from our lottery
project. But we can go ahead to
V or F dot chain link, we can go
to V RF, that chain link can
make sure we're on rink B here.
Let's see our other
subscriptions. And it looks like
we have one here. So I'm going
to copy this and paste it in for
Rigby. Now again, we can go over
to DockStar, chain link EVM
chains, contract addresses for
using reminisce to see more
parameters in here, especially
for Rigby and make sure these
are all correct. We have our
subscription here, we'll add a
new consumer very soon once we
deploy this contract if we're
actually going to use RankBrain.
So we'll do a little log here
with a bunch of hyphens. We'll
now get args equals, we'll make
our arguments here. And what do
we need, we need the coordinator
subscription, gasoline callback,
address, dog, your dog token,
your eyes and admin fee. So
we're going to need VRF
coordinator for the to address
subscription ID. And we'll need
the network config. Chain ID dot
gas lane. We need the network
config chain ID dot meant fee,
then we'll leave that work
config chain ID dot callback gas
limit
the right order? Yes it is. And
then we need the dog token your
eyes and the mint fee with the
done here.
Now what do we not have, we
don't have this array of token
your eyes. Now we can do this
one of a couple of ways. If you
go to the GitHub repo associated
with this, go to deploy, we
actually did the randomness for
oh three in the get here,
there's one section where we
just automatically say, okay,
great token, you rise is just
going to be these three. And
then if we can actually even
copy paste these CDs on IPFS,
these are the better ones that
actually do have the IPFS as the
image. And we can see them like
that. So we could just use the
stuff that I've already
deployed. And if you want to do
that, you absolutely 100 percent Can,
or what we could do is we get to
actually learn to upload
programmatically our own images
to IPFS. That sounds a lot
cooler. So let's go ahead and do
that. Now what I want you to do,
if you want to use your own
images for this, feel free to do
so. But if you want to just
follow along with us, then we're
going to go to the Hardhead NFT
FCC repo. And we're going to
grab these random NF T's from
him. So all you can do is you
can come to here. And we can go
ahead, we can right click Save
Image, Jas, we'll save it to our
downloads, let's actually create
a new folder, we'll call it
images. And the images will
create a new folder called
random, then we can pull it just
right into here, make the name
random NFT. And this is just
going to be plugged up png. So
we can do that for all of our
images. Now in our images tag,
we have the pug ship in you and
St Bernard. So we have these
locally. But we want to upload
these to IPFS. We want to upload
them in a way that anybody can
actually pin them and work with
them. So before we do all this
stuff, where we get the
arguments to deploy this
contract, we're going to need to
get the IPFS hashes of our
images. And there's a couple of
ways we can do this. We do with
our own IPFS node, which I've
already shown you how to do that
manually, we can also do that
programmatically. Now, I'm not
going to show you how to do this
here. However, if you go through
the IPFS documentation, you
actually can learn how to do
through the command line and
even through some scripts.
However, if we're the only node
that's running this, again, it's
kind of centralized. So ideally,
we'd want these images and these
token your eyes and this and
this token metadata on our own
IPFS node and some other nodes.
So the second way that we can
look at this is using something
like Hinata Hinata is a service
that basically you just pay to
help pin NF T for you. And this
is going to be the one that
we're going to be looking at
here. Now the issue with binotto
of course, is that we're just
paying once single centralized
entity to go ahead and pin our
data, we're kind of trusting
that they're actually going to
pin it and that they're not
going to go down. The final way
that we could look into actually
getting our data is was this
thing called NF T dot storage.
And if T dot storage uses the
file coin network on the back
end to pin our data now filecoin
is a blockchain dedicated to
pinning IPFS data and storing
decentralized data. For us, the
process is a little bit more
complicated. But NFT dot storage
makes it really, really easy.
Now, we're not going to go over
using NFT dot storage in this
video. However, if you want to
look into NF T dot storage, for
putting your data in the GitHub
repo associated with this
course, we do have a script that
uploads your code to NFT to
storage called in the utils
folder, upload to NFT. Storage.
And if you want to go and try it
out, I recommend that you do so
working with NF T dot storage
will be one of the most
persistent ways to keep our data
up. But it's still good to
upload your own data to your own
IPFS node, which we've learned
how to do manually and at least
get one other person also
pinning your data. And then
ideally, an entire decentralized
network, pinning your data,
which is what NFS storage helps
you do. But for now, for us,
we're just going to work with
pinata to keep it nice and
simple for this video. And then
uploading uploading our metadata
and our token, your eyes up to
IPFS will give us this list of
token your eyes for our three
dogs. So up at the top here,
we're going to do a little if
we're gonna say if process dot e
NV dot upload to pinata equals
true, yes, we're going to use
the string true like that. Then
we're going to upload to pinata.
Above here we're going to say
let's token your eyes. And we're
gonna say token your eyes equals
await,
handle token your eyes. And
we're going to create a function
called handle token your eyes,
which is going to upload our
code to pinata down outside of
this, we're going to create a
new function called async.
function. And we'll token your
eyes. And this is going to
return an array of token your
eyes for us to upload to our
smart contract, we're gonna say
token, your eyes equals this and
then way at the bottom, we're
gonna say return token your
rise, right, so we're going to
be returning this array here.
Now we need to do two things, we
need to both store the image in
IPFS. And then we need to store
the metadata in IPFS. So first,
we're going to create a store
images function. And this is
where we're going to actually
get to go to our utils. And
we're going to create a new
folder in here, we're going to
create a file called New File,
Upload to pinata dot j s, we're
going to add all of our code for
actually uploading to pinata in
here. Because again, pinata is
this service that we're going to
be using to just pin data for us
and work with pinata, we can go
ahead, try for free. And we can
create our own application.
And we're good to go. See the
setup here looks really similar
to an IPFS node, because that's
essentially what pinata is. It's
just an IPFS node, run by
somebody else. And we can say,
Hey, can you please pin this
data for us. So a manual way we
could do this is we could just
hit Upload Cid just like an IPFS
node and put the hash of some
IPFS file, and pinata would pin
it for us, we could also upload
a file or a folder just like an
IPFS node. But for us, we're
just going to leave this blank
because we're going to want to
do this programmatically,
because we're engineers. So what
we can do is we come over to our
profile, we'll open up API keys
and documentation. And the
documentation pretty much has
everything that we need to get
started. If you scroll down to
the pinata Node js SDK, this is
basically what we're going to be
working with, they've already
created an SDK for us that we
can work with, we're gonna go
ahead and install this pinata
SDK. So they're using NPM,
install dash to save, we're just
gonna go ahead and use yarn, add
dash dash dev at pinata dash
SDK, and they have all these
different endpoints, we can call
to actually pin data, we're
going to be doing pin file to
IPFS, because we're going to
upload our files and also pin
JSON to IPFS. Since JSON is
going to be the metadata, and
file is going to be the actual
image. And if you click on it,
it'll even give you kind of the
output of the SDK here. So back
in our code, now that we've
downloaded this, we can go ahead
and start creating this. So
we'll say const pinata SDK
equals require at pinata slash
SDK, and then we'll create a
function async function called
store images, it'll take an
images file path. So we're going
to use this function will pass
it our images, random n of t
file paths, and we're going to
have it store everything in that
folder to help us work with
paths. We're also going to
Install this path package. So
we're gonna do yarn, add dash
dash dev path, like, so, we're
just going to work with Fs as
well not Fs extra. So now that
that's up, we're gonna say
const. Path equals require path.
And in here, we're gonna say
const, full images, path, equals
path dot resolve, images file
path. So if we give that like
dot slash images, slash random,
you know, NF T or whatever, this
will just give us give you the
full output of the path. So
we're getting the full images
path, and then we'll say, we'll
get those files by doing const
files equals Fs. So we'll do
we'll grab s will say const Fs
equals require Fs just to read
these files in here, that read
DirSync. We're just going to
read the entire directory and
get our files back to read
DirSync full images path. And to
actually test that this is
working, what we're going to do
is we're going to do module dot
exports, equals store images.
And then back in our deploy
script here, we can just go
ahead and
comment out args. And we can do
import const, store images
equals require dot dot slash
utils, slash upload to pinata.
And in this script, we could
just do a little, we just call
this we could say await, or
images, and then we'll pass pass
our images location, maybe way
at the top, even outside of the
function, we'll say const images
location equals dot slash images
slash random and ft. So we'll do
a weight store images like that.
And we should be able to run
Hardhead deploy. Then if we add
some tags to this deploy thing,
module, dot exports, dot tags
equals, we'll say all random
IPFS. And then main, we do
Hardhead deployed dash dash
tags, random IPFS will also do
mocks believe, and I need to
create a test folder in here New
Folder test. And we need to add
that VF coordinator v2 Mock in
here. So again, I'm just copy
pasting the VRF coordinator v2
Mock from our raffle project.
Feel free to pause, copy, paste
it over, or again, everything's
available on the GitHub. So
we'll try one more time. Tags,
random IPFS, and mocks and boom,
okay, mocks deployed and perfect
pug dot png ship any png St.
Bernard PNG. Great. So we're
getting the files correctly
here. Now let's create a little
array for responses from the
pinata server. So we'll say
responses equals this. And we'll
say for each file index in files
for each one of these files in
here, we're gonna say const
readable stream for file equals
Fs dot create read stream of the
full images path slash files of
file index. What does this line
doing? Well, we're creating a
read stream. Since this is an
image file, it doesn't work
exactly the same as just like
push this data, right? We have
to create a stream where we
stream all the data inside of
these images. Because these
images, even though they're just
like a cute little image here,
they're really this kind of this
big file with all this bytes and
all this data in here, and then
we're going to send it by doing
try, we'll say const response
equals await. And this is where
we're going to do pinata stuff.
If we go back to the pinata
docks, there's some stuff about
keys in here. What we can do, if
you go to your profile, go to
API keys, we can create a new
key, we'll say this is an admin
key, why not? We'll give it all
the pinning access here. Maybe
we'll give it this, maybe we'll
just give it everything,
whatever you want to do. And
then we'll call this hard hat,
Free Code Camp key, create key.
Now we're going to want to grab
these and drop these into a dot
env. So the API key, go ahead
and copy, come back over here.
Open up our dot env. And we're
gonna call it our pinata. And
data API key equals that key.
We're going to grab the API
secret and say pinata API secret
equals that key. We don't need
this massive token here for what
we're going to do. But if you
want it, you can absolutely have
it. And then outside of our
store images, we're going to say
const pinata API key equals
price says, do you need that
pinata API key? And then can't
pinata. API secret equals
process dot E and V dot pinata
API secret. And then we'll say
const. pinata equals pin auta s.
DK of pinata
API key comma, pinata API.
Secret in order to work with
pinata, we need to pass it an
API key and API secret so that
pinata knows it's us who's
working with them. So once we
initialize this pinata thing, we
can now run pinata dot and then
do some pinata stuff, right, we
want to work with this pin file
to IPFS, which takes this
readable stream, which is why we
created that readable string, so
pinata that pin file to IPFS. Of
readable stream or file. And
then we're going to push this
response on to our responses
array. So we'll say responses
dot push response. And then
we're going to catch error, just
in case there's some weird error
here. And we'll just say console
dot log error, and then we're
going to return responses and
files. So we're going to return
all the responses from pushing
all these files up, and then the
files as well. Now, at this
current point, we can go ahead
and actually test this out
ourselves. So we have this in
here. If we go back to our
deploy, at the top, we have this
if process dot E and V dot
upload to Niada equals true, do
this stuff here, uploading to
IPFS. And the final thing we
need to do in here, of course,
is going to be require dot env
dot config, so that we can pull
in our dot env file. Down here,
we're just doing a weight store
images. So if we run this as is,
it should go ahead and store
images. So let's run that same
command, or that deploy random
IPFS and the MOX to run this
store images command. And if we
come back to our pinata, after
we run it, we'll be able to see
the code uploaded here. If we
run now, the script loaded IPFS
it'll give us a little bit of a
delay, because it needs to
upload these big picture files
to IPFS. or more correctly.
pinata, I'm gonna say uploading
to nada. And we could even say,
console dot log, working on file
index, done Excel. And okay,
great. It looks like it finished
running. So if we come back to
our project here, and we do a
little refresh, we see our three
files have been uploaded, and we
see they each come with their
own CID. Now, if you want, you
can go ahead and copy the CID.
And if you have your IPFS node,
what you can do, what we can do
is actually we can hit import
from IPFS. Paste it in here. And
we can say exactly what this is,
which is IPFS dot dot slash last
as the St. Bernard called St.
Bernard. Important. And now
we'll have it pinned on our
IPFS. I've got mine saved in a
little puppies file. Now that
we've got them uploaded, and
pinata do actually recommend you
pin your own on your own node as
well. So cool. So we've got a
way to get those images up onto
IPFS. Awesome
onto. Now that we've done that,
we're also going to need to
store the token URI metadata. So
let's go ahead and we'll delete
that for now. What we can do
back in here, is back up at the
top again, we can say const meta
data, template equals and we'll
create a metadata template. This
is going to have all the basics
of what we need for our metadata
for our token URI. So in here,
we'll have a name, set, it's
blank, we'll have a description,
which will also set as blank
will have the image which this
is going to be replaced with the
image URI that IPFS URI we just
created. And if you want to give
your NFT like any types of
stats, you can do some you can
create this Attributes section
like so. And if you give it like
traits type, cuteness, comma,
value 100. And this is how if
you wanted to create like
different cards or have
different attack, defense, HP
speed in different different
stats for your NF T's, you would
add them in this Attributes
section. Typically, you'd want
these attributes also stored on
chain so your contracts can
obviously programmatically
interact with these attributes.
But so now we have this metadata
data template. This is what
we're going to fill out for each
one of our dogs. Yes, we're
going to create a new function
in here called async, store
token URI metadata. And we'll
pass in the meta data to the
async function. And we'll pass
in the metadata that we get from
our script over here. So we have
this little template here. And
we're going to populate this
template based off of what we
get from storing data in IPFS.
So now we're going to write the
rest of this handle token your
eyes bit. And so we're going to
want to do in our data and V,
we're going to say, upload to
pinata equals true, so that we
can do everything and handle
token your eyes. So upload to
pinata, it's true, we'll scroll
down, we'll start creating this.
So the first thing we got to do,
obviously, we're gonna want to
get those responses and those
files, right, because it's in
the responses, pin file to IPFS
is going to return the hash of
the file, right, and we need
that hash, to add to our
metadata. So we're going to do
is down here, we're gonna say
const, responses, which is going
to be image upload, responses,
comma files, equals await, store
images, and then images,
location. And so this response
is, is going to be a list of
these responses from pinata. And
these responses are going to
have the hash of each one of
these uploaded files. So now
we're going to loop through that
list and upload each of the
metadata does. So we're going to
say for each image upload
response index, in image upload
responses.
For each one of these, we're
going to create the metadata,
we're going to create metadata
and then upload the metadata. So
we're gonna say let token URI,
metadata equals dot dot, dot
meta data template. So this is
some fun JavaScript, syntactic
sugar, which kind of means like,
unpack. So basically, we're
saying token URI metadata is
going to be equal to this stuff.
We're sticking all this stuff
into this token, your metadata
variable, now we're gonna say
token, your metadata. dot name
is going to be equal to files
of, of the index, dot replace,
dot png, dot png with nothing.
So files is going to be each one
of those files, right? It's
going to be dot png can be St
Bernard dot PNG, and it's going
to be Shiva dot png. And
basically, all we're doing is
we're saying, okay, cool, the
name inside of our token,
metadata is just going to be
pug. So we're just going to drop
the extension, basically. So
that's how we're gonna get the
name token, your AI metadata dot
description, is going to be
equal to and adore a bowl. And
then we're just going to get the
name, token URI metadata dot
name. So it's going to be an
adorable pug pup and adorable
St. Bernard pop or an adorable
ship and you pup token URI
metadata dot image, which is
probably the most important one
here, this is going to be, it's
going to be that IPFS extension
with the IPFS hash that we get
from the response. So we can get
that by doing image, upload
responses of the image upload
response index dot i IPFS. Hash,
so we can go to the pinata docs.
And we can see pin file to IPFS
returns in IPFS hash, the pin
size and the timestamp, all we
care about is the IPFS hash. And
we're going to use that to give
the our metadata image here. And
then finally, I'll do a little
console dot log uploading. And
then we'll say, token, your eye
metadata dot name, dot dot dot.
And now we'll have to store the
file or store store the JSON to
pinata slash IPFS. And this is
where in our upload to pinata
bit here, we're going to add
this function here. So we have
store token URI metadata. And
all we're gonna do in here, so
we're gonna say try const
response equals await, and nada,
that pin JSON to IPFS of the
metadata, right. And again, we
have, we want pin JSON to IPFS,
which is going to be really
similar. So we need to pass the
body, which is going to be the
JSON. And we have some optional
stuff here, but it's gonna give
us the same return the IPFS hash
pin, size and timestamp. And
then if this works, well, we're
just going to do return
response. Otherwise, we'll do
catch error. And then we'll just
do console dot log error, and
then we'll just do return null
and then we'll exports or token
URI metadata. And then back in
our deploy, we'll go ahead and
import this store token URI
metadata. And we'll scroll down.
And they'll do const, metadata,
upload response equals await,
store token URI metadata where
we pass the token, Uri,
metadata. And now finally, and
now with all of these metadata
is being uploaded are finally
going to have the token you
arise that we need. So we'll
say, token, your eyes dot push,
IPFS, slash slash, and then the
metadata response here, metadata
upload response dot IPFS. Hash.
So we finally will have this
array of IPFS hashes that points
to the metadata, and each one of
these metadata are pointing to
the image. And then we'll do a
little console dot log token.
You arise, uploaded, they are
and then we'll do another little
console dot log token your eyes.
Oh, all right. So let's go ahead
and run this. And let's see if
it works. In our pinata, we
should see both the images and
then also the metadata. If
process dot E and V dot upload
to pinata equals true, looks
like it is true. And we should
run this and handle token, your
eyes will both upload our images
with store images here and then
upload our metadata. We'll only
see it in here once because
again, it's gonna have the exact
same Cid right, it's gonna have
the same hash, so we won't get
duplicates of the same file in
pinata, or in our IPFS. So let's
open this up. Let's run this one
more time, or had deployed dash
dash tags, random IPFS and
mocks. Okay, it looks like we
almost worked uploading to
banana working on zero working
on one working on two metadata
template is not defined. Ha,
because I spelt meta data
template, meta data template,
let's spell things correctly.
Now let's try this again, it
working on zero is it working on
two image upload response is not
defined. I should spell
correctly. There we go. Let's,
let's do our caps correctly.
Let's try this one more time.
Okay, 012, uploading pug
uploading Shiva in you uploading
St. Bernard token your eyes
upload it and they're here. Now
if we grab this, and stick it
into our browser, or your IPFS
node, boom, we have them in
here. And what we can do is we
can grab this hash, we can jump
into our IPFS desktop, go to
files, we import from IPFS paste
it in here. And you know give it
the name etc, that we have it on
our own IPFS node as well.
Awesome. Now if we go over to
pinata give this a little
refresh, we can see we have
everything in here. So if I copy
one of these, and I go to IPFS
dot dot slash paste that in, we
can see the metadata in here.
And everything looks good. So
this is absolutely massive that
we've just done this because now
we can store data both on our
own IPFS node and at least one
other nodes so that if our
computer goes down or our server
goes down, and there's at least
somebody else who's done it.
Now we finally have this list of
token your eyes, we can finally
go back to our arguments. And
now we can do like this. And we
can upload all of those token
your eyes to our smart contract.
And then we're going to need a
mint fee as well for this. So if
we go to our upper heart at
config will create like a little
mint fee in here, say mint fee
is going to be whatever we want
12345678123456789 What we'll do
is 0.01 eath. So we'll even drop
this down one, we'll do it for
we'll do it for the Hard Hat
Network. And then we'll also do
it for Rinckey as well. We have
the arguments here. Now we can
finally deploy our contract. So
we'll do const random IPFS. And
if t equals await, deploy, if
the contract is random IPFS NF T
from Deployer. args is args. Log
is true. And then wait
confirmations is going to be
network dot config dot block for
confirm terminations, or one,
and great they might do another
little line here. We'll do the
verification bit. I'm actually
just going to copy that from our
deploy. Our basic I'm just going
to copy this it's going to be
code is going to be exactly the
same, except for we're going to
verify random IPFS instead of
and then actually we use args
instead of arguments, then that
is it. So we'll give this a
quick deploy test, HH deploy or
yarn Hardhead deploy. And it
looks like we almost worked we
almost got Everything's done.
Network config is not defined,
because we didn't import it. So
let's go ahead and import
network config from our helper
Hardhead. Config. So import
network config. We'll try this
one more time chain ID is not
defined, it's going to be chain
ID, that chain Id try one more
time. And awesome, it's at least
working for our heart Hat
Network. And then we can copy
this array, and just paste it in
here. Boom. And now we have this
token your eyes. And now back in
our dot env. Now we can set this
to false. Since we have all
those token neurons already, we
just run hard hit Deploy, we'll
just use the token heroes that
we already have uploaded. Yes,
we have done it. Now I know
you're excited to see this on
something like open See, you're
excited to see this right away.
But let's save deploying all
these to rink B for our last
thing, because again, deploying
to test nets is really slow. So
let's just wait until our last
bit and then we'll go ahead, and
we'll deploy this to rank B. But
before we write tests, something
that I noticed when I was
writing my test is that we
forgot to update the token
counter. So in here, before we
do, our safe, men will do s
token counter plus equals s
token counter, which is going to
be esto. Encounter equals es
token counter plus one. And
that's a perfect example of why
writing tests is so important.
Before you write any tests,
you're definitely going to need
to fund that subscription, which
we didn't do in here. So we need
to do a wait VRF coordinate Tor
V to mock dot fund, sub
scription. subscription ID,
comma will do fund amount, and
then just up at the top,
actually, we can even pull this
out too. Since that's not gonna
change at all. We can do let
token year I was like that looks
like const fund amount equals
cool. Or you could do you know,
you could also do ethers dot
parse. But as you know, before
we can even deploy to rink beam,
what should we do? Well, you got
it right, we should absolutely
100 percent write some tests. So we're
create a new file called random
IPFS NF t dot test dot j s. And
we can write some tests here.
Now, once again, there isn't
anything new that you're going
to learn in this test here, it's
going to be very similar to the
lottery tests that we've written
before. So here's what I'm going
to say, I'm going to highly
recommend once again, that you
try to write at least two or
three of your own tests, but
definitely write a test fulfill
random words. But I'm going to
encourage you to pause the video
now, please pause the video and
try to write some tests yourself
struggling with some of these
tests. And writing some of these
tests is going to be what really
gives you those coding muscles,
if you will, that's going to
give you the skills to keep
writing these tests and be
really fast and really
efficient. When you're building
these smart contracts. These
tests are the tests that protect
you from writing bad immutable
code. So please pause the video,
I'm going to copy paste from the
GitHub repo. But please take
this time to write some of your
own tests here.
Alright, great. Did you write
some tests? Hope you did. If you
didn't write some tests, pause
this video and go write some
tests. I promise you doing these
tests, writing exercises on your
own will help you dramatically
at this point, what have we
done, we've done some some
amazing stuff, we've deployed a
basic NFT with pretty much
nothing to it, then we've
deployed a provably random NFT
with random stats with random
traits with different rarities,
for each NF T's depending on
when it was minted, or who
minted it. We've stored the data
for this on IPFS. And we've
learned how to programmatically
upload our files to pinata,
which is another pinning service
for us. We learned a little bit
about NFT debt storage, which is
another way to pin data to IPFS.
And then of course, we learned
that if we wanted to, we could
programmatically pin data to
IPFS on our own node. But since
a lot of us aren't gonna be
running our own computers 24/7.
We went ahead and said, Okay,
well, we'll stick with pinata
for our default here. Now that
we've done all that, boom, got
another little checkmark here.
Now I got something to say we
don't need to host our data on
IPFS can actually host our data,
our metadata directly on chain
if we want to. However, there
are some pros and cons to IT
pros of hosting on IPFS, or
that's going to be cheap. And
the cons are that someone needs
to pin our data, right? There's
at least one person always needs
to have her data pinned, right?
It's decentralized, but you at
least need somebody to pin your
data, right? And using something
like file coin is a way to
incentivize people to pin that
data. But if you're not using
File coin, it's not necessarily
guaranteed the pros of doing our
SVG on chain NFT the data A is
on chain. And you never have to
worry about somebody actually
pinning the data. The cons are
that this is much more
expensive. These little images,
right here are actually
surprisingly large and storing
them on chain can actually get
pretty expensive. So we're going
to use some different images, so
much smaller images, much
cheaper images to work with
here. And if you want to see
another version of this, I have
another video, how to make NFT
art with on chain metadata, it
goes through pretty much what
we're about to go through here
as well if you want a second
reference, and there's a link to
this in the GitHub repo
associated with this course. So
instead of these PNGs that we're
using, we're going to use
something called SVG s. Now, an
SVG stands for Scalable Vector
Graphics. And these are much
much more minimalistic files
that we can go ahead and upload
to to the blockchain. So that's
why we're going to use them
because since there's so much
more minimalistic, they're a lot
cheaper to upload. Because
remember, the more data that you
upload to the blockchain, the
more expensive it is. Now in
this video, I make randomize SVG
data on chain. And here's kind
of an example of what one looks
like. It's just a whole bunch of
random lines. Not super
thrilling, but random and kind
of cool. And it's 100 percent. On
chain, these SVG is actually
work right in HTML. So if you
want to use these for your
websites, you can as well now
there's a link to this tutorial
in the GitHub repo associated
with this course, where we can
go ahead and try it yourself.
And we can actually play with
making an SVG, right, so they
have all these different
commands in this web through
schools.com/graphics/svg intro
dot ASP, you can see some of the
different commands, right, you
can make a rectangle you can
make a circle path is a big one
where you can say exactly what
the path or the line you want to
draw is going to look like.
There's a whole bunch of stuff
you can make in this SVG. And
the cool thing is, no matter how
big you make an SVG, the quality
is always going to be exactly
the same, because SVG just
explains exactly how to draw it
no matter how big or how little,
the image is going to be. So if
you want to learn more about SVG
is you want to play with SVG is
you know, you can come in here
and try it yourself. So with
that being said, that's what
we're going to store on chain.
So that's how we're going to
store this SVG stuff on chain.
But we're gonna go one step
further, we're gonna make this
dynamic, we're gonna make this
actually change based off of
some data on chain. If you go to
the GitHub repo associated with
this lesson, and you go to the
images, and you go to dynamic
NFT, you'll see two images, see
happy dot SVG, which looks like
this. And you'll see frown dot
SVG, which looks like this. So
we're going to make this NFT
dynamic in the sense that we're
going to say, if the price of
eath is above some number, then
we're going to have it be a
happy face. And then if it's
below that, we're going to make
it a frowny face. So our NFT is
going to change based off of
some real world parameters. And
this is obviously really
powerful and really cool,
because we can have an NFT that
changes based off stats, we can
have an NF t that changes based
off of really whatever, and
we're going to store all the
data 100 percent on chain, it's going
to be a little bit more
expensive. So that's what we're
going to be building here.
Let's go ahead, let's jump into
it. And let's do the final
contract for our ultimate NFT
section. So we're going to
create a new contract in here,
new contract, and this is going
to be our dynamic, SVG and F T
dot soul. And it's going to look
real similar to what we've been
doing. slash slash dynamic. SVG
and ft dot saw, slash lat spdx,
license identifier, and my team
pragma. solidity, Eric zero,
point 8.7. Contract, dynamic
SVG, NF t. Now let's talk about
what the architecture of this is
going to look like. It's gonna
look like pretty normal NF T,
with a couple of caveats. We're
gonna give it a min function to
mint, these NF T's are also
going to store our SVG
information somewhere. And then
we're going to need to have some
logic to say show x image or
show y image, right. And as we
know, that's really just going
to be switching the token URI to
say show X or show y. So let's
go into how we'd actually do
this. So first, we know this is
going to be in ERC. 721. So we
can go ahead and import that
from open Zeppelin. So we're
going to say import at open
Zeppelin slash contracts, slash
token slash ERC. 721 slash ERC.
721 That's all. Now we're not
going to call that set token URI
function that we call before so
we can just use the raw ERC 721
instead of an extension. So
we'll say our contract is ERC
721 and Now that we're making it
an ERC 721. We can say construct
dorm like this, then we'll call
the constructor of the ERC. 721,
which we're going to call this
dynamic SVG, and f t DSN,
dynamic SVG and s, t and f t,
like so then we're also going to
need a mint function. So let's
just create that right now say
function, mint and f t or
request NFT. And we'll be a
little bit looser here, we'll
say the user doesn't need to pay
any money for this. So this will
just be a public function. And
we're just going to mint them
and NFT. Same thing, we're just
going to call Safe mint message
dot sender. And of course, we
need that token count term. So
let's go ahead and in our top
will do you in 256, private s
underscore token counter, we'll
do token counter here. And then
after we meant we'll do tag
counter plus, there's gonna be
equals token counter plus one.
And then that's pretty much it,
we have a way to meant we've
done some of the basics here.
We'll even we'll be explicit
will say s token counter equals
zero to initialize it. But now
what is this token going to look
like? We want these to look like
SVGs. And we want it to be based
off the price of some asset in
our constructor, all right,
create a string memory. We'll
call it low SVG and a string
memory, high SVG. And in our
code will save this low SVG in
this highest V G. So these will
be the images, these will be
like the frowny face and the
smiley face that will just
import as input parameters here.
So as we know, we can make these
immutable since these are
probably not going to change. We
can say String, private, I
underscore low image URI. And in
string private, I underscore
high image URI. But if we just
pass the SVG data, right, the
SVG data is going to look like
what in this GitHub, I can go to
display the source blob here and
I can see exactly what this code
looks like this code here is
definitely not an image URI.
What we need is the image URI to
look something like this, right?
Now, the way that we're going to
pass it in is like with this SVG
code, right? Because we want to
just pass it the SVG code, and
then have the contract handle
everything else.
So how do we actually do this?
Well, what we can do is we can
create a function called SVG to
image URI. And on chain, we can
convert these SVGs from SVGs. To
image arise. So instead of
having IPFS, as their start,
we're gonna use something called
base 64 encoding, you can
actually encode any SVG to a
base 64 image URL. That's right.
It'll look something like this
base. 64 is group a binary to
text encoding schemes that
represents binary data. Or in
our case, our SVG data. Base. 64
is particularly prevalent in the
world wide web, or one of its
uses is the ability to embed
image files or other binary
assets inside textual assets,
such as HTML, and CSS, what we
can do, can actually convert all
this SVG stuff to a URL or an
image URI would be great, right?
That's exactly what we want, we
want to be able to convert this
to a URL or an image URI. Now,
if you take one of these images,
or these SVG images, like the
happy to have SVG, what we can
actually do in this happy dot
SVG is we can actually copy the
image address, which is going to
be the URL of this address. And
if we paste it back in, we'll
see justice file here. And in
this site, we can actually do
data type, remote URL, paste it
in here. And we can say encode
SVG to base 64. And down here,
we'll get this weird job role of
numbers and letters and stuff.
This base 64 encoding represents
the SVG that we just got and
what we can do in our browser,
we can type data, colon, image,
slash SVG, plus XML, semicolon,
base, 64, comma, and then paste
that massive thing in here and
Enter. And wouldn't you know it,
we get exactly that image back
up. So that huge, massive thing
here is the base 64 encoding of
this image. So with this basic C
four encoded image, we can use
this on chain as the image you
arrive for our images. And then
for our metadata. We'll just
bake that directly into our
token URI. You'll see what I
mean in a second. So we have a
way where we can actually
directly put our SVG code right
into our smart contracts. Let's
figure out how to do that. So we
have function, SVG to image URI,
so we know we're going to want
to probably do that same base 64
encoding on chain. We're gonna
100 percent do this off chain if you
want to save some gas but it's
kind of fun for To show how to
do this all on chain, so we'll
make this a public pure
function. And we'll have it
returns a string memory. So
we're going to give this
function an SVG, which we're
going to pass in from our
constructor. And we're going to
return a string, which is going
to be that base 64 encoded URL
that we just saw, while up at
our top will do string, private
constant, base S feed, base 64,
encoded SVG prefix equals that
right there. And we'll use this
to generate our SVG now, well,
we can do. And then we're going
to do string memory SVG, we're
going to encode this SVG in
basically for ourself by adding
the base 64 encoding on chain.
Now, we don't really want to
have to rewrite that ourselves.
So luckily for us, somebody has
already done this. And we can
see the GitHub repo associated
with this, this was created by
one of the LoopRing devs really
awesome project, if you want to
check that out as well. And
we're going to borrow this code
for our SVG on chain. So what we
can do is we can add this in
here, add their GitHub code,
where they have basically
everything that we need in here
to encode and decode basics
before, we can do yarn, add dash
dash Dev, base 64 Dash soul,
this is going to add their code
as a dependency. And once we've
added it, we can go ahead and
import it with import, base 64,
dash soul slash, base 64 dot
Sol. And this contract comes
with an encoder. So then we can
just do string memory, SVG base,
64, encoded, equals base 64 dot
ENCODE. And here's where it gets
a little bit weird.
We'll do bytes string, abi dot
ENCODE, act, SVG, and then we'll
return string API dot encode
packed, base 64, encoded SVG
prefix, comma SVG base 64
encoded, and just this function,
this SVG to image URI will take
in any SVG and spit us back out
a URL or URI that looks exactly
like this. Now, I kind of sped
through some stuff in here.
There's a whole bunch of new
stuff like ABI dot encode packed
that we did twice, what is this
ABI dot encode packed doing?
Well, let's learn about that. So
from a really, really high
level, this is basically how you
concatenate strings. Right, this
is how you combine strings
together. And we're going to
jump over remix to actually
explore this ABI dot encode pact
and this ABI encoding stuff a
little bit more. Now the section
that we're about to go through
is definitely advanced. And
we're going to be going over
some really low level stuff, and
how solidity works behind the
scenes, how the binary works,
and this thing called opcodes.
And all this crazy, low level,
tricky, difficult things to
understand. If you want to move
past this section, there are
timestamps in the GitHub repo.
To help you move past this.
However, I do encourage you to
at least try to absorb most of
this material, if you don't
understand it the first time.
That's 100 percent. Okay, this is more
advanced. Anyways, for most of
your basic projects, you won't
really need this information.
It's only later on once you get
more advanced that knowing all
this is really going to make you
a phenomenal solidity developer.
And when you approach this
section, when you approach this
sub lesson on EVM, opcodes, and
coding and calling, just know
that if you don't 100 percent
understand it the first time
that is okay, if you want to
watch this section a couple of
times fantastic. So if you want
to jump over to remix and follow
along, let's do it. Now in our
contract section, let's go ahead
and create a new file, we're
going to call it encoding dot
soul. And remember, all the code
that we're going to be going
with in here is going to be in
this sub Lesson folder of the
Hardhead NFT. FCC. And all the
code we're going to be working
with is going to be in this
encoding dot soul. And then in a
little bit, we're going to work
on this call anything that soul
so we're in this encoding dot
soul. And let's just make our
basic code here. So we'll say
spdx, license identifier, MIT
pragma, solidity, carrot, zero,
point 8.7, like that, do
contract encoding, boom,
compile, or Command S or ctrl S
great things are looking good.
Now remember, the whole purpose
for this is to first understand
what's going on here, and more
about this API dot encode packed
stuff. So let's first just write
a function that should owes us
wrapping API dot encode packed
with some strings and wrapping
it around a string is going to
return a string. So we could do
function, bind strings, or
concatenate strings. This will
be a public pure since we're not
going to be reading any storage,
we'll say returns string memory.
And we'll say return string, API
dot encode packed. I'm I'm
comma, space in here, I miss
you, like so. We need another
parenthesis here. Okay, great.
Now let's go ahead and deploy
this, we'll start a JavaScript
VM will deploy encoding
coding.so. We'll come down here,
we'll click Combine strings, and
we get that whole string output.
Hi, Mom, miss you. So what we're
doing here is we're encoding hi
mom misuse together into its
bytes form, because API dot
encode packed returns a bytes
object, and we are typecasting
it by wrapping it in this string
thing to be a string. And
solidity says, okay, yeah, bytes
to string, that's fine, that
totally works. And this API dot
encode packed are these globally
available methods and units. And
actually, in solidity, there's a
whole bunch of these, there's
this solidity cheat sheet, and
there's gonna be a link to this
in the GitHub repo as well, that
has a whole bunch of operators
and it has a whole bunch of
these global variables and
methods. You can see if we look
in here, we look for ABI dot
encode pact, we see ABI dot
encode pact right here, we
scroll down, we'll see some more
that we're familiar with as
well. Like, for example, message
dot sender, sender of the
message, message dot value.
There's a whole bunch of other
globally available methods and
variables that we can use when
we're coding our stuff. Now, I
will say though, in 0.8, point,
well, plus, you can actually do
string dot concat, you know,
string a, comma string B, if you
want to, instead of doing this
API to encode packed, but I
still wanted to show you the API
dot encode pack, because it's a
great segue into all this ABI
stuff that we're about to go
over. But let's focus on this
encode packed thing. So what is
actually going on here? Well,
before we dive deeper into this
encode pact, let's understand a
little bit more about what
happens when we send a
transaction. So when we compile
our code, and again, all these
pictures are going to be in the
GitHub repo. Remember back to
ethers.js, we had those two
files, we got a dot ABI file,
and a dot bin or dot binary.
Back in our ether symbol
storage, when we ran yarn,
compile. The two main files that
we got, were this symbol storage
that abi, which was this, you
know, this ABI thing that we've
become familiar with. And then
the simple storage dot bin,
which is the binary, which has a
whole bunch of just numbers and
letters and stuff we didn't
understand. And you can see that
in remix to, like if we were to
compile this, you get a
compilation details, you get a
whole bunch of stuff in here,
right? You can see the ABI in
here, which this is kind of like
a different way of viewing that
API, we also get this bytecode
bit and it's this object that
has the same stuff that has like
those random numbers and
letters. But this is actually
the binary this is actually
what's getting put on the
blockchain. It's this binary,
it's this low level stuff. Now,
when we actually send these
contracts to the blockchain,
we're sending like I said, we're
sending this binary thing.
That's exactly what we're
sending to the blockchain. And
remember how, again, back in our
ethers project, we saw what is a
transaction, right, a
transaction has a nonce, it has
a gas price guess limit to value
data, we kind of skipped over
the VRS a little bit, because
that's kind of that mathy
component of the transaction
signature. But again, back in
our ethos project, we did this
as well, right in our deploy
script, ended up sending a
transaction ourselves, using
just ethers. We passed a nonce,
a gas price, gas limit to value
data was this massive thing to
declare a contract, and then
also the chain ID. We didn't
work with the VAR s, because
ethers does that for us. But
there's also this VAR s
component that we don't bother
to look at. When we send a
transaction that actually
creates a contract, the two is
going to be empty. We're not
going to send this contract
deployment to any address. But
the data of this is going to
have the contract initialization
code and contract bytecode.
Right. So when we compile it, we
get all this code, like how do
you initialize the contract, and
then what the contract actually
looks like. So if you look at
any of the contracts that you
deployed, for example, I'm going
to look at our raffle that we
deployed. If you go to the
transactions of your contract,
we can see create raffle, right,
let's go to that transaction. If
we go down and click to see more
in the ether scan, we can see
this input data thing. And once
again, it's got all this random
garbled numbers and letters.
This is that binary data of the
contract initialization code and
the contract byte code right
what we send in our trend In
this action is this data thing,
we send this this weird bunch of
garbled nonsense. Now we're
going to head back to remix. And
I'm just going to leave this as
comments in here in the encoding
dot soul and the GitHub repo.
There's a ton of comments in
here explaining exactly what I'm
explaining. So if you want to
follow along there, you can as
well. But now in order for the
blockchain to understand, okay,
what do these numbers and
letters even mean? You need a
special reader cerium or the
blockchain needs to be able to
read all this stuff, it needs to
be able to map all these random
numbers and letters to what they
actually do. How does Aetherium
or polygon or avalanche know
that all this nonsense is
basically telling it to make a
contract, you kind of think of
it as saying, like, take off
your coat. The only reason that
we as human beings understand
what take off your coat means is
that we understand English,
We're all reading English, for
solidity. And for blockchains.
Instead of English, I read these
numbers and letters kind of like
words, just instead of take off
your coat, it's like deploy
contract, and the contract does
next XYZ and all this random
stuff. So this bytecode
represents the low level
computer instructions to make
our contract happen. And all
these numbers and letters
represent kind of an alphabet,
just like how take off your coat
is an alphabet. And when you
combine them like this, it makes
something that to us makes
sense, you can kind of think of
the alphabet for these as what's
called opcodes. If you go to
create a new tab, if you go to
EVM dot codes, we'll get to this
place where it just has a list
of all these instructions. On
the left side, you can see this
thing called opcode. And then
you can see name, so this opcode
section is saying, Hey, if you
see a 00 in this bytecode, that
00 represents this opcode stop,
which does what which halts
execution, if you see a 01
you're gonna do some addition
stuff, a 02 is multiply, there
are all these op codes that are
kind of like the alphabet, or
the language of this binary
stuff, right, and they go all
the way down to f f self
destruct, these op codes also
have, and that's what this is
reading. Right? So if we look at
our transaction here, and your
yours might be a little bit
different. Oh six, one says,
Okay, the first thing we want
you to do is the O six, one
opcode. And if we go to EVM,
opcodes, we look for six one,
it's saying push to place to buy
item on the stack. That's
exactly how it's reading this
any language that can compile
down to this opcode stuff down
to this specific set of
Aetherium opcodes, or EVM.
opcodes, is what's known as the
EVM, the Etherium virtual
machine. So being able to read
these op codes is sometimes
abstractly called the EVM, the
Etherium virtual machine, the
EVM basically represents all the
instructions, a computer must be
able to read for it to interact
with Aetherium, or Aetherium,
like applications. And this is
why so many blockchains all work
with solidity because solidity
compiles down to this bytecode
here, and polygon, avalanche
arbitrage Aetherium, they all
compiled down to the exact same
type of binary, and they all
have the exact same readers. Now
why are we telling you all this
stuff, you might be saying, hey,
Patrick, this is cool and all
but it looks like ABI dot encode
packed, all that does is
concatenate strings, abi encode
pack can do actually way more.
And if we look at these global
variables, API dot encode packed
is like what the third one down
the list because it's a non
standard way to encode stuff to
this binary stuff that we just
talked about, we can actually
encode pretty much anything we
want to being in this binary
format, basically. And let's
take a look at at encoding
something. So let's create a
function called encode number.
And this will be a public pure
function, since we're not going
to read any state, and we'll say
returns a bytes memory. We're
going to have this function
return a bytes object, we're
going to have it returned the
what this number is going to
look like but in binary, so
we'll say bytes, memory number
equals ABI dot encode one, and
then return number. So we're
going to encode number down to
it's a bi or it's binary format.
So I know a lot of times when we
say oh, what's the ABI what's
the ABI right? Previously, we
say, Oh, the ABI is, is this
thing, right? It's, it's all
these inputs and outputs. This
is kind of the human readable
version of the ABI. But again,
the ABI is the application
binary interface we want to
encode or numbers down to it's
basically it's binary, this ABI
dot ENCODE is going to be a
little different than like the
ABI that you see when you're
looking at compilation details.
This is technically like the ABI
technically is how to interact
with this contract. However,
it's not the actual binary
version of it. So we're saying,
okay, encode this number one
down to its binary version, so
that our contracts can interact
with it in a way that they
understand. So we're just saying
okay, Watch that number one,
let's make you machine readable.
And if we go, we compile this
and we deploy this right, let's
delete that that old contract,
we deploy this, we now have
combined strings and encode
number, we click it, we get this
big hex thing. This is how the
computer is going to understand
the number one. Now we can
encode pretty much anything
actually, we could encode a
string. So we'll say,
function, encode string, we'll
make this a public key here as
well. It'll return a bytes
memory, because we want to give
it that binary stuff or that
bites stuff. And we'll say bytes
memory, some string equals ABI
dot encode some string, and then
return some string. Now let's
compile that delete our old
contract, deploy that code
string, we get this big, big,
big object here. And this is the
binary. Now you'll notice
something here, there's a ton of
zeros, and those zeros take up
space, right, that's a lot of
space for the computer to take
up, even though they're not
really doing anything. They're
just kind of taking up space. So
solidity also comes with this
ABI dot encode tact, which
performs packed encoding of the
given arguments. And you can
read more about it in the
solidity docs, if you want. And
this is called the non standard
packed mode. And it does the
same encoding with some
stipulations type shorter than
32 bytes are concatenated
directly without padding, or
sign extension, dynamic types
are encoded in place. And
without the length array
elements are padded, but still
encoded in place, you can kind
of think of ENCODE packed as
sort of like a compressor,
right? It's the ENCODE function.
But it compresses stuff, if we
wanted to encode some string but
want to save space. And we
didn't need the perfect low
level binary of it. We could do
function and code string packed,
make this a public pure, and
have it return a bytes memory.
We could say, bytes memory, some
string equals ABI dot encode
packed once again, some string.
So we're doing a code pack
instead of a code. And we'll
return some string here, we'll
compile this and we'll see the
difference, right compile, we'll
delete our old one, we'll deploy
this. Now we have ENCODE string,
which again, that's what encoded
string is gonna give us and we
have encoded string packed,
which returns us this much, much
smaller bytes object. So you see
the size difference, if we're
trying to save gas, in code,
string packed is going to be a
way for us to save a lot more
gas. Now, abi dot encode pact is
actually really similar to
something that we've done
before, which is typecasting, if
we didn't function and code
string, bytes, public pure
returns, bytes, memory, bytes,
memories, some string equals
bytes, some string, turn some
string, these two are going to
look nearly identical, right? So
if we compile, we'll delete our
old contract, deploy this code
string bytes, which gives us
this and encode string pack
using the ABI to encode pack,
they give us the exact same
output, whereas encode strings
to give us this big piece. So
the two of these get the same
result. But behind the scenes,
they're doing something a little
bit different. And I'm not going
to go over exactly what that is.
But I've left a link inside of
the code here, if you want to
learn more, which is exactly
what we're doing in our NFT.
Right, we're doing ABR dot
encode packed, we're combining
two strings. By putting them
together, we're encoding them to
their bytes implementation to
their packed bytes
implementation, and then we're
just typecasting them back from