bytes to string. And that's how
we concatenate them. Now, at
this point, you
might be thinking, okay, cool.
Great, Patrick. I'm all set. I
understand this. I'm happy to go
back to my project. And if you
want to do that, absolutely go
for it and skip over this
section, but some other viewers
might be going okay, Patrick,
this is seems pretty cool. But
I'm sure this encode pacts in
this encode function aren't just
here to concatenate strings,
they probably have some other
function, what do they actually
do? Well, if that's what you're
asking, I'm glad you asked. And
I'm glad you're curious, because
we're going to find out. Now not
only can you encode stuff, like
strings and numbers, and really
anything, but you can decode
stuff. So I can say, function,
decode string, public, your
returns string memory, string
memory, some string equals ABI
dot decode. This is going to
take a couple parameters. So if
you look in the docs here, abi
dot decode, it takes as a first
argument, the encoded data, and
then it takes a tuple. You can
kind of think of it as a list
but not quite a list, a set of
types to decode this into and it
returns the number of parameters
that you gave it. So we might
want to say this string memory
some string Adding, let's give
it as input this encode string
function, the result of this
encode string function, right,
which again, is going to be this
big thing. So this is kind of
equivalent to sticking this
massive thing in here, but we're
just not going to stick the
massive thing in there, because
it's really big. So we're gonna
say, Let's decode the result of
ENCODE string, and let's decode
it into a string. Because we
need to tell solidity, hey,
we're going to decode this, but
it doesn't know what to decode
it into. It's like, okay, cool.
I can decode this, but like,
what, what do you want me to do
with it, and we say, Oh, this is
a string, so decode it into a
string. And then we can do
return some string. Now, once
again, we deploy that old
Cotters, we delete the last
contract, we deploy this new
one. So in code string, and code
string, whereas in code, string,
and code string returns this
massive thing, as a human being,
we're like, God, I can't read
that computers can read that.
But we can't really read that.
So we say, okay, let's decode
that back into its string form,
we hit decode string, and we get
back some string. And now we can
actually multi encode and multi
and decode, right, we can encode
as much stuff as we want. So I
can say function, multi ENCODE,
public pure, returns bytes
memory, we're going to encode a
couple of things, we'll say
bytes, memory, some string
equals ABI dot encode some
string, comma, it's bigger. So
we're going to encode two
strings here, we're gonna encode
some string, and it's bigger. So
we have two strings, we're going
to encode and we'll return some
string, even though it's you
know, bytes. And then we can
actually multi decode. So we'll
say function, multi decode, this
will be a public pure returns,
we'll say it returns two
strings, string memory, and
string memory. And instead of
doing string memory, some string
equals API decode, we'll say,
string memory, some string,
comma string memory, some other
string. So we're gonna get to
returns equals Avi dot decode.
Let's decode this multi encode
result, which is the doubly
encoded strings into a string
and another string. And then
we'll return both of these are
some string, there we go. Now
we'll return some string, and
then some other string,
I need a semicolon here. So now
when we deploy this, let's close
this out, deploy this new one,
right, we now have this multi in
code, which gives us this even
bigger bites object, right?
Because this is two strings
encoded. And now if we hit multi
decode, take a second, what do
you think it's going to put out
output? Let's go ahead and hit
it. Now it's gonna give us two
strings, right, it's gonna give
you these two strings, some
string, it's bigger. So we can
tell solidity to encode a bunch
of stuff. And then we can even
decode it by telling it, okay,
this big object here, it's two
strings combined, and then we
decode it. Now you can even
multi encode with that encode
pack thing, right? We could do
function, multi encode packed,
public pure returns, bytes
memory, and then bytes memory,
some string equals ABI dot
encode packed some string,
comma, it's bigger than return
some string, we could do this,
right, but this is going to give
us the packed version of these
two strings. So the decoding
actually isn't going to work on
this because this is packed
encoding. So if we tried to do,
I'm gonna say this doesn't work.
Try to do function, multi
decode, packed, public pure
returns, string memory, string
memory, some string equals Avi
dot decode multi encode packed
in a string and have exactly
what we did above to, if we do
return some string, what do you
think's gonna happen? Let's,
let's try to delete the old
contract, deploy a new one.
We'll do multi decode, packed,
multi encode multi decode,
packed, and we actually just get
an error. solidity basically
goes, Yeah, this looks like it's
packed. I don't know how to
decode that. But instead, what
we can do is we can do function
more to string cast packed like
this a public pure returns
string memory, string, memory,
some string equals string, multi
and code packed, return some
string. This one will work right
because again, this pact
encoding is kind of similar to
just type casting. So we'll
compile will redeploy multi
string cast pact, we get some
Trying, it's bigger, right? And
we don't have a space here. But
we should have put a space in
there. Now that we've learned
more about this in ABI dot
encode and decoding, and we know
that okay, this is what the
computer, this is, what
Aetherium. This is what the EVM,
or any EVM compatible chain is
looking for. It's looking for
this bytecode. It's looking for
this, this binary stuff. And we
just learned a little bit more
about how to encode different
variables into the binary into
that data bit. Well,
what do we do now? Now since we
know that our transactions are
just going to be compiled down
to this binary stuff, what we
can do then is we can actually
populate this data value of our
transactions ourselves with the
binary that code is going to
use. So here's our transaction
for a contract deployment, the
data field of the contract
deployment is going to be all
that binary code of the contract
for a function call, the data
piece is going to be what to
send to the address what data
what function to call on the to
address. Let's look at another
one of our transactions on ether
scan right on one of our
contracts, you don't have to I'm
going to look at enter raffle
from a previous section. And if
we select down, we look at input
data. It says function enter
raffle method ID. But if we look
at the original, this is what's
getting sent in the data field.
It's this binary, it's this hex
it's this weird, low level bytes
thing. This is how the Ethereum
blockchain or the or whatever
EVM chain you're working with
knows which function to call, it
translates this into a function.
And we can do the exact same
thing and call these functions
ourselves. So what we can
actually do with this crazy
newfound data and coding stuff,
what we can actually do is send
the data field of a transaction
ourself, in a transaction call
back in this ether throwback
where this data thing was the
contract creation code. Well,
instead, we could populate this
data thing with our function
call code, the exact function
that we want to call in the
binary in hex addition. Now you
might be thinking, Oh, well, why
would I do that, I can always
just use the interface, the ABI,
all that stuff, well, maybe you
don't have that maybe all you
have is the function name, maybe
all you have is the parameters
you want to send. Or maybe you
want to make your code, be able
to send arbitrary functions, or
make arbitrary calls or do
random really advanced stuff,
right, that's where sending our
function calls directly by
populating this data field is
going to be incredibly
important. So remember, I said,
you're always going to need the
ABI, and the contract address,
send a function. Now, when I
said, you always need the API.
Originally, we were kind of
talking about this thing, this
big, this big thing, which is
cool, which is the API. But this
is like the human readable API,
you can also do it with the non
human readable API. And
additionally, you don't need all
this stuff, you can really use
just the name of a function, and
then the input types to send a
function call. So the question
is, then, okay, how do we send?
How do we send transactions that
call functions with just the
data field populated? And then
the next question is, how do we
populate the data field? What do
we populate the data field with
to make one of these function
calls? And then how do we send
these transactions slowly,
actually has some more low level
keywords, namely, static call
and call we actually we've used
call in the past before, does
this code look at all familiar
to you? Well, it should, because
this is, we use a similar setup
in our fulfill random words for
our lottery, right, we sent
money doing this recent winner
dot call, right? Recently, it
was the address of the recent
winner, and we did not call. And
then we have this weird stuff in
this brackets here, and then
nothing in the parentheses. So
we did actually, essentially, we
use this call keyword
previously, but we didn't really
tell you what it did. So call is
how we can call functions to
change the state of the
blockchain. Static call is
basically how at a low level, we
call our view, or pure
functions, write static calls
gonna be like, okay, don't
change the state of the
blockchain with this one, just
give us the return value. So
this is kind of similar to like
a view or a pure function at low
level, there's also a Send word
but like, basically forget about
it. We're just gonna be working
with call, instead of call. And,
you know, later on, we'll
learn about another one called
delegate call. But don't worry
about that for now. Recent
winter duck call like this, in
these little squiggly brackets,
we said, Okay, we updated the
value directly of our
transaction in solidity. So
which again, if we have these
transaction fields, and we just
directly updated value in these
little brackets, right, we can
also directly update gas limited
gas price in these little
brackets if we wanted to as
well. And in here, these
parentheses is where we're going
to stick our data. Since all we
wanted to do with our
withdrawal. function previously
was send money. We said, Okay,
send money change the value that
we're going to send. But don't
pass any data, keep that data
bit empty, which is why, again,
remember how we hit this button
before, right and we had called
data be empty, that's
essentially running this command
with called data be empty with
this section be empty, and then
just updating the value that we
set with the transaction. And so
it's this section that we can
use to populate data to actually
call specific functions. We're
going to put a whole bunch more
comments here. So when our
squiggly brackets, we're able to
pass specific fields of a
transaction like value. And in
our parentheses, we're able to
pass data in order to call a
specific function. But in here,
there's no function to call
since we were just sending them
if we want to call a function or
send any data, we can do this in
the parentheses. And I think I
spelt that wrong. Now, we've
learned a ton here. So let's do
a quick refresher of what we
just learned. And then we're
going to actually learn how we
can call any function just by
using this syntax here. Well, we
learned from really high level,
if we want to combine strings,
we can do ABI dot encode packed
and then typecast that to a
string. And in newer versions of
solidity you can do, you can do
string dot concat, you know, Hi,
Mom, come on, miss you. In newer
versions of solidity. This works
as well, but not in older
versions of solidity. Then we
learned a lot about some low
level stuff we learned, okay,
when we compile our contracts,
we get an ABI file, and this
weird binary thing that numbers
and letters stuff that gets when
we deploy a contract that gets
sent in the data field of our
contract creation transaction.
So for contract creations, the
data is populated with that
binary code for function calls
is going to define which
functions to call in with what
parameters and this is what
we're gonna go over next. Now,
we learned that we can actually
encode stuff into this binary
into this low level code. And
any program any process that can
read this low level stuff and
execute accordingly, read this
EVM stuff, read the specific
binary that Aetherium has
specified, or the EVM has
specified is considered EVM.
compatible. We can encode
numbers, we can encode strings,
we can encode pretty much
anything we want to encode. To
save space, we do encode packed,
we can decode stuff that we've
encoded, but we can't decode
stuff that we encode packed, we
can multi encode stuff, and then
multi decode stuff. And then
finally, we can use this call
function and add data in here to
make any call that we want to
any smart contract. And this is
what we're going to learn next.
Alright, so now's a great time
to take a break, because we just
learned some really difficult
concepts. And like I said, if
you don't get it the first
time, that is okay. Alright,
welcome back. Now that we've
learned about this encoding
stuff, let's learn how we can
populate this parenthesis this
data field, so we can call any
function and we can do
essentially, what the blockchain
is going to do at the low level,
we can work with just that
binary, we can work with just
that bytes, we can work with
that hex to interact with our
smart contracts. So let's create
a new file. And we're gonna call
it call anything, that's all
start off with spdx, license
identifier, MIT. And let's talk
about this. Now in order to call
now in order to call a function
using only the data field of the
call, we need to encode the
function name, and the
parameters that we want to add,
right, because when we call a
function, we call the function
name. And we call the
parameters. So we need to encode
these down to the binary level
so that the EVM, or these
Aetherium based smart contracts
and solidity stuff can
understand what's actually going
on. In order to do this, we're
going to need to work with two
concepts to encode the function
name so that the EVM or solidity
can understand it, we actually
have to grab something called
the function selector. Now the
function selector is going to be
the first four bytes of the
function signature. And the
function signature is just going
to be a string, which defines
the function name of parameter.
Now, what does this actually
mean? Well, if we have a
transfer function, this right
here is known as the function
signature. So the function name
is going to be transfer. And
it's going to take an address
and a un 256 as its inputs, if
we encode this transfer
function, and then we take the
first four bytes of it, we get
this, which refers to the
function selector. So that's how
solidity knows. So in the
bytecode, in the binary code,
this function selector is how
slitting knows Oh, they're
talking about the transfer
function they want me to call
the transfer function. And this
is one of the first things that
we need to use call to call any
function that we want, we need
to get the function selector and
we can get it a number of
different ways but one of the
ways is by encoding the function
signature and grabbing the first
four bytes. So we'll create this
contract we'll do pragma
solidity zero point 8.7 Say
contract, call anything. And
we'll give this to stored
variables, give the to stored
variables and address public s,
underscore some amount, or some
address, and then you in 256,
public s underscore mount. And
then we'll create a function
called transfer function
transfer. Now normally in here,
we would actually do like
transfer for like an ERC 20
transfer, but we're just going
to do address some address, and
then you add 256 amount, amount
here, we'll make this a public
function. And then all we'll do
is we'll set S, some address
equals some address, and then s
amount equals amount. So here's
gonna be the function that we're
going to work with. And the
function selector for that
function is this, the function
signature is this. So it takes
an address some address amount,
that gets boiled down to the
function selector, and the
function signature. And of
course, in our bytecode, there's
going to be some code saying,
Okay, here's what this function
does, blah, blah, blah. So we
can actually even write a
function to get that function
selector. So we can say,
function, get selector and I'm
gonna say get selector one,
because I'm gonna show you a few
ways to get the function
selector, we'll make this a
public pure. And we'll have this
return a bytes for selector, we
could say select or equals bytes
for, and then we hash with a
check to 56 of the bytes of that
signature, which is transfer.
And it takes an address and a
UNT 56. Right? If we compile
this, and then we run it, let's
get rid of our old contract,
deploy, make sure we're on call
anything, if you have the other
one up. In here, now we have a
couple of things, we hit Get
selector one, we get this Oh X,
a 905, blah, blah, blah, right.
And that's the same as the
example I just gave. So this
right here tells solidity tells
our smart contract, okay, when
we make a call to this contract,
if you see this in the function
data, this is referring to our
transfer function with an
address and a un 256 as input
parameter. So we see address you
into 56. Our function knows to
execute this data here. Great.
And then of course, sml, and S
address are zeros. Now, while
we're here, we can also see,
okay, what happens if we call
the transfer function, right? It
takes an address and an amount,
so let's just give it its own
address or an address. And we'll
do 777 for an amount. If we hit
transfer, we have the log up,
right, we'll get a little
checkmark here saying success.
Now, if we hit S amount, we'll
get 777. And then the address
will be the same, right? So
that's us directly calling
transfer. When we directly call
transfer, we're basically
saying, hey, grab this function
selector, and then do some other
stuff, which we'll we'll tell
you the other stuff in a minute.
Now we have the function
selector. Okay, great. What else
do we need, we also now need the
parameters we want to add. So
we're going to need to encode
those parameters with our
function selector. So what we're
gonna do is we're gonna say
function, get data to call
transfer. And in here, we're
just going to have this get data
to call transfer, we're going to
have it take these input
parameters, and we're going to
encode these to work with our
function selector, we're gonna
say address, some address. And
if it is x, amount, public pure
returns, bytes memory.
And then we can return and use
one of those ABI and codings
from the cheat sheet. Now, so
far, we've just been doing API
and code for a lot of our
encoding. So it since we have
the function selector, we can
actually do ABI dot encode with
selector. This ABI encodes the
given arguments starting from
the second and prepends, the
given four byte selector. When
we do in Cobra selector, we're
just sticking our selector onto
the data that we're going to
give it. So we're going to do
return API dot encode with
select door. And we're going to
pass it the result of get
selector one, and then we're
going to give it some address,
and amount. So what this is
going to do, it's gonna give us
all the data that we need to put
in that data field of our
transaction, to send to this
contract to let this contract
know, hey, go use the transfer
function, pass in some address,
and then an amount. And then if
we compile this, we run it,
let's delete our old contract,
we'll deploy up, we now got a
new function called Get Data to
call and transfer, we'll just
pass you know, we'll just pass
this contract address and then
we'll also do 777 again. And so
this thing right here is what
we're going to put into the data
field of our transaction in
order for us to call transfer
from anywhere. So this is the
bytes This is the binary encoded
data of Hey, call the transfer
function with this address that
we specified. with, you know,
777 Mt. So what we can do once
we have all this, we can
actually call our transfer
function without even having to
directly call it. So what we can
do is we can say function, call
transfer function directly, or I
guess with binary might be a
better title, but you get the
gist, we'll say address some
address, you in 256 amount,
we'll make this a public
function. And we'll have a
returns a bytes four and a bool.
You'll see why in a minute. And
we'll do that same call thing
that we did to send our raffle
money. So what we'll do is,
before we did recent winner dot
call, right, we're going to do
some address. And then for us,
we're going to address this dot
call. And then we're saying this
contracts address which we could
put any address here address dot
call, and we're going to call
the encoded data that points us
to the transfer function with
some parameters. So we're going
to do address this.com. And we
could just do get data to call
transfer
address amounts, right, we could
do it like this. Or we could do
it kind of the wrong way. We
could do ABI dot and code with
select dorm, get selector one,
comma, some address, comma
amount. And actually, there's no
semicolon there, sorry. So those
are going to be the same. And
this dot call thing, right, it's
going to return exactly what we
saw before, it's going to return
a bool success. So whether or
not the transaction was
successful, and then bytes,
memory, returned data, which is
going to be you know, whatever
the call returns. So right, and
this is where we put like
require success, right. But for
us, we're just going to return
bytes, four bytes for a return
datum, and then success. So
we're just going to return the
first four bytes of whatever
data we get returned. And then
we're going to return whether
this was successful or not. So
this function is going to have
us directly call the transfer
function by passing these
parameters without us having to
do like contract dot transfer,
or, or transfer whatever, right.
And you can do this across
multiple contracts across
different contracts, just by
changing the address that you
call on. So let's go ahead and
compile this. We'll run this now
we'll delete our old contract,
we'll deploy call anything. Now
if we if we were. So right now
sml, and estimators are both
zero. Now, if we do call
transfer function directly, and
we'll pass in this one's
address, and then we'll do 777.
Now, if we pull up the logs, we
hit this, we're gonna get this
transaction response here. But
if we scroll down, we'll ever
see the decoded output, which is
a bytes for of just a bunch of
zeros, right? Because our
transfer doesn't actually return
anything. So it's just gonna be
a whole bunch of zeros, and then
our Boolean true, which means it
was successful. So since it was
successful, these two should
have changed based off of that.
So let's go ahead and try them
out. And we do indeed see that
they're changed. So we have just
directly called this transfer
function without having to call
the transfer function itself, we
can also do encode with
signature instead of selector.
So if we go to our cheat sheet,
there's also this encode with
signature down here, which takes
the string memory signature, and
it's equivalent to doing ABI dot
encode with selector bytes for
CAC bytes, you know, signature,
it's, it's equivalent to doing
exactly what we did up here. But
it does this step for us. So we
could copy this whole thing,
paste it down here, right, and
we could do, instead of encoded
with selector, we can do encode
with SIG netshare, the function
signature, and then we'll copy
our function signature from up
here, paste that in here.
Compile, we ran into a
compilation error, up, these are
the same call transfer function
directly SIG, called that
compile, leader, old contract,
deploy. Now these two are both
zeros again. Now if we copy the
contract address, we do call
contract call transfer function
directly SIG. We paste that in
here, we do 777, we call it, let
me check these we can see that
that does the exact same thing.
So this is API dot encode with
signature. This is abi dot
encode selector. Encode with
signature just turns us into the
selector for us. That's all up
here, we just, we encoded this
selector ourselves. Now, there
are a whole bunch of different
ways to get the selectors. And
we're not going to code these
out ourselves. I'm just gonna
say a bunch of different ways to
get selector. And who knows why
why you might want to use one of
these other reasons, right?
There's there's a ton of reasons
why you might want to get the
selector a different way. And
here's some now in this video,
we're not going to explain or go
over all these different all
these different function
selector getting methods. But if
you go through them in the
GitHub repo associated with this
course, they all have a ton of
comments to explain what they're
doing. Well, we are going to
show you though, it's actually
how to contracts can interact
with each other without actually
having all the code for each
contract. So we're going to make
a second contract that has all
this binary this byte
information to call the transfer
function on a different
contract. And we're gonna show
you how that can work. This is
just another contract that I've
made called call function
without contract. Actually, down
here, we're going to call the
transfer function, just by using
the address and the function
selector signature and stuff,
we're going to update these
storage variables in our call
anything contract from another
contract just by doing this
binary calling, if you will,
right, so let's compile, it's
going to deploy, we can actually
leave this up right, we can
leave this up is let's deploy
our call function without
contract, we'll pass it as an
input parameter, the call
anything contract address, we'll
deploy it. Now in here, I can
call the transfer function
directly by you know, maybe I'll
switch it to this, this contract
address this new contract
address, and we'll give it a new
number of 123. Right, and we'll
click call transfer function.
And then when we go back up
here, we see that this has
indeed been updated. Now doing
this call stuff is considered
low level. And it's a best
practice to try to avoid it when
you can. So if you can import an
interface, it's much better to
do it like that. Because you're
going to have the compiler on
your side, you're going to be
able to check to see if your
types are matching and all this
other stuff. So usually doing
these low level calls some
security auditor checkers might
say, hey, like this books been
out a little bit, you doing this
low level stuff.
But with that being said, You
have just learned a ton about
lower level solidity. This is
some really advanced stuff. And
like I said, if this was hard,
if you're kind of confused here,
don't worry, you can always come
back to this section and try it
again, when you're a little bit
more advanced, if you want to
try to understand it all now.
Awesome. Absolutely, we've left
some links in the GitHub repo
associated with this lesson that
I definitely recommend you check
out one of the ones you should
definitely check out, it's going
to be this deconstructing
solidity by openzeppelin, it
really breaks down exactly
what's going on behind the
scenes of a contract. If you
want to learn more about
opcodes, about low level stuff,
definitely give this a read, it
is a phenomenal read,
essentially, it breaks down a
little bit more than what we
went over here. A couple other
videos as well. And I've left a
whole bunch of links in here
too. With that being said, here
we are back in our NFT. And now
we know all about this ABI dot
encoding stuff, right and what
it does, and we know that ABI
dot encode packed, the way we're
using here is just a way to
concatenate strings. And we're
not using ABI dot encode for
really any of its crazy
superpowers, but we might in the
later section of this course. In
other case, so we do use this
base 64 dot encode thing that
we've imported, right, we
imported this base 64 dot encode
so that we can encode our SVG
that we pass it in to its base
64 encoding. I'm going to copy
paste an example here, you don't
have to do this. But like, for
example, we'll pass it in like
SVG width equals blah, blah,
blah, all this SVG stuff, kind
of similar to what I was showing
you before, we pass that in as
an input parameter here, and
output it, we're gonna get the
base 64 encoding of it, we're
gonna get this massive kind of
string here. We will test this
later to make sure that this
works. Normally, if I added a
function in like this right now,
I probably would test it right
away. For now we can just leave
it in here. That's going to be
great for getting this image
here. But we don't want just an
image, right? We were going to
need that metadata. We need this
to be a JSON object, not just an
image URL like this, we need
stick this image, this base 64
encoded image into this image
field of our JSON. So how do we
actually do this? Well, what we
can do is we know that our ERC
721 code comes with a token URI,
and it's that token URI that
points to this, which tells us
what our code is going to look
like. So what we can do is we
can actually base 64 encode our
JSON as well, to turn into a
JSON token URI. So we basically
four encoded this image to get
this, we're going to stick this
URL into our JSON. And then
we're going to base 64 encode
our JSON, and that's going to be
the URI that our token uses. So
we have our function, token URI,
right. And this takes a un 256
token ID, we'll say it's going
to be a public view, public view
override, and it returns a
string memory. So we're going to
override the token URI function
of the ERC 721 to whatever we
want it to be. And here we're
going to encode some JSON text
that we give our contract into a
base 64 based JSON token URI
just to get started we'll do a
require underscore exists. Token
ID, and then I'm just gonna say
your I query for non existent
token. And yeah, this price
should be an if not exists,
Revert with an error. However,
we're just going to go like
this. And this exists function
comes in my ear C 721. So we're
going to do same thing here. So
we're gonna say require this
token, a D exists. And again, we
can 100 percent. And probably should
make this an IF EXISTS token,
ID, you know, now what we want
to do is we want to figure out
how to make this token URI
return a base 64 encoded version
of this JSON. So first, we know
how to how to concatenate a
string, right, so that's gonna
be the first thing that we're
going to do. So we'll do API dot
and code packed. And we're going
to encode ourselves the JSON on
chain, we're going to use single
quotes here, because inside of
this API and code packed, we're
going to use double quotes in
here is where we're going to add
our JSON. So we'll give a name,
right, so the first piece of
metadata needs to be a name. So
we'll give it a name. And we'll
put a comma here. And we'll say
the name of this NF T is going
to be the name we get from, we
have a name function, which
returns the name. So we're gonna
say the name is going to be the
name. And we're gonna just
concatenate all this stuff, name
right there. We're gonna
continue on with the JSON. So we
put a little quote here, and a
little quote here. So we
encapsulate this name in quotes,
right? Because remember, we're,
we're concatenating, this big
string that we're making here,
we'll do a comma, we'll say,
description, we'll do another
quote. And this time, we're just
going to put the description
ourselves, and we'll say, and
NFT, that changes, based on the
chain link feed, we'll put an
end quote here and a comma, and
we'll put a comma outside the
quote, down here, we'll say,
attributes.
We'll just say, trait type, it's
going to be coolness. Comma,
value, me 100. Boom, to a comma
to image. We'll put a comma out
here. And this is where we're
going to put our image URI,
image URI, which we're going to
have to get from somewhere. So
for now, I'm just gonna say,
string.
Memory image URI equals i,
right, which clearly isn't an
image arrived. But just to make
this format and stuff, we'll
we'll put this there. This is
where we're going to put that
image URI that we get from SVG
to image URI. And then that's
it. I mean, close off our JSON,
though. So doing ABI dot encode
pack is going to concatenate
this all together. So this is
basically going to be a string
that looks like this. Great. But
how do we turn this into a base
64 encoded token you arrive so
that other people can read it is
we're going to typecast this
whole thing to bytes. And then
now that this whole thing is in
bytes, we can do exactly what we
did with the SVG above is now we
can base 64 encoded. So we'll do
base 64, dot ENCODE. And then
we'll just put another pair of
parentheses around this save and
auto formatted. And this here is
going to give us this second
line, right, it's going to give
us all of this bit, but it's not
going to give us this first bit,
right. So we just need to append
to this first bit now. And we
should be good to go. For basics
before data image SVG plus XML
basics, the form, this is the
prefix for images for SVG
images, right? We use that above
because that's the prefix for
SVG images. The prefix for base
64. Jason is going to be it's
going to be data application
JSON base 64. So we're going to
do it like this instead. Now the
ERC 721 has something called a
base URI that we're going to
override and that we're going to
use. So we're gonna say function
underscore base URI. This will
be internal pure. And we're
going to override the one that
ERC 721 has. And this is going
to returns a string memory. And
we're just going to return this
bit right here. And now we can
use this base URI. to append,
right, we're going to append
this first part to our base 64
encoded JSON. So in order to
append them, once again, we'll
do ABI dot ENCODE, packed. And
then we'll put this down here.
And we'll say, we're going to,
we're going to concatenate base
URI to this massive thing that
we just created. And then we
save and we ought to format the
now this is obviously a bytes
object, and we want it to be a
string. So then all we got to do
is typecast it as a string, but
another prints see down here,
and then we can actually just
return this, but basically what
we're doing is we're creating a
JSON string, we encode it in
bytes, that way we can encode it
in base 64. Once we have encoded
in base 64, which is going to
look like this second string,
it's gonna look like here out,
we then just append this initial
part. But for JSON objects, it's
data application JSON. We we
append that we do API dot encode
packed, and then cast it to
string and then boom, we now
have a token URI. That'll look
something like this. And then
all we have to do is update our
image URI with what we get from
our function appear, and then
we'll be good to go. So let's
finish this out. Let's do this.
So in our constructor, we're
passing a low SVG and a high
SVG. And what are these low SVG
is in these high SVG as well,
basically saying, when the price
of this asset is too low, show a
frown. And when the price of the
asset is high, show a smiley
face. So we're gonna give it
this frown, SVG, and this happy
SVG as input parameters, low CG
and high SVG, we probably want
to save those. But we don't
necessarily want to save them in
like their SVG format. So we
just want to store the image
URI, right, we will just want to
store this string up here
instead of the actual SVG. So
right in our constructor, we can
do I underscore low image URI
equals, and we have this SVG to
image your eye function, where
we can pass the low SVG. And
then we can do the same thing
for the high image URI. So now,
SVG image URI is going to return
something that looks like this.
And we're going to store just
this string this image URI on
chain. Now that we have the two
of those, we can use that down
below. In our token, Uri
function, when somebody calls
token, your I have token ID
zero, we're going to stick into
our JSON, either the low image
or I or the high image arrive.
And we're actually going to base
that off of the channeling price
feed. So how do we do that?
Well,
we've already worked with
channeling price feeds before so
let's go ahead and add it. So
yarn add dash dash dev at chain
link slash contracts. Once
that's done at the top, we can
do import at chain link slash
contracts, slash SRC slash V
0.8, slash interfaces, slash ag
reg gate, Tor V three interface,
that soul like so. And then down
here, let's comment this out.
For now, we're going to want to
call a price feed to figure out
what the price is and then show
the high image or the low image
based off that. So in order to
get a price feed in our
constructor, let's just add
another price feed address,
street address. And then we'll
make another variable. We'll do
aggregate Tor v3 interface.
Internal, immutable, I
underscore price feed. And we'll
say in our constructor, I price
feed equals aggregate Tor v3
interface at price feed,
address. And then what we can do
down here, the old bunch of
commas in here into 256 Price
comma, comma comma equals i
price feed that latest round
data. And what we can do is we
can say if price is greater than
or equal to some value, then
show one image dry otherwise,
show another one. So we can say
String memory, image URI equals
s underscore low image URI. And
then if the price is higher than
some value, well greater than
the image URI we're going to use
is going to be there's gonna be
AI is going to equal the high
image URI. And then we have
image right down here. So all we
got to do is figure out the
price. So we can make, and in
our mind, we'll let the mentors
choose the value that they want
to use. So we can say, into 256,
I value and we'll assign each
NFT, their own high value. So
we'll need to create like a
little mapping up top, we'll
say, mapping, you went to 56.
Two, you went to 56. Let's just
make this public for the heck of
it public s underscore token ID
to high value. And we'll say
that when they meant an NF T
will do s token ID to high
value, s underscore token
counter. We'll set that equal to
high value. So when they meant
they choose the high value that
they want. And then down here
we'll say if the price is
greater than or equal to the
high value of the token ID, then
we'll use the high one.
Otherwise, we'll just use the
low one. Oops, and this needs to
be you into videos x two into
256. Excuse me, since we want to
be able to compare them pretty
equally. And boom, our contract
looks really good. Now the only
thing we'd want to add in here
is probably an event. So we
probably want to emit an event
in time we met to one of these
NF T's. So we might do event
created NF T, will say you went
to 56 indexed token ID comma int
256. I value like so. And then
when we met this NFT, will do
emit create n t, s underscore
token counter, comma, I value.
And then it's best practice to
to have to update our token
counter before we actually do
the minting. So we'll do that as
well. Okay, there's a ton of
code here. And like I said, we
definitely would not have
written all that code without
having compiled to run some
tests first, but we decided we
want to just write it all right
off first. So and I did some
misspellings. Let's just make
sure everything compiles here.
Awesome. Everything's compiled
here. As you already know, a
couple things that we're going
to need to do to test this out.
First thing we're gonna need to
do is write our deploy function,
we've got our basic NFT, we've
got our random and f t, both of
these hosted on IPFS. Now we're
going to do a dynamic NFT that's
hosted 100 percent on chain, and it
changes based off the price of
an asset. So let's do this. Oh,
three, deploy dynamic, SVG
nft.js. We are no, we're gonna
need a little bit of
boilerplate. So let's go to our
basic NFT. And we'll just grab
all this the first seven lines
or so. And we'll just paste it
in here. What do we need for our
constructor? Well, we
need a price feed address, a low
SVG and a highest CG. Okay, so
let's get all of those. So price
feed address is something we've
already done before. And we can
add that into our helper
Hardhead config. And we'll do
one and a foreign local, we're
going to use what we're going to
use a mock. And if we're on
Rinkeby, or an actual network,
we're going to use an actual
address. So let's go ahead to
dark side chain that link will
grab a price feed address, the M
Aetherium. data feeds will go to
rank B, rank B and let's just
use eath USD copy that will make
a new entry eath USD price feed
like so. And for localhost,
we're good. So since we know for
localhost, we're going to need
to do a mock. Let's see if we
have a price feed mock. Okay,
now we don't, we're gonna need a
mock v3 aggregator dot soul. I
just copied pasted mine. If you
want, you can just go right to
the to a repo here. Or you can
copy from a previous section,
just a reminder heart at f and f
t FCC contracts asked moc v3
aggregator and this is using
point 06 of solidity. So we're
going to want to make sure that
in our hard hat dot config, we
have at least one 0.6 version,
which we do so we're good there.
That means in our deploy mocks,
we're going to want to add So
initial price will be 2000
decimals will be a team. So now
we've waited to deploy mocks for
that price feed. So we're gonna
say const chain ID equals
network dot config dot chain Id
do if development chains dot
includes network dot name, and
the more we need to import
development chains looks like
where did say const eth USD
akregator equals we'll get that
price feed equals awaits ethers
dot get contract Mark v3 Air
gate tour, and then we'll up
here we'll do let eath USD price
feed address eath USD price feed
address equals eath USD
aggregate tore that address else
will say the eath USD price feed
address is going to be equal to
what we find in the network
config. Network config. Chain ID
dot eth USD price. Okay, so we
have the eth USD price feed
rate. Now we need the lowest VG
and the high SVG. So we're going
to create a new folder in our
images folder. So we go CD
images, MK dir dynamic NF t. And
now we'll have two folders in
here dynamic which is empty and
random, which has all the random
stuff. If you want to use your
own SVGs for this, you
absolutely can. But if you want
to just come to my images file
and then save these images as so
just come right click Save image
as. Save them. and then drag and
drop them into your images files
here, you can absolutely do
that. So now that we have those,
we want to go ahead and read
those into our script here.
We'll say const, low SVG equals
a weight. And we're going to use
Fs again. So we're gonna do
const Fs equals require Fs, or
do await Fs dot read file sync,
we're going to read in this
file, which for me, it's at dot
slash images slash dynamic NF T
slash brown dot SVG. And we're
using encoding of UTF eight. And
then we'll say const. Hi, SVG
equals await Fs dot read file
sync. Copy this whole thing,
because we're using the same
stuff. This one's going to be
happy about SVG. And that's it.
So when price is good, we're
gonna do happiness, SVG, when
price is bad, we're gonna do
frown at SVG. Now, let's go
ahead and let's deploy this
contract. So we'll say arguments
or args equals, it's gonna be
the price feed address, low SVG,
and then high SVG. And we'll say
const, dynamic S, G and F T
equals await, deploy dynamic SVG
and f t, comma little bracket
here, from Deployer.
args, args log true. And the
weights confirmations, it's
going to be network dot config,
that block confirmations, or one
will do some logging, I will do
log to do that. But Larry, do
some verification, I'm actually
just going to copy paste that
from our last script, because
it's going to be exactly the
same copy paste. But instead of
random IPFS, it's going to be
dynamic SVG and f t. The rest of
this looks good. And that's just
about it. So we'll do module,
exports dot tags, equals and
we'll do all dynamic. SVG. And
we'll do main. Oh, okay. Let's
try to see if our deploy script
that we just created works. To
do h h, or yarn hardhat deployed
dash dash tags, die Namic SVG,
that makes sense, because we
didn't deploy the mocks. So
we'll do tags, dynamic SVGs. And
then also the mocks. Local
network detected play marks, we
deploy the marks, deploying
dynamic SVG, awesome. You know
what comes next? You Gosh, darn
right, it's time for some tests.
Now, once again, I'm going to
encourage you to pause the video
now and try to write your own
test for this test for this
section actually can be a little
bit tricky. Since we are going
to be manipulating the price of
our mock aggregator, we are
checking for these long strings,
and such. So be sure to use the
GitHub repository associated
with this lesson, in case you
get lost. Now, I want to show
you what this looks like on a
marketplace, like OpenCL. So we
are going to deploy this to rink
B. Now keep in mind test that
can be slow. So you might want
to be patient here. And you
don't even have to do it if you
don't want to. But it is kind of
nice to see. Okay, that's what
it really looks like. And you
can go to the contract on chain
once it's verified. And you can
read the token URI and
everything. And it's pretty fun.
So let's just add one more bit
to our deploy folder. Let's add
a mint script that just emits an
NF T for each one of these
contracts. So we're going to
create no for mint.js. And we're
just going to have each one of
these contracts mint NFT. Let's
go ahead and do this. So in
here, we'll do const ethers
network equals require arhat.
And then I'm going to do a
little copy paste in. I'm just
going to copy this part because
I know I'm going to need that.
We are going to need a deploy
but we're not going to need to
deploy. So I'll grab get named
accounts, get named accounts,
it's going to come right from
there. So we have a Deployer.
Our deployer is just gonna be
used to mint them. First we'll
mint the basic NF t. So we'll
say const basic NF t equals wait
ethers dot get contract, basic N
ft, and we'll connect the
deployer to it. And then we'll
say const basic mint and if T or
basic mint, TX equals await
basic NF T dot mint NF t. And
then we'll do a weight basic
mint, TX dot weight one and then
we'll do a little console dot
log base Again, T index zero has
token URI, we'll put in a little
await basic NF T dot token URI
of zero. That's it for the basic
entity. Now we'll do our random
IPFS and empty. So we'll say
const, random IPFS NF t equals
await ethers dot get contract,
random IPFS and f t, connected
to the Deployer. This one, we
need a mint fee. So we'll say
const, mint V equals await
random IPFS NF T dot get mint
fee. And then we'll do the mint.
So we'll say const, random IPFS
and ft mint, TX equals await,
random IPFS and F T dot request
and F team. And for this one, we
need to pass a value, which is
going to be the mint v.to
string. Now for this one, just
like what we saw in our tests,
we're going to have to do this
await new promise again, right,
because we need to wait for it
to return need to listen for
those events, we probably should
set up the listener first. So
let's actually set up the
listener first. So we're going
to do await new promise, and
we're gonna do async function.
And we're going to do resolve
reject. In here, we're gonna use
that, that fun little arrow
syntax in here.
And now since we're in this
function here, we actually set
the timeout resolve like this,
which means we have five minutes
to time this out, you might want
to bump this up even more five
minutes might not be enough,
this is gonna be 300
milliseconds here, we're gonna
do that once again. So we'll say
random IPFS and ft dot once.
Once we get that NFT minted
event, we're going to run an
async function, we're just gonna
do resolve. And inside here is
where we can actually put,
actually requesting the NFT. But
below our listener, right, so in
there, and then we can say if
developments chains, that
includes network dot name. So
let's just make sure we import
those development chains and
network or affect them and
chains that includes network dot
name. So we're on a test net,
this is where we go ahead and we
pretend to be those mocks. So
we'll say const Request ID
equals random IPFS. Oh,
actually, we're going to need to
do const random IPFS and ft min
TX receipt equals await on IPFS
and empty minted TX dot weight
one. So we're gonna need to get
the receipt. And from the
receipt, we can get the request
ID. That events one dot args dot
request id.to string. And then
we can do const VRF. coordinator
V to mock equals await ethers
dot get contract, the RF
coordinate for V to mock,
connect this to the Deployer.
And then we'll do a wait the RF
corded and a Tor V to mock that
fulfill random words with
Request ID, random IPFS. And if
T dot address, we can do console
dot log random IPFS and have T
index zero token URI to await
random IP. That's NF T dot token
URI of zero. Finally, we can do
our dynamic SVG, NF t. So we can
say const, high high value
equals ethers.utils.do parse
ether here. So we'll say
4000 $4,000 will be the high
value. We'll say const. Dynamic
SVG and f t equals await ethers
dot get contract, dynamic. SVG
and a T will connect it to the
deployer say const by Namic, s,
B, G, and f t mint, TX equals
await dynamic SVG and F T dot
mint and f t i value to string
then we'll just do wait. This
stat wait one. And finally
console dot log dynamic. SVG NFT
index zero token URI is going to
be a weight dynamic. SVG and ft
dot token URI of zero. Okay, I
think that looks good. Let's try
this on a local network. So
we'll do yarn hard hat deploy.
And we'll run all those scripts
It looks like everything worked.
So we have random, basic NFT
index zero has a token year, I
have this IPFS thing, random
IPFS NFT. index zero has this
thing. And then our SVG has this
giant monstrosity, okay,
perfect. And then we can even
check, right, we can even grab
this IPFS hash, we go to our
IPFS node, or if you installed
IPFS in your browser, or you're
working with Brave, we can just
pop it right into our browsers
and see what it looks like.
Right. And then if I zoom in,
and adorable St. Bernard, with
the image of the St. Bernard,
looking like that, this one's
also gonna be St. Bernard. And
then of course, are SVG, which
we can also copy, paste, and
boom, that looks great. And then
we can copy the image. And it's
a frowny face or shad. But
Awesome. Okay, so it's working
locally for us. Now, let's go
ahead and try to make this work
on an actual test net. So
hopefully, our helper hard hat
config is set up correctly. And
there's enough stuff in here
where we need to make sure that
we have a subscription ID,
right, we're going to need to
make sure we have a subscription
ID. And we shouldn't call the
mint function, right, because
we're going to need to add our
consumer to the VRF. Before we
can actually meant so let me
let's add some tags to our meant
here. So we'll do module dot
exports, dot tags equals, and
we'll say all comma meant a
while ago, I said okay, let's
add a main tag. Now we're coming
around to why we added this main
tag here. So what we want to do
is want to deploy all of these
contracts. But before we finally
meant for our IPFS one, we need
to add that contract to our
consumer, here's what we're
gonna do, we're gonna run yarn,
Hardhead, deploy dash dash
network Rinkeby dash dash tags
main. Now, this won't meant any
of our NF T's, okay, won't mean
to any of our NF T's, it'll just
deploy those contracts might
just sit around and wait a
little bit for these to actually
deploy. So this is a great time
to go take a break, maybe go
take a walk, get a sip of water,
get a cup of coffee, whatever
you want to do. Yeah, once
everything is deployed, then we
can go to V or F dot chain dot
link, we're already connected
here, we used our subscription.
And then we would just add our
IPFS consumer in here. And we'd
be good to go. And All right,
once everything goes through,
and we have all three of our
transactions on the blockchain,
we can go ahead, we can grab our
random IPFS NF T, we'll grab
that address, we'll come back
over to V or F dot chain dot
link slash rink D, we'll go to
our subscription ID, and we'll
add a new consumer will add that
contract address. So we'll go
ahead and approve and Metamask.
And once this goes through, we
can finish running the mint part
of our deploy folder. Once it's
confirmed, we can close maybe we
can do a little refresh, we
should see our new address added
as a subscription here. Now that
we've added that we can mint one
NF T from each one of these
contracts are in hard hats,
deploy dash dash tags meant dash
dash network Rinkeby. And we'll
have to wait a little bit for
this too. Okay, now that we have
them all minted, we should get a
little output like this. Right?
Basic NF t zero has token URI
here. Basic random IPFS NF T has
token your eye here. And then
our SVG has this as a token
year, right. So what can we do
now? Well, let me go grab, I'll
grab my wallet address and stick
it into Rinkeby ether scan. And
we can see we called mint
request and mint again. And we
created three contracts, right,
we created our basic NFT, our
random IPFS NFT and our dynamic
SVG NFT. What we can do now is
we can grab, we can copy the
address of our contract. And we
can go to test nets that open
see that i Oh,
and we can put that address in
the bar here in the search bar
here. Now this part is
incredibly, incredibly variable.
Okay, open C can be really slow.
And it can take open see up to a
couple of hours to register that
a contract has been deployed to
a test net. So if it doesn't
show up right away, don't be
discouraged. Don't let it drag
you down. But if it does, you
should be able to click on your
collection and see the NFT is
actually here. I'm going to grab
our random IPFS NFT. Let's grab
that contract address. I'm going
to grab that test net site open
c.io. Paste that address in
there. And what do you know we
do indeed see, random IPFS and f
t, right and I've deployed a
couple of them. So this one's v
two, and we have our adorable
Shiva in you right here. So this
is what it looks like an open C
now we can 100 percent verify that our
code is good even if it doesn't
show up on Open. See. If we go
to the contract we go to read
contract. And then we go to
token URI punch and zero here. A
query, grabbed this, stick it
into our browsers, the JSON
looks good. So let's grab the
image URI. Paste that in. And if
we can see this here, that means
that our code is good. And you
have successfully deployed a
number of FFTs to the
blockchain. We have learned a
massive amount in this course,
this is definitely one of the
most jam packed one. And it's
all about art. Right? Isn't that
crazy? Let's do a quick
refresher of this entire course
here. So first off, we learned
the basics of an NF T with our
basic NF T dot Sol, we learn
that these NF T's are based off
of the ERC 721 standard. And
that just means they have
functions like name, token, Uri,
etc. We learned that NF T's use
this token URI to tell us what
the token actually looks like a
token, your eye will look
something like this, it's going
to be a name a description, it's
going to have an image URL,
which points to a different
location for what the NFT
actually looks like. It'll have
stuff like attributes, it can
have stuff like attributes, and
a few other tags. This is known
as the metadata of the NFT. And
this tells us about the NFT. We
can also have all that metadata
on chain, of course, to
customize it on chain, and make
it look and grow and change and
be interactive on chain, we
learned more about IPFS, we
actually wrote a script called
upload to pinjarra.js, where we
can actually programmatically
upload images and files to
another IPFS pinning service for
us, we can of course, always use
our own IPFS nodes if we want.
Now this token URI can really be
anything. And we hosted it on
IPFS for our basic NFT and for
our random NFT. But for our
dynamic NFT, we actually hosted
the token, you're right 100 percent On
chain, so we didn't use IPFS.
And we made this dynamic where
the token URI actually changes
based off of the price of a
changeling price feed in our
random IPFS NFT, we gave our NFT
a chance we gave different
rarities to the different dogs
so that we could create
programmatically rare NF TS
where our pug is super rare. Our
Shiva is sort of rare, and our
St. Bernard is pretty common. So
the fact that we got to ship it
in you was awesome. We did some
amazing deployments, we wrote
some tests. Not only that, but
we learned a lot about
transactions, and how we can
actually add whatever data we
want to this data section. And a
little bit more about what our
transactions look like, and how
we can actually use functions,
selectors and function
signatures to be able to call
anything, right and we learn
more about ABI dot encoding, and
encoding packed and all this
binary stuff if you want it to
go deep into that. So this was
an absolutely JAM PACKED
session. And you should be
incredibly proud of yourself,
especially with your little
puppy that you can see on open
sea or you can see directly on
ether scan, or you can just look
at it and IPFS and be really
proud of what you've done. But
with that being said, huge
congratulations on making this
far. Definitely definitely
definitely take a break here,
and we'll see you in the next
one.
Okay, now we have less than
fifth team, which is going to be
our next JS NFT marketplace. And
if you finish this lesson, you
are a web three full stack
monster, this is going to be our
most complicated front end using
the web three stack and using a
lot of really advanced web
three, and blockchain tools. So
get really excited because we
are going to learn a ton in this
lesson. Now there are actually
three different repos associated
with this lesson. The first one
is going to be our typical hard
hat project. For the back end,
after the hard hat project, we
actually have two repos both are
going to be our front end repos,
and they're going to be slightly
different. In this project,
we're going to learn more about
how events are so important and
why events are so important,
especially for off chain
services. And so we're actually
going to look at two different
ways to work with them, one
using the mirallas, or a
centralized database, and then
one using the graph. And the
reason that I want to show both
of these is that oftentimes,
when people are looking to scale
the projects, when people are
looking to get things done
really quickly, taking a more
centralized approach can often
be a little quicker, and you can
sometimes add more functionality
to your website. And there's
still a lot of protocols that
have decentralized backends. And
centralized front ends. One such
example, is open sea, open sea,
for example, has the ability to
actually like different and fts.
Now, this isn't something that
we would actually want to spend
any gas on. But it is something
that we're gonna have to store
in some type of database
somewhere, so that people have
the ability to do that. So I
want to show you this optional
first way to build these front
ends, since all of our logic is
still going to be 100 percent. On
chain, the front end matters a
little bit less, because anybody
can still interact with the
contracts that we build on
chain. Now in web three, we
don't want to stay there.
However, getting an MVP done
getting a minimal viable project
done is really, really
important. So using a
centralized server, like
Morales, or centralized project
can make us much quicker. In
fact, we have been using
centralized services, like
alchemy, kind of throughout this
whole project. But of course, I
also want to show you the
decentralized way to make your
front end. So after we work with
Morales, we're also going to
show you how to use the graph
then for to do all this event
indexing. Now the graph is going
to be the decentralized way we