can make our front end and work
with these events. And the graph
also comes with its own graph
repo. So we'll learn all about
that once we get to the front
end section. But let me show you
what we're going to build
because it is really cool. Now
that we've learned a ton about
how to make NF T's what they
are, we're going to make our own
NFT marketplace. And like I
said, this is really going to be
our deep dive into all these
amazing front end tools. So
here's what our front end is
gonna look like. But what we can
do is we can connect with our
little connect button, we hit
Metamask Metamask pops up, we'll
go ahead and connect. And now
that we're connected, we can see
the different entities in here.
And if we're on an address
that's owned by us, it will say
owned by you. And if we switch
addresses, or UI will go ahead
and update, connect there. And
now we're owned by a different
address. Now, if it's owned by
us, we get this little hover
that says Update listing. And
right now it's worth 0.18.
That's what it's listed for on
our marketplace. If it's owned
by us, and we click it, we can
update it to a different price.
Let's update it to 50 eath, or
whatever your layer one currency
is, we'll just say new listing
price, we'll go ahead and
confirm. And I'll say listing
updated, please refresh, and
what we can do them. And we'll
mine some blocks on the back
end, and boom, now we see that
it's worth 50 here. Now if we
switch to a different account,
now we can see owned by blah,
blah, blah, and the hovered now
says by me, if his selected as a
different user, I'm gonna get
this transaction to actually buy
it. Now go ahead and confirm
that I'm gonna buy it, I get a
little pop up. This is item
bought successfully. Now if I do
a little refresh, we'll now see
that that NFT is gone from the
marketplace, since we bought it
right, it's no longer available
to be sold. Now what we can do
then is we can come over to sell
NF Ts and at the bottom, we'll
see a withdraw proceeds. So
whenever somebody buys an NF T,
the NFT marketplace actually
keeps the proceeds that actually
keeps the result of the sale. So
if we switch back to our address
that had the NF T listed, we can
now see Withdraw 50 proceeds
because we know that we have 50
eath, because we just bought
that for 50. So if we hit
withdraw, Metamask is gonna pop
up, we can go ahead and confirm,
wait a little bit as transaction
populates, and boom once it goes
through, we'll see now we have
zero proceeds. Right, we
withdrew everything from here.
So what we can do now, is we can
relist that NFT. So if we come
back, let's go back to the one
who just bought that NF t. If we
know the address and the token
ID of the NF t and we own it, we
can go ahead and relist it,
because we can place the address
in here with the token ID Give
us some sort of price, we'll
submit, we'll approve giving the
NFT marketplace access to our
NFT to our little doggie. And
then we'll go ahead and actually
send the transaction to actually
list the NFT on a marketplace
that we get NFT listed
successfully. After we remove
some blocks in the back end, we
can go back to the front end.
And we now see, it's owned by
us, instead of the original
owner, right and set for 10
ether. And then we can of
course, switch back to a
different user, and we can have
them actually buy. So this is
going to be a NFT marketplace
that's completely decentralized,
we are going to learn a ton
about front end a ton about
indexing a ton about events, and
why they are so powerful. And
I'm really excited for you for
this one. Because if you get
through this one, you will have
so many tools at your fingertips
for working with the blockchain.
Are you ready, let's jump in.
Let's build the contracts first,
and then we'll build the front
end. Let's do this. Now this
project is going to be based off
the Arteon project, which is a
completely open source
decentralized smart contract NFT
marketplace, I'll leave a link
to it in the GitHub repo
associated with this course,
ours of course, is going to be a
minimalistic version of this.
So we're in our VS code pre
normal. And we're going to
create a new folder here called
hard hat. And if T marketplace,
FCC, oops, MK dir, like them,
we're gonna cd into it. And then
open this up and its own VS
code. Once again, you can use
code period, or file open
folder, and open this folder.
Once we get in here, we're going
to do all of our normal stuff
that we've been doing throughout
the course. And once again, if
you want to copy paste over your
package, JSON, if you want to
copy paste in the modules,
whatever you want to do, feel
free to do so I'm gonna go ahead
actually, this repo here, we're
gonna scroll up and just grab
once again, this line from less
than nine. And just run that I
know I'm gonna be using prettier
so I'm just gonna go ahead and
copy paste those two prettier
files over prettier ignore and
prettier RC going to be using
them again, for linting. With
solidity we're going to use Sol
hint dot JSON. So we're going to
grab that dot soul hint dot
JSON. And the dots will hint dot
ignore. I'm also going to grab
the hard hat dot config dot j s
because we're going to be using
a really, really similar setup.
And this hard hat dot config dot
j s. It's got waffle in it,
ether scan, hard hat deploy
coverage gas reporter sizer and
Dottie and v dot config, we're
going to bring over our Dotty
and V. And we're also gonna
bring over our utils folder as
well. Right, so a lot of that
boilerplate we're gonna bring on
over. And now just like that,
since we have the hard hat dot
config dot j s in here, if we
run yarn, hard hat, right now,
yarn hard hat will actually see
we get the output like this. So
let's go ahead. And before we
actually write our contracts,
let's go ahead and write a
little doc saying what our
contract is even going to do,
what do we want this to do?
We're going to create a
decentralized NFT marketplace.
So what does that mean? What
will we probably need? Well,
we'll probably need some type of
list item function, because
we'll want to list NF T's and
this will be to list NF t's on
the marketplace, we'll need some
type of buy item to buy the NF
T's. And then we'll probably
need maybe like a cancel listing
or cancel item, if you no longer
want to sell it, maybe an update
listing, update price. And then
maybe a withdraw proceeds to
withdraw payment or my bot and
fts. So when somebody buys an
NFT, I'm gonna have to withdraw
it from the contract since the
contract is going to be the one
to actually hold those funds.
That looks pretty good to me.
Let's go ahead and start
building this. So let's create a
new folder, contracts. And let's
jump into this. So we'll create
a new file NFT marketplace.
That's all. So let's get our
boilerplate. spdx pragma,
solidity, carrot zero, point,
8.7, contract and ft.
Marketplace, boom. If we're
doing this, right, h h compile
or yarn Hardhead to compile or
MPX, art, hit, compile, boom,
things are looking good. So if
we go back to our readme, we can
grab these here, even stick them
in as like a little comment for
us to kind of reference later
on. Let's start with listing the
items. How are we going to keep
track of listing people's items.
And once again, remember, when
I'm usually coding this, I'm
going back and forth between
writing tests and writing the
actual code. We're just going to
write all the solidity in one
chunk, and then go write the
tests. So we're going to say,
these are going to be our main
functions. I'm going to start
with function list item. And we
are going to make this one look
really, really good. So we're
going to do natspec. And
everything, this is going to
need to be an external function,
right, we're probably not going
to want any of our internal
functions calling list item,
it's going to be called by
external projects or external
accounts are probably going to
need an address and ft address,
write the address of the NFT,
contract a un 256 token ID, the
ID of the token ID of the
contract that we're going to
use. And then we're going to
want to set a un 256 price. So
first off, we're probably going
to want the price to be greater
than zero. So maybe we'll put in
like a little if or require
statement here, we'll say if
price is less than or equal to
zero, then we'll go ahead and
revert with a price must be
above zero error. And then of
course, we'll prepend it with
the name of the contract into
underscores. And then at the
top, the error price must be
above zero. Now in order for us
to list it, we could actually do
this one of two ways we could
one, we could send the NFT to
the contract, this would require
us doing like a transfer, right,
we could have got the contract
hold the NFT. Now we could do
this, but this is going to be
kind of gas expensive for
someone to actually list on f t.
And we can have the owner of the
NFT be our NFT marketplace, we
could 100 percent do that. The issue
with this, though is that the
marketplace will then own the
NFT. And the user won't be able
to say like, Hey, I own this
NFT, it's in the marketplace,
they technically would be able
to but they would have to
withdraw it, we might do this a
slightly different way where we
can say owners can still hold
their NFT and give the
marketplace approval to sell the
NFT for them. Now, of course the
owners of the entity could
withdraw approval at any time
and the marketplace wouldn't be
able to sell it anymore.
However, this would be really
easy for people to actually
read, they would all they would
have to do is read like is
approved for marketplace. And
they can actually see if the
item was really listed or not.
So we're gonna go ahead and
write it this second way,
because that's what Ardian does.
And this is the least intrusive
way to have this marketplace,
right? People still will have
ownership of their NF Ts, and
the marketplace will just have
approval to actually swap and
sell their NF T once the prices
are met. So since we want to
make sure the marketplace has
approval, let's make sure the
marketplace has approval. So we
can call we can call this get
approved function on that token
ID to make sure that the
marketplace is approved to work
with the NFT. To do this, we're
going to need the AI ERC 720
interface and we can actually
grab that from open Zeppelin.
Right and this interface will
wrap around an address and then
we can call get approved on that
address. So we'll do import at
open Zeppelin slash contracts
slash token slash ERC 721 slash
I ERC 721 dot Sol. And since
we're doing an import from open
Zeppelin, we'll do yarn add dash
dash Dev, add open Zeppelin now
that we have this interface in
here, what we can do is we'll
say I ERC 721 NF t equals IRC
721 wrapped around this NF T
address that we're passing in.
And we'll say if NF T dot get
approved of the token ID that
we're trying to list does not
equal address this. So if we are
not approved, then we'll revert
not approved or market place.
And then we'll of course we'll
want to do prepend it with NFT
marketplace into underscores. So
error like this, Bada bing bada
boom, now that we've gotten a
little bit of that out of the
way, we're probably going to
want to have some type of data
structure to list all these NF
T's. And typically we get to
Okay, do we want to use an
array? Or do we want to use a
mapping? What do you think?
Before we continue? Let's pause
for a second, do you think it
makes more sense to put these NF
T's and an array or an A
mapping? And when you're
thinking about this, try to
think about, okay, well, people
are gonna have to buy these and
sell these, what makes more
sense, think about this for a
second, maybe pause it and write
in a comment here, what you
think an array or a mapping is
better. Now, if you said
mapping, I would agree with you.
You couldn't do an array and you
wouldn't necessarily be wrong,
but it's not the way that I
would go about that for an
array. Anytime someone wants to
buy an item, we're gonna have to
traverse through the array,
we're gonna have to make this
massive dynamic array. And that
might get a little bit dicey as
that array gets really, really
big. So we're gonna go ahead and
make this a mapping. And this is
probably going to be a global
variable or a state variable. So
up at the top, let's go ahead
and create this mapping, it's
going to be a mapping of
addresses of NFT addresses.
Right? So it's going to be the
NFT contract address mapped to
the NFT, token ID mapped to some
type of listing. So we'll say, a
mapping of address to a mapping
of UNT 256. to, well, what do we
want here? Well, we want we want
the price, right? So is that
another you went up to six. But
we also want, we also want to
keep track of the sellers, we
know who to send money to. So we
could make two mappings or we
just create a new type of type
listing, let's go ahead and do
that. We'll comment this out for
now. And so at the top, since
this is going to be a type
where, say, struct listing, and
in here, we're going to do a
utility six, the price of the NF
t, and then address the seller
of the NF team. And now that we
have that new typing, we can
uncomment this, we can say NFT,
contract address map to the NFT
token ID mapped to the listing,
and we'll make this a private
variable called S underscore
listings. Now back down in our
list item function, we're going
to update that s listing
mapping. So we're gonna say s
listing of NF T address, right,
the address of the NF T at the
token ID is going to equal we're
gonna create a listing of the
price. And then who, well the
seller is going to be message
that sender, right? So message
dot sender, they're the one
who's actually listing the item.
And since we're updating a
mapping here, what's the best
practice for update mappings,
you guessed it, we need to emit
an event and especially for this
project, you're gonna see why
emitting events, for at least
this project, this is so
helpful. So we're gonna go ahead
and emit an item listed event,
which we're going to create in
just a second. And we'll give
the message that sender, the NFT
address, the token ID, and the
price item listed. And then up
at the top, of course, but below
our structure, we're gonna say
event item listed will do an
address indexed seller
address indexed NFT, address,
address indexed token ID, and
then a un 256 price. Sorry, this
needs to be a un 256 token ID,
you int 56. This looks pretty
good to us. However, we probably
want to make sure we only list
and FTEs that haven't already
been listed. So we can add like
an if then in here. And this is
kind of where preference comes
in a little bit. But I'm
actually going to create a
modifier called not listed. So
we make sure we don't relist,
and if T's that are already
listed above our main functions,
or do like a little indicator
modifier not listed. This is
gonna take an an address NFT
address, a un 256 token ID and
an address owner. And what we're
going to say is we're going to
check, we're going to make a new
listing memory listing equals s
underscore listings of NFT
address token ID. Now we're
gonna say if listing dot price
is greater than zero, we're
gonna go ahead and revert with
already passing the NFT address
and a token ID. And of course,
we're going to prepend this with
NFT marketplace. And at the top,
we do error ft marketplace
already listed, like so. And
then we're going to put a little
underscore right underneath and
then up here, we'll do address
and if the address you went to
56. Okay, ID. So this modifier
looks pretty good. Let's just
make sure it's actually going to
compile we'll do yarn Hardhead
compile or hh compile. Great.
That looks good. We'll add this
modifier to our list item
function will do NFT address,
token ID message dot sender.
Cool. What else should we check
for here? Well, we should also
check that the NF T that's being
listed is owned by message dot
sender. This way only the owners
of the NF T can actually listed
here so let's go ahead and we'll
add a is owner modifier modifier
is owner NFT address token ID
spender you into 256 here and an
address spender I ERC 721 NF t
equals IRC 721 And if the
address address owner equals NF
T dot owner a Have a token ID.
And then we'll say if spender
does not equal owner. And we'll
revert with a not owner error
that we're going to go ahead and
create up top. So we'll say
error, not owner. And we'll
prepend it with NFT marketplace
with two underscores revert
revert not owner, then will do
underscore for the rest of the
code, and boom, now underneath
are not listed will do is owner
NFT address, token ID message
dot center. So now our list item
checks to see if it's already
listed, make sure that only the
owner of the NFT of that token,
Id can list it. And then it goes
ahead and lists it looking
nicely. Okay, cool. So that is
our list item method here. Now
let's go ahead and do a little
bit of natspec on
this. And now we have a little
natspec here, which looks really
professional. Alright, great. So
we have a list item function.
All right, what's next? Well,
maybe let's make a buy item
function for people to buy their
NF T's after they've been
listed. So let's create them do
function by item. So we'll take
an address, and if the address
un 256 token ID, and this will
be an external function. And
that will also make this payable
an external function because we
know only people or contracts
outside of this contract are
going to call by item and
payable so that people can spend
eath to spend eath, or whatever
layer one currency to actually
buy these prices, we could want
100 percent at channeling prices in now
for listing, we could of course,
add price and then do like, you
know address token price. And do
what we did before with chain
link price feeds to convert the
price of these tokens into how
much they actually cost. And we
could 100 percent do that with chaining
price feeds. But for simplicity,
we're gonna leave that off. But
I will put that as a challenge
to you through challenge is
going to be have this contract
accept payment in a subset of
tokens as well, of course, we
would need to give a little hint
here is channeling price feeds
to convert the price of the
tokens between each other, we're
gonna choose which NFT in which
token ID we want to buy. So
what's the first thing that we
probably want to do? Well, we
probably want to check that this
by item is actually listed. So
we're actually going to make a
new modifier instead of not
listed we'll make it is listed
up and modifiers modifier is
listed. And this is going to
take an address and up the
address un 256 token ID. And to
check to see if this is listed,
we'll say listing memory listing
equals s underscore listings of
the NFT address of the token, Id
sort of go into the mapping
here. And then we're just gonna
check the price. So we'll say if
the listing that price is less
than or equal to zero, so
basically, if there's no price,
if it's defaulted to zero, if
the price is zero, then we're
gonna say revert, not listed.
And after the address, token ID,
and of course, we're going to
prepend. And if the marketplace
and the marketplace underscore
underscore, not listed, and then
we're gonna copy this up here,
we're gonna say air listed, and
this is going to take address,
NFT address, and au int 256
token Id like so, the down in
our modifier, then we're going
to add the underscore and to add
the rest of our code here. So
now we have an is listed
modifier, we're going to check
to make sure that that NFT is
actually listed down here now
we're gonna say is listed
address and ft address or excuse
me, and if the address and token
ID. Now once again, we're gonna
say listing memory listed item
equals s underscore listings.
And if T address token ID, or
say if message dot value is less
than listed item dot price, then
we're going to revert with price
not met. Then we'll do NFT
address, Open ID listed item dot
price Excel so we're going to
create a new air price not met
error. Price not met of course
we're going to prepend this with
NFT marketplace to take an
address. And if the address you
went to 56 token ID and then a
UNT 256 price. So we can see exe
exactly how the price wasn't
met, and then back down here,
we'll get the full error. So we
want to make sure they're
sending us enough money. First
of all, when they send this
money, it needs to belong to
whomever listed the item. So we
actually need to keep track of
how much money these people
have. So let's create another
data structure called proceeds
where we keep track of how much
money people have earned selling
their NF T's. So we'll create a
mapping of address to you and
256. And this is going to be a
mapping of seller address to
amount earned. And we'll make
this private called S underscore
proceeds. And what we'll do is
when somebody buys an item, is
will update their proceeds.
So we'll say as proceeds of
listed item, that seller equals
s proceeds of illicit IO dot
seller plus MSG dot value. Now,
once we buy this item, we're
going to want to delete the
listing. So to delete a mapping
from a wreck, so to delete an
entry and a mapping, we just use
delete s underscore listings and
ft address of the token ID. So
we remove that mapping. And then
finally, we're going to go ahead
and transfer it. So we'll say I
ERC 721 and ft address, we're
going to call dot transfer from
the listed item dot seller to
the message dot sender with the
token ID. Now you'll notice
something here, we don't just
send the seller the money. Now
why is that? Well, solidity has
this concept called pull over
push. And it's considered a best
practice when working with
solidity, you want to shift the
risk associated with
transferring ether to the user.
So instead of sending the money
to the user, this is what we
don't want to do want to have
them withdraw the money, we
always want to shift the risk of
working with money and working
with eath or whatever layer one
you're working with, to the
actual user. So we don't want to
send them the money directly, we
want to create this s proceeds
data structure and we can have
them withdraw from it later on.
Now, we could probably do some
checking here. Or we could say
okay, check to make sure the NFT
was transferred. And if we look
at I ERC 721 though, and we're
looking at the transfer from
function, we don't see it
actually has a return. And if we
go to the IP 721 We can see that
none of these have a return type
though, transfer from doesn't
have a return type here.
However, we do see this safe
transfer from bit safe transfer
from it's going to be a little
bit better, right because if we
look at transfer from transfers
ownership of an entity, the
caller is responsible to confirm
that underscore two is capable
of receiving entities or else
they may be permanently lost. So
maybe instead we want to use
safe transfer from which throws
an error unless message sender
is the current owner and
authorize operator, or blah,
blah, blah. So instead of
transfer from we're going to
actually use safe transfer from
just to be a little bit safer.
So we'll do safe transfer from
instead of transfer from. And
then since we're updating a
mapping, we're going to do what,
you guessed it, let's omit an
event, we'll call item bot. Lab
will be a message that sender,
an empty address, token ID and
for listed item that price. So
off the top, let's create a new
event. To event item bought. And
this will be a an address
indexed fire an address indexed
NFT address an address indexed
token ID and then a un 236
price. Just kidding, that
doesn't look fantastic. This
should be intuitive six. Now it
looks fantastic. Now in this buy
item, we've set this up in a way
that is safe from something
called a reentrancy attack. And
we've been coding these
contracts in a way where we kind
of do all this state change
first. And then we transfer the
NFT that token or etc. But why
are we doing that? Cognitively
we think it might make sense.
Okay, first, maybe we should
actually send the NFT right,
we'd want to send the entity
first.
This is actually a huge security
vulnerability. And to understand
why let's learn about one The
most common hacks in blockchain,
the reentrant. See attack. Now
in this sub lesson, we're going
to talk about reentrant. C, and
in the GitHub repo associated
with this lesson, we're going to
have the code for everything
that we're going to go through
here. And the code that we're
looking at is based off of this
solidity by example. reentrant.
See example. And I have a link
to it in the GitHub repo
associated with this course.
Now, I have a sample contract
here, it's a place where you can
deposit and withdraw your eath.
So what it does is it has a
mapping called balances, where
you can call deposit, and it'll
update how much you've deposited
into the protocol. And then it
has a withdrawal function as
well. So what it does is it
first grabs your balance from
this balances mapping, make sure
that you have more than zero.
And then the way that we've been
sending eath, this whole time,
we do message that sender dot
call, we send the balance, and
then we update bounces of
message sender equals zero. Now
this is the line that actually
makes this contract incredibly
vulnerable. And if we run this
right now, though, we'll say
hey, no, it looks like it's
working as expected, we can go
to deploy a copy the accounts
that I'm working with, like that
in a bounce zero, we can
deposit, you know, it's going
away, let's go to ether, will
deposit to ether, come down,
what deposit now had to balance
bounces up, we'll hit withdraw,
now have bounces goes back to
zero. And it seems like it's
working as intended. Now,
there's actually a way we can
attack this function to drain
all the money in this contract.
And this is what's known as a
reentrancy attack. The two most
common kinds of attacks in this
space are going to be reentrancy
attacks, which is what we're
talking about here. And Oracle
attacks, which usually only
happen when a protocol doesn't
use the decentralized Oracle,
lucky for you, we're teaching
you right from the get go how to
use chain link so that you can
be protected. And it's these two
types of attacks that often
result in the most amount of
money last, there's a
leaderboard called rec dot news,
which keeps track of many of the
top attacks that have ever
happened in the defi space. With
many of them if you go into the
retrospectives are either an
Oracle attack or a reentrancy
attack. And you might be saying,
Hey, where are we just talking
about NF T's this, this doesn't
have anything to do with NF T's
we'll get there, don't worry. In
a new contract below, we're
going to create a new contract
called attack down here. And
what we'll do with this attack
contract is we'll grab this
reentrant vulnerable contract,
we'll say reentrant, vulnerable,
public reentrant vulnerable,
like so. And we'll save that
reentrant vulnerable contract as
a global variable. And we'll say
construct door address,
underscore ranch and vulnerable
address. And then we'll say
reentrant vulnerable equals
rancher and vulnerable at
reentrant vulnerable address.
Now what we're going to do is
we're going to create a function
called attack. And it's this
function that's going to call
withdraw in a malicious way. So
we're going to say attack, this
is going to be an external
payable contract. And we're
going to call the posit on this.
So we'll deposit some money
first. So we'll do reentrant
vulnerable dot the posit
will send a value of one ether.
And then immediately we will
call re N Trent vulnerable dot
withdraw. Now at first glance,
this seems pretty harmless.
But remember, when we call
message dot call like this to
send we're calling back to this
this attack contract. Now when
we call this attack contract, is
there a way to execute any other
code? Well, there is remember
how we learned about fallback
functions. If we put a fallback
function in here or a receive
function. When this code runs
call and seconds our contract
ether we can have it trigger our
fallback function to call
withdraw again. So that will
send our contract more ether
than it's do before we update
the balance. So let's see what
this looks like. So in our
fallback here, we'll say if the
address of reentrant vulnerable
balance is greater than or equal
to one ether aka we're saying if
there's money left in the
contract, then rancher
invulnerable dot withdraw. And
then we'll put to get balanced
function in our attacking
contract. We're going to attack
reentrant vulnerable by calling
withdraw. When we get to this
send section, what are we going
to do, we're going to have our
fallback function trigger
calling withdraw again. Now when
we call withdraw again, bounces
a message that sender hasn't
been zeroed out yet. So the
contract code will go, oh, you
still have some money here.
Let's go ahead and let's send
you that, which will then again,
trigger us to call withdraw. And
so we'll just keep calling
withdraw until we're done. So
let's see what this looks like.
So we compile this, and then
let's go to deploy, first, let's
deploy the reentrant vulnerable
contract. Alright, and we can
have any contract address, you
know, like the one that deployed
it, we can have a deposit, let's
do, we have a deposit one ether
deposit. Now we can check the
balances of it. Copy. Paste
great, is one. So now let's have
a do 10. Deposit, it took the
balance. And now we have this
much in here. So we have this
much in here. And if we
withdrew, we withdraw all of it.
And if we switched accounts, to
somebody else, we hit withdrew.
Nothing would happen because
that other account doesn't have
anything, which makes sense. So
there's a lot of money in here,
right. And if we do get balanced
with the contract, we can see
how much money it has, right? It
has this much money total. Now
what we can do on a different
account, let's choose this, this
brand new account, let's go
ahead and deploy the attack
contract. And we'll pass it the
reentrant value address as an
input parameter. So we'll deploy
that. And now what we'll do is
we'll call attack. And you'll
see even though this contract
doesn't have anything deposited
in the reentrant vulnerable
contract, we will still steal
all the funds in here or just
about all the funds. So right
now hit get balance, and a
reentrant vulnerable, here's
what it is, get balance a here
zero, you know, there's the
address, we had attack now, now
that get bounce, oh, excuse me
in public, and withdrawal should
be payable as well. Now we'll
pass one ether as an input
parameter to our attack
function, and we're going to
deposit just one ether. And then
we're going to withdraw. And
we're going to keep withdrawing,
because our fallback function is
going to keep calling withdraw.
And all we had to do was deposit
one ether, and we're gonna be
able to pull out all 11 that are
in here.
So we'll hit attack now.
Transaction went through, the
new balance of our contract is
12, because the one that we
deposited and then the 11 that
we stole, and the new balance of
our old contract is now zero. So
this is known as a reentrant.
See attack. Basically, since we
call a function in another
contract in the middle of our
withdraw, we allow code to run
on a different contract. And the
code that ran runs on this
contract, recalls withdraw
before balances is set to zero,
we get to here we call the
fallback function of our other
code, and it calls withdraw, and
we need to reread withdraw
before we get to setting
balances a message that sender
equals zero. So this is an
issue, obviously. And there are
two ways we can prevent it.
There's the easy way. And then
the mutex way, I don't wanna say
the hard way, it's just a
different way. So one of the
things you'll always see in
security tools is you always
want to call any external
contract as the last step in
your function, or the last step
in transaction. And we want to
update bounces to zero before we
call that external contract,
because of balances of message
sender is reset to zero before
we call external code, then if
it were to try to re enter this,
it would hit this require step
and just cancel out right here
and wouldn't be able to send any
ether again. So that's the first
step that we can do. The next
step that we can do is using
something called a mutex lock.
And this is what open Zeppelin
does with one of the modifiers
that they have, we can have some
type of a Boolean called locked
or something and just right at
the top, we can just say require
not locked. Otherwise, revert.
And then the first thing we do
in this contract is we can say
locked equals true. And then the
last thing we do in here is we
say locked equals false. And
using this lock in here, we only
allow one piece of code to ever
execute in here at a time and we
only unlock it once the code
finishes. Now open Zeplin comes
with a reentrancy guard which we
can use on our code. And it has
a modifier non reentrant which
does essentially what we were
talking about with our locks it
creates a variable called status
and changes it to enter whenever
a function has been entered. It
runs out code, and then changes
it back to not entered when it's
finishes. And whenever any code
runs, it just requires that it
is not entered. So if we wanted
to use this on our code, we can
import at open Zeppelin, slash,
contracts, slash security, slash
reentrancy. Guard about so we
can inherit the functions by
saying NFT marketplace is
reentrancy guard. And then any
function that we're nervous is
going to have this reentrant see
issue, like maybe by item, for
example, we would just add the
modifier non reentrant. Just
like that. And that'll add that
mutex, that locking mechanism
that we talked about. Now, the
mutex way is a little bit more
explicit with our security,
right? Because we're saying,
Hey, this is locked. This is a
non reentrant function. Still a
best practice, whenever you call
external code, like what we see
here is you do all of your state
changes before you call an
external contract. Now, you
might be saying, Oh, that's cool
at all. But what about how does
this relate to our NF Ts? Well,
imagine for a second, instead of
message that sender dot call,
this is, you know, all success
equals, you know, some NF T dot
transfer from, and then we do
some transfers from stuff in
here. And instead of doing some
fallback stuff, our NF T has our
NF T's function transfer from
the similis code to re enter
into our withdraw. If we have
our withdrawal set up like this,
since we're still calling an
external contract with NFT. To
transfer from that transfer from
in that external contract could
be malicious and try to re enter
our contract. As a best
practice, you always want to
change your state, before you
call any external contracts that
you might not have control of, I
highly recommend playing around
with this a little bit just
because seeing is believing. And
with that being said, again, all
the code for this is going to be
available in the GitHub sociated
with this lesson for this
reentrant vulnerable code. And
with that, let's go back to our
NFT project.
Okay, so now we know why we're
doing this safe transfer from at
the bottom of our function here
at the bottom of our bio,
because if our safe transfer
function from was a little bit
higher, maybe what ends up
happening is we send multiple NF
T's to the wrong address before
we update them. So that's why we
do that. And we favor push over
Paul. As we said, Here, there's
a whole lot of these security
tips that you'll learn going on
through this course and in
solidity. But this is still
fantastic, right, we have our by
item. And we have our list item
functions. Let's do a cancel
item now, or cancelled listing.
So we'll do a function.
Cancel listing we'll do the NFT
address. And the UN 256 token
ID. This will be an external
function. One will want to make
sure only the owner of this
entity can cancel it. So we'll
say is owner.
And if T address, token ID
message dot Sen. Want to make
sure that the NFT is actually
listed. So we'll do is listed
and ft address, token ID. And
great. Now to cancel this, all
we're going to do is we're going
to delete s listings NFT address
token ID, we're just going to
delete that mapping. And then
we'll emit an event item
cancelled message dot sender and
if T address and token ID. And
of course, we're going to create
a new event here. We'll say
event item canceled. And it will
be an address indexed seller
address. Index NFT address. You
want to 56 indexed token ID. All
right. Great. That was pretty
quick. Cancel listening. Boom.
Jack. Done. What's next? Okay,
let's update our listings. So
we'll do function update listing
address and if the address you
went to for the sixth token ID
you went to the six new price
will update the price of this of
this external we'll make sure
it's listed with is listed
say is owner do a token ID and
then we'll do message dot
sender. Now to update our
listing We'll just say s
underscore listings of NF T
address. At token ID dot price
equals the new price that we're
giving it. And then we'll admit,
we can omit like item updated.
But we can also just omit an
item listed with MSG dot sender
NFT address, token ID, new
price. Because essentially, by
updating it, we're essentially
just relisting it with a new
price. So we're just going to do
an item listed event, we only
have one more function to do, we
need to do a withdraw proceeds.
So we'll say function, withdraw
proceeds to get all the payments
for all of our entities. So
we'll get the the proceeds by
doing new activity six proceeds
equals s underscore proceeds of
MSG dot sender, right, we're
getting all the payments that
were collected in by item, and
we're saying if proceeds is less
than or equal to zero, then
we're going to revert with no
proceeds. And we're going to
make this a NFT. Marketplace
underscore underscore no
proceeds. Excel create at the
top error empty marketplace no
proceeds being otherwise, we'll
say s underscore proceeds of MSG
dot sender equals zero. So we're
going to reset the proceeds to
zero, right, we're going to do
this before we send any
proceeds. And then we're going
to do our traditional way we
send payments, so bool success
equals payable, message dot
sender call value is going to be
proceeds all blank here. And
then we could do require, you
know, we could do require
success, or we could say
if not success, reverts revert
with Aleksey marketplace,
transfer failed. And then we'll
make this a new air, air NFT
marketplace transfer failed. Put
a semicolon here. And we're
looking pretty good. Now we even
have a way to withdraw. So we
have our five functions here.
Awesome. Let's just create a
couple of getters. So maybe
we'll do we even copy this.
Paste it here we'll say getter
functions like so. And we'll do
function maybe we'll do get
listing. Take an address, NF T
address, the utilities X token
ID, external view, which returns
a listing in memory. And we'll
say return s underscore listings
of NF T address token Id like
so. And also function, get
proceeds of address seller,
external view returns, you went
to the desex return s underscore
proceeds of the seller. So we'll
get how much money somebody is
owed. And then any listings and
let's run a little compile here,
yarn, or hit Compile or hh
compile just to see where we
messed up. Oh, we did a mess up.
Wow, that's great. And now,
guess what? You have
successfully created a
minimalistic NFT marketplace
that's completely decentralized.
That is pretty wild. And that is
incredibly powerful. And you
should feel really excited for
yourself. Very cool, very good
job. But you know, we're not
done, we got to write some
deploys and some tests. So let's
jump into that. Now since we've
done this a couple of times, I
actually encourage you to pause
the video here and try writing
your own deploy scripts and your
own tests. And then go ahead and
come back and follow along with
us and see if you did it
correctly, we're going to create
a new folder called deploy. Of
course, we already have the hard
hat deploy in our hard hat
config. So we know we're good to
go here. So let's go ahead and
create a one. Deploy NFT
marketplace.js. Now once again,
you've seen a lot of this
before, so we're going to spare
the details do const network
equals require hard hat to
constant development chains,
equal equals require dot dot
slash help our hard hats config,
which we should have let's see.
Do we copy paste it over? No.
Okay, so we didn't copy paste
over Are helper Hardhead config
from the last project, let's go
ahead and grab it. Or we can
grab it from the smart contract
lottery and paste that in here.
And we really only need this
file for the development chains
here. Right for hard hat and
localhost, we're going to grab
the development chains from
that. And then we'll also grab
const. Verify, equals require,
get this from utils. Verify,
right? Do we have utils, we have
verify. Fantastic. Now we'll do
module that exports equals
async. an async function where
it's gonna take get named
accounts and deployments. From
the hard hat input parameter,
and then we're gonna do const.
Deploy comma log equals
deployments. And then const,
Deployer equals await, get named
accounts. Which, of course,
we're getting from our heart
head dot config. We have named
accounts, we have a Deployer.
And we have a player or whatever
you have in here from our last
project. And now does our entity
marketplace have a constructor?
Construct? Nope, no constructor.
So we know args is going to be
blank. And then we can say const
NFT. Marketplace equals await,
deploy. And if T marketplace,
say from Deployer, args is going
to be args. Log will be true.
And then wait confirmations will
be network dot config dot wait
confirmations or one, two, this
is going to be block on for
patients, we'll go to the
config, just make sure that
those are in here. I'm sorry, I
didn't add them in here. So
we'll do block confirmations is
going to be six
for all of our networks. So I
actually grabbed this not from
the last project, it looks like
I grabbed this from the hard hat
starter kit. So I'm just going
to add those block confirmations
in there. And now we're good to
go. Now we're gonna say if we're
not on a development chain, not
development chains that includes
network dot name, and process
study and be done ether scan API
key, then we're gonna go ahead,
we'll do log verifying. And then
we'll do a weight verify. And if
the markets place dot address
with arcs, and then we'll do
like log a whole bunch of
hyphens here. And then finally,
module that exports dot tags
equals all and then NFT Mar good
place. And we can test this
deploy function with yarn
Hardhead deploy. Tada, we did
it. Great. So now we have the
deploy function, we can verify
we have our contract, what else
are we probably gonna need to
do. Since this is an NFT
marketplace, we're probably
going to need some NF Ts. So
what we can do is in our
contracts, and we'll create a
new folder for tests got a new
file in here called Basic NF T
dot soul. And in here, we can
add that basic NF T from our
last project. Or you can just go
to my or you can just go to the
GitHub repo associated with this
course, go to contracts, test,
basic NF t, and then just copy
paste. That works too. So this
basic NF t that we're using is
just pointing to the pug as the
basic NF T for us to use just to
test this out. So now that we
have a basic NFT we're gonna
need to create new file, oh to
deploy basic NF T dot j s, and
we'll borrow a lot of the
boilerplate from over here. So
we'll copy all of this actually
paste it in. We'll say const
args equals blank, and we'll say
const basic NF t equals await
deploy basic NF T. From
Deployer. args is going to be
args. Log is going to be true
weight con confirmations is
going to be network dot config
dot block confirmations or one
and then we'll verify this with
if not develop meant chains dot
includes network dot name and
process dot EMV that ether scan
API key that will say log or To
find dot A dot await there if I
basic NFT dot address, and arcs,
module dot exports dot tags
equals all, and basic NFT. And
we can test both of these with
yarn, art had deploy. And
fantastic. Both of these have
been deployed. Again, you don't
have to pause. But it is a good
way to really hone in to really
sharpen those skills on doing
all this. And repetition is the
mother of all skill. So
repeating this stuff yourself
and thinking through these
problems yourself and trying to
code these things yourself, are
really what's going to make you
successful at this. All right,
awesome. Now that we have our
deploy Betson, it's time to
write some tests. Now, if you go
to the GitHub repo associated
with this course, and you go to
the test folder, the tests and
here are some of the robust,
we've actually written out of
all of our projects, there's a
lot of tests in here. Now,
pretty much everything in here,
we've already learned about and
you already know how to do you
have the ability to do it. So
I'm just going to go ahead and
get you started off, and we're
going to write one test
together. And then I highly
recommend you going back in, you
tried to write some tests
yourself, to get that code
coverage to get that test
coverage to be 100 percent. So let's go
ahead, we'll write one test
together, then you should pause
this video and try to write some
tests yourself. When you're done
writing tests and you think
you've hit 100 percent, feel free to
compare back to the test that we
wrote. So let's create a new
folder called tests. Test. And
in here, we'll do a new one
called unit. And if you want to
write staging tests later on,
you absolutely can we will not.
We'll create a new file in here
called NFT marketplace.test.js.
And we'll start some tests. So
we'll do const.
cert, expect equals require Chai
const. Network deployments,
ethers, equals require hard hat
const development chains equals
require dot dot slash dot dot
slash helper, hothead config.
And we're gonna do the same
setup we've been doing. We'll
say bang development chains dot
includes network dot name,
question mark, describe dot
skip. Else describe. And if NF T
marketplace tests, comma async
function, excuse me, this is
just gonna be a function.
Scrabble oval is just a
function, not an async function,
like so. Great. Now let's get
some variables and do a before
each. So we'll say NF T
marketplace, basic NF T, we'll
create a constant price. So
we're just always set the price
of all of our NF T's to the same
thing. This will be ethers dot
utils dot parse
ether 0.1. We'll say const token
ID for now will always be zero.
And then we'll do before each
will be an async function.
And we'll get out and we'll also
get Deployer. Say deployer
equals await, get named
accounts. We're gonna need to
grab getting into accounts from
hard hat as well wrap this all
up dot deployer Excel and then
we'll also in our heart
hat.config.js. Under get named
accounts, we also have something
called player. Now I didn't talk
about this too much. But we're
going to have a second account
which is defaulted to the first
index, right? So we can do at
the top to come up player. And
we can say player equals await
get named accounts dot player.
Now we have a player and a
deployer account will do await
deployments, that fixture. All
will just deploy all of those
contracts will run through
everything in our deploy folder.
We'll get our NFT marketplace.
We'll say NFT marketplace equals
await ethers dot get contract
and ft. marketplace. And then
we'll do basic NF t equals await
ethers dot get contract. Basic
NF T. The way ethers dot get
contract works is it defaults to
grab thing, whatever account is
that account zero, which right
now is our Deployer. If we want
to call a function on NFT
marketplace, with the player
being the one calling the
function, we would have to say,
entity marketplace equals await
and empty marketplace dot
connect player like this. And
now whenever we call a function,
we would use the player instead
of the Deployer. Sometimes what
I like to do and you'll see this
in my code, is I'll do let NFT
marketplace contract. And then
let NFT marketplace, and then
I'll do NFT marketplace contract
equals await ethers dot
contract. And then I'll connect
and set that to the NF T
marketplace. Yes, we can do, we
can automatically choose who to
connect by placing whoever want
to connect to write and get
contract. But sometimes it's
really nice to be kind of
explicit. So it's really up to
you. I'm going to undo all that,
I just want to re show you that
to make sure that you knew
that's how you kind of switch
around with the different
accounts and the different
users. Now that we have an NF T,
we're probably going to need to
mint the NFT so that we can
actually place it on the market.
So we'll do await basic NF T dot
meant NF t, and then we'll
approve to send it on to the
marketplace. So we'll do a wait.
Basic NF T dot approve and T
market place dot address token
ID, which is going to be zero.
And just like that, the NOC
marketplace remember, it can't
call approve, because it doesn't
own that NF t. So we need to
have the Deployer. Call
approved, right. And remember,
since we're not we need to put
basic NF T in here. Since we
didn't tell ethers who to
connect this to it just
automatically connected it to
our Deployer because that's
what's at account zero. So it's
the deployer calling minting it
and then the deployer approving
to send it to the marketplace.
Only after this approved
function has been called canned
the NFT marketplace called
transfer from all those NF T's.
Now we're just going to do one
test here. We're gonna say it
lists and can be bought. That's
it, and this will be an async
function. And we're just gonna
list the NFT and buy a weight
entity marketplace.if We go to
our energy marketplace, what are
we doing, we're listing it
right, we want to list the item
or with the address token ID and
the price. So we'll do dot list
item. Basic NF T dot address,
token ID is zero, which we've
defined right here. And then
price we've hard coded up here
as well. So we're listing it. So
the deployer owns the NF T, the
player is now listing it, now we
want to buy it, let's have the
player be the one to buy it. So
what we're going to do is we're
going to have to connect the
player to the NFT marketplace.
So we can say const player
connected NF T, marketplace
equals and ft marketplace dot
Connect. Player. And then we can
buy the item by saying a weight
player connected and ft
marketplace.by item. It'll be
the basic and if we look back at
the end of the marketplace, what
does buy item need, needs the
NFT address and the token ID. So
basic NF t that address
and then the token ID and after
this bot, we should check to see
that the player actually does
indeed own that NF team. So we
can say const new owner and we
check to see if that owner is
indeed updated. We can say basic
NFT dot owner of because NF T's
have an owner of function, token
ID and then we also want to see
that the deployer actually is
going to get paid. So we can say
await and if T marketplace dot
get
proceeds of Deployer. So now we
can do assert new owner dot two
string equals player and we can
assert deployer proceeds.to
string equals price.to string
because they should have been
paid that price. And that's
right, it's actually a little
bit easier. instead of grabbing
players from getting named
accounts. It's a little bit
easier just to grab it right
from ethers. So we'll do const
accounts equals await
get signers. And then we'll save
player equals accounts of one
just because when we connect
it's expecting it type of
account and then the the get
named account is a different
type. So Oh, it's just a little
bit easier to actually connect
like this. So now we'll connect
to the player like so just know
that player and deployer are now
different types. So you'll see a
little bit differences there. To
me, this is ethers that gets
signers. And then when we buy
the item, we're of course gonna
have to pass a value, it's gonna
be price, of course, we're going
to need to pay the price of the
NFT. And then of course, this
needs to be player dot address.
And that's the difference right
now we got to do player that
address whenever we want the
address of one of the ethers
accounts. And then this new
owner, of course, should be in a
wait. And now we can run this
all. In Tada, we see things
pass. So our NFT marketplace is
able to facilitate the buying
and selling of an NF T with
arbitrary humans. This is
fantastic. So we just ran the
single test to show a little bit
of the oddities when working
with NF T's and some different
accounts. But 100 percent If you feel
up for the challenge, take this
time, pause this video and try
to write some tests. Remember,
the goal here is for us to do
yarn hardhat coverage, and see
what our coverage is and try to
get it to be 100 percent coverage. If
we run it right now, we'll see
Oh, my goodness, we are missing
a lot of coverage. Here, we have
a ton of uncovered lines, on top
of uncovered functions,
branches, statements, etc. Try
to write some tests to get this
to 100 percent and then come back.
Okay, welcome back. Hopefully
now you've written some tests.
And when you run your tests, you
can get some of them, I look
like this, right. And these are
my tests, these are the tests
that I wrote, you could do more
you could do last. And let's
see, when I run yarn Hardhead
coverage, I even missed some
lines. And I could I could test
a little bit more. So make your
tests even better than the ones
that I made. So these are the
tests from the GitHub repo
associated with this. Now that
we've written some tests here,
let's just write a couple of
scripts. And the reason we're
gonna write a couple of scripts
is we're gonna need these a
little bit later. So we'll write
some scripts to mint, some
amount of teased by some NF T's
etc. And we'll need this to
fiddle around and play on the
front end a little bit later. So
to create a script, again, we've
done this perform, let's do a
script called mint, and list dot
j s. And this will be to mint at
NFT. And then immediately listed
on the marketplace. So let's
create an async function called
mint, and list. And down below,
we're going to call mint and
list I'm going to copy paste
with that same script thing that
we've been doing. Obviously,
instead of Maine, though, we're
calling this mountain list. Now
in this mountain list, where
it's a constant, NFT mark, and
of tea market, place equals
await ethers dot get contract.
And ft marketplace. And right
we're going to import ethers
from hard hat. And then we'll do
we'll grab basic NF t. So we'll
say const. Basic kind of T
equals await ethers dot get
contract. Basic NF t. And then
first we'll mint a basic NF t.
So we'll do console dot log,
maintained at the top. And we'll
do a weight or actual we'll say
const. Mint, TX equals await
basic NF T dot mint NF t. And
then we'll do await min TX dot
Wait, wait one block. And
actually we'll say const. Mint
TX receipt. So that equals that.
And in this receipt, here's
another reason why events are so
good. When we met this NFT.
We're omitting the token ID in
an event in this document ID
event. So we could say const
token ID equals mint TX receipt
dot events of zero. That args
dot token Id like that. And now
we have the token ID. And now
that we have the token ID and
the basic NFT. minted we can now
call on our NFT marketplace list
item. So now we'll say console
dot log. Approving NFT right,
it's gonna be real similar to
our tests here. I'm gonna say
const approval TX equals await
basic NFT data prove
NFT marketplace dot address
token ID and then we'll do a
weight approved TX dot wait one
and we'll do console dot log
listing NF t.at that and then
we'll do const TX equals await
and if T market market place
that list item and we'll do NFT
marketplace that address So can
Id do await TX dot wait one,
console dot log listed and cool.
And we can try this out by
running yarn hardhat node, which
is going to run through our
deploy scripts, right, it's
going to run to these deployed
scripts here. And then in a new
terminal, we'll run our script,
yarn hard hat, run scripts meant
and list dash dash network
localhost. And we missed an
argument, oh, we need a price as
well to list our entity. So
we'll create a constant price
equals and we'll say ethers dot
utils dot parse, ether 0.1. And
we'll pass the price and to the
list item. So oops, and sorry,
it's not the marketplace that
we're listing, the basic NF t
that we're listing, of course,
so run that again. And Bada
bing, bada boom, got some listed
events. And we can see here,
we're doing some listing and
awesome. So now we have a
script. Alright, so now that we
have a script, and we're going
to be writing a couple other
scripts a little bit later, we
essentially have a really solid
repo here are our totally
decentralized, NFT marketplace,
this is absolutely massive, and
you should be incredibly,
incredibly proud of yourself.
Now, of course, this is all
code. And people can interact
with this, if they're software
developers, which is great. But
we're going to want to allow
anybody to be able to interact
and list their own NF t's on our
marketplace. So what are we
going to do? Well, we're going
to want to build a front end for
this. And now we're gonna get
into the second part of this
lesson. So on lesson 15, we just
finished the backend. Now we're
gonna move on to the front end,
we're gonna start with this
morass code. The code for both
of these is pretty much nearly
identical. But we're going to
start with Morales, and we're
going to teach you how to do
both of these. And we're going
to teach you the difference
between the Morales and the
MoGraph. And kind of why we're
even using them in the first
place, we're going to start with
Morales. So if you want to
follow along with this next
section, all the code we're
going to be working with, is
going to be in here. So you
excited, I hope you are because
this is going to be a phenomenal
session, we are about to build
one of the most sophisticated
front ends that we can using the
tools that we have. And like I
said, we showed you a little bit
earlier what this is going to
look like. So let's do a quick
refresher here. So here's what
our front end is going to look
like. But what we can do is we
can connect with our little
connect button, we hit Metamask
Metamask pops up, we'll go ahead
and connect. And now that we're
connected, we can see the
different NF T's in here. And if
we're on an address that's owned
by us, it will say owned by you.
And if we switch addresses, are
you I will go ahead and update,
connect there. And now we're
owned by a different address.
Now if it's owned by us, we get
this little hover that says
Update listing. And right now
it's worth 0.18. That's what
it's listed for on our
marketplace. If it's owned by
us, and we click it, we can
update it to a different price.
Let's update it to 50 eath, or
whatever your layer one currency
is, we'll just save new listing
price. We'll go ahead and
confirm. And I'll say the
listing updated, please refresh,
what we can do them. And we'll
mine some blocks on the back
end, and boom, now we see that
it's worth 50 here. Now if we
switch to a different account,
now we can see owned by Baba
blah, and the hovered now says
by me enough is selected as a
different user, I'm going to get
this transaction to actually buy
it. Now go ahead and confirm
that I'm going to buy it, I get
a little pop up. This is item
bought successfully. Now if I do
a little refresh, we'll now see
that that NFT is gone from the
marketplace since we bought it
right and it's no longer
available to be sold. Now what
we can do then is we can come
over to sell NF tees. And at the
bottom, we'll see a withdraw
proceeds. So whenever somebody
buys an NF T, the NFT
marketplace actually keeps the
proceeds that actually keeps the
result of the sale. So if we
switch back to our address that
had the NFT listed, we can now
see Withdraw 50 proceeds because
we know that we have 50 eath,
because we just bought that for
50. So if we hit withdraw,
Metamask is going to pop up, we
can go ahead and confirm, wait a
little bit as transaction
populates, and boom once it goes
through, and we'll see now we
have zero proceeds. Right? We
withdrew everything from here.
So what we can do now is we can
relist that NFT. So if we come
back, go back to the one who
just bought that at a T if we