know the address and the token
ID of the NF t and we own it, we
can go ahead and relisted you're
gonna place the address in here
with the token Id give it some
sort of price. We'll submit
we'll approve giving the NFT
marketplace access to our or
NFT, to our little doggie. And
then we'll go ahead and actually
send the transaction to actually
list the NFT on a marketplace
that we get NF T listed
successfully. After we move some
blocks in the backend, we can go
back to the front end. And we
now see, it's owned by us,
instead of the original owner,
right and set for 10 ether. And
then we can of course, switch
back to a different user, and we
can have
them actually buy. Alright, so
now that we have the contracts,
we know what this looks like on
the contract side. So now let's
figure out how to do this on the
front end side. So let's jump
into our code editor. And begin
if we're on our hard hat and my
NFT marketplace Free Code Camp
folder. That's great. But we're
going to create another folder,
we're going to CD down and
directory. And we're going to
make a new directory. I'm going
to call it next Jas and if T
marketplace dash FCC. Now you
can do next Jas marketplace dash
mirallas FCC if you want. Again,
we're starting with mirallas CD
next Jas NFT marketplace FCC. So
now that we have this folder,
will do code dot will open up a
new VS code, or you can do File
Open folder and open this new
folder. And we can begin working
in this new folder in here. Now
that we're in our new project,
we're in our new folder, we're
gonna do exactly what we've done
before. Yarn create next app,
period. Okay, we've done our
setup here. Now, I don't like es
lint. So once again, I'm just
going to go ahead and delete
that. And what we're going to
add in instead is our prettier
stuff. So prettier, ignore
prettier RC. Again, some people
may strongly disagree with me on
that, but to each their own
right, this is what I like to
do. So this is what I'm going to
do. Now we have a minimalistic
react project, right? If we run
yarn Dev, we open up our UI on
that site, copy this, or
Command, click it. Tada. Welcome
to next. Jas Yeah, we've got an
x js application. As we know, we
go to pages, we go to index.js.
Let's delete everything in here.
Bom will leave the stuff and
head if it comes with stuff and
head will write Hi, exclamation
mark. We'll save we'll come
back. And now we see Hi. And
I'll zoom in a whole bunch.
Boom. So now we have some
minimalistic reacts minimalistic
next, Jas. Now, I know we
already started the project
here. But let's jump to the
readme that's given to us. And
let's talk about how we want to
do this what we want this to
actually look like. Well, we're
going to want to make a
homepage. And in this homepage,
we'll say we'll have it show
recently listed, NF T's homepage
will show recently listed
entities that will say if you
own the NFT, you can update the
listing. If not, you can buy the
listing. So we'll have that. And
then we'll have a sell page. And
in this page, you can list your
NFT on the marketplace. So these
are going to be our two main
pages, we're gonna have a
homepage and a sell page. Now
we're going to have a ton of
components, but we're really
only going to have two main
pages. So if we go back over to
Pages, right, right now we have
our apps dot j s, which serves
our app, which is cool, which
everything runs through. And
then we have our homepage. Let's
also create right now, our sell
page or selling of T dot j s.
And then in here, we'll just
make this really minimal, that
we can copy most of what's in
here, we can actually just copy
paste this whole thing, paste it
in here. And instead of high,
we'll say sell page. We'll save
that. Now if we go to our
localhost do debt slash sell.
And if T oops, we gotta run. Run
the front end again. With yarn
Dev. Sorry, we'll run yarn dev
again. Now we refresh. And now
we can see sell page. So sell
pages that slash sell page, and
then home is just going to be
high. Okay, cool. So we have our
two pages. Which one should we
work on first? Well, let's work
on our homepage. So we're going
to be in our index.js. I'm going
to keep this front end bit
running, we're going to hide it
oops, that's the opposite of
hiding it, push it down, we're
going to hide it like that. And
let's go ahead and let's start
building this. So we see in our
index js, we have some head
stuff here, I'm going to change
this to NFT. Marketplace.
Description is going to be just
an empty marketplace.
Like so Fabcon looks great. Now
if we do a little refresh, now
it says NFT marketplace up at
the top here, which is good.
That's what we want. Well in our
index page, what's one of the
first things that we're always
going to need to do? You guessed
it, we're going to need a little
connect button right? We're
going to need our users to be
able to connect to to web three
to connect to a blockchain. So
same as we've done before. Let's
go ahead let's create a
components folder. And we'll
create a header component
component Nance folder and we'll
create a new file The header
digests. Now remember, since
we've done this before, with our
front end lottery code, we can
always refer back to the lottery
code as well when we're building
this, okay. And of course, we
have all of the code for this on
the GitHub repo. So you can use
that to what I'm not going to
have you all do is last time, we
did that manual header thing,
right, where we had to do all
the local storage and do all
that crazy stuff, we're not
going to do that. This time,
we're going to just do it the
easy way, we're going to just
use the web three UI kit. So to
use this connect button, we're
going to do yarn, add. And we're
not going to do dash dash Dev,
because this connect button is a
necessary component for the
front end, yarn add web through
UI Kit. This also means we're
going to do Morales and react
mirallas. I said, and this is
where it might be a little
confusing. I know I said in here
that we have both a Morales and
other graph edition. So we're
still going to use the Morales
package in both of them. The
only difference is we're going
to use a Morales server as well
in our Morales edition. And
we're not going to use a morale
server on our the graph edition,
they're both can use the Morales
package because all the open
source hooks and tools are still
incredibly powerful, even if we
don't use the Morales server. So
we're still going to use the
Morales package even when we're
going to be using the graph.
Great. So now that we've added
those all, we're going to do
exactly what we did before on
our last next Jas process. So in
order to use our web through UI
component in our app, dot j, s,
and do import mirallas provider
quotes and without sorry, and
curly brace, it's from react
mirallas like that. And then
we're going to wrap our whole
component thing in a morass
provider. So we're gonna do
return, little open parentheses,
close parentheses here. We're
gonna do rounds provider. And
then we're gonna do in if she
allies on Mount is going to
equal false, because we're not
going to use the server yet, or
else provider. Okay, cool. Now
that we've wrapped our app in a
Morales provider, and go back to
our header, we're gonna say
Export default function header,
we're going to grab our Connect
button from what through your
eye kit. So we'll do import
connect button from web three UI
kits. And then in here, we're
just gonna say return. The next
button. Now what we can do back
in our app, J. S, is we can do
import, import, do header from
dot dot slash components header,
and we have our header, we'll
just put our header right above
the component. And we're going
to add some stuff to the header
in a bit. Let's just make sure
that we're importing the header
correctly. Let's go back to our
UI here. And okay, boom, we have
our connects button. If we click
it, you know, we'll get this
little pop up. And I'm way
zoomed in. So I'm going to anway
zoom in.
Now, what else do we want to put
in our header? Well, we're
probably going to want to like
give this like a name and make
this look a little bit nicer,
probably going to want to a link
as well to our cell NF T page.
So let's create a navbar. So
instead of just returning the
connect button, put this in
parenthesis and we'll have a
return some other stuff too. So
we can use this nav tag, which
usually defines like a nav bar.
So it's really similar to a div,
it's just another tag. Right, so
now we'll put everything into
this nav tag. And in next Jas,
we can actually make links using
the next Jas link tag. So what
we can do in this is link allows
us to basically connect to
different links or URLs in our
application, like so. So we can
do import link from next slash
link. And in here, let's say if
we want it to go to the
homepage, we can make a link.
And we'll say h ref equals slash
equals slash. And inside of
this, we would wrap this in an a
tag to make it clickable. And
then we could just say something
like NFT marketplace. Now if we
save that, we go to our front
end, we now we see have a NFT
marketplace button that we can
click and since we're already at
home, we're not going to go
anywhere. But if we copy this
link section, paste it below,
and we make another one for cell
and f t. And we title this cell
NF t. Now we save we go back to
our front end, we now have NFT
marketplace and sell NFT if I
click sell NF t we now get to
the sell page right we'll go
back to the homepage sell page
flip back and forth. Awesome,
very exciting. So now we have
have an incredibly minimalistic
header obviously looks terrible.
So let's do just a little bit of
formatting. And oftentimes
you'll do the formatting last.
But while we're here, we might
as well do our formatting we're
going to use what if you guessed
tailwind? You guessed correctly.
So remember, tailwind with.
Next. Jas, you can always just
follow along here. And we'll
grab, we'll do the exact same
thing we did before we'll do
yarn, add dash dash Dev, that
stuff right there. And then
we'll run a knit after these
finished
installing. So we'll do yarn,
and then paste that in. And
there we go. So now we've got
our post CSS config, we've got
our tailwind config. We're going
to grab tailwind.config.js.
Paste it in here. And then we're
going to grab Global's dot css
and open up Global's dot css,
paste that in there, and cool.
Now we have tailwind in here.
Now that we have tailwind, we
can do some tailwind stuff to
our header here. Let's let's
create a div for all of these
for everything here, we'll
create a little div for all the
stuff here, we'll make like a
big section for almost like a
big sign saying, Hey, you're at
the NFC marketplace, h1, which
stands for header one, and we'll
give it a class name of padding
y of form. Padding x of four,
we'll do font bold text will be
three XL, and then it'll just
say NFT marketplace. Now we have
this NFT marketplace, which is
nice bolt. Awesome. If you're on
your server you're going to kill
it's going to kill it with Ctrl
C, and then we're going to
restart it. And that's going to
pull in all the tailwind stuff.
And now if we refresh our local
main, we should now see okay,
and if T and F c, r gets place,
right, we now see this and big
and bold, which looks a lot
better. So let's keep going.
Let's give our whole nav a class
name. Equals we'll give it
padding of five, border bottom
to flex flex row justify just if
between n items center. We'll
see how that looks. Haha, looks
a lot better. We're now kind of
like setting this up with a
bottom border kind of stick and
some stuff like this, that looks
much much nicer already. Let's
go down here. Let's make our
buttons have a class name equals
lax lax row items center. And
like I said, this is not a
styling class. So we're not
really going to go over exactly
how we're styling this. And that
is okay. But that's going to
move that over make that look a
little nicer. We'll give our
link here, a class name equals
Mr. For P six. And we'll give
both of these the same class
name both these links, give them
some padding, so they moved away
from each other some margin to
the right, so they're away from
each other. And oh, I forgot to
do this Morales off equals
false. We need Morales auth
equals false so that we don't
automatically connect to a
Morales database or try to
connect to Morales database,
when we connect, we want to just
connect with our Metamask. And
we'll change this to home
instead of the marketplace. But
otherwise, that looks pretty
good home selling of T Connect
button. And we can adjust the
formatting of this to make it
look a little different. But I
think for the most part, this
looks much better,
right? Alright, cool, much, much
better looking header. Here, we
have our app.js setup with the
mouse provider headers
components. Let's now move on to
our index. Let's now move on to
showing these NF T's showing all
the NF T's in our marketplace.
And here's where it's going to
already start to heat up and get
really interesting. And actually
one more thing, we're going to
grab this headpiece in the index
if you haven't. And we're just
going to have it be in the app
JSX. So yeah, and our app.js
we're going to put that header
up at the top, and just put a
little, little div, Div. div,
like so wrapping around this
whole thing. This goes here. And
this way, no matter what page
we're on, we're always going to
have this as our header. And we
don't have to define it each one
of our little our things here.
So we'll do a refresh. And it
says head is not defined. Sorry,
that's because we're going to
need to copy import head from
next slash head. Paste it into
our app that Jas import head
from next head. And now we can
see we're going to empty
marketplace no matter what page
we're on, because we're defining
it at our app level. We have the
header in here, we have this
stuff in here, index almost has
nothing in it now. Let's do
this. So what do we want to do?
We want the homepage aka our
index to show recently listed
NFT. So the question is, how do
we show the recently listed NF
Ts. How do we do that? Well,
let's go back to our contract.
We go back to our hard hat NFT
marketplace So we're looking at
at the marketplace, what do we
have in here? How do we actually
see where NFT is stored? Well,
they're stored in this listings
mapping. However, how do we see
all of the listings that are in
here? Well, this is a mapping,
which means we have every single
address on the planet in here,
we can't loop through the
mapping, we'd have to loop
through every single address on
the planet, which is some
insanely large number that you
and I could never fathom how
many addresses there are. So
what are some solutions that we
can take to this problem, right?
Because we're obviously not
going to loop through
everything. So what do we do?
What's what's kind of the first
approach, one of the first
approaches would be like,
alright, Patrick, well, why
don't we just create an array,
an array of listings instead,
and this might be a good
approach. But what if then later
on, we also want to get some
other weird data, maybe we want
to get all the NF t's a user
owns NF t's a user owns, there's
no array of NF T's that a user
owns. Again, that's just a
mapping. But what if we want to
query some other weird data, or
what if an array will be very
gas expensive, which it is, if
we make this an array to loop
through, it'll be incredibly gas
expensive. So we don't want to
have to go back and change. So
I'm going to I'm going to type
this out. Because this is
important. We don't want to
change our protocol for just the
website, we don't want to change
our protocol for just the
website, or we don't want to
much change our protocol for the
website. Because if we were to
make this an array, it would
become incredibly gas
inefficient. And it would become
much harder to use this NFT
marketplace because it would be
so much more expensive. And as
you build more and more complex
protocols, you're going to
realize that having an array for
every single mapping you have
isn't feasible. This is one of
the reasons where these events
come into play. So every single
time we list an NF t, we call
this list item function. And we
omit item listed, this item
listed event is stored in a data
structure that's still on chain,
but just smart contracts can
access it. However, guess what
can't access it off chain
services can access these
events. So what we do in this
case, is what we're going to do
is we will index the events off
chain and then read from our
database. So what we're
literally going to do is we're
going to set up a server to
listen for those events to be
fired, fired. And we will add
them to a database to query. So
yes, we're literally going to
take every single time an item
is listed, we're going to index
it in a database for ourself.
And then we're going to call our
centralized database to start
and we're going to call that
database to do that. Now the
question then becomes Whoa,
isn't that centralized? Hey,
Patrick, we're talking isn't
that centralized? What the
Hickety heck, and the answer to
that is, it's not necessarily.
So the graph is a protocol that
does exactly this. It's a
protocol that indexes events off
chain, and sticks them into this
the Graph Protocol. And it does
it in a decentralized way,
Morales, the way we're going to
show you first does it in a
centralized way, Morales is
going to do it in a centralized
way, which might be the route
that you want to go for speed
for extra bells and whistles, so
that you can do local
development, which is what we're
going to be focusing on here, or
any of the other functionality
that Morales comes with. Because
Morales does a lot more than
just that. That's something to
keep in mind too, is even though
we are adding a centralized
component, or logic, our smart
contracts, the real bulk of this
application is decentralized.
And you can verify all your
interactions are working with
this decentralized smart
contract, we've actually been
using a lot of protocols that
are centralized, like ether
scan, like open see, and some of
these centralized protocols are
really important to this space.
So we're showing you Morales to
get you familiar with working
with one of these centralized
servers, in case you optionally
want to make an application that
provides a centralized service.
And there's a ton of tools in
the space like opens up and
defender tenderly and more, that
are centralized, but give us
massive, massive benefits. We as
a community are bringing more
and more things to being
decentralized. And sometimes we
need some training wheels to get
there. And then the graph is
going to be the decentralized
way, which is a bit of a longer
process to go main net, but
we'll explain all that when we
get there. Let's learn how we
can list the most recently
listed NF T's and Morales in the
graph. Both have some really
solid videos, I'm going to leave
some links in the GitHub repo
associated with this. So if you
want to learn more, you should
definitely watch both of those
because they are absolutely
fantastic and will help you
understand this event stuff
better. So normally, when we
read from the blockchain, we do
something like contract dot get,
get listing, you know, and then
we put it whatever our input
parameters are. Contract double
blah, so instead, so we're going
to read from a database that
houses All the mappings and an
easier to read data structure.
Both Morales and the graph do
this.
We've been using the morass,
open source packages and tools.
However, Morales also comes
optionally with a server back
end to give your web three
applications more functionality.
However, there's a ton of stuff
that we're not going to cover
that Morales can do to help
build your web three
applications. So instead of me
continuing to talk about
Morales, and what it can do, we
have Ivan here to give a brief
overview of some of the other
things that Morales can do take
it away, and
my name is Ivan, I'm from
rallis. And I'm here to tell you
how you can speed up your
development by 10 times and I'm
not over exaggerating, when
you're building something, you
want to ensure that is scalable,
because your DAP may go global,
it may get viral, it may go
mainstream, it can happen. And
if it happens, you don't want to
start from scratch, you want to
use tools and services that
allow you to go fast, and also
to go big. And that's exactly
what mirallas provides. At
mirallas. We create tools, we
create infrastructure for
developers in a way that you
have a single workflow, and they
will soon explain what it means
because this is what saves you
time. If you have a single
workflow for doing things. And
workflow in web three really
means that you have to have a
smart contract, whether it's a
token, the game, some kind of
staking some kind of
marketplace, some kind of defy,
it will be on chain, but at the
same time, you have to connect
it to your back end. Because
when something happens on chain,
you need to monitor that. So you
can create web hooks, you can
create email, you can create a
push notification, you can run
some custom code, you can run
some calculation, you can save
something to the database,
everything on chain at the end
of the day needs to go into our
back end. And when something is
in your back end, it needs to go
to the front end. So for
example, you change the UI when
something happens on chain or
you change the UI. If your user
receives a transfer there is
above a specific threshold. Or
if your user has this NFC, you
can allow them access into some
kind of chat or some kind of
exclusive piece of content. So
at Morales, we provide you with
a full stack suite of tools that
is used by over 100,000
developers, it's really becoming
one of the most adopted tech
stacks in web three. And it all
starts with Morales identity,
which ensures that you get one
piece of code, you write one
piece of code and you can log in
your users across different
blockchains across different
wallets. And in your morale is
dashboard, you will get the user
profile, and you will get a web
session. So mirallas allows you
to manage identities because a
user profile can have many
different wallets from many
different chains connected to
it. And all of the transactions
will be synced from that user,
all the real time transactions
will be synced about that user.
And also, you have established
web session between your front
end whether it is a game,
whether it is a web website, we
ensure that you have secure
authenticated web sessions, and
we provide you with session
management. So in case you have
your own bike, and then you have
mirallas session identity
management, you can invalidate
sessions, you can log in users
and do all of that great, all of
these great things with one line
of code. That's very important.
Number two is Morales real time
I already mentioned a bit of it.
But basically when you have a
user, you know exactly what's
going on in real time. You can
run custom code, whenever a user
does a transaction, you can run
custom code or do a web hook or
email or push notification
whenever a user interacts with a
smart contracts or when a smart
contract simply emits an event.
This can be an trade in an NFC
marketplace, this can be ERC 20
transfer, you can be very
flexible by setting filters. So
you can say only give me alerts
only give me web hooks when the
user transfers more than 10
NFCs. Or when this token
transfer is above $1,000, and so
on so forth. This is morale is
real time very, very powerful
things. Next are mirallas SDKs.
So whether you're building a
website, whether you're building
a game where full integration
with game engines, whether
you're building for some other
platform, we have extensive SDKs
that are easy to use that allow
you to do all of this that allow
you to connect to Morales and do
this very, very easily. And if
you go to our documentation,
which I highly recommend you to
do, you go to Morales, Doc's dot
morales.io, if you go to Doc's
dot, Marisa Yo, you will first
and foremost understand what
mirallas is in depth. So you can
think of it kind of like
Firebase, but for crypto,
basically, it's a managed
backend, that you can connect
your front end. Also, you can
connect it to your own back end
using no GS SDK, it's very, very
easy. But what I wanted to show
you here is cross platform. So
for each thing we have, let's
say you want to get nfts for
your user, we'll show you how to
do it in simple JavaScript,
vanilla JavaScript, how to do it
and react, how to do it using a
web request. Let's say that you
just want to use a raw web
request. Let's say you're using
some kind of language that we
don't have SDK for you still can
use Morales just that you have
to call the raw HTTP request.
And we'll also show you how to
do it in Unity using C sharp in
Unity game engine. So we're
very, very clear cross platform.
And we are cross chain. So this
means for example, when you log
in the user, you can create the
user profile where you have the
lambda address, let's say your
user uses Solana then they can
easily connect Aetherium, they
can easily connect Binus chain,
the end, we're gonna add more
chain soon, they can easily
connect L Ron, to one user
profile. And then you have all
kinds of different wallets,
different chains, and you have
one single user profile one
single user ID. This is, by the
way, how it will look like in
your database. As you can see,
you're going to have a user user
table right here, you're going
to have all of their accounts.
So in this case, I only have
eath. But if I have Solana, if I
have other types of blockchains,
it will all be right here. And
this is a database that also has
all my transactions. This is a
database where I can set up
different listen events or smart
contracts. So for example, open
see I can watch open see smart
contracts or something else. And
it's very, very variable,
because this is MongoDB. This is
MongoDB, you can run MongoDB
queries, it's very, very
variable. So in that sense,
mirallas gives gives you a nice,
nice dashboard with everything
you need to know about your
users, their sessions, their
permissions, and so on, so
forth. And of course, you can
connect to your own back end
using the Node js SDK. So this
is Morales SDKs. And finally,
when we're speaking about the
workflow, the final thing is the
API's, which I also already
showed you, but the API is that
you can do RAW requests from any
programming language from any
kind of architecture. So using
this workflow, you can easily
achieve anything you want very,
very quickly. You really have to
try Morales it is it will change
your life. I can explain here
all I want, I have limited time.
But as you can already see, by
this presentation, you're very
curious, as you already can see,
by this presentation, you want
to try this as you already feel
by watching me here, you are
very, very excited. We have to
get your hands dirty. So go,
number one, two dogs, authorize
the sale, and go here getting
started connector SDK in vanilla
or react and go through all of
this. See the magic for
yourself. And if you want
practicalities, go to youtube
channel and go to morality Oh,
slash projects, guys, you all in
the community. Using Morales,
you will succeed using rallies,
you will achieve your goal. And
you're going to do sooner than
you expect yourself. You're
gonna surprise yourself. But
don't let yourself down. Go to
morales.io sign up, get started,
you guys. Now that I've
explained all of that, what does
this look like? Well, this is
where we're actually going to
start using mirallas with its
server capabilities. And we're
going to sign up for a server
here. And we're going to use
Morales as our back end for our
application. So to get set up
with Morales, we go to
morales.io. We can go ahead and
sign up for free. We'll put our
email in, we'll create some
password. Why are you here?
Other please specify Patrick's
amazing hardhat video, you don't
have to write that. But if you
want to write that you can. What
did you hear about Morales for
the first time? Well, you all
heard about it on YouTube,
because you heard it from me,
and then pick your roll, I'm
going to be a developer, we'll
hit next, I don't want to
subscribe. But I'm going to not
be a robot and create your
account. And it even gives us a
little property or create your
first server. So our back end is
going to use a server to do any
stuff on the back. So we'll
create a server. And if we were
going to do a main net or a
testament, we choose one of
those. But for now we're going
to do a local dev chain server.
And again, this is one of the
advantages of Morales is it
allows us to work with our local
dev chain. For indexing events,
we can actually index our events
from our local hard hat node,
which is incredibly, incredibly
powerful here, so check your
email, and we'll have an
activate my account thing,
email, we'll hit activate your
account. And it'll bring us back
here and we'll recreate and
we'll do local dev chain.
Alright, so now we're going to
create a new local dev chain
server. So we're going to call
this NFT marketplace, we're
going to select the region,
whatever region you want, I'm in
the eastern United States. So
I'm going to choose New York.
But whatever location works for
you, we're gonna do local dev
chain, and we're going to do
eath, local dev chain. And
again, if you're building for
polygon, if you're building for
avalanche, if you're building
for Phantom, if you're building
for any of these EVM compatible
chains, again, your eath local
dev chain, it's going to work
exactly the same. So we're going
to add instance now. And we're
going to create a new
application here. So we're going
to close now we have the server
here, and it says ganache, but
it's really hard hat. Don't
worry about that. Now that we
have our server up, we can go to
the Morales documentation, what
we're looking for is events,
we're looking to sync with
events. So we can even do a
little search in here for
events. And we see smart
contract events platform
Automatic Sync, and even tells
us a little bit more about why
do we need to sync and watch
smart contract events. So
basically, this server our
database is going to be looking
for these events to be emitted.
But before we can do that, we
need to hook up our application
to our server and if you go to
the React Morales GitHub right
at the top And you'll probably
see saw this before, when you
have this Morales provider in
their docks, they actually pass
an app ID and a server URL. And
this is how we can actually
connect directly to our servers
on mirallas. So what we're gonna
do is right, now we're gonna go
back to our app that Jas and
originally we've been saying
initialize on Mount equals
false. When we say this, we're
saying, Hey, we're not going to
use a morale server, we're just
going to use the open source
morass tools that y'all provide.
Now, we actually do want to use
their server, right, we do want
to use all these bells and
whistles that Morales comes with
out of the box. So we're going
to change that. So instead of
saying initialize on Mount
equals false, we're just getting
ready with the app ID and the
server URL. So we're going to
delete this. And just like it
says, in the documentation,
we're gonna give it an app ID
and a server URL. So we're gonna
say app ID equals, and this is
where as a string, we'll put our
app ID. So if we go back to our
Morales database, we can go to
view details. And we see all
this information in here. And we
can grab our application ID, we
can copy it, paste it in here.
And then we'll want to grab our
server URL, which is at the top.
So this is the URL of our unique
custom morale server. So we'll
say server, URL equals and then
paste that in there like that.
Now, if you've been following
along with these tutorials, you
might be thinking oh, we're
we're kind of just hard coding
that stuff right in there like
that, how that seems kind of
that seems kind of bad. Well, if
that's your intuition, that is
fantastic. So instead, we're
actually going to put these into
environment variables. So we're
going to create a new file, a
dot env file. And this is where
we're going to put all of our
environment variables. Now next,
Jas comes with built in support
for environment variables, which
allow you to do the following
use dot env, dot local to load
environment variables or those
environment variables to the
browser by prefixing. It with
next underscore public. So
there's a couple of different
environment variable paths we
can use. We can do dot env, dot
local, we can do dot env, dot
this dot that that the other
thing, we're just going to do
dot env, to keep it simple here.
But in order for our front ends,
to read environment variables
from our dot env file, we have
to do next underscore public
underscore, and next Jas will
look into our dot env file for
variables that start with this
and only stick these environment
variables into our application.
If we were to just do like
Morales server equals blah,
blah, blah, it has no idea what
this is because we need to do
next underscore public
underscore. And if we do that,
and we'll do a console dot log,
look here, process dot env. Next
public morale server and we
actually need to kill it and
restart it. And then we go back,
we do a little refresh here,
it'll say Look here as a do bla
bla bla, because that's what is
in the dot env file with that
next public. So we'll grab our
app ID, we'll copy it. And then
our dot env will do next public
app ID equals and we'll paste
that in there. We'll grab our
server URL, we'll go back to
here. We'll do next public
server URL equals, we'll paste
that like that. And now at the
top, we'll say const. App ID
equals process dot E and V dot
next, public app ID. And then
we'll say const. Server URL
equals process dot E and V dot
next public server URL. Now that
we've had these variables, we'll
stick them in like this.
So this is how we can connect
our application to our morale
server. Now, of course, we
haven't done anything yet. But
we're getting started, right?
This is how we're going to
connect to it. Now that we've
signed in, well, I told you that
our morale server was going to
be indexing our events. And if
you go to this Dashboard button,
this is our entire database.
Everything in this browser tab
is what's in our database right
now. And as you can see, right
now, there's not a whole lot of
anything, if we had any events
data in here, it would be in
here. So we need to tell our
server, hey, you need to start
listening for events. So we can
show the most recently listed
entities. So morale server, you
need to start listening, you
need to create a database entry
for every single one of these
item listed events. And whenever
somebody buys an item, right,
whenever somebody buys that
item, or cancels an item, you
need to remove that from your
database. How do we start
telling Morales to start
listening to our events? Well,
first off, well, first off,
we're gonna need to connect it
back to to our blockchain. And
then we're going to say, which
contract which events and what
to do when it hears those
events. So we need to connect it
and then we need to tell it what
to do when it hears those
events. So how do we connect our
mirallas server to our hard hat
blockchain? And right now, we're
not running one. But let's go
ahead and we'll start up our
hard hat, our local host
blockchain. So in one terminal,
we're running the front end and
another terminal will see the
download directory. We'll cd
into our hard hat NFT
marketplace dot Free Code Camp
or Free Code Camp, and we'll do
yarn hard hat node. And if we've
done everything correctly, it'll
deploy our NFT marketplace.
It'll deploy our Basic NFT and
then it'll start local HTTP web
socket at blah, blah, blah. So
that's good. So now that we have
that Node running, what we can
do is we can go to view details,
and go to dev chain proxy
server. So this dev chain proxy
server is going to be how we
actually tell Morales to listen
to our locally running hard hat
node. Now, to do this, what
you're going to need to do is
we're going to need to download
this what's called a reverse
proxy. And I have a link to this
in the GitHub as well, depending
on what computer you're running
on will tell you which one of
these we actually need to
download. And then there's some
troubleshooting tips down here
if you ever get lost, and if
you're really, really confused,
what we can do what Morales FRP
to download, do a quick search
on this. We even come right to
the documentation, connecting
ganache to Morales note for Mac
users download FRP dot Darwin
dot bla bla bla for the nosh
proxy server. So I'm on a Mac.
So I'm going to download this
Darwin AMD 64. And for look at
the releases, that's the first
one at the top, Darwin AMD 64.
So this is the one that I'm
going to go ahead and download.
I'm gonna click it, I'm going to
download it. Once I have it
downloaded, we're going to open
it up, and we're gonna get a
folder and we're gonna get a
folder that looks like this. The
main things that we need are
going to be f RP and FRP C dot
ini. F RPC is going to be the
executable it's going to be what
we're going to run to connect
our blockchain node to Morales,
and F RPC dot ini is going to be
basically the config file to do
this. Now, again, this is one of
the sections where downloading
this is going to be one of the
hardest steps here. So if you
get lost, please ask questions
in the GitHub, please ask
questions in the Morales forum,
there is a Morales forum as
well, where you can ask a ton of
different questions. And please
check out the troubleshooting as
well. But what I'm going to do
is I'm going to create a new
folder in here new folder called
F R P. And I'm doing it in here
just to make it a little easier.
But you could really put this
wherever you want, and then
always refer back to it. And
what I'm going to do is I'm
going to take I'm going to copy
these two files, and place it
into this FRP folder. So now I
have FRP C, and F RPC that ini
if you click on the F RPC, it's
going to be like, hey, it's
binary, you can't really look at
this, don't click that, it'll
just be a whole bunch of
nonsense, but the F RPC dot ini
looks like a pretty typical
config file. And this is what
we're going to adjust. If we
even go back to our morale
server, it'll give you what you
need down here. And we're using
hard hat. So we're going to copy
everything here. We're gonna go
back to our F RPC dot ini, and
then just paste whatever is in
there in here. And that's how
we're going to tell this F RPC
thing that we need to connect. I
haven't tried this out for users
using WsL. So if you're using
WsL, let us know in the full
blockchain solidity course, Jas,
make a new discussion, if you
haven't seen it already, saying,
Hey, I'm using WsL for the F
RPC. And here's what you need to
use. And then at the bottom, it
says, run and enjoy. I'm running
on a Mac OS, which runs Linux
commands, so I can just copy
this, I'll create a new
terminal. And what I'm going to
do is I'm going to cd into that
FRP folder. And I'm going to
paste that thing that I just
that I just copied from Ross. So
we're running that F RPC
executable dash c, which is dash
config, F RPC dot ini. If I hit
Enter, it's gonna say log into
server success, get run ID,
blah, blah, server, UDP port,
and then a whole bunch of other
stuff. If you're seeing success
stuff here, that means you did
it right. And you can hit CTRL C
to cancel because we're not
going to keep running it. Now,
if you want to just run this,
you absolutely can. But I'm
going to show you another way to
do this. And this is using the
Morales admin CLI. So everything
that we're doing here, all these
buttons that we're pressing,
Morales actually comes with this
thing called the Morales admin
CLI or the command line
interface. So this is a way for
us to connect and run all these
buttons and stuff that we're
pressing right from our terminal
and right from our shell. So I'm
going to show you a couple of
commands on how to work with the
admin CLI. And we're going to be
working with a lot of admin CLI
commands. But all we're going to
do is npm install dash g
Morales, admin CLI or for us
yarn Global Add. So we're going
to grab that will do yarn,
Global Add routes, admin CLI
like that. And now we should be
able to run Morales admin CLI
and see a whole bunch of stuff
like that. And if you ran
routes, admin CLI, we have all
this stuff. And one of the big
ones, one of the important ones
that we're going to be working
with is this connect local dev
chain. So running this F RPC
dash c dash f RPC ini. That's
going to be the same as running
this connect local dev chain.
Now what I like to do is jump
into our package dot JSON. And
we'll create an additional
script in here for us to just
run yarn, whatever the name is
that we want, and just to do
that, and just to make it a lot
easier for us to connect our
local dev chain so underneath
lint, I'm going to do a calm
Ma'am, I'm going to create a new
command. I'm gonna say Morales
sync. And we're going to run the
Morales admin CLI version of
this f RPC dash c thing. So what
we're going to do in here is
we're going to say mirallas
admin CLI, connect local dev
chain, dash dash chain, hard
hat, dash dash mirallas. Capital
sub domain.
This is where we're going to put
the subdomain of a morale
server, which if we go to, we go
back to our routes, admin data
servers, we can go back to
server details. So it's going to
be not the HTTPS, it's just
going to be from here all the
way to the.com. So not even the
port, we're going to grab that
we're going to paste that there.
And then we're going to do space
dash dash f RPC path is going to
be dot slash F RPC, slash FRP
slash F RPC. Now if we save
this, and we run it, it's not
going to work though. So if I
run yarn with our new script,
Morales sync, it's gonna say
specify Morales API key, it's
going to give us this prompt.
And in our dashboard, we have
our API key, which we can copy,
we can paste it, and then API
secret, we can copy and then
paste it. And then we'll say
starting connection to hard hat,
which is great. But that's
really annoying. And I don't
want to have to do that. So
we're going to Ctrl C, we're
going to kill that. And what we
can do is we can go into our dot
env. And we can actually add
those as environment variables
that Morales is expecting. So
when we run this Morales admin
CLI, it'll check our dot env
file for Morales API key, which
we can copy right here. And then
Morales API secret, which we can
copy, and paste right here. Now,
the reason that these aren't
capital and doing next public,
these are not going to be part
of our front end piece. These
are keys that we're using on the
back end to test and for our
local dev chain connection. So
we don't need to do next public,
we're just going to leave it
like this. But now if I hit up
and run yarn Morales sync,
again, it's not going to prompt
me this time, it's just gonna
say starting connection to hard
hat. And if you see this, this
starting connection to hard hat
bit, we can come back to our
servers, we'll go to dev chain
proxy servers, we'll hit this
disconnected button and refresh.
And if you see connected, you've
successfully connected our heart
add node, which is running here
to our Morales server, which is
awesome. And in fact, if you sit
on your heart had no terminal,
you'll see the actual RPC calls
to our blockchain here. And
you'll see Morales is
consistently calling f block
number to make sure it's up to
date with what it has. So how do
we tell a morale server to start
listening for events? Well,
there are two ways we can do
this. The first way is with the
user interface. So we can go to
view details, we'll go to sync.
And right now it says no sync
services installed. So we'll hit
Add a new sync. And we can see
sync and watch address and sync
and watch contract events, we
can watch the address for
transactions or we can watch
some address for any events. And
we can manually add all our
information here, you can select
the chain description, decide if
we want to optionally sync
historical, we could put the
topic of the event, the ABI of
the event, the address of the
event filter, and then a table
name. Or we could do all this
programmatically, which is what
we're going to do, we'll create
a little script that we can run,
tell our morale server to watch
for those scripts. And we'll see
our database get upgraded to
listen for those events. So back
in our code, we're going to
create a new file called add
events that Jas now we have one
terminal that's running our
front end one terminal that's
running our blockchain one
terminal that syncing our
blockchain with morass. And now
we're going to do another
terminal. For anything else we
want to do like run little
scripts become the Morales
docks, and you click connect
with SDK, there's a ton of
different ways we can actually
connect with the SDK, we've
already learned how to connect
with react by using React
Morales. Now we're going to
connect with no JS since we're
going to run a little Morales
script. And here's like a little
example of what it looks like in
the documentation. But I'm gonna
go ahead, so I'm gonna say const
Morales, equals require oralis
slash node. And we're going to
import the node extension of the
Morales package into our script
here, we're going to require dot
env
dot config, which means we're
going to need to install dot env
yarn add dash dash dev dot env.
And now we have to tell our
morale server all the same
information that we would need
to tell it on the user
interface. So one of the first
things that we're going to need
is the address of our contract.
We're gonna need to say const
contract address equals and this
is where we go oh, well, how do
we how do we get that contract
address? The easy way to do this
is we just go back where we're
running the blockchain And we'd
grab where that NFC marketplace
is deployed. And similar to our
smart contract lottery where we
created an update front end
script, we're gonna do the exact
same thing here. So back in our
heart hat, NFT marketplace, and
if T code, we go to our deploy
script or deploy folder, we're
gonna create a new file called
99 Dash update, front end dot j
s, and we're gonna create a
little bit of our deploy process
that will automatically update
our front end. So we can just
grab the network address from a
file that is programmatically
created. So we're gonna do
module dot exports equals async
function. And now we'll say if
process dot EMV that update
front end, then console dot log,
updating front end so that in
our dot EMV, we have update
front end equals true. And that
will be how we decide whether or
not we actually want to update
the front end. And then we'll
create a function called up date
contract addresses, which we
will await. And this will update
the contract addresses of our
front end. So let's make that
function. Do async function
update contract addresses, make
sure those are spelled the same.
So we'll say const NFT, market
place equals await ethers dot
get contract. And then yes, we
need to import const ethers
equals require hardhat, we'll
grab the NFT market place. And
then we're going to want to
write our files in here to
someplace in our front end code
for us, we're going to do in a
new folder constants. And we're
going to create a new file in
here called network mapping dot
JSON. And we'll have this just
be a JSON object which keeps
track of all of our deployments.
So if we deploy something to
rink V chain will keep a list
will keep a list of it will say
NFT marketplace will keep a list
of all the addresses of the IoT
marketplace, comma basic NF T,
right, and then I list of all
those right now we don't have
anything deployed. So we'll just
have it be an empty JSON object.
Now back in our deploy script in
the hard hat NFT marketplace
project, we're going to keep
track of that location. So right
at the top, we're gonna say
const. Front, and contracts file
equals, and we'll place where it
is according to your file setup.
So if I do cd dot dot slash,
next JS NFT, marketplace, free
code, Camp constants, network
mapping dot JSON, this is where
mine is. So you're going to want
to put it wherever your location
is in relation to your heart at
Mt marketplace Free Code Camp,
it's my front end contract file,
it's going to be right here. Now
that we have all that we're
going to get the chain ID. So
we're gonna say const, chain ID
equals network dot config dot
chain, id.to string. And we're
going to need to import network
from hard hat as well. And then
we're going to want to read from
this network mapping file to see
what's currently in there. So
we'll say const. Contract
addresses equals and we're gonna
do a JSON dot parse Fs dot read
file sync, front, and front and
contracts. File comma UTF,
eight. Now here's what we're
gonna say, if chain ID is in
contract. addresses, let's say
if this list of contract
addresses doesn't include the
marketplace, then added on,
we're gonna say if contract
addresses of chain ID of the
NFT. Marketplace will say dot
includes NF T, market, Mar get
place dot address, then so we'll
say contract address says chain
ID NFT marketplace, dot push NFT
marketplace dot address else
we're gonna say contract
address says of chain ID of NFT
marketplace, which is going to
be a new entry now equals NFT.
Market market place dot address.
So now we've updated our
contract addresses object and we
just need to write it back to
the network mapping. So now
we're gonna say Fs dot right
file sync front and contracts
file comma JSON dot string five
contract addresses and then at
the bottom we'll do module dot
exports dot tags equals and
we'll say all or front end. Now
what we can do is we can run
just this update front end
script with yarn hardhat deploy
dashed dash, network localhost.
And we only want to do this
update front end script. So we
say dash dash tags front end,
and we run this, and I ran into
an error FS is not defined, oh,
I forgot to do const Fs equals
require Fs stride again, cannot
set properties of undefined NFT
marketplace. Oops. And that's
because this line is off instead
of this line, sorry. Basically,
right now, what it's saying is,
it's saying, hey, this NFT
marketplace thing doesn't exist.
So we need to make it exists. So
now we'll say contract addresses
of chain ID equals a new entry
of NFT marketplace and adds its
first parameter, it's going to
be NF T, Mark gets placed dot
address, like that. Now we can
run it, and updating front end
looks like it's done. So if we
go back to our front end, we now
see we have an entry for
localhost with NFC marketplace
with the address in our network
mapping dot JSON. So if you did
that correctly, you should get
this. If not, if you're having a
hard time with that you can, of
course, just go ahead and hard
coded in but I do highly
recommend you do it
programmatically, because your
life is going to be a lot
better. So cool. We have this
update front end script that
works now, so we can put this
back off to the side. And let's
keep going. So we now have this
network mapping file with
contract addresses based off of
the chain ID. So what we can do
is we can pull that in as well,
we'll say const contract,
address says equals require dot
slash constants, slash network
mapping dot JSON. And now we can
get the contract address based
off the chain ID. So we'll say
chain ID equals process dot E
and V dot chain ID, or 31337. So
in our data and V, we'll make a
new entry called Chain ID. And
for now, we'll do 31337. And now
we can get the contract address
by saying contract address
equals contract addresses at the
chain ID of n, f t, Mark get
place of zero. So we're going to
go into that network mapping, go
to the chain, Id go to the NFT
marketplace and get the most
recently deployed NFT
marketplace boom. So now we have
the contract address contract
address says Excuse me. Now in
our add events, we'll create a
new function kind of similar to
what we're doing, we'll do async
function main. And this will be
our main function. And then of
course, we're going to copy
paste that main script thing
we've been doing this whole time
domain dot then catch blah,
blah, blah, we go back to the
morass documentation, though, we
can see we're going to need to
grab our server URL, app ID
master key, and then start it
up. So we're gonna do the exact
same thing. So once again,
sorry, before we even get into
our main, you can do it in your
main function, if you want.
We'll say const server URL
equals, and we can just grab
this once again, from our web.
So we'll say process web dot
next public Morales server URL,
we'll get the app ID equals
process Studien v dot next
public Morales app ID, and then
we'll say const, master key
equals process study v dot
master key. So we don't have a
master key in here yet. So we'll
create a new one called master
key. We'll go back to our
Morales front end, we'll close
out of this, we'll hit View
Details. And we'll grab that
master key. So we'll copy that,
go back to our code editor and
paste it in. And now we have a
master key in our web as well.
We don't want our master key on
our front end. So we're not
going to put next public like
that. Now, the first thing we're
going to do in our main function
is we're going to do await
Morales dot start server URL,
app ID and master key as the
input parameters for this will
do a little console dot log,
working with contract address,
contract address. Now we're
gonna go ahead and add all those
same pieces that we see on the
UI. So what are the events we
want to listen for? Well, if we
go back to our code here, so we
have our NFT marketplace, where
just type in event we have item
listed item bought an item
cancelled. So we have three
events we want to listen and a
Morales, they have this add new
events synced from code, which
we're basically going to be
following. To do this, we need
to obviously start and then
create our options for the
event. We have the chain address
topic, abi elimite, table name
and sync historical and then we
just do Morales dot Cloud dot
run, watch cloud event options
use master key. And that's
pretty much it. So we're going
to follow these documents here
to do our code. So let's start
with item listed. Let's create
some options for our IDed listed
event. So we'll say let item
listed options, or we could do
const if we want to, but I'm
just gonna do let item listed
options equals. And first we're
gonna need the chain ID, which
we have, because we're getting
it from Morales. Now the first
thing to point out about chain
ID is that ralis understands a
local chain is 1337. So even if
you're on 31337, if you're doing
a local development, you got to
switch it to 1337. So we're
going to make another variable
called Morales chain ID. And
we're just going to say, let
Morales chain ID equals chain ID
equals 31337. Question mark
311337. Otherwise, chain ID but
we're saying since Morales
understands that any local Dev
is going to be 1337, we're going
to say if chain ID equals 31337.
Then have Morales chain ID equal
1337. Otherwise have an equal
whatever whatever our chain
ideas and in our dot env we can
decide okay, if we want to do
rink B, localhost main net, etc.
We're gonna say Okay, chain ID
morass will do your Morales
chain ID, comma, we'll say what
else do we need? We did the
chain ID, we're gonna skip
description, a sync historical.
So hit sync historical allows
the node to go back throughout
the blockchain, grab all the
events ever emitted by that
contract. Since this is a very
small local blockchain will just
say sync historical is true.
Like that. Okay, what else do we
need? Okay, we need the topic,
the topic is going to be your
event information. So to get the
topic, go back to our event
code, and the topic is just
gonna be the name of the event,
plus the type of the parameters.
So we're gonna go back to our
code, we're gonna go back to
here, we're gonna say, topic is
going to be item listed, and it
takes an address, an address, an
address, you went to 56, and a
UNT 256, address address, you
interviewed six, YouTube and
six. Those problems seem like
that, we also need the API of
just the event, which again, we
can find we go back to our hard
hat project, we go to artifacts,
we go to contracts. And if the
marketplace dot soul NFT
marketplace dot JSON, our ABI
starting from here is going to
be the ABI of the whole
contract. And we just want that
item listed event. So we did
Ctrl F, and we found it here.
And we're going to grab from
right after it says type event,
we're going to copy we're going
to scroll up to write up to
anonymous false, right, so this
bit describes the ABI of the
event. So we have internal type,
address, name, seller type,
address, and if T address token
ID price item listed, right, so
this is going to be the ABI of
our just our item listed event,
we can take that and we just
stick it in here, hit save, and
mine auto format it to get rid
of the parentheses. Okay, what
else do we need, we have the
topic, we have the ABI, we
already have the address, we're
not going to do a filter. And
then we need a table name. So
we're going to do a new line,
we'll say table name, it's going
to be item listed. And this is
going to be the name of the
table that we update in our
database. So we're gonna get a
new table in here called item
listed, and it's just gonna be
filled with information about
the item listed event. And
that's it right and we would hit
confirm if we were doing this on
the UI. And since we're doing
here, we'll just hit save, this
is one of our events, we want to
do this for all of our events.
Let's do it now for item bought.
So we'll say let's, item bought
options, equals and we'll repeat
the process, some of the stuff
at the top is gonna be the same,
the chain it is gonna be the
same sync historical is gonna be
the same. So we can just grab
those two, paste them down here
for item, but the topic is going
to be different. The topic is
going to be item bot is the name
of the event, it's going to take
an address, an address, a un 256
and a un 256. The ABI is going
to be different. Once again,
we're gonna go to our Hardhead
NFT marketplace, we'll look for
a bot, you'd find this event
here. We'll copy this, go back,
we'll paste it in here, we now
have item bot, we'll give it a
table name of item bot. And then
one more then we have let item
cancelled options equals and
we'll do chain ID that's going
to be rouse chain ID gonna be
the same boilerplate from the
top address. Contract address
topic is going to be different.
The topic for this it's called
item cancelled, and it takes an
address, an address and a UNT
256 will say sync. Historical
will be true, historical is
true. And then we need the ABI.
Once again we can go back to our
hard hat, compile information we
can look for item cancelled,
grab that ABI of that event.
Copy that. Come back to our
running code pasted in. Oops and
I didn't give item canceled.
Let's give item canceled the
table name, which will be item
canceled. So now if I zoom out
just a hair, I now have item
cancelled options, item bought
options. And item listed options
are telling Ross Hey, listen for
these events, whenever you hear
an item canceled event, stick
all this stuff into a database.
Whenever you hear an item bought
event, stick all this in a
database, whenever it emits an
item listed, stick all this in
in a database so that we can
read from it. So we're indexing
these events so that we can
query them much easier. Now to
send them up to our our server
will say const listed response
equals await or Alice or Alice
dot Cloud dot run, watch
contract event will pass the
item listed options. And then
one more comma, and then we pass
an object in here where we're
just gonna say use master key is
going to be true. And we'll do
the same thing we'll say const
bot response or passing the bot
item options. So we'll say bot
response equals await or else
dot Cloud dot run, watch
contract, event, comma, item
bought options. Comma, use
master key that's going to be
true. And then finally Kant's
canceled response equals await
oralis dot Cloud dot run, watch
contract event, comma, item
canceled options, comma use
master key is going to be true.
Now this Morales dot Cloud dot
run API call to our server that
we're making is going to return
a response. And let's look at
the docs to actually see what
that response looks like if it
worked out. Well. In the
terminal, you'll see success
true. So this is the return