we're getting from the API. So
just to make sure everything
goes well, I'll do an if listed.
response dot success, we're
getting that success object from
the rails server, we'll just do
a console dot log success
database updated with watching
events. And then else we'll say
console dot log, something went
wrong with a duck. And of
course, we're not just looking
for let's say response dot
success to be true. We also want
canceled response that success
and bots response
is successful. Then say hey, you
did it. Otherwise say hey,
something went wrong. So this is
how we're going to
programmatically tell our server
our database to listen for
events. So we just do await
Murata Clodagh, run, watch
contract events, we pass it this
object with all these parameters
and flags in there. And then
that's it. And then we can send
them is because I put next
public Morales server URL. And
in my DMV, I just have next
public server URL. So let's
change the name here. Looks like
our server URL was wrong. And
our app ID name is also wrong.
So let's fix that next public
app ID master key looks correct.
Okay, cool. So let's know things
right? More Alice, like cada
run, Rasta cloud run, when we
run this in our database, if we
hit refresh, right now, we don't
see those tables in here. But
once we run this, add events.js,
we should call our server and we
should tell it hey, you need to
add these tables. And you need
to start listening for those
events. So in a new terminal,
we're going to run this add
events such as, so I'm going to
make the terminal nice big. And
this is where if something goes
wrong, it can be a little
frustrating to figure it out how
to fix this. So if you run into
an issue here, if something's
not working as expected, please
use the GitHub repo associated
with this course. And also the
Morales forum is here for you,
and Stack Exchange Etherium. So
we're going to run Node, add
events, dot j s, and we'll hit
enter. Okay, boom, now we see
success database updated with
watching events. Now, if you ran
into an issue, and you rerun it,
and it gets something went
wrong, there's a chance that it
could still be correct, right,
because it returns false. It
returns that there's an issue if
any of these already have the
table in there. So if we go back
to our database here, and we hit
refresh, I can now see item
bought, item canceled and item
listed in my database. And
again, you can see them by
hitting the drop down on your
server and hitting dashboard. We
also see event Sync Status. And
this is how our database knows
that it needs to be listening
for some events, and it's got
all the information about how to
listen for our events in here.
So cool. So now we are listening
for events. This is fantastic.
So now what this means is our
database is now listening To our
blockchain node, and it's
listening for events in here
it's listening for these item
listed item bought item,
cancelled events. So let's go
ahead and test this back in our
hardhat NFT marketplace Free
Code Camp window. We have some
scripts in here. One of them is
mint and list. So we went to New
NFT. And we listed on the
marketplace when we list an NF
T, well, our mirallas database
should hear that item listed
event and go ahead and stick it
into this item listed table that
it made. So for us to test this
out, let's open up our terminal
in our Hardhead NFT marketplace
repo. And we'll run Minton list
for our localhost before we
actually run it, just be sure
that our hard hat node is synced
up with our Morales server in
order for your database to
actually grab that event. Your
local hard hat node needs to be
connected. So we'll do yarn,
hard hat run scripts, mint and
list.js dash dash, network
localhost. Let's enter. Okay,
minting, approving listing
listed now if we flip back to
our database, after a quick
refresh, what do you know, we
see that there's an indeed an
item listed events in our
database, we can see information
about a tool we can see there's
a block hash, a timestamp, we
see the token ID that was
listed, we see the price of the
listing the transaction hash, we
see all this information about
our event. And now it's in this
database for us to query. So if
you have reached this point, you
have successfully set up an
indexer with the Morales
database. And you should be
super pumped because this is
really powerful. And now we're
getting advanced, we're starting
to do some advanced stuff. So if
you've made it this far, huge
congrats. This is already really
cool. Now, some other
troubleshooting help here that
I've run into many times myself,
let's say I've left this
project, and I've killed my
heart hit note, I'm going to
kill it right now. If I stopped,
my heart had node and I come
back to my Morales admin, I'm
going to view details dev chain
proxy server, I'm now
disconnected. And if I hit this
little refresh, I'm disconnected
of course, because I'm not
running my heart headnote
anymore. If I restart my node,
my note is now restarted. My
connects local dev chain command
is still running. If I re fresh
it, it'll now say connected,
which is great. However, if I go
back to my blockchain, or if I
go back to my hard hat, NFC
marketplace script, I run yarn,
hard hat script, mint and list
again, network localhost, I go
back to my database now, and I
do a refresh, we don't see that
item listed in here. So our
mirallas server is looking to
make sure that that the
blockchain we're working with is
the same one. So if we reset our
blockchain, like we did, right,
we canceled it and we reset it,
our database is gonna get really
confused. So what we have to do
is we have to hit reset local
chain, reset local chain, we
want to make sure that our new
local chain is running, and that
we're connected here. So we'll
hit reset local chain, and this
will tell them Ross, hey, we
reset the chain, it's okay,
please continue doing so. And
once we hit reset local chain,
we're not going to see that item
listed in here. However, if we
go back, and we rerun mint and
list network, local host with
this reset local chain. Now, if
we go back to our Morales
database, we hit refresh, we now
see that new one has gotten in
anytime you stopped your hard
hat note, anytime you reset your
hard hat node, the takeaway is
you're going to need to go to
View Details dev chain proxy
server and reset local chain.
Now you can do that
programmatically as well, we're
not going to go over how to
programmatically do that. But
that might be something you want
to add to your hard hat deploy.
The other thing to note is that
it didn't clear out our last
event, right, the last event.
And if I go one minute and list
again, after completes, we'll
have another event in here.
Okay, this is great. So all of
this is being said, the reason
we're doing all this in the
first place is so that in our
index.js we can start listening
for events. How do we show the
recent listen entity. So now we
have a database of listed
entities. So what we could do,
we could just query this item
listed table right and grab
everything in here. However, we
have an issue here, what happens
if someone buys an NFT, if
someone buys an NF T, the item
listed event will still be in
our database. But technically it
won't be on the marketplace
anymore. It'll be gone, it won't
be listed. So what can we do,
there's a number of
architectural choices we can
make to get around this problem
to solve this problem. But one
of the things we can do is
actually we can use mirallas
Cloud Functions. So Morales
cloud functions allow us to just
really add anything we want our
front end to do from the morale
server. And these are functions.
These are scripts that are going
to run on a morale server
whenever we want them to. So we
go to our server hit the little
drop down and we hit Cloud
Functions. Now this is where we
can write somewhere else stuff
to run on our server whenever we
want. And we are going to set up
our Cloud Functions in our IDE
by hitting this little drop done
to actually sync up our Visual
Studio code with our Cloud
Functions, we can just run this
command here, and it will add
whatever cloud functions we have
in some cloud folder to here. So
what we can do back in our VS
code, let's make a new folder,
new folder called Cloud
Functions. And in here, we'll
create a new file called Update,
active items.js. So in here, if
we were to write something like
console dot log, hi, we can
actually have this automatically
saved on a morale server. And
the way that we do this is by
running this command. Now, we
want to make it so that it's a
lot easier for us to run this
command than just always having
to run this massive thing. So
what we're going to do is we're
going to open up our package
json, and we're going to make
another Morales script here,
right below here, we're going to
make another Morales script,
we're gonna say Morales Morales
cloud, and we're going to have
it, run this command. So we're
going to copy this command here,
paste it into our package json.
So it's going to be Morales
admin CLI, watch cloud folder,
we don't need the Morales API
key, because it'll grab that
from our environment variables.
We don't need them rouse secret,
because it'll grab that from our
environment variables, we do
need the morale subdomain
autosave one. And then the
Morales cloud folder is going to
be that new Cloud Functions bid
that we made that slash cloud
functions, functions. Now, in a
new terminal, if I run yarn,
more Alice cloud, which is going
to be same as running this huge
function here, I hit enter,
it'll say compile, you know,
version, blah, blah, compiling,
blah, blah, changes uploaded
correctly. And if we go back to
our front end, we can see this
console dot log ky and our front
end being updated. And if we
continue to run this in our
update active items at Jas, we
could also write console dot
log, you'll save it. And if this
is still running, it'll
automatically upload it. And now
we can see if we do a little
refresh on our front end Cloud
Functions, we can see it's been
uploaded here. Now at this
point, if you have a ton of this
stuff running, you might see CPU
100 percent, you might see this little
thing pop up and the server
might start going a little bit
slower, we're starting to use a
lot of network activity here. So
I'm going to close my yarn
Morales cloud for now. And I'm
just going to upload it once
when I need to. Because we're
connected, we have it listening
to events, we're having it doing
more and more stuff here. And it
can start to put a lot of load
onto the server. So we're just
gonna go ahead and we're going
to cancel that out. And now the
CPU is a lot lower. But if we go
back to Cloud Functions, we can
see it's still in here. And
anytime we update our Cloud
Functions, it'll update our
server with those cloud
functions. And we'll just run
that darn morass cloud once
we're all done here. Anyways, so
right now we're trying to figure
out, Okay, we have item listed,
but if someone buys an item,
technically, it won't be listed
anymore. But our item listed
table will still have it listed.
So what we can do is we can
create a Cloud Function that
runs whenever we want. And like
I said, we can have these run
whenever we want. We can call
these whenever we want. But
we're going to create a Cloud
Function that only runs.
Whenever one of these events are
synced item listed item
cancelled or item bought, we're
going to create a new table
called active item, an active
item is going to say, okay,
anytime it's listed, it will be
active, but when it's bought or
cancelled will remove it from
the active item list. So we're
going to create a new table. So
let's go ahead and do that. We
started off with more Alice
thought. And then if you're IT
auditors that you don't need
this, we don't need to import
Morales here, because we're
going to upload it as a Cloud
Function. And our server already
just automatically injects
mirallas into our scripts. So
we're gonna say Morales dot
cloud, that after save, and
there's a whole bunch of stuff
you can do with your Morales
cloud. And again, you can find
these all in the documentation.
The after save keyword means
that anytime something gets
saved on a table that we
specify, we'll do something. And
it takes two parameters. So it
takes what table that we want to
do something after it's saved.
And we're gonna say item listed.
So we're saying anytime
something is saved to the item
listed table, we'll run some
async function.
And we'll put request in here.
Because anytime something gets
saved, it comes with a request.
So anytime an item listed
happens, we want to add it to
our active items list. And our
requests come with this is
flagged called confirmed. So
we'll say const confirmed
because every request, every
event actually gets triggered
twice. So once a transaction
goes through, it triggers a save
and then once again, once that
transaction is actually
confirmed, we actually only want
to update our active item when
the transaction is actually
confirmed. So we'll say const
confirmed equals request dot
object dot get confirmed.
Screening, get the confirmed
attribute from that request. And
then we're also going to make A
logger will say const logger
equals oralis dot Cloud dot get
logger. And you'll see why in a
second, we can actually write
logs to our Morales database
with this logs thing. So any
logs we can add into here, and
I'll show you that in a minute.
So console logger Morales dot
cloud, get logger. And then
we'll just do logger dot info.
Looking for confirmed x, and we
can actually test this right
now. Right, we can actually test
this right now. In our logs. We
should see looking for confirmed
TX Once an item listed and saved
now to test this out just to
test that our logger is actually
working. Let's run yarn, yarn
Ross cloud just update active
items to our to our morale
server changes uploaded
correctly. Okay, we'll kill it
now. And now in our where we
have our Minton, lists script.
Let's run Minton list. And we
should see on our server we
should get those logs. Now if we
go to our server, we do a little
refresh here. And if we look at
our logs now we can now see
looking for confirmed TX in our
server logs. Now in our logs.
Here we see we only see that
looking for confirmed TX once
and I just told you, it actually
triggers twice once when the
transaction is first sent. And
then once when the transaction
is confirmed, aka has block
confirmations. And additionally,
if we look in our database at
the item listed, and we scroll
all the way to the right, we can
see confirmed equals false. So
we only want to count this item
listed event interactive items
when confirmed is true. So what
we want to do actually is we
want to update our scripts to
add one block confirmation on
top of our local Hardhead
blockchain so that these can be
changed to confirmed now to get
around this. What I usually will
do in my mentalist script is
I'll add a new utility. So I'll
go to my utils, I'll do new
file, and I'll create a move
blocks.js. And this will be a
utility that I use to actually
move the blocks. So when we run
our own heart hat node, we
actually have complete control
over what we want our heart hat
node to do. So what we can do is
we can actually manually mine
nodes and actually move blocks
ahead so that Morales knows Oh,
okay, this transaction is
confirmed, right, because we're
mining the block with the
transaction. And that's it, and
Ross is just going to forever be
waiting for the next block. So
we want to add some
functionality to our scripts,
where we just mine a block after
it's done. Now, keep in mind
that if we mined like 1000
blocks or a ton of blocks really
quickly, Moorehouse might have a
hard time indexing that. So we
really want to just mined one at
a time and give me enough time
to index each block that we
mined. So we're actually going
to build a little script, we're
going to manually mine using
this EVM mine RPC method that
comes with our heart hat
blockchain. So we have this new
move blocks script. And let's go
ahead and make this. So instead
of this being our script, we're
going to have like a main
function at the bottom, we're
just gonna have this be a
utility that we're going to
import into other scripts. So
we're not going to need a main
function here, we're just going
to need to make this an async
function. And we'll call it move
blocks. And then we'll say
amount, which is going to be the
number of blocks, we want to
move, we'll also put a sleep
amount and default it to zero,
this sleep amount is going to be
an optional parameter. If we
want to move blocks and sleep
maybe a second between blocks to
resemble a real blockchain, we
can have that in here too. So we
can have it resemble a real
blockchain by sleeping every
time a block is moved or just
kind of waiting every time a
block has moved. So in our move
block scripts, we'll do console
dot log, moving blocks, dot that
dot, and we'll say for let index
equals zero, and we'll do a for
loop around the amount and call
that EVM. Mine in this for loop
index is less than amount index
plus plus a weight network. And
then we got to import network
oops, we got to import network
from hard hat here, await
network dot provider dot
request. And then we're going to
request the method e v, mime,
comma params are going to be
empty. And this is actually the
same way we can make raw calls
to our blockchain nodes. We
don't do a lot of this because
ethers abstract this under the
hood, but we're making a raw
call to EVM mine. Obviously, you
can't call EVM mine on a real
blockchain because you can't
just tell a blockchain node to
mine the next block. Since this
is our local hard hat node, we
can call the VM now we're gonna
say if sleep amount is greater
than zero, or just if sleep
mount, then we're also going to
have this script sleep or wait a
short duration. So up at the
top, we're actually going to
create a new function called
sleep, which is going to input a
time in milliseconds. And this
is going to return a new
promise, right? Because
remember, in order for us to
wait for some time we got to use
promises, which we've learned
before. And this promise is
going to take a function with
resolve as an input parameter.
And we're just going to say, set
timeout is going to be resolve,
comma, time in Ms. So the way we
can sleep in JavaScript is we
return a new promise. And we
just call this set timeout
function, which basically just
weights the time in
milliseconds. Now to actually
sleep. We'll say console dot
log, sleeping for sleep amount.
And then we'll do await, sleep,
sleep amount, and this is going
to be in milliseconds. So since
sleep returns a promise, we can
call it with await to say, okay,
wait for this sleep function to
finish. And the sleep function
is only going to finish when the
time in MS in time in
milliseconds finishes. So now we
have a function called move
blocks, which will actually
mined blocks on our local
blockchain, so that Morales can
get that block confirmation that
it's looking for now at the
bottom, we'll just do module dot
exports, move blocks, move
blocks, and then we'll also
export sleep as well, because
why not? Equals like that. Now,
what we can do back in our
Minton list, up at the top,
we'll say const, move blocks
equals require dot dot slash
utils slash move blocks. And
then we'll also import network
from ethers network. And the
down in our script. Just right
at the bottom, we'll just say if
network dot config, that chain
ID equals equals 31337 await,
move blocks, we'll say we'll
move to blocks and then we'll
also do sleep amount equals
1000. We'll wait one millisecond
between each block that we
mined. So sleep mount equals
1000, which is going to be one
millisecond. Now let's even just
comment all this out for a
second. We'll just run this
script with only this live.
Right we'll pull this up the
yarn hard hat, run scripts,
mentalist dash dash network,
local host, we'll just move the
blocks move back to our front
end, we'll refresh, we'll go
look at item listed. We'll
scroll all the way to the right,
and now we see confirmed is
true. And now if we were to look
in our logs, we would see that
logging item happened twice.
Alright, so Let's uncomment this
and continue. Now that we have
this now that we're learning
about logging, now that we're
doing all this stuff, we can say
If confirmed, we're going to do
some stuff. If confirmed, we're
going to create a table called
active item and add this to the
active item table. So we're
going to do a little logger dot
info bound item. And we'll
create a new table and a new
entry in this table. So we'll
say const active item equals
more Alice dot object dot extend
ACC active item. This we're
saying if active item exists,
great grab it if not create it.
So we're going to create this
active item table if it doesn't
exist, if it does exist, great,
grab it. And we're going to say
const active item equals new,
active item. So we're going to
create a new entry in this
active item table that we're
creating. And we'll say active
item dot set. And we can set any
of the columns we want for this
new table that we're creating.
So let's give it a marketplace
address column. So we'll say
market place address. And this
will come from the request dot
object dot get address all of
these requests from events come
with the address that they're
coming from, which for us is
going to be the marketplace
address, we'll do active item
that set and if T address which
these events saved come with all
the parameters of our event. So
we'll say request that object
dot get NFT address will get the
price will say active item dot
set price is going to be request
dot object dot get price will
get the token IDs will say
active item dot set token ID
request dot object dot get token
ID and then we'll get the seller
will say active item dot set
seller is going to be request
that object dot get seller. So
we're getting all of this
information from our event. And
this event update from Ross
automatically always comes with
the address that the event was
omitted from. So we're gonna
grab all that we're going to
create this active item table.
We're going to add all these
rows. We're going to add this
one row with all these columns
in it. Awesome. Now we'll just
do logger dot info just to do a
little print out. We'll say
adding address. We'll do a
little string interpolation
we'll say request dot object dot
get address period token ID with
request dot object dot get token
ID. And I need to close this off
here, better. And then outside
of the logger dot info, we'll
just say logger dot info,
saving. And then we just run
await active item dot save. And
now we have cloud function
that's going to create a new
entry in a new table called
active item anytime item listed
happens. So after item is called
the trigger for our cloud
function, and there are a whole
bunch of different triggers for
different Ross Cloud Functions.
If you go to the Morales docs,
we look for trigger, we can find
a list of all these different
triggers in here, like after
save for Save. After save,
before delete, after delete,
before save file, there's all
these different triggers to
trigger this cloud code. Now, if
we upload this new script to our
morale server with yarn morass,
cloud changes uploaded
correctly, okay, great, we'll
kill it. Let's go to our cloud
server, do a little refresh just
to make sure that it's not still
processing that update. Okay,
CPUs low enough. Okay, great.
Now in our database, we don't
see an active item table in
here. But if we go back to our
Hardhead script, and we call
mint and list, since now we have
a Cloud Function that says okay,
anytime an item listed event
happens, update that active item
table, we should see active item
update. So let's run this. And
remember for all of this, we
need to have our heart head node
running connected to Hardhat.
And if we reset our local chain,
we need to click that reset
local chain button. So we went
ahead, we ran this. Now if we go
back to our database, we give it
a little refresh. And right now
I actually don't see anything.
So if I go to my logs go to
info, I can see any errors or
issues in here. So it looks like
after save failed for item
listed for user bla bla bla,
looks like there is an issue
cannot read properties of
undefined reading extend. And
that's also in the info, I made
an issue. I didn't quite write
all my code, right. And if we go
back to our update active item,
I can see where I messed up. It
should be Morales dot object
with a capital O dot extent. So
what I'm going to do, then run
yarn morass cloud again, now
that I have this correct, we're
going to cancel that, we're
gonna run our mminton list
again, now that we've fixed our
script. And now that we've fixed
our script, go back to our
database, we'll give it a little
refresh, I can now see we have
an active item entry in
here. Now at this point, there
are going to be times when you
don't want to leave and go get a
coffee, right, or go to the
bathroom or go get some food.
And you're going to want to stop
your terminals from running. So
let's actually practice
restarting everything and re
getting into this local
development environment. Because
it can be a little weird and a
little tricky. So let's practice
this. So once again, let's come
over here. And what do we need
to do? Well, we're going to Ctrl
C, we're going to kill our
blockchain Ctrl C, we're going
to kill our connection to our
Morales server. And if we're
running a front end Ctrl C, that
too, now if we go to our server,
we go to view details. Dev chain
proxy server, if we hit status,
this reset button here will
still we will be disconnected
now. And now everything has been
disconnected. Now if we want to
restart everything, if we're on
our heart hat NFT marketplace
will run yarn Hardhead node, and
that will spin everything up
again, we'll run yarn Morales
sync to sync back with our
routes connection, we can go
back to our server will do view
details and we should be
connected now. Connected. Since
we restarted our local
blockchain, we now need to
remember to do reset local
chain, we'll go ahead and run
that. Great. If we want to
restart our front end, we can
restart our front end like so
now the thing is, our database
will still have even when we
refresh it even though we reset
the local blockchain, it'll
still have all this stuff in it.
Now these entries in here are
entries from a blockchain that
no longer exists. So what I
often will do is I'll click this
button up here, and we'll just
delete all rows in this class.
To confirm we do active item,
read the name of the table. And
let's do it for item listed too.
We'll select that edit, delete
all rows, item listed. Yes,
delete. We'll do a little
refresh. Now everything is
zeroed out here. Now we have an
empty database for these events
in our after save here. And now
that we've added that little
weight in our script, let's go
back to our hard hat NFT
marketplace, we'll run yarn, RT
hat, run scripts, mint and list
dot j s dash dash network, local
host. This will mint it approve
it listed and then we mined two
blocks to give Morales time to
index our event and then on a
morale server. We go ahead and
refresh we now see item listed
as one and active item is One
all at the same time. So that is
how we're going to make sure
that Morales always indexes
whenever we call a function,
we're just going to mind one
additional block to tell Morales
Hey, that transaction has indeed
been confirmed. So really
exciting. And we got to practice
closing and restarting and doing
all that good stuff, too. So now
this is fantastic. Now that we
have this additional
functionality to make it a lot
easier for someone else over
okay, awesome, we can check
active item. Well, we're not
quite done yet, right? Because
what if somebody buys an NFT, or
sells an entity we should have
active item be removed? Right,
right now there's one item
listed in one active item. But
if we buy an item, active item
will still show that that item
is active. So let's go ahead and
let's update our cloud function
to also say, okay, anytime an
item is bought, we remove that
item from being active. So let's
create another after save. Let's
first built this for canceling
the item. And then we'll build
one for buying the item. So to
make another after save to make
another trigger, we'll say
mirallas dot Cloud dot after
save, we'll say item cancelled.
And this will be an async
function that takes the request
as an input parameter again, and
we're going to do the same
thing. We're gonna say const
confirmed equals request that
object dot get confirmed, we'll
say const. Logger equals routes
dot Cloud dot get logger, like
so. And then we'll do logger.
Oops, lowercase L. And then
we'll do logger dot info,
marketplace, the little pipe
object and then just request dot
object. And then we'll do the
same thing. If confirmed. If
this transaction is confirmed
after one block, we're going to
remove it from active item. And
we're going to be using a query
to first find that active item
that's getting cancelled. And
you can learn more about basic
queries in the Morales
documentation here. So we're
going to get that table by
saying const active item equals
more outlets that object for the
capital O object dot extend
active item. And we're going to
create a new query. So we're
going to query our table before
we actually set or save
anything. So we're gonna say
const, query, query equals new
Morales dot query of active
item. So we're going to query
our Morales database to find an
active item that's in there,
that's going to match the
request here, so we can cancel
it. So we'll say query dot equal
to
marketplace address, comma
request that object dot get
address, we're looking for an
active item where the
marketplace address is going to
be the same as the address of
the item cancelled. We'll say
query dot equal to NF T address,
comma request dot object dot get
an F T address will say query
dot equal to token ID, comma
request dot object dot get token
ID. And that should be it right?
So let's look again at our
contract here. And what is the
item canceled give us it gives
us a seller NFC address and a
token ID seller and ft address
and a token ID. And we're
looking for NFT address and the
token ID, we don't need to look
for the seller, we just need to
look for these two. And then of
course, the marketplace address.
So great. So now that we have
those two, we can say logger dot
info, and then we'll just print
out marketplace type query. And
then we'll just print out this
query that we're running. And
then we can say const, cancelled
item equals await query dot
first, we're going to find the
first active item in the
database that has the same
marketplace address and a T
address and token ID that just
got cancelled. So we're going to
find that first cancelled item.
We'll do a little bit more
logger information, we'll say
logger dot info, marketplace,
pipe, cancelled item. And then
we'll just do some string
interpolation. And we'll print
out that canceled item.
Cancelled item and we'll say if
cancelled item. So if the query
doesn't find anything, it'll
return undefined. So we're
saying if cancelled item which
will return true if it found
something. So if cancelled item,
then we're gonna say logger dot
info. Deleting and then we'll do
request dot object dot get token
ID at address, request dot
object dot get address address
space since it was canceled, so
we're going to do a little print
little logging here. Take the
leading that thing since it was
canceled and then we're going to
run a wait canceled item dot
destroy and that's when we
remove it from the active item.
And then we'll just say else.
Logger dot info, no item found
with address, request dot object
dot get address, and token, Id
request dot object, dot get
token ID. So cool. So now we
have this after save here, it
looks like my terminal
automatically added this require
in here, which we don't want. So
I'm just gonna go ahead delete
that. We can upload this to our
Morales server by running yarn,
Morales cloud and great changes
uploaded correctly. And now to
test this test that this is
working, let's create a new
script in our hard hat NFT
marketplace called cancel item.
So we'll go to scripts right now
we have mentioned list, we'll do
new file, we'll call it cancel
dot Jas. We'll do cancel item,
Jas. And this will be a script.
So we're going to use that that
main thing here, but we're going
to call our function cancel. So
we'll do async function cancel,
and then at the top, we'll say
const token ID equals Now let's
go to our active item list. And
let's find a token ID that's in
here. Okay, token ID zero. And
so we'll use this as the token
ID that we want to delete. So
we'll use token ID zero. So in
our cancel item.js script, we'll
say const token ID equals zero
and let's cancel it. So we'll
say const NFT. Marketplace
equals await ethers dot get
contract. And yes, const ethers
equals require hardhat. And ft
marketplace will say const basic
NF t equals await ethers dot get
gets contract. Basic NF team do
const TX equals await NF T
marketplace dot cancel listing
basic NF T dot address token ID.
And we're going to call cancel
item should be cancelled listing
we call the cancel listing. So
cancelled listing Yep, like
that. And it takes the address
of the NFT and the token ID. So
the basic NF T dot address and
the token D Okay, great. And
then we'll do a weight TX dot
weight one. And then we'll do
console dot log NFT cancelled.
And then we'll say if network
dot config dot chain ID equals
equals 31337. We'll go ahead and
we'll do a wait move blocks to
two and then we'll say sleep.
Mount equals 1000. And then
we'll just say const. Move
blocks equals require dot dot
slash utils slash move blocks.
Okay, cool. That looks really
good. So let's go ahead and run
this yarn hardhat run scripts
cancel item.js dash dash
network, local host and ft
cancelled moving blocks
sleeping. Okay, great. Our node
is running. Awesome. We're
connected to our mirallas we've
uploaded our cloud function with
yarn Morales cloud. Now if we go
back to our database, do a
little refresh. Looks like I
have an issue here. I go to my
info it says after save failed
for item Cancel for user blah
blah, blah. Here's the login
information. Morales dot cloud
apt get latar is not a function.
Uh huh. Well, that makes a lot
of sense. Get water. Let's do
let's make this get logger.
Shall we get logger to let's re
upload them. Changes uploaded
correctly. And now I'm going to
have to manually go to active
item I'm gonna have to manually
delete this one will have a
delete this row. Yes, delete, do
a refresh. And the reason I have
to do that is because it's
already been saved. And we're
doing an after save. So because
I messed up. If you spelt that
right, you probably did, right.
But because I messed up, we're
gonna have to rebuild a new one.
And then delete that new one.
I'm going to run yarn, hard hat
run scripts, mint and list
network localhost. And we just
meant to add a new one. Let me
check the Morales database,
we'll do a refresh. I can see it
in here, I can see it an item
listed. It has a token ID of
one. So let's go ahead and
cancel that now. So I'm going to
change my token ID and cancel
item to one. And now we'll run
that script Barnhardt at run
scripts cancel item, network,
local host run this NFT
cancelled moving blocks. Now
we'll go to the front end, we'll
do a refresh. And we can see
it's been removed from active
item programmatically, which is
great. So this is where these
logs can be really helpful. Now
it can be a little scary to do
things wrong on purpose, but
learning how to use information
like the logging and learning
how to debug effectively is
going to make you a lot faster
of a coder because guess what,
you're not going to be perfect.
You're going to run into issues
understanding how to use The Log
Understanding how to read the
errors is going to make you much
faster developer. So now we have
something for cancelled item,
we're also going to need
something for what? Well, you
guessed it for buying the item.
So let's make another one of
these murales to cloud that
after save. And we're going to
be using most of this same exact
code for item bought that we use
for item cancelled, we probably
should turn it all into a
function. But for practice,
we're just going to go ahead and
do it one more time, we'll do
Morales dot cloud. And then my
VS code keeps sticking this in
for some reason. I'm going to
undo that Morales dot Cloud dot
after save. Item bot is the
event. There'll be an async
request little arrow function
here, say const confirmed equals
request that object dot get
confirmed will get whether this
transaction is confirmed. We'll
get the logger I'm just going to
copy paste so I get it right
this time. So I'm going to copy
and paste those two lines const
logger equals Morales dot Cloud
dot get logger logger dot info.
And we'll say If confirmed const
active item equals Morales dot
object dot extend active item
const query and for this query,
I'm actually just going to copy
these lines because this is
going to be exactly the same.
We're going to look for the NFT
address and the token ID and the
marketplace address. And if we
look in our NFT dot soul and up
to marketplace dot som alright
and bot event as the NFT
address. And the token ID which
is what we want to find are
listed and of team. So we'll run
that query. We'll do const bots
item equals await query dot
first, and we'll do exactly what
we did before. If bots item then
logger dot info, deleting
request dot object dot get
object ID await bought item dot
destroy logger dot info deleted
item with Open ID request dot
object dot get open ID at
address request dot object dot
get
address. And then if we don't
find it will say else. Logger
dot info, no item found with
address request that object dot
get address and token, Id
request that object dot get
token ID. Cool. So that looks
good. Let's go ahead and upload
this to the cloud. So do yarn
oralis Cloud changes uploaded
correctly. Let's go make sure it
looks good on our server. So
we'll give a morale server a
little refresh. Go to Cloud
Functions here. I can see the
item cancelled in here still.
And now I can see the item
bought after save perfect. Looks
like I'm at 100 percent capacity. So
we're gonna give it a second
just to cool down thinking give
it a little refresh and looks
like we're back down after our
cloud function has been
uploaded. Okay, cool. To test
out that this part is working.
Let's go ahead we'll write
another script here. Do new file
by item dot j s. And we'll do
the same thing right now. On our
database. We don't have any
active items. So we'll just run
real quick. We're on mint and
list. Mint a new one. We'll go
check our database we'll do a
little refresh. Looks like
active vitamins in here with a
token ID of two now. So we'll do
is we'll buy that token ID so
we'll say const ethers network
equals require arhats const move
blocks equals require dot slash
utils slash move blocks const
token ID equals to async
function by item const NFT
marketplace equals await ethers
dot get contract NF T
marketplace const basic NF t
equals await ethers dot get
contract basic NFT coms listing
equals await and ft market place
dot get listing basic NF T dot
address and the token ID will
say const price equals listing
that price that to string and
we'll say const Tx and this is
us going to actually buy it
equals await and ft marketplace
dot buy item basic n f t dot
address, token ID, comma. And
then the value of course is
going to be the price. Do await
TX dot wait one, console dot log
bots NF t. And then if network
dot config dot chain ID equals
31337, then await move blocks to
comma, sleep amount equals 1000.
And then this is a script of
course, so we're going to use
the same stuff we're using for
cancel. But instead of
cancelled, it's going to be
called by item. So we have the
item inactive item here, we run
yarn, art hat run scripts by
item.js Dash network, localhost.
Now we can test buying this
item. Okay, Bob, the NFT looping
blocks, we'll do a little
refresh on our database, and
boom, we can see the active item
is gone. And we can see, the
item has now been bought.
Awesome. We're almost done
keeping our active item, just a
table of active items. But
there's one more thing we should
do. We're not going to test this
here. But if you want to test
it, we can we actually in our
NFT marketplace, go to
marketplace dot Sol, we actually
have an update listing function
as well, that also admits an
item listed. So we also want to
check to see if item listed is
coming from update listening. So
back in our item listed Cloud
Function, before we actually
start saving stuff, we want to
check to see if it already
exists. So we're gonna say so
we'll say const query equals new
mirallas dot query. And sorry, I
keep sticking the sin of active
item. And we're going to do
exactly what we've been doing.
We're gonna say query dot equal
to NFT. Address, we're gonna
look for the NFT address request
dot object dot get and ft
address, query dot equal to
token ID, request that object
dot get token ID, query dot
equal to marketplace, address,
comma request dot object dot get
address query dot equal to
seller requests dot object dot
get seller will say const
already listed item equals await
query dot first. And then we'll
say if this item has already
been listed. Then we'll go ahead
and say logger dot info.
Deleting already listed request
dot object dot get object ID.
And we'll do a weight already
listed item dot destroy. And
then do logger dot info, deleted
item with token ID request dot
object dot get token ID at
address request dot object dot
get address since it's already
been listed, if the object has
already been listed, we know
that it's coming from this
update listing function. So
we're going to delete it first,
and then we'll resave it with
its new price. So and let's just
go ahead, and let's upload this
to the cloud yarn Morales cloud.
upload this to our server
changes uploaded correctly.
Let's go check our server, give
it a little refresh. We'll go
check Cloud Functions. And it
looks like our item listed query
for deleting is now in here. But
with all that, we now have a way
to constantly have this active
item table only be the items
that are actively on our
marketplace without having to
spend any additional gas in our
application. And this is going
to be way better for user
experience because they're not
going to have to pay extra gas
to keep all these entities and
maybe an array or some more data
structures. If you've made it
this far. This is easily one of
the hardest parts of this
course, because we're working
with a ton of technologies.
We're working with a smart
contract, we're working with
Cloud Functions, we're working
with a back end database. Now if
you've made it this far, you
should be incredibly incredibly
proud. So now let's just go
ahead, let's mint and list one
more NFT. So we'll do we'll run
yarn heart at run scripts, mint
and list network local hosts
will meant it will list it or
sleeping. Let's go check our
database. We'll do a refresh. We
see the active item in here. And
now let's learn how to call all
of the objects in In our active
item database here, let's do it.
And remember, if you ever reset
your local blockchain, you're
gonna have to come in here and
delete all the rows in the
support tables.
With all that being said, it's
time to finally come back to our
front end, and come back to our
index dot J. S and answer this
question. How do we show the
recently listed NF Ts, we only
want to show the active NF t's
on the marketplace. And now we
have a system for getting only
the active ones, only the ones
that are currently on the
market, because we're indexing
these events. Now, I'm going to
delete all these comments here.
And let's do this. So what we're
going to do is we're going to do
this thing called use Morales
query. So if we go to the React
Morales docks, there is a hook
called use Morales query. And
this allows us to fetch and make
queries to our database in a
React context. Back in here,
we're going to say, import, use
Morales query from react
mirallas. Now, if you look in
the docs here, use mouse query
returns data error is loading.
And this will automatically run
this query the instant our index
pops up. So to get the data from
the query to get all of our
active items from our database,
we'll say const data, and we'll
rename data to listed and fts.
And then we'll also check to see
if this query is still fetching.
So we'll say is fetching and
then we'll rename that to
fetching listed NF t is equals
use Morales query. And inside
here, this takes two input
parameters, it takes the table
name to do the search on and
then it also takes a function or
the query. So the table name
that we're going to be looking
for is going to be active item.
And then the function for the
query is going to be we're going
to say query dot, we'll limit it
just to 10. So we'll say only
the first 10, we'll do it in dot
descending order, based off the
token ID. And then if we wanted
to do different pages, we could
do this thing called dot skip
with page numbers, we're not
going to do page numbers here.
So we're just going to leave it
like this for now. And that's
it. So we're saying, okay,
great, grab from our database on
the active item table, grab just
the first 10 in descending order
of the token ID. Now it's going
to save the result of this to
this listed NF TS section. Now
to see if this is working. Let's
just do a little console dot log
listed NF t's just to see what
this using Ross query actually
returns for us. And now we have
our local blockchain Node
running, we have our connection
to our Morales server, and we
have our front end running. So
let's go to our front end, we'll
do a little refresh here, we'll
right click and hit Inspect,
we'll go to the console. And we
see we have this array being
spit out here. Now the first
time it console dot logs, it's
empty. This is because when it
initially loads listed out of
T's hasn't returned yet. And
it's so it's actually just going
to be an empty array. But when
it finishes loading, we're going
to get an array of size one, we
get an array of size one,
because active item only has one
enter right now. So we get this
array of size one, and we can
see it index zero, we have class
name active item, we have the
item ID, we have all these
attributes, which are going to
be created at the marketplace
address. And if the address the
price, the seller and the token
ID this is exactly what we see
in our database here. So
Perfect. That's exactly what we
want to be able to show these NF
t's on the front end. So how do
we actually show this NFT and
list this NF T. For people who
aren't developers and aren't
going to go into the console dot
log? Well, what we're going to
be doing is in this return here,
we'll put some parentheses
around this. First, we should
check to see if we are fetching
those listed NF T's. So we'll do
some JavaScript stuff. And we'll
say fetching listed NF T's and
we'll do a ternary operator. So
we're gonna say if we are
fetching those NF T's, let's add
like a little div div that just
says loading that that done,
we'll put a little colon here.
And if we're not fetching, we'll
do we'll say listed NF TS dot
map. So dot map basically loops
through and does some function
on all of the listed entities in
the function we're going to want
ours to do. And it's going to
take each NF t as input
parameters. So we say we're
going to basically loop through
each NF T. And we're going to
say, console dot log and F T dot
attribute attributes with an S.
And then inside of these inside
of this attributes are the
different pieces that we want.
So we're going to get those
pieces we'll say const we want
to show the price. The NFT
address, the token ID in the
marketplace address, which of
course is just gonna be this
one, and then the seller, that's
all this information that we're
going to want to show on the
front end will say that equals
NF T dot attributes. So we're
going to pull these out, and we
can see price seller token ID,
etc. We're going to pull those
out of NF T dot attributes. And
we can show those by in this
function here, we'll say return.
And then we'll return some HTML,
we'll do like div div. And then
we can say like price, price,
price,
period, and f t address and ft
address, token ID, token ID
seller, then added this for some
reason. So I'm going to delete
that add $1 signs before all
these for some reason, delete
those, save. Now if I go to the
front end, I can now see
information about our NFT from
our database is listed here.
That's fantastic. We see the
price we see the address, we see
the token ID we see the seller.
Now if we go back to our NFT
marketplace, our little our
little hard hat MC marketplace,
let's mint another one. Yarn
hard hat run scripts mentalist
Dash network localhost, we're
going to run that it's going to
mint one more. If we go back to
our Morales database, we do a
little refresh on that active
item table, we now have a new
item in here. So if we go back
to our front end, we give this a
little refresh. And boom, now we
have two items in here. So this
is awesome, we now have a way to
actually show the most recently
listed NF t's on our
marketplace, plus ah.
Now, of course, you might be
saying to yourself, hey,
Patrick, that's cool and all.
But that looks really ugly. And
I would agree with you. But 100 percent
agree with you. So we should
come up with a component to show
our listed entities that looks a
lot nicer. So when instead of
returning and just printing out
the raw information, we probably
want to show the image, right,
we want to show the image, we
want to make everything look a
lot nicer. So we're going to
create a new component that
we're going to return in here to
format all of our NF T's
appropriately. So we're gonna go
to components, we'll do new
file, and we're going to call NF
T box dot j s. And this is where
we're going to grab all the
information on how to show what
our NFT actually looks like. So
let's get started working on our
entity box, we're gonna set this
up, the way we've been setting
all these up would do export
default function, and ft box.
Now something that's a little
bit different for this one,
though, is that in our index, we
have all this information. So
we're gonna need to pass all
these variables to our NFT Box
component. So to do that, we'll
add them as input parameters for
our component here. So we'll say
price, and if the address, token
ID, marketplace, address, and
seller. So right now on our
front end, we just have a whole
bunch of text, and we even have
this gross warning, we're gonna
get rid of that tip. And as we
know, tokens have their token
URI, which points to an image
URI or an image URL of what the
actual token looks like. So what
we're going to want to do is
we're going to want to call that
token URI, and then call the
image URI to show the image. So
we're going to actually have to
wait those two API requests to
get the actual image. And we're
going to save that image as a
state variable on this component
here. So as you already know,
we're going to work with use
state to keep track of that
image URI. So we'll do import,
use state from react like this.
And in here, we'll say const,
image, Uri, comma set image, URI
equals use state. And we'll
start it off as a blank string.
Now let's create a function,
we're going to call it update UI
to update our UI and grab this
token URI and the image URI. So
we'll create an async function
called Update UI. And in order
to get the image first, we're
gonna need to get the token URI,
and then using the image ag from
the token URI gets the image. So
first thing we're gonna have to
do is get the token URI. So we
know how to do this with use web
three contract. So we'll do
import, use web three contract
from react Morales. And as we
know, use web through contracts
is going to need some
parameters. So we'll say const
run contract function, get token
URI, equals, use web through
contract. First, we need the ABI
of the NFT because we're gonna
need to call token URI. So to
get the ABI we're gonna need to
once again update our front end.
So let's comment this part out.
We'll go back to our hard hat
piece. And let's look in our
deploy scripts. We have this
update front end right now. All
this is doing is updating calm
object addresses. Well, that's
good. We're also going to want
to add API's to our front end as
well. So let's create another
function in here called Update
API. And we'll pass the API's as
well. So we'll do async function
update API. And we'll give it
both the basic NFT API and the
NFT marketplace API, because
we're going to need both of
them. So we'll say const NF T,
marketplace equals await ethers
dot get contract. And f t
marketplace, we're going to
write the ABI to the front end
API location, we have the front
end contracts file. So let's
also do a const. Front and ABI
location equals, and we'll do
dot dot slash next, Jas, and if
T marketplace dash FCC slash
constants, and instead of
actually just giving the file
name, we can just give it the
front end API location. And then
we'll actually have it generate
that file for us because we're
just going to overwrite the ABI
file anytime we work with it. So
now that we have the
marketplace, we'll just do Fs
dot right file sync, and we'll
do front and ABI location, and
ft marketplace, dot JSON. And ft
marketplace, dot interface that
format ethers dot utils dot
format types dot JSON. So we're
also going to want to do that
for the basic NF t. So we'll say
const basic NF t equals await
ethers dot get contract basic NF
T Fs dot right? file sync, it's
going to be that exact same
place right here. Except for
it's going to be a different
location, it's going to be basic
NFT dot JSON. And of course,
we're gonna do a comma basic NF
T, that interface dot format
ethers dot utils, dot format,
types dot JSON, you can find
this NFT marketplace that
interface in the Hardhead
documentation. And you can find
this in the ethers
documentation. So now we have
this update ABI function. Let's
also add this to our module that
exports so we'll do a weight up
the ABI like that.
There's a hyphen here that
shouldn't be here. And we'll run
just this part of our hardhat
front end, run yarn, hard hat,
deploy dash, dash dash tags, the
tag here is front end, front
end. And now it's had nothing to
compile updating front end, it's
done. So if we go back to our
front end, now, we go to our
constants, we now see two
objects in here, which are going
to be API's, the basic NFT, and
the NFT. Marketplace. Awesome.
So now that we have that, we can
import those into our front end.
So we can say import, and if T
marketplace, abi from dot dot
slash constants slash NF T,
marketplace dot JSON. And we can
also get the NF T API. So we'll
do import NF T, abi from that
the slash constants slash basic
NF T dot JSON. Now in our run
contract function, our token URI
function is part of the NFT API.
So the API will be the NFT, abi,
the contract address
is going to be the address of
the NFT, which we're passing in
as a parameter. So we'll pass an
NF T address, the function name
is going to be token URI, and
the params are going to be the
token ID, which is getting
passed as an input parameter to
this function to this component.
Right. And we can double check.
We're good to our basic NF T dot
soul, right? We scroll down, we
have this token URI that we're
overriding. And this is the
function we want to call takes
the token ID. So this the
the token ID. Okay, great. So in
our update UI, first, we'll say
const, token URI equals await
token URI. Now let's do a little
console dot log token your eye,
just to see what this returns to
make sure that update UI is
called, we'll add it to a use
effect, we'll say use effect.
And this takes an input
parameter of a function to do,
we'll just say Update UI. And
then we'll only have this run
anytime is web three enabled
changes. So we want to run
update UI, but we want it to be
dependent on is web three
enabled. And then we'll say if
it's web three enabled, then
update UI. So we need to add use
effect as well. So we're using
use state, we'll do comma, use
effect. And now we should at
least be reading our token URI
off the blockchain. We're not
going to set the image yet,
right, because we're going to
get the image URI from the token
neuron. Let's add this NFT box
to our index to see if it's
working well so far back in our
index Next, up at the top, we
will import NF T box from dot
dot slash components slash NF T
box. And down here, while we're
returning this will add our NF T
box component will make sure to
pass in all the parameters it
takes. So the price is going to
equal that JavaScript price. And
ft address is going to equal the
JavaScript entity address. The
token ID is going to equal the
token ID, marketplace address is
going to be marketplace address
seller is going to be the
seller. And you saw that warning
where it's saying, hey, all the
components need to all the
things in the mapping need to
have their unique key. So we'll
say key, we'll give these all a
key as well. We'll say key
equals this, we'll do some
string interpolation, we'll just
say the NFT address, combined
with the token ID can be the
key. So if we save that, go back
to our front end here, do a
little refresh marketplace
address is not defined market
place address. So let's make
sure we spell things right,
let's go back to the front end,
we'll give it a refresh is what
three enabled is not defined.
Oops, excuse me in the NFT box,
we need to grab that from us
Morales, so we'll import use
Morales. And in our ponents here
we'll say const is web three
enabled equals use Morales.
We'll save that. And one thing I
noticed actually is this needs
to be wrapped in squigglies.
Sorry, I forgot to do that. Our
component actually just takes a
props, props input parameter.
And we would need to do like
props that token ID to get token
ID. But instead, we just extract
it out by doing putting the
little squiggly brackets here.
So put the squiggly brackets
there. Great, we'll do a little
console dot log token, your eye,
or index.js has everything
updated. Here. Let's do a little
save. And we can even say if is
web three enabled up the UI.
Like that we'll save we'll go to
the front end, we'll do a little
refresh. We'll see if
everything's working as
expected. And as long as we're
on that hard had localhost and
our meta mask. And again, you
can ignore this error, this
warning that's up here for now.
And if you click this, and you
have your IPFS and brave or your
IPFS companion, we can now see
we're getting our token URI,
which is perfect. The piece that
we want now is this image bid.
And for this one that I'm using
it is an HTTPS, which
technically isn't decentralized,
right, we would need it to come
from instead of HTTPS, we would
need to come from IPFS colon
slash slash but but actually
having it as HTTPS ipfs.io. For
now was good, we'll explain why
in just a second. Now that we
are getting the token URI, we
can call this URL, and we can
get back the image that we want
to actually show on the front
end. So in here, we'll do a
little console dot log, the
token, URI is string
interpolation, like this, and
then we'll say if token URI,
we're going to need to now grab
this token URI, and get the
image from it. And this is where
we're going to get a little bit
funky. And we're going to cheat
a little bit. Now for our
application, not everybody is
going to have IPFS companion,
not every browser is IPFS
compatible. So we're gonna have
to actually cheat a little bit
here, we're actually going to
change the token Uriah from its
IPFS edition to an H HTTPS
edition. And this is known as
using an IPFS gateway, which is
a server that will return IPFS
files from a normal URL. So
we're going to use an IPFS
gateway, which we can just make
regular HTTPS calls to, and it
will return those IPFS files. So
technically, are we making the
centralized doing this? Yes. And
is that ideal? No. However,
until the world adopt IPFS, and
until the world adopts the
standards, it's kind of what we
have to do right now. Because
otherwise, the front end will
just show up as blank to them.
And we can't have that we don't
want that. So we're gonna say