const request URL equals token
URI dot replace IPFS, slash
slash with HTTP s, HTTPS.
slash slash ipfs.io/ipfs/so.
We're saying, if you have a
token URI that starts with IPFS,
that's great. But we're going to
switch it to using an IPFS
gateway. It's really use the
IPFS gateway provided by the
team that builds IPFS. So pretty
reliable gateway is is kind of a
cop out. Yes. Are our files
still on? IPFS? Yes. So it's not
the end of the world. But this
is just going to make calling
these API's a lot easier for us.
And we're going to say const
token URI. Response equals
await. And this is going to be a
little weird. We're going to do
two awaits. await a weight fetch
request, URL dot JSON. So fetch
is a keyword you can use in
JavaScript to fetch or get a URL
fetch keyword is essentially
doing the same thing as pasting
this into the browser, like so.
And getting this JSON response.
So we await to get the response.
And then we await to convert the
response to JSON. And that's how
we get the toggle response. So
we now have this object in our
JavaScript, which is perfect
because this object has this
image attribute that we want. So
we're gonna do the same thing we
did here, we're gonna use the
IPFS gateway, this one's already
using HTTPS that ipfs.io. But if
it wasn't, we would still want
to convert it. So now we're
gonna say const. Image URI
equals token you are i response
dot image. So we're gonna get
the image tag of this response
here. And then we're going to
say const. Image URI URL, is
going to equal to, and we're
gonna do the exact same thing
that we did up here, we're going
to use the gateway image URI dot
replace IPFS, colon slash slash
with HTTPS ipfs.io/ipfs. And
now, and that's how we get this
URL right here. And so we can
finally do set image URI, to
that image URL. And now we have
our image URI is going to be
that image right here. Now, is
this a little bit wonky? Yes.
Are there better ways that we
can do this? Yes, there's
actually a number of better ways
that we could do some of this,
we could actually, since we're
using Morales, we could render
image on our server and just
call our server, what else could
we do well, or test nets and
maintenance routes actually
comes with a bunch of hooks like
us NFT balance that will show us
an F TS show us how many NF T's
shows all this information about
NF T's but it only works on test
nets and main net, we'd have the
world adopt IPFS. So we don't
have to do this wrapping.
Unfortunately, it doesn't yet so
such as life. But now that we're
setting the image, alright, we
have this image URI, we have
what this actually looks like,
we're going to have this and if
we click on this, we use this in
our browser, it returns this
dog. So now we have the image
URI in our website, we can
finally use it to show what this
is going to look like. So
finally, we can create a return
in here. So down below, we'll do
return to a little div. And then
we'll do another div just
because I want to. And we can do
some JavaScript, we can say if
if that image array exists,
we'll do some stuff. Otherwise,
we'll do some other stuff. So if
it doesn't exist, maybe we'll do
a div for now. div that just
says loading dot the dot. And if
it does exist, for now, we'll
just say, just do a little div,
close the div. And we'll just
say found it. Now if we go back
to our front end, let's see if
we're good here.
Uh huh. If I do a refresh, we
see found it for both of these
NF T's. Okay, cool. So how do we
actually show these NF T's, we
finally have the URL that we can
use to show the NF T's. But we
want to actually use them next.
Jas actually comes with a
component called the image
component that we can use to
render images really easily just
by using a URI. Now, because
we're going to use this image
tag, and because it does some
optimizations on the back end,
that means that this website
won't be able to be deployed to
a static to a static site, like
IPFS. Because now our website
requires a server technically,
requires a server just because
we have Morales. So that might
be another reason, we might not
want to, since we're using this
image tag, we can't deploy this
statically to something like
IPFS is we're going to up at the
top, we're going to import image
from next slash image. And we're
gonna down here we're going to
say, instead of founded, we're
gonna go Image, we're gonna
close it off here, too, we're
gonna give a loader of just a
blank function that just gives
us the image URI. Don't worry
too much about loader. For now,
we're gonna say the source of
the image is going to be the
image URI. And then we'll give
it a height of maybe 200. And
then we'll give it a width of
also maybe 200. And if we did
this right, after we save, we
should see the image on our UI.
So we'll go back to our website,
and oh, my goodness, we can see
the dogs holy cow. This is
getting really exciting. We can
see the puppies, we can see the
images, we're definitely doing
something right here, which is
really exciting. Now I know I
said this before that this isn't
a CSS. This isn't a formatting
tutorial, because that's
definitely not my expertise.
However, let's make this look a
little bit nicer. And we're
going to use once again, the web
three UI kit, because the web
three UI kit has a whole bunch
of tools that are really, really
helpful for us to use. So if we
go to the web three UI kit, we
can go to that live storybook
Another interactive bit, and we
can scroll down to the section
that has called card. Or we can
make these little clickable
cards and we can display some
information about our nfts. So
let's go ahead and at the top,
we'll do import import card from
web three UI kit. And now
instead of just showing the
image, we'll wrap the image in a
card like this. We'll save that.
Now back on our front end, give
it a little refresh. Now we've
got this kind of clickable
section that looks a little bit
nicer. We'll even label it. And
we can even label it with a
title and description. Now we
can grab the title and the
description from the token URI
response. So up at the top,
let's go ahead, let's grab the
title and the description of the
token UI as a state variable. So
we'll say const, token name, set
token name, equals use state,
start off as blank, the const
token description, that token
description, equals use state.
Start off as blank to download,
we do this update UI bit, we'll
call set token name. So we'll
say name is token, your response
dot name, we'll say set token
description, which will be
token, your response dot
description. And then we'll use
those descriptions and title in
the cart. So we'll say title
equals token name, description
equals token description. Save
that. We'll look at our front
end here. Give it a little
refresh. Oh, and now we have the
name of the NFT. And its
description on our front end.
Okay, cool. Let's keep going.
What else do we want on this?
Well, we probably want who it's
owned by. So we'll put a little
div inside the card, say div,
maybe we'll even put the token
ID we'll do a little number.
With the token ID.
We'll do another little div, and
then we'll make this italic.
We'll say class name equals
italic. And then text is going
to be small. And we'll say owned
by, and this is where we can get
the seller that we're passing in
as an input parameter. And then
maybe underneath the image, we
want to put the price. We'll do
a little div here. And then
we'll say price like this.
However, we're probably don't
want it in way we want it in
human readable units. So we'll
import ethers, we'll say import
ethers from ethers. And then
instead of just showing the
price, we'll do a little, little
JavaScript and here we'll do
ethers dot utils dot format,
units, price, price and ether.
And then we'll do space eath.
And then we'll make this be
class name equals font bold, so
we can read how much it's listed
for on our marketplace. Let's go
back a high we can now see, this
is token ID number four. We can
see who it's owned by we'd see
the price of it and then more
information about the dog. Yay.
Now let's format all this stuff
in here a little bit nicer. So
let's wrap everything in a div
in one more div. And that will
say class name is going to be
flex. And this is going to help
format everything, we'll put
everything in a column items and
get to. And now if we look back
there, kind of like in a column
now, wrapping one more div, give
them some padding, last name
equals P to say a little bit
padding has been added. Okay,
nice. And then we'll go back to
our index, and we'll add some
formatting to our index here. So
our main one, we're going to
remove styles dot container,
we're just gonna say container.
MX auto, we're going to make an
h1 in here, class name, equals,
I form E X for font bold text to
XML. This is we're just gonna
say recently listed, then we're
going to do another div. Class,
name equals flex, flex wrap.
We're going to end this div
around our JavaScript here. And
let's look at our UI. And let's
see what that does. Okay, cool.
Let's go back to our index.
Let's remove all this stuff.
Since now we're adding that to
the card. Let's save. Now it's
looking a lot better, we finally
able to start listening our NF
Ts and then have them show up on
our marketplace like we see
here. Fantastic. Okay, if we go
to the readme homepage show
recently listen to empties. Oh,
my goodness, this is a check
we're done here. Now, and I know
what seemed like a lot of work,
but a lot of it was setting up
that morale server correctly.
And because we have our own back
end, now, we have some back end
services that we needed to
configure. But now that
everything's set up, the rest of
this is going to be easy St. Now
we are only going to want this
to show if we're connected to
web three. Right? Now, if we
click this, this still shows up.
So we're going to have to update
this a little bit. And in our
index.js, we're now we're
checking to see fetching.
Listen, NF T's right before
that, right? Before we do that
we actually want to see is web
three enabled. And this is going
to be a little bit of nested
tertiary operations. If web
three is enabled, then we're
going to do all this fetching,
listed NF T's stuff here. We're
gonna do everything in here. So
if it's not enabled, let's do
like a little div that says web
three, currently not enabled.
And of course, we're going to
need to grab is web three
enabled. So we're going to say,
for the top we'll do const is
what three enabled equals use
oralis as we've been doing, and
we're going to grab use Morales
from react Morales, we'll save
that go back to our front end,
give it a little refresh. If
we're connected, we'll see the
marketplace. If we disconnect,
we see web three currently not
enabled, which is what we want.
Perfect. So what is next in our
readme. If you only NFT, you can
update the listing. Let's first
let's figure out if somebody
actually is the owner of these
entities. Let's make it really
easy for the people on this
website. Well, first we can get
the person's Metamask by
grabbing the account from us
mouse, so we'll do a comma
account. So then we can easily
just do const is owned by user
equals seller equals equals
equals account. So the seller
we're getting from the contract,
the account we're getting from
whoever's connected here, if the
seller equals the account, there
is no seller equals equals
equals undefined. We'll just say
they're owned by you. And now
instead of saying owned by
seller, we can say const,
formatted seller address equals,
and we'll do the ternary
operator will say if it's on by
you, then we'll just say you
instead of seller. Otherwise,
we'll say seller. Now we'll say
owned by formatted seller
address like this. So if we go
back to our front end, we do a
little refresh. depending on
who's connected, you might see
owned by blah, blah, blah. Now
if I go to my Metamask, let me
go ahead and switch account to
account three, let's go ahead
and connect our account three,
we now see owned by you instead.
Right, and we can even switch
again, we'll switch accounts
again, we'll switch to account
one, we now see owned by blah,
blah, blah, like so since when
we switch back and forth, the
diameters of this actually
change which is really annoying.
So maybe we want to go one step
further. And we want to truncate
this seller address make it a
little bit smaller. So we want
to make a seller a little bit
smaller. So let's create a new
function. And we can create this
outside of the export default
function because this is going
to be a function that doesn't
depend on anything inside our
app. It's just going to be kind
of a raw function. So we're
going to create we'll call it
const truncate string, and this
is going to be a function that
takes a full string, and a
string length as parameters. And
we're just going to pass the
seller address and how long we
want to make this string. So
this is going to be an arrow
function we're going to do here,
and we're gonna say, if all
string dot length is less than
or equal to str Lang, return
full str. Otherwise, we'll say
concept ra torx equals three
little dots. And we'll say,
Let's separate Tor length equals
Sep. Ra Tor dot length. To make
con separator length, we'll say
const chars to show is going to
be the the string length minus
the separator length, we'll say
const. Front chars or front
characters is going to equal
math dot ceiling chars to show
divided by two const back chars
is going to equal math dot
floor, chars to show divided by
two. And if you don't understand
this math here, don't worry
about it. And then we're gonna
say return full string
substring of zero to front chars
plus the SEP IRA tour plus full
STR dot substring. of full STR
dot length, minus back chars.
And now what we can do is we can
grab this truncate STR this
truncate string and for is
formatted seller will say if
it's you will still do you but
otherwise we'll do truncate
string of seller or blank if
there's no seller, and we'll
have it be size 15. And now if
we save that, go back to our
front end, if it's owned by you,
it's still gonna say on by you.
But if we switch accounts, and
now says owned by, you know,
blah, blah, blah, dot the dot
blah, blah, blah with a
truncated address. And then
these sizes don't actually
change, which is a lot nicer
than them getting bigger and
smaller. So awesome. So now we
have this formatted even better.
Okay, now what do we want to do?
Well, now that we know who owns
the NFT, NF T, and it's
formatted pretty nicely, we need
to figure out a way to update
the listing. So what we want to
do is, once again, if it's owned
by us, and we can switch back to
the account, it's owned by if
it's owned by us, when we click
on it, we want to be able to
update the listing on the
marketplace. So to do this,
we're going to create a new
component called Update listing
ngModel. So we're gonna create a
new component, new file, update,
listing ngmodel.js. A ngModel is
something that like pops up. So
for example,
this little pop up here is known
as a modal. And this is what we
want to build. If it's owned by
us, when we click this, we want
it to pop up this modal thing.
So to get started, we'll do the
same thing we've been doing for
all of our components here,
we'll do export default,
function, update, listing
ngModel, like so. And we're
probably going to want to pass
it these parameters from the
entity box, probably gonna want
to pass these parameters. So the
ngModel knows what function it
needs to call in our NFT
marketplace. The way we're going
to update listing is we're going
to call this update listing
function where we need the
address token ID and then some
new price. So we're going to at
least need those. So we're going
to need the NFT address, and at
least the token ID to make this
little pop up, we're not going
to code it ourselves, we're
going to once again, use the web
three UI kit, web three UI Kit
has this nice pop up section,
where it has some code to work
with a modal. So we're going to
import that will do import
ngModel from web three UI kit,
like so here's what it looks
like we have modal and then we
have all this stuff on working
with the modal. So we'll do our
return, do a little modal, like
this. One of the key things in a
ngModel is whether or not it
should be visible. So it has an
is visible tag, which we're
actually gonna have to grab,
we're actually gonna have to
grab from the empty box. So
we're going to pass a little is
visible here as well, in our NFT
box, we need to tell our ngModel
when it's visible. So we'll
we'll make that code in a little
bit. Right now, it'll just be
blank. And inside of our
ngModel, we're going to want to
give an input field for how to
update it. So I know we've done
some regular inputs before,
since we've been working with
web through UI kit, let's just
use the input that it has as
well. So we'll do a little comma
input here. And inside of the
ngModel we'll create a new
input. So on our input field,
we'll give this a label which is
going to be update listing price
in L one currency. And we'll
just do eath. For now we'll just
hard coded as eath name will be
new listing price, and type is
going to equal a number we'll do
Little backslash here, oops,
we'll do a little backslash
instead of like that. So cool.
So when this modal pops up, it's
gonna have this input in here.
And we can actually test to see
if this is working. We can
import this into our NFT box,
we'll do import, update, listing
ngModel. From that slash,
update, listing ngModel oops,
and sorry, this doesn't need
parentheses, and at the top of
our return here, right before
our card will add it in. So
we'll just add another div
though. So that these two can be
in the same react. But we'll add
another div, we'll say Update
listing ngModel, like so with a
little backslash here. And right
now we just have to pass is
visible. And then for now, we're
just going to say true. So now
with this listing ngModel on our
front end, we do a little
refresh. And we get this little
box like this update listing
price and one currency. And we
have to close two of them.
Because technically we right now
both modalities are true, right.
So if we do a refresh, we get
this little input pop up this
little modal and we close it
twice, because we have two NF
T's if you have a ton of NF T's
here, you will have to close a
ton of those. So we change it to
false, we go back to the front
end, we do a little refresh, and
boom, now it's false. So true,
save, run, and it's there.
Gross, delete, delete, false,
save front end, it's not there
anymore. Okay, cool. So we're
gonna have to tell this ngModel
only to pop up when somebody
clicks this and have tea that
they own. So to actually toggle
this and actually make this
work, we're going to update our
card. So whenever we click our
card, we're going to create a
function called handle card
click that handle card click is
going to update a variable for
whether or not we should show
this ngModel. So we're going to
do is we're gonna say on click
of the card, aka, once we click
our dog, we're going to call
some function. So we're gonna
say on click, equals handle
card, click, animal card, click,
and we're going to make this a
function, we're gonna say const,
handle card click equals a
function, we'll use some Arrow
stuff here. And then we'll just
say, if it's is owned by user,
if it's on by user, we'll show
the ngModel. Else, we will call
the by item function, since we
want our whole UI to rerender.
Once we change, once we change
the variable to show the
ngModel, we're going to do this
as a US state. So we'll say
const, show ngModel. Come a set,
show ngModel equals use state.
And then we're going to start it
off being defaulted to false. So
by default, we are not going to
show them on down which is what
we want. But if it's owned by
the user, we're gonna say Set
Show ngModel to be true. And
then else right now we'll just
put console dot log, let's buy
will actually update this to
bind the item a little bit
later. So now instead of having
is visible be false, we'll have
is visible equal to show
ngModel. Or show ngModel.
Variable. Okay, great. So now if
we save that, we go back to our
UI, we right click, we hit
Inspect, if we own it, and we
click it, the ngModel will pop
up, and we can click it out,
click another one, but that will
pop up if we don't own it. So if
we switch accounts, Connect will
switch. We click it, nothing
happens. And if we go to
inspect, we go to the console,
we click it, we should see let's
buy pop up, which is what we do
see, we'll do a little refresh
here. Click we see let's buy pop
up, click again, let's buy click
let's pilots pilots, why? Great,
cool. So now we have a word for
that ngModel. To actually show
up correctly, let's switch back
to the person who actually owns
this NFT we click it, we want to
be able to when we hit OK, or
submit, we want to send a
transaction to update the price
of our NFT here, so what we can
do is in our input will have a
label called on change equals
and this is the function that
will call whenever this updates.
So we're gonna say on change
event is going to be a function.
And we're going to create a
function called set price to
update listing listing with
event dot target dot value. So
we want to keep track of
whatever we've put in here. So
when we call the function to
update the price, it'll just
already automatically have it.
So we'll create this function
and event dot target dot value
is going to be whatever's in
this input box here. So we'll
create this set price to update
listing with will have this be a
use date because we are going to
want to change the UI based off
this so we'll say const price to
up date listing with comma set
price to update listing with
equals use state and then we'll
have this be zero to start or
blank. And so now, whatever is
in here is going to get updated
with this. So now I can do like
our console dot log price update
listing with Get back to the
front end, oops, we need to
import use state import, use
state from react. Go back to the
front end, we click this, we
right click Inspect.
By type one, we can see 114, we
see 14. So let's remove the
console dot log now. Now what we
can do in here is we can create
field called on okay, this is
going to be the function that we
call when we hit this, okay
here, so on. Okay, it's going to
be equal to a function, we're
going to use a little arrow
notation, and we're going to
call that update listing
function on the blockchain,
we're going to need to grab that
function so we can use it. So
once again, to use that
function, we're going to import
use web three contract from
react mirallas. And as a new
hook, we'll say const run
contract function called Update
listing, equals use web three
contract. And this is going to
be a function that we're going
to call on our NFT marketplace.
So ABI is going to be the NFT
marketplace API, which we can
get by doing an import, similar
to what we did over here. And we
actually just copy paste from
our NFT box. So we'll do import
NFT marketplace API from dot dot
constant send it to marketplace
that JSON, we're gonna need the
contract address, which is going
to be an input parameter to our
update listing ngModel. So we
can even do a comma market place
address, copy this place that
here, that means in our NFT box,
pretty soon, we're going to have
to pass all these variables to
it, but we'll save that in just
a second. So NFT marketplace
address marketplace address
function name, is going to be
what it's called Update, listing
in our smart contract, and then
the params. So if we go to this,
we have update listing takes the
NFT address token ID and new
price do NFT address, which will
be NFT address, we'll say token
ID is going to be token ID and
the new price your price will
get from price to update listing
with but will convert it from
human readable to ethers. So
we'll import ethers from ethers.
And the new price will be ethers
dot utils dot parse ethers or
ether price to update listing
with or just in case it's blank,
we'll just say or zero. So we
have the NFT address the token
ID marketplace address in our
NFT box, we're gonna have to
pass those parameters in here.
So we have is visible, we're
also going to have token ID,
which is going to equal token
ID, marketplace address is going
to equal the marketplace
address. And the NFT address is
going to equal the NFT address.
And as we code and test this
something that's going to be
really annoying, because it's
really annoying for me right now
let's refresh our website. And
if we click it, this thing pops
up. But when I hit X, and I
click this, again, nothing shows
up. That's because technically
show ngModel is still true right
now, even though we've exited
out. So what we want to do in
the NFT box is in our update
listing ngModel we're also going
to pass it in on close, and
we're going to pass it a hide
ngModel variable that we're
going to create, and right under
Show ngModel Set Show ngModel
we're going to create const Eid
ngModel. And this is just going
to be a function, that's just
going to say set, show modal. to
false, we're going to pass this
function to our update modal
listing. So we're going to do
comma on Close. And in our modal
here, we're going to say, on
Close. On, cancel, we're going
to do, we're going to call that
on close function, or on Close
button pressed, we're also going
to call that on close function.
Now if we refresh our website,
click this modal pops up, we
click X, click it again, it'll
pop back up, because now we're
properly setting it to false and
then resetting it to true. Now
to actually send this update
listing function, we're going to
pass this another thing, another
variable, we're going to pass it
on Okay, which is going to be a
function as well. It's just
going to call update listing
that we just created. Now, it's
always a good idea to add an On
error. We'd say on error, take
that error as a function and
console dot log.
The error and this needs to be
in squiggly brackets like that,
but contract address is wrong.
So we'll make this contract, con
tract address and spell that
correctly. Spelled correctly.
Now let's go back to the UI,
we'll give it a little refresh.
Click, this will add one. And we
see Metamask pop up. So this is
working out perfectly. Now I'm
going to cancel it, and our apps
gonna freak out and stuff. But
that's okay, we are doing
fantastically okay app popped up
like that, which is good. We
have this little error handling,
which I like to add for all of
these run contract functions.
Let's also do an on success. So
let's say when this does go
through successfully, we'll call
a function called handle update,
listing success. And this will
be a function that we'd call
when this goes through
correctly. So at the top, let's
make this new function, we'll
say const. Handle update,
listening success is going to be
a new function using the arrow
syntax here. And we'll have this
setup a new notification for a
web application. So for us to do
notifications, we're going to
use web three UI Kits use
notification, this is going to
be that same notification
service that we used in our last
one. So up at the top here,
we'll import it, use
notification. And then we'll
say, right in our component,
we'll say const, dispatch equals
use notification. And since
we're using notifications back
on our app.js, we have to import
it in here. So we'll do import
notification provider from web
three UI kit. And inside of our
Morales provider, we'll add the
notification provider around our
header and our component, so
that we have context for this.
Now in our handle update listing
success, inside this function
will say dispatch, say type is
going to be success. message
will be listing updated, title
will be listing updated, please
refresh, please refresh and move
blocks. And then position. Top
right. And then we'll do on
clothes, and on clothes. And
we'll say set price to update
listing with back to zero. I
also I'm editing this a little
bit in the future. And I
realized that I actually forgot
to add the TX to a lot of these
handle functions. So on these,
whenever we call one of these
run contract functions, like
we've been saying they have this
on error in this onsuccess. Now
this onsuccess automatically
passes the result of the call to
whatever callback function is
there. So for example, up the
listing returns a transaction,
and we'll pass that transaction
to whatever you add to the
onsuccess. So now in here, you
can actually have it have a
transaction as an input
parameter. And this would be the
transaction that's going to go
on the blockchain to you know,
update the price. So we actually
want to change it from a regular
function to an async function.
So we can actually do await TX
dot Wait, one, because we don't
want to say, hey, success, you
know, listing has been updated
before the transaction actually
goes through. So we want the
transaction to go through first.
And then we want to pop the
dispatch up saying, hey, it's
gone through so and then
additionally, when we actually
call these modells on the on,
okay, on the onsuccess, we pass
them in just by referencing the
name of the function. So we
don't do this arrow syntax,
anymore like this, we just say,
hey, the onsuccess is going to
be this, go ahead and pass your
results to it. So that's how we
actually call it down here. If
you look at the GitHub repo
associated with this, you go to
components, and we go into
these. So in this video, I
forgot to add the await TX dot
wait one. But in the GitHub
repo, we have these. And when
I'm demoing things in the video
here, the dispatch, it's gonna
pop up before the transaction
actually finishes going through.
So just want to let you know,
and back to the video. So now we
have a little success thing
that'll pop up when we're
successful. And the other thing
is, when we call this, we are
going to omit an item listed
inside of our Morales dashboard,
the price should actually update
in our active item because of
our Cloud Functions. So we're
going to put this all together
now. So we're on the front end.
And if the marketplace owned by
you will click it. Update
listing to 25. We're gonna hit
OK, meta masks is gonna pop up.
We're gonna go ahead and confirm
and ran through an error because
we need to click Metamask I need
to reset my account. So I'm
going to do settings, advanced
reset account.
Okay, now let's go ahead
Metamask has popped up again,
we're gonna go ahead and confirm
it closed, the pop up modal, and
we got our little notification
there. And we can see an
activity we have that
transaction has indeed completed
So now if we go to active item,
we give it a little refresh.
Right now we see our item listed
event. But the issue is that
it's not confirmed yet. So what
we're going to need to do is
we're going to need to move our
blocks by one. So in our NFT
marketplace, we're just going to
create a new script, a new file
called Mind dot Jas, just to
move our blocks once, and we're
going to say const, move blocks,
equals require dot slash utils,
slash move blocks, we'll say
const blocks equals to const
sleep amount equals 1000 async
function mine, do await move
blocks will do blocks as the
parameter and then sleep sleep
amount will equal sleep amount.
And this will be a script. So
we'll add our copy paste our
that same syntax we're doing
here just with mine. And now we
want to just mine these two
blocks. So we'll run yarn, art
hat run scripts. Mind that Jas
dash dash network, local host.
So we're going to mine those two
blocks. Now if we go back to our
database, we go back to active
items, we can see it's been
updated because now in our item
listed, that 2500 event is now a
confirmed transaction, and we
get to confirm their excellent.
So that means since it's
confirmed back in our front end,
we'll give this a little
refresh. We can see the pup is
now worth 25 eath. Awesome. So
we're updating ngModel is
working perfectly. Excellent
job. So now let's go to the
readme. If you own the NFT, you
can update the listing. That's a
checkmark. Excellent. Next, what
do we want it to do? If you
don't own it, you can buy the
listing. Okay, so let's go back
to our website, let's switch
users to a different account,
we're probably going to want an
account that own some money. So
let's go ahead and send this
other account some money
transfer between my accounts,
we'll send 100 eath to account
one, confirm on our hard hat
chain here. Alright, great. Now
we can go ahead and switch to
account one, and we have 100
eath. Okay, great. As these
pops, each cost less than 100
eath. So that's gonna be more
than plenty for us to test this
out. Let's go back to this box.
Because I think somewhere we
said, we did a little handle
card click, if it's owned by the
user, have the modal pop up. If
not, let's do the by
functionality. So to do the by
functionality, we're gonna go
ahead and do another run
contract function. So we'll do
const run contract function,
we'll call this one by item. And
this will equal use web three
contract. And this is going to
be the ABI for the NFT
marketplace. API, the contract
address is going to be the
market place address. The
function name is going to be by
item, the message value is going
to be the price of the NFT.
Because we need to send that
amount to buy the item. And then
params are going to be NFT
address, which is going to be
the NFT address. And the token
ID, which is going to be the
token ID now that we have this
by item on handle card click, we
can say okay, said show ngModel
is true. Otherwise, we're gonna
call by item. And we're going to
do on air. Air is going to be a
function where we're just going
to console dot log the air and
onsuccess. It'll be a function
where we call handle by item
success. So we'll create a new
handler for this right
underneath handled cart click
the const handled by item
success equals a function. And
for this, we'll also have this
do a little notification. So
once again, we're going to
import we're going to import use
notification from web through UI
kit. We're going to say const.
Dispatch equals use
notification. And then in
handled by item success. We're
gonna say dispatch
type, success. Message. Item
bought. Title will also be item
bought. Then pole position will
be top right That's it. So
handle card click, if they own
it, we're going to show that
update listing ngModel. If they
don't already own it, someone's
gonna buy it. So let's go back
here. And I'm currently on an
account that does not own these
NF T's. Let's go ahead and click
it. Our Metamask does indeed
show up for 25 eath. That's
crazy expensive. Let's go ahead
and confirm item has been
bought, we'll go ahead and click
that little x, we go to our meta
mask, the transaction is
pending. And it's gone through.
This is fantastic. Okay, our
homepage is done, we can show
recently listed NF T's if not,
you can update the listing. If
not, you can buy the listing.
And now it's time for our cell
page. So the last thing that we
need to do is our cell page,
let's get this cell page, let's
get this done pages, we have our
cell NFT page, which right now
does a whole lot of nothing. And
on our front end, we go here,
there's not a whole lot here.
And actually, you can list your
NFT in the marketplace, we also
needed to add withdraw proceeds.
So I didn't add that. But that's
probably going to be something
we're going to want to allow
people to do as well. So let's
get started here. So we can
remove this head stuff now that
we're adding that in our main
page. And for us to submit a new
NFT, we're probably gonna need a
space to add the address of the
entity that token ID of the NFT
and all this other stuff. So
we're gonna need a form to do
this, which guess what, we can
also grab a form from the web
through UI kit as well. So we're
gonna go ahead in our cell NMC
page, we're going to import form
from web three UI kit. And we're
going to create a new form in
our cell page. Now, the
parameters we can add to our
form, again, you can find them
in documentation here, or we're
going to add with one of the
main pieces is going to be this
data piece, which is going to be
an object that has a list in it,
of all the different fields, we
can put in our form. So maybe
we'll do our first one have a
name of NFT address. That's
gonna be of type text, excuse
me, and these are all going to
be this is a list of list of
objects like that. Now, if we
save that, we go back to our
cell page, we can now see an
empty address and a little
Submit button. That right now
does a whole lot of nothing. So
we have an NFT address, it'll
take a text, maybe we'll also do
in foot width of 50 percent will have
the starting value be blank. And
the key of this will be NFT
address, what else do we need,
we're going to need to give it
the token ID so we'll say name,
token ID, type is going to be a
number value, we'll start off
it's blank. And then the key for
this will be token ID. Next,
we're going to need the price.
So we'll say name will be price.
In eath. type will be a number
value will be blank. And the key
will be price. And we don't need
to have to form tags, we'll just
delete that second one and have
it auto close with one tag. And
then in here, we'll do title
equals sell your NF T ID equals
main form. So cool. So now we
can take an empty address, a
token ID and a new price with
the title of cellular NFT.
Great, that looks really nice.
Right now our form doesn't do
anything, we probably want to
give it the functionality to
actually do stuff. So we'll say
on Submit, and we'll have to
create a new function to
actually list our NF T's. So
we're going to create a function
called approve and list we have
to approve our marketplace to
pull the NFT from our wallets.
So we're going to create a new
function, a sync function
approven list, which is going to
take a data input parameter on
our form, when we hit on submit,
it's automatically going to pass
this data object to our approved
list function. So that's how
we're going to get the value of
the address the value of the
token ID and the value of the
price. So in our async function
approven list, do console dot
log, approving the contract, the
NFT address is going to come
from this data object. So it's
going to be data dot data at
index zero, or zero with object
here is going to be our address
that input result.
Our token ID is going to equal
data dot data. One because
again, this one is going to be
our token ID that input result.
And then the price is going to
equal that ethers dot utils dot
parse units of data dot data
have to the input result, comma
ether.to string. So we're going
to get the price in eath. In
human readable form, we're going
to convert it to Aetherium
readable form. And then we're
going to pass it as a string
because this returns a big
number, which we don't want. So
we have the NFT address, the
token ID and the price of the
new listing, what we can do now
is we can say const approve
options equals a little function
here, the ABI which is going to
be our NFT abi, which we need to
import, we need to import both
ethers from ethers. And we also
need to import the NFT abi, for
its NFT ABI from dot dot
constants slash basic at A T dot
JSON, I just copied and pasted
from the NFT box, the contract
address is going to be the NFT
address, the function name is
going to be approve params are
going to be two, the marketplace
address, which we're going to
define in just a second, and
then the token ID will be token
ID. Now the marketplace address
in our NFT box, we're getting
this directly from index, an
index is getting it from our
database. Now we want our app to
be smart enough to be able to
grab the NFT marketplace itself,
the marketplace address. And if
we go to our constants, right
now, we actually have it in this
network mapping. So we're going
to want to grab it right up at
the top by saying const
marketplace address equals
network mapping, network mapping
of what of the chain ID of the
entity marketplace address at
the zero with index. So network
mapping of the chain ID, which
we're going to get honest chain
ID equals us Morales. Now chain
Id actually comes like we said
it's a wax hex form for Morales.
So we're gonna have to convert
the chain ID to its string
readable version. So we'll say
const, chain string equals chain
ID. And we'll do a tertiary
operator, if the chain ID
exists, will parse int of the
chain id.to string. So we'll
parse it from its hex to a more
readable version, and then do.to
string. And then otherwise,
we'll just say we're on 31337.
So chain ID string. So in the
network mapping at the chain ID
string, dot NFT marketplace at
index zero, that's going to be
our marketplace address. So we
got the marketplace address,
this is all we need to call the
approved function on our NFT we
can now call running contract
function for a proof. So we're
actually going to do this a
little bit differently. We're
just going to say const. Run
contract function equals use web
three contract, you could import
just run contract function, and
then pass all those options to
it like what we're gonna do
here. Now we're just gonna say
await on contract function.
Because this is an async
function await run contract
function, we're gonna say params
are going to be approve options.
And we're gonna say onsuccess,
we're going to do something, I'm
going to say on error, we're
also going to just do error,
little arrow function, console
dot log error. Now on success,
once we send this transaction,
after the Approve goes through,
we're going to want to call the
list function right underneath
this will call async async.
Function, handle approve
success. And this is going to
take the NFT address, the token
ID, and the price is it put in
parameters. So once this run
contract function goes through,
we're going to call
of handle proof success. And
we'll pass it the end of the
address, token ID and the price,
which will say console dot log.
Okay, now time to list and we'll
do the same thing. We'll do
const list options, equals and
this is going to be all the
options for calling the list
function API is going to be on
the marketplace this time. So
NFT market place abi, which
again, we're going to have to
import so I'm going to go back
to NFT box. We're gonna copy
that line here, paste it in the
top. That's going to be the API
for that contract address. It's
going to be the marketplace
address, which we already have.
function name is going to be
list item. And the params are
going to be NF T address of the
NFT address, token ID of token
ID, price of price. And now we
have those options, we can do
await, run contract function
with params. Of list options,
will say onsuccess arrow
function, handle list success,
which is a function we haven't
made yet. It will say on air
error. And we'll just say
console dot log error. Okay, so
let's make this handle list
success handle one spell handle
correctly handle the success,
this will be an async function.
And this is also going to call
dispatch and make a little
notification. So we're going to
grab that from web three UI kit,
use notification. We'll say
const dispatch equals use
notification. And now down in
handle the success say dispatch,
type success. Message NFT
listing, title NFT listed
position. top bar, and cool. And
we're also gonna have to grab us
Morales from react Morales. So
do import us Morales from react
or else. So let's import this
network mapping. Import network
mapping from dot dot slash
constants slash network mapping
dot JSON. Because I spelled
contract address wrong again,
good our front end we'll give it
a refresh us web three contract
isn't defined. Let's get that
from react moralss. Well save
that refresh our front end. And
tada, we're good to go here.
Alright, now to test this out,
we're going to want to do is
we're going to want to create
another script here. So we're
back in our heart at NFT
marketplace, we're looking at
our scripts. And we're going to
create a new file just called
mint.js. So we're not going to
list this time, we're just going
to mint it just going to mint an
NF t so we can list it ourselves
on the UI. And actually, we can
just copy our mminton list code,
paste it into here, and just
remove the approval and the
listing code. Boom, remove that,
remove this, remove this. And
that's all we need. And now
we'll just change the name to
mint. Well, we can remove price
as well. And we'll change this
to mint. And that's it. Now we
have a script that we can call,
well, we'll just mint an NFT, we
can also get rid of the NFT
marketplace. Actually, we will
probably want the token ID so we
can know what it is. So let's do
const token ID equals. So let's
actually get the receipt we'll
do const mint TX receipt, but
the receipt, I can there equals
that. And then I'm just going to
copy this from the mminton
receipt. Cons token ID equals
this, paste it into our mint.js
and then a console dot log. Got
token ID, string interpolates
token ID, hard hat, run scripts,
mins dot j s dash dash network,
local host. And we're going to
mint an NF T. Got token ID six
means we know m token ID six, we
can list this entity. Let's also
add the address. Let's do
console dot log NFTL. And if the
address is going to be we'll do
string interpolation.
And you know what? Let's make
this again. Mint dot j s okay
cool. Got token ID seven and if
the address this so what we can
do now we'll grab this NFT
address. So from account one,
let's go to Account three
because that's the account that
I've done my imports on now when
you switch accounts, we're going
to want to refresh the page as
the address seven 0.6. Submit
Metamask pops up. Give
permission Yes. Okay, now it's
time to list you now have one
pen, okay. Local host list item.
We can see all the data and
everything. Okay, let's go ahead
and confirm NFT listed Okay,
okay. Okay. Okay. So this is
good. Now to get Morales to
catch up to speed back in our
node. Let's just go ahead and
run yarn, RT hat run scripts,
mine dot j s dash dash network,
local host. We're going to mine
those two blocks. And now if we
go to our item listed, we'll
give this a little refresh. Go
to active item. We can see
there's a new item listed for
0.6 eath. In our database. This
is fantastic. Now that we've
listed this, if we go back to
now let's make And let's move on
to one more. Let's list the
second one, just to see that
it's actually working. Okay,
token ID eight. Let's grab this
address. Let's give this a
refresh. paste this in token ID
eight. We'll do 0.999. Let's
submit. we'll approve this. Yes.
Then we'll send it. Yes. Okay,
now let's go ahead and mine two
blocks. So I'm just going to hit
up and go back to mine will run
the mining, moving blocks. Okay,
great. Now, if we go back home,
we'll see there are three NF T's
now listed, we have the original
one, that we have those two that
we just listed eight, and seven
for 0.6 and 0.999. Listed on our
NFT marketplace. This is so
exciting. Our listing is working
correctly, okay. Now, due to the
fact that this lesson is already
incredibly long, actually
decided to cut the part of that
and then withdraw a bit, because
we don't really learn anything
new there. However, feel free to
jump back in to get every bit
associated with scores, where we
will have that withdrawal
functionality for you if you
want to implement it. Otherwise,
feel free to skip and move on
ahead. This is incredibly
powerful. And you should be
incredibly excited about
yourself. If you've made it this
far. This is awesome. You just
made a decentralized marketplace
and then built a front end on
top of it to allow anybody to
interact with your marketplace.
Easily. Huge, huge.
Congratulations here. Oh, this
is a perfect time to go take a
break and celebrate. And this is
a great time to ping me on
Twitter to ping me on Twitter
saying hey, Patrick, I just
completed the NFT marketplace.
Full Stack front end part of
your Free Code Camp course, I
now know how to build full stack
front end on top of my smart
contract applications. And be so
so pumped with yourself because
this is so awesome. I can't
understate how excited I am that
you've made it this far, you are
learning and working with a ton
of technologies, solidity smart
contracts, and front end you are
doing full stack you were doing
a lot of stuff here. So you
should be really proud of
yourself. huge congratulations,
be sure to absolutely give
yourself a pat on the back. And
then get ready to continue to
our next section.
Now that we've done all of this
using our Morales back end, I'm
about to switch it up on you,
instead of indexing all of our
events with a centralized
server. Now we're going to learn
how to build this using the
graph, which is a decentralized
event indexer that we can use, a
lot of the code is going to be
exactly the same. So instead of
us starting from a new, what
we're going to do, first of all
we can we can close all our
local stuff, we can close all of
these things, we can close all
of our terminals finally, which
is really exciting. And in this
folder, what we're going to do
is we're actually just going to
copy everything into a new
folder. So I'm going to CD down
a directory, we're going to make
a new one called next Jas. And
if T marketplace, the graph,
dash FCC, and all the code for
this section is going to be here
for front end the graph indexer
we're gonna have to make another
repo and we'll get to that in a
little bit. For all the changes,
it's going to be in this section
here. So what we're going to do
is we're going to make this new
folder, and we're going to do
copy dash R. Next, Jas and ft
marketplace FCC into next Jas
NFT. Marketplace, the graph FCC.
So we're going to copy
recursively, everything that's
inside that folder we just
created into this new one that
we're going to make a lot of
adjustments to. And this might
take a little bit of time to run
because we've got a lot of stuff
in this folder. And Alright,
once we've done that, we can cd
into this next Jas and ft
marketplace, the graph FCC and
do code period and open this up
in a new code editor. Or as
always, you can do File Open
folder to open it like that. Now
that we're in here, we're going
to learn how to do this exact
same project, instead of using
mirallas. But using the graph,
one of the things that we're
first going to do is we're
actually going to deploy our
contracts to rink B. So we're
going to grab our marketplace,
that soul, pull this over, we're
going to grab our hard hat
marketplace dot soul project,
pull it over. And first, we're
going to run our deploy script
on rink v. So hopefully, you've
got all your deploy stuff set up
correctly, so that all the
arguments can go through
correctly for rink v as well. So
we're gonna go ahead and run
this yarn, hard hat deploy dash
dash network Rinkeby. And to
make sure that it's going to
work for Rinkeby. Let's check
our hard hat config. Okay for
networks, looks like I have my
Rigby stuff in here for
networks. Okay, I've got my RPC
URL, which I'm getting from my
environment variables. If I have
a private key, I have a private
key, which I'm also getting from
environment variables, I have a
chain ID block confirmations and
save deployments. So let's go
ahead and run this. Now we're
going to go ahead and be
deploying the NFT marketplace to
the Rigby network. And our
deploy script also has an ID
some verification. So we can
verify this as well, you can't
really follow along with this
section without deploying a
marketplace to rink be here. So
deploy to rank B, or whatever
test net is recommended in this
lesson 15 section, and go from
there. Alright, great, we've
deployed our NFC marketplace.
Now we're gonna go ahead and
deploy our basic NFT. And once
these are done deploying, we can
start updating our front end
code to work with the graph
instead of mirallas. Okay, we've
verified everything to which
looks great. Now we're going to
verify our basic NFT. And we've
have it verified. Awesome. So
now we have an NFT marketplace
deployed to ring P, and a basic
NFT deployed to rink B. And both
of them are verified. So be sure
to take note of those, because
we're going to need them when
we're moving over to our the
graph section. So now let's grab
our code editor titled next Jas
and ft marketplace, the graph.
And let's get going. Now, we
just deployed that to rink B.
But we forgot to add some code
in here to update our network
mapping. However, if we go back
and we open back up code dot
dot, next Jas NFT marketplace,
FCC, in the network mapping in
here will now have a new entry
for rink B, if we did it
correctly, let's copy this
network mapping and paste it
over in our network, our next GS
and ft marketplace, the graph
section, or you can just
manually add your new entry.
Right. So you want to add
network ID for network
marketplace. And the address of
that network marketplace that
you just deployed, is we're
going to delete this Cloud
Functions bit. Goodbye, because
since we're not working with the
server anymore, there's not
gonna be any cloud functions or
any back end to run. So we're
gonna move that to trash
goodbye. Next, we don't need FRP
anymore, because we're not going
to be connecting our local
blockchain to the graph, we're
only going to be working with
the test net here. So let's go
ahead and delete that. Goodbye,
what's next in our pages, and
our app dot j s. Right now we're
connecting to a Morales provider
like this, we're going to switch
this back to initiate allies on
Mount, this is going to go back
to being false, we're no longer
going to connect to our Morales
database like this, we're just
going to use the hooks again.
Now with that the only thing
that's going to change is our
index.js. Right now, in our
index.js, we're getting our list
of NF TS from our Morales query.
So we're going to change this,
let's update our readme. So
we're gonna say instead of
reading the events from ralis,
we will first off we're going to
index them with the graph. And
then we're going to read from
the graph. So the question is,
what is the graph.
So the graph is going to be a
decentralized layer for storing
event data. So there are all
these blockchains and all these
different storage networks. And
the graph is and the graph is a
network of different nodes that
read from blockchains and index
this data, and it exposes an API
for us to call we can read that
data. Rather than just myself.
We actually have nattered
Abbott, who can explain it a lot
better than I can take it away.
And at.
First, I'd like to thank Patrick
for creating such a wonderful
educational resource and
inviting me to be a part of it.
My name is Nadia dabit. I'm a
developer relations engineer
working with the graph. The
graph is an indexing and
querying protocol for
decentralized networks like
Aetherium IPFS, dozens of other
EVM compatible networks, as well
as near and then the future
cosmos and Solana. Using the
graph developers can build and
publish open API's called
subgraphs that they can then use
in their applications to enable
better querying capabilities of
data stored on these networks,
including features like
filtering, sorting, relational
data, and full stack search.
subgraphs live in between the
blockchain and the UI providing
an important piece of software
infrastructure, a flexible
performant and decentralized API
layer, and the traditional tech
stack databases, servers and
API's query filter, sort
paginate group and join data
before it's returned to an
application, usually via some
type of HTTP request. These
types of data transformations
are not possible when reading
data directly from Aetherium or
other blockchains. Before the
graph teams had to develop and
operate proprietary indexing
servers. This required
significant engineering and
hardware resources and broke the
important security principles
required for decentralization,
how we interact with and build
on top of blockchains it's much
different than what we are used
to in the traditional tech
stack. In a blockchain data
isn't stored in a format that
can be easily or efficiently
consumed, or retrieved directly
from other applications or front
ends. The problem is that you
need to have the data indexed
and organized for efficient
retrieval. Traditionally, that's
the work that databases and web
servers do in this centralized
tech stack. But that in indexing
layer was missing in the web
three stack. Let's take a look
at a couple of other examples of
indexing in the real world.
Search engines like Google crawl
the internet indexing relevant
data making it available for
users to search via their web
interface and other API's.
Without this indexing layer,
it'd be hard for us to know
where and how to find relevant
information across the web.
Another similar analogy is a
library. Using an indexing
system like the Dewey Decimal
System, we know where to find
the book that we're looking for
without having to go through
book by book looking throughout
the entire library. The graph
serves over 2 billion queries
per day to many different types
of web three applications,
including apps in the defy
gaming and FC space. Before we
dig into any code, let's take a
look at how to build a sub
graph. To get started, you would
go to the graph.com and create a
new sub graph and the graph user
interface. You would then use
the graph CLI to scaffold out an
empty sub graph boilerplate that
you can then update with your
own contract information. In
your subgraph configuration, you
would define things like your
data model, the network, the
contract addresses and other
configurations that are specific
to the data that you would like
to index. For our data model, we
use Graph QL, schema definition
language defining top level
types as well as fields within
those types. When we're ready to
deploy our subgraph, so we can
begin testing it out and using
it in our application, we can
use the graph CLI running the
deploy command. Once the
subgraph is deployed and the
data begins to be indexed, we
can start testing it out using
the graphical interface directly
in the graph dashboard. When
we're ready to start queering,
our sub graph from our
application, we can use the API
URL that's been given to us by
the graph along with any Graph
QL query. If you'd like to learn
more about the graph, check out
the graph.com as well as Graph
Protocol, Twitter, the docs at
the graph.com/docs, or our
Discord at the graph.com/discord
Thanks matter. And now that we
have a better idea of what the
graph is, we can actually start
building with it. Now if we were
to try to run this app as it is,
it obviously would fail, right,
because index.js, right now is
reading from mirallas instead of
from the graph. So like it says
in our readme, first thing we're
going to need to do is we're
gonna need to index from the
graph, and then we can just this
project to read from the graph.
So let's go ahead and learn how
to build our sub graph. In order
for us to tell the graph network
to start indexing the events
from our contract, we're gonna
go to graph.com, we're gonna go
to products. And we're going to
go to sub graph studio, if you
go to products, the first thing
you see is the Graph Explorer,
these are already existing sub
graphs. And if you go through
here, you'll see a lot of
incredibly popular decentralized
protocols all have different sub
graphs, hosted service is going
to get discontinued at some
point. So we're going to skip
there. So let's go to sub graph
studio, this is going to help
enable us to create a sub graph
for other nodes to start
indexing our events. So we're
gonna go ahead and connect our
wallet with meta mask. And I'm
going to choose account one
here, next connect, and we're
going to want to switch off of
Hardhead. Local, over to the
Rinkeby test network. And I'll
go to Account one here. And
we're going to get a signature
request from the graph summary
to the website that we just
built. The subgraph website has
some signings functionality with
a database on the back end. So
we're seeing in real life,
exactly the methods that we just
used. So instead of signing with
Morales, they're just have their
own custom sign in here. So
we're gonna go ahead and sign in
so that the graph website knows
that it can interact with us.
And we can go ahead and enter
our email if we want. I'm gonna
go ahead and skip. And you'll
even get a little notification
here saying only subgraphs
indexing Aetherium or main net
or Rigby can be created in
subgraph studio. So let's go
ahead and create a subgraph. So
we're going to pick a cerium
Rigby and the subgraph name is
going to be NFT marketplace.
We'll go ahead and hit Continue.