Now, this is going to be our
dashboard for creating our sub
graph. And there's a ton of
instructions over here and
documentation that we can view
to get started, I'm going to add
this documentation to the GitHub
repo associated with this
course. So this NFT marketplace
sub graph is going to need its
own git repository itself. So
what we're going to do back in
here is we're going to CD down,
we're going to make a new
directory, and we're going to
call it graph. And if T
marketplace, FCC, we're going to
open that up as well. So code
graph NFT, marketplace, FCC, or
file open graft code marketplace
FCC, and in this window, we're
going to build our subgraph.
Locally, we're going to build
our subgraph and push it up to
the subgraph studio. And in
here, there's a whole bunch of
instructions that we can follow
along with to go ahead and
install. The first thing that we
need to do is install the graph
command line interface. And we
want to install this globally.
So I'm going to copy this part
here. Come back to my terminal
Oh, yarn, global ad and paste
that in. It's this command line
that's going to help us build a
graph and build instructions for
the graph to actually start
indexing our events. Now that
we've installed the globally, we
can initialize our graph code.
So we can copy this line. And
we'll run graph a knit dash dash
studio NFT marketplace and hit
enter. The protocol is going to
be Aetherium, or subgraph. Slug
will be NFT. marketplace. We
want the directory to be here,
but it's saying directory
already exists. So we'll just
give it NFT marketplace. And
then we'll move it after this.
And this is on the Rinkeby. Test
net. And now we want to give it
the contract address. So we want
to grab that address that we
just deployed. And it should be
now in our network mapping. So
we're going to grab that
contract address that we just
deployed, and paste it in here.
Like so. And since we've already
verified on ether scan, it
automatically grabs the ABI for
us from ether scan, we'll give
it the contract name, which is
the NFT marketplace. And it's
going to give us a whole bunch
of boilerplate code in this NFT
marketplace directory. And this
might take a couple of minutes.
Alright, awesome. So now that
it's done, we see subgraph NFT
marketplace created in NFT
marketplace. Now, I don't want
it to be in the seller folder.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to move it down a
directory, but you can leave it
where it is, if you want, I'm
going to say move, I'm going to
say move NFT marketplace, star
to dot slash. Now everything
inside of NFT marketplace will
be in this current directory.
And then if the marketplace will
be empty. So with that, I'm
gonna go ahead and delete. And
if the marketplace. Alright,
great. Now let me walk you
through exactly what's going on
here and what these files are
that we just created. So our
first folder is going to be
API's. In order for the graph to
index and read our contract
index our events, it's going to
need the ABI of our events. So
we've got the ABI of our entire
marketplace, from ether scan, if
we didn't verify an ether scan,
we can just create this API
folder ourself and add the NFT
marketplace JSON in here. Now we
have this generated folder. This
is an auto generated file. He
even says at the top, do not
edit this file directly. You can
kind of think of this as the
build folder, or where we
compile graph code. Node
modules, of course, is going to
be node modules and
dependencies. SRC is going to be
where we define and we tell the
graph, how to actually map and
how to actually work with our
contract. And it is a TypeScript
file. So for all of you who have
been just doing this in
JavaScript, I will have to teach
you a little bit of TypeScript
just to get through this part.
Then we have networks dot JSON,
which gives us all of our
network information about which
networks, what are the
addresses, and what are the
different contracts that we're
going to be indexing, package
dot JSON, which of course is
just a normal package dot JSON.
And it's got some graph scripts
already built in schema dot
graph. QL is going to be our
Graph QL schema. So this is also
going to be how we tell the
graph how to actually work with
our events and index our events.
And if you're familiar, the
schema follows the Graph QL
syntax. So if you've ever worked
with Graph QL, before, it's
going to be the exact same way,
graph. QL is a query language
for your API. And instead of
being kind of a relational
database, it can query in a more
graph type way, I'm not going to
go too deep into how it actually
works behind the scenes. But if
you want to learn more, I'm
going to leave some docs in the
GitHub repository associated
with this course, the sub graph
dot Yamo tells our subgraph how
to combine all the files
together. So we have data
sources, data sources, where
they're coming from different
addresses, different entities or
events, the API's where to grab
our files from different event
handlers, which we'll talk about
in a minute. And then the main
file, which is going to be our
mapping.ts, we have a TS config,
which is a configuration file
specific to TypeScript. And then
of course, we have our yarn dot
lock. With all this information
with all this code, we are now
going to update all this code to
tell the graph to start indexing
our events. So we can read our
events from the graph in a
decentralized context, as
opposed to from a centralized
database. And after we build
everything, we're going to run
through this off and deploy
code, which is to authenticate
ourselves, and then deploy our
code to the graph to start
indexing. So without further
ado, let's jump in. And let's do
this. So one of the first things
I'm going to do, I'm going to
add a highlighter for these dot
Graph QL files. So in our
extensions, we're gonna look at
Graph QL. And we're gonna stall
this Graph QL extension. Now
that we've installed it, if we
go back to schema dot graph, QL,
we've got it with some colors
now, which is exciting. So this
schema dot Graph QL is going to
define what entities we have in
our contract if we were to be
analogous to mirallas. These are
going to be how we're going to
define what our tables are going
to look like. And these are
going to be our events. plus
that active item table that we
created. So we're not going to
have an example entity though,
we're going to have a type
active item. And this is going
to be an add entity. So these
are the different types we have
in our graph that we can
actually query on, our main
thing that we're going to want
to query on is same as before,
it's going to be our active
items. And then inside of our
active items, we're going to
tell the graph, what parameters
each one of these active item
types has, well, it's going to
have an ID of type ID. So the
variable is ID of type ID. And
you can read more about the
different types in the graph
documentation. And this
exclamation mark means it must
have an ID. So every active item
needs to have and will have an
ID, we'll say there's going to
be a buyer, which is going to be
an address, so that's going to
be a byte and the buyer could be
blank, right? It could be the
0x 000, we're going to have all
of our active items have a
0000 dot.if. If no one has
bought yet, we're going to have
a seller, which of course is
also going to be a bytes because
it's going to be an address,
we're going to have an NFT
address. So the address of the
NFT, which will also be bytes,
we're going to have a token ID
which isn't going to be bytes,
this is going to be of type big
int, and then we're going to
have a price, which is also
going to be a big int. Now price
we're going to leave as not
required for price, we're just
going to have price be nullable.
So price can be null. So we have
an active item. Awesome. What
else are we going to need? What
what other tables do we have in
Morales? Well, we're going to
need type item listed. And this
is going to be at entity is
going to need an ID, it'll have
a seller. Whenever an item gets
listed, it's going to have a
seller right, which is going to
be a bytes again. And if the
address the address of the NFT,
which will also be bytes, the
token ID, which is going to be a
big int, and then the price,
which will also be a big end,
we're gonna need a type item
cancelled at entity
which will have an ID seller an
NFT address. And a token ID will
be a big end. And then last type
item bought will be in that
entity is going to have an ID
ID. It's going to be a buyer
bytes.
And then of T address a bytes
and a token ID again, and then a
price of beginnt. And with
Justice Information, we've
defined what we want our
subgraph to keep track of wants
to keep track of item bought
events, item, cancelled events,
item listed events. And then
we're going to make this new
active item table similar to
what we did with mirallas. And
it's going to be some function
of these these other three
events. And now we're done with
our schema dot graph. QL.
Awesome. So what do we do now
we're going to need to tell our
sub graph to actually listen for
these events. So what we can do.
So what we want to do to tell it
how to listen for these events,
is we're going to go to src
mapping.ts. It's this mapping.ts
file that's going to tell our
subgraph how to actually map and
how to actually store all the
event information that we have.
If you look in it right now, it
might even give you kind of a
sample event. So it says Export
function, handle item event.
This is what Maya says right
now, it takes as an input
parameter event item bot. So
this is saying whenever an item
bot event occurs, do this handle
item bot function. So anytime
item bot happens do this handle
item bot. And we're actually
getting this item bot from our
generated NFT marketplace from
some generated code. In the
graph. If we run graph code Gen.
This graph code Gen command
grabs all the stuff we have in
the schema dot Graph QL and puts
it in this generated file. Now
that I've run graph code Gen,
you'll see in here there's an
item bot class, you see there's
a schema, that type script. And
actually we can even find that
new active item class that we
created in our schema. So
anytime you update schema dot
Graph QL, you're always going to
want to run graph code Gen, so
you can update those types. And
if this failed, it means that
you messed up something in your
schema dot Graph QL. Now in our
mapping.ts, we're actually
importing item bought item
cancelled item listed from
generated and if the marketplace
and if the marketplace from our
generated code. These are going
to be our events. And we're not
going to need to do anything
with the NFT marketplace. We're
just going to need our event
information. For now. Let's go
ahead and just delete everything
inside our handle item bot or
whatever sample is given to you.
So we're importing a or events
from our generated code. And
then we have this line here,
which we're going to change in a
second. So again, we have these
three functions handle item
bought, handle item canceled and
handle item listed. Whenever we
get an item bought event, we're
going to do this function.
Whenever we get an item canceled
event, we're going to do this
function. And all this code is
defined in our sub graph dot
Yamo. You can see the different
entities here in a bot item
cancelled item listed, and the
event handlers. So it says,
okay, anytime this specific
event gets fired with an index
address, an index address index,
YouTube 36 in YouTube had six
call handle item bought, which
again, we're getting in here
handle item. But so that's
exactly how this works. So let's
figure out what to do when an
item bought event triggers. And
I think that item bought item
cancelled item lists it is a
little confusing. So I like to
change this to item bought as
item bought event item cancelled
as item cancelled event item
listed as item listed event. So
I'm just changing the names of
these three that are imported
from NFT marketplace. And now
I'm going to change event item
bot to item bought event. Event
item cancelled to item cancelled
event and event item listed to
item listed event. Okay, great.
And we're just going to remove
this line for now. And we also
don't need this line at the top
at the beginning, we will in a
minute, but we'll delete it for
now. So here's our minimalistic
code here. So whenever we list
an item, what do we need to do?
Well, we need to save that event
in our in our graph. And then we
also need to update our active
item, exactly as we did with
Morales. So first thing that
we're going to need to do is
either get or create an item
listed object. And something
that we need to know is that
each item needs a unique ID. And
we actually need to create that
ID. So one of the first things
I'm going to do is going to
create a function called Get ID
from event params. And it's
going to take a token ID and
here's where TypeScript comes
into play a little bit. In
TypeScript, we actually need to
define the types of our
different parameters. So token
ID is going to be a big int. And
we'll also take an NFT address,
which will take in a type of
address. And we also need to say
what return type or function is
going to give, which we're going
to return a string, we're going
to create an ID from event
params. And it's just going to
be a combination of the token ID
and the NFT address. The
combination of these two will
give a unique ID for each one of
these types of event. So we're
just gonna say return token ID,
and token ID has a function
called to x string, I'm gonna
say plus, and if T address.to X
string, like so. And big int an
address, we need to import from
at Graph Protocol slash graph
TX. It already imported big
enough for me. So I'm just going
to add address in here is the
two special types that come from
the graph. And then string is
built into TypeScript. Now that
we have a way to get a special
ID for each item in our function
here, we have to now either get
or create a new item listed. Now
right now we have an item. But
event we don't have an item
bought object. So the item
bought object is going to be
what we save, the item bought
event is just the raw event. So
we have to create an item bought
object from our item bought
event. And in TypeScript, these
are going to be two different
types. So we have to import
these item by objects. So those
actually get auto created from
generated schema. In here we
have active item, we have item,
we have an item bought class, we
have an item cancelled, etc. So
we're gonna have to import those
types from there. So we can say,
import, item listed, comma,
active item, item bought an item
cancelled from dot slash,
generated slash schema. Let's go
ahead and get or create an item
bot object. So we'll say let
item bot equals item bot dot
load. And this is how we load an
item we load its unique ID by
calling this get ID from event
params dot load, get ID from
event params. And we can pass
event dot params. That token ID
because an item bot event is
going to have a token ID and
event that params.nf T address.
Now I know we probably should
have done handle item listed
first but we're doing item bot
first. Since we're buying an
item, we probably will also have
an active item as well, right?
We haven't made yet an item
listed. But this is going to be
similar to what we did with
Morales. So we know that every
time we live Certain items will
also list an active item. So
we'll say let active item equals
active item that load. And we're
going to do this exact same
thing. So I'm just going to copy
paste it into here. And even
though these are going to have
the exact same ID, it doesn't
matter because they're the same
ID across different types. Now
we're gonna say, if there is no
item bot, we'll say item bot
equals a new item bot object.
And we'll give it an ID, which
is going to be exactly our ID
giving parameter here, get ID
from events, and pass that
there. So we're going to create
a new item bought here. And now
we're going to update all its
parameters. So back in our
schema dot graph, QL. An item
bought has an ID, buyer address,
token ID and price. So we're
gonna say, item bought, that
buyer equals event dot params
dot buyer, item bought.nf T
address equals event.params.nf T
address, item bot, dot token ID
equals event dot params dot
token ID. And that looks good.
And our active item will be from
item listed, and item listed
should give it all these
parameters, except for it won't
have a buyer. So we just need to
update the buyer on our active
item. So we'll say active item,
dot buyer, we'll do a little
exclamation mark. This is some
TypeScript stuff, saying we will
have an active item. Don't worry
too much about it if you're
unfamiliar with TypeScript. And
we'll say that equals event dot
params dot buyer. And now
similar to Morales, we're gonna
do item bot dot save and active
item with an exclamation mark
again, that save and this is how
we're going to save this item
bought event as an object in our
the Graph Protocol. And also,
we're going to update our active
item. So this is our full
function of handle item bought.
Whenever somebody buys an item,
we update a new item bought
object, and we update our active
item to be a new buyer, we're
not going to delete it from our
active items list, we're just
going to update it with a new
buyer. And we'll just say if it
has a buyer, that means it's
been bought. If it doesn't have
a buyer, that means it's still
on the market. Awesome. So now
that we've done our handle item
bot, let's now do our handle
item listed, which will
hopefully make our handle item
bot a little bit easier to
understand. So for handle item
listed, we're going to do the
same piece here. So we're going
to say let item listed equals
item listed dot load. And we're
gonna do the exact same thing as
what we did for all these will
do get ID from event params.
Like so, get a different event
params. And we're gonna say let
active item. And this line is
going to be exactly the same as
up here. So I'm just going to
copy paste. So we're saying,
okay, great, grab our item
listed, and grab our active
item, see if those objects
already exist. I will say if
there is no item listed, which
there shouldn't be, we'll go
ahead and create a new one,
we'll say item listed
equals new item listed. And its
ID is going to be from this
function that we created are
unique IDs. Now, unlike what we
did above, we're also going to
say, if there is no active item,
then we're going to create a new
active item, right? Because
we're listing an item, it
shouldn't be an active item. Now
this functionality is going to
make a lot more sense here,
right? Because if we're updating
the price of an item, active
item will already exist. If it's
a brand new listing, though,
active item will not exist. So
we'll say okay, if it doesn't
exist, okay, that means it's a
brand new listing, we'll say
item listed equals new item
listed, and then we'll give it
an ID. That's the same ID
methodology, paste that in. So
now all we got to do is update
these new objects. So I will say
item listed that seller equals
event dot params dot seller. And
I'm just going to copy paste
this line. Because this is just
gonna be active item dot seller
now. Oops, see me and then it'll
make this active item. active
item instead of item listed. And
what else comes with item
listed? Well, let's go to the
schema item listed has an NFT
address, token ID and a price.
So okay, so let's add those.
item listed dot NFT address
equals event.params.nf T
address. Copy paste this line
because it's gonna be the be the
exact same for active item. Now
item listed that token ID equals
event dot params dot token ID.
Copy paste this line. Same thing
for active item. Item listed dot
price equals event dot params
dot At price, copy, paste this
line for active item. And then
we just say those two. So item
listed that save active item.
Save. So in our protocol here,
if it's already been, if there
already is an active item, then
we just go ahead and we get that
active item. This would be for a
listing that we're updating. If
not, we make a new one. We
update it with whatever came in
through the event. And then we
save it to our graph protocol.
Okay, perfect. Now we only have
one left, item cancelled. So
let's figure out how to do item
cancelled, it's going to look
really similar to item bought.
So we'll say let item cancelled
equals item cancelled that load.
Again, we're going to do this
exact same Id get our that we're
doing for everything, we'll say
let active item equals, and I'm
going to zoom out a little bit
less active item equals active
item dot load. Or do this exact
same thing here. Boom. And then
we're gonna say, if not item
cancelled, which there shouldn't
be because this should be the
only item canceled event here.
We'll say item cancelled, equals
new item cancelled. And we're
gonna give it an ID using the
same ID methodology we've been
using. Now this is going to look
a little bit different. We're
gonna say item canceled, that
seller equals event dot params
dot seller. So far, so good.
Item canceled dot NFT address
equals event dot params dot NFT
Address item canceled dot token
ID equals event dot params dot
token ID. And then finally, we
are going to change the active
item a little bit different than
what we've seen. active item
exclamation mark again, ignore
if you're confused by that dot
buyer. And we're going to update
the buyer to equal address dot
from string.
We're going to give it what's
called the Dead address. And
that's this right here.
0x 1-234-567-8910 1112 1314
producing 718 1920 21 to two to
three to 45 to 67 to
8930 3130 230-334-3536 zeros
lowercase d, uppercase E,
lowercase A uppercase D, this is
known as the dead address. And
this is how we're going to
decide if an item is still on
the marketplace or not. Or if an
item has been bought or not. If
we have the dead address as its
buyer, that's going to mean that
the item has been cancelled. And
that's how we are going to be
able to tell that an item is on
the marketplace or not dead
address means it's been
cancelled. An empty address,
which is what will happen for
handle item listed means it's on
the market. And an actual real
address means that it's actually
been bought by somebody. So the
way we can tell if it's on the
market is it's 0x 0000000.
Because the data address is
obviously going to be different
than than all zeros. The data
address is a commonly used
address kind of as a burner
address that nobody owns, then
we can just say, item cancelled
that save an active item that
say active item, exclamation
mark dot save and perfect. Our
mapping file is now completed.
We now have three different
functions to define how to
handle when items are bought
events, how to handle when items
are cancelled event and item
listed events. And if you're
confused, remember all the code
for this is available on this
the graph section of my GitHub.
So you can just follow along
with the code here, if you ever
get lost or need help. And with
that, we're almost ready to tell
our subgraph to start listening
to our contracts, there's just
at least one more thing that we
want to do. So in our sub graph
dot Yamo, we'll see source
address blah, blah, blah, this
is telling us to start indexing
events since the beginning of
Aetherium. Now we don't really
want it to do that, because it
will take a really long time, we
want to tell our subgraph Hey,
you don't just start from
beginning of time, you just need
to start from right before our
contract was deployed. So we can
add what's called our start
block to tell it what block
number to start deploying. Now
if we have our address, which we
do right here, we can copy it,
we can paste it on to the rink
fee, ether scan, paste it in
here, or really any block
Explorer, and we'll see what
block number our contract was
deployed. And it looks like it
was this block. So I'm going to
copy that address, go back to my
code and say starting block,
it's going to be right here.
Starting block is going to be
when it was deployed, minus one.
So we're gonna go right before
we deployed our contract, we're
going to start reading any event
that is indexed from it. Now if
you just deployed this, it might
not have any events in it at
all, which we're going to fix in
just a minute so don't worry,
but with that all the
instructions for how to build
Our sub graphs are ready to be
deployed to the graph, start our
indexing and start working with
our instructions in a
decentralized context. So what
we can do now is back in the
graph, we actually have the auth
and deploy code right here, we
can copy this, this graph auth
dash dash studio, which is our
deploy key on how to deploy. And
we can run this in our code
editor. So we're going to paste
that in here, graph off dash
studio, hit enter. And we're
gonna say deploy key set for the
graph. So this is just setting
us up so that whenever we push
our code, it's going to push it
to this sub graph configuration
that we've made on their site to
help us deploy automatically.
Now we can do, we don't need to
enter the subgraph, because
we've already moved stuff down,
is we'll build the sub graph,
we'll run graph code Gen, we can
just run graph kojem,
which again, is just going to
make sure our schema dot Graph
QL looks good. And then we're
going to run our graph build.
And this graph build command is
going to compile and run all of
our sub graph stuff, everything
in mapping that JSON all our
generated code. And it's going
to put this into a real build
folder, the generated folder has
kind of like a pseudo build
folder. And then we have a real
build folder. So the generated
is just to build some typings
for our TypeScript. And it's
this build folder, this real
build folder, is what we're
going to actually be deploying
and sending to the graph. And we
can actually deploy our
subgraph. Now, with graph deploy
dash s studio. And if the
marketplace, which we're going
to run right now, now is going
to give us a version label
option, which we're going to
give it the 0.0 point one, since
this is our first version, and
it goes ahead and starts
deploying it to the graph, we
also get to upload our sub graph
to IPFS. And we have a little
hash right here for IPFS for a
subgraph that we could look at.
But now if you're successful, we
now have this build completed
thing. And we have these sub
graph endpoints for queries and
subscriptions. So we can
actually start querying and
subscribing to our sub graph.
But if we go back to our site
here now and we hit refresh, we
can now see status deployed, we
can see that we're sinking. And
now we have some nodes that are
listening for our events to be
emitted here, which is
incredibly exciting. We can go
to logs to see if anything went
wrong. And right now it's just
indexing, it's listening. It's
going through all the different
blocks in the blockchain,
listening for our events. And
then we have a playground here
where we can run some queries to
see different events and the
different responses from our
Graph QL, which right now, it's
totally blank, because we
haven't done anything yet. So
once again, let's pull up our
hard hat and ft marketplace
code, or open it up in a new
terminal, whatever you want to
do. And let's go ahead, and
let's run our mminton list
script. But for rink B, so we'll
do yarn, hard hat, run scripts,
mint, and list item dash dash
network Rinkeby. So we're going
to mint an NF T, right, this is
going to be to transaction, so
we're gonna have to wait a
little bit, and then we're going
to approve the NFT. And then
we're going to list it on our
marketplace. And once it's
listed, it's going to emit an
item listed event. And we should
see now we have an active item
and an item listed data in our
Graph QL. Now you can learn more
about now what you see here on
the left hand side is what's
known as a Graph QL query. Now,
we're not going to go over how
to do these, but I'm going to
leave some links in the GitHub
repository. If you want to learn
how to do more of these queries,
these are going to be similar to
what we saw with Morales. But
instead of them being kind of
regular table lookups. They're
in Graph QL syntax, and the
results of our query, end up
being over here, we can see more
information about our schema all
the way to the right over here.
But if we look at our code, now,
we've made the NFT approved it
we've listed it on our
marketplace. So now if we go
back to the graph, and we run
this query, and we do a little
refresh on our NFT marketplace,
we might have to wait a few
minutes for the graph to index
these new blocks. But in our
playground, we should see the
show up as a query. If you don't
automatically get these you can
pause the video to write these
into your Graph QL playground,
right? So after a few minutes,
refresh on ether scan, I can see
that list item transaction has
gone through. This means we've
emitted a new event. So if I
come back to my playground, and
I hit play here, oh my goodness,
we can see we have active items.
And we see we have item listed.
This is fantastic. That means in
a decentralized context, we have
a off chain service that is
indexing our events for our
contract so that we can update
our front end and we can update
people in a decentralized way.
This is so exciting.
Awesome, so now that we have
this all set up, we can finally
go back to our next JS project
or next Jas NFT marketplace the
graph FCC. The reason we did all
this is because right Now in our
code base for our next Jas NFT
Marketplace application, we're
reading from a Morales database,
which we're not going to do
anymore. Instead of reading from
a Morales database, we're going
to read from the graph, let's go
ahead and learn how to update
our code our index dot j, s to
read from the graph instead. So
to highlight this, to show this,
we're actually going to create a
new page, a new file, and we're
just going to call it graph,
example, dot j, s. And we're
just gonna make this a really
minimalistic page to show you
how to do a graph query. So
similar to index dot j, s, we're
gonna do export default graph
example. It's going to be a
function, or default function,
graph example. And we're gonna
use this tool called Apollo
client, copy, paste it over. And
we're going to add it with yarn,
add dash dash dev at a P O ll O,
slash, client, or excuse me, not
Dev, because we do need this on
the front end. So yarn add at
Apollo slash client. Oh, sorry,
we also need to do yarn, add
Graph QL, we need to add both of
those. And it's this Apollo
slash client, which is how we're
going to make queries to our
newly created graph. QL. So
we're gonna say import the use
query hook, from this package we
just installed from at a P, O,
ll o slash client. And we'll
also import G QL. So to create a
new query, we'll say const, get
active item equals g QL. And
we'll add this backtick here.
And we'll add all of our Graph
QL stuff in here, this is gonna
be equivalent to this, this is
Graph QL. Syntax. And we're
gonna be putting this Graph QL
syntax into our code base here.
But we only want to get the
active items. So how are we
going to get the active items?
Well, we can actually build it
over here on our playground
first, and then add it to our
code base. So we'll say we want
to grab the active items, we'll
grab the first five, and then
we'll say where the buyer is
going to be 0x 12345678. We're
saying where the buyer is empty.
So we're grabbing the active
items where there is no buyer,
and then we're going to do and
then we're going to get the ID,
the buyer, the seller, the NFT
address, token, ID and the price
from that. And if we hit run, we
get our active item here. So we
see here, the buyer is this
exact 0x 12345678 Because it
gets defaulted to zero when
there is no buyer. And this is
why for item cancelled, we
updated the buyer to be that
dead address. So if it's bought,
it won't be active anymore. And
if it's cancelled, it also won't
be active anymore. Now we can
copy this query and paste it
into our code. And now we have a
Graph QL query that we can use
for our graph example. Now in
our graph example, we'll use
this query with this use query
hook. So in export default
function, graph example, we can
say const. And it comes with a
whole bunch of stuff like
loading error, and then the data
returned equals, use query. And
then we'll just pass it this Get
active item, or get active
items, let's put an S on it, get
active items. And then we can
just return return a little div.
And we'll say hi in the div, and
then we'll just do console dot
log data. And then now we'll go
back to our app.js, where we're
wrapping everything in a Morales
provider, we also need to wrap
everything in an Apollo
provider. And we need to
initialize it kind of similar to
how we initialize connecting to
our morale server, but we're
going to initialize connecting
to our Graph QL. So we're gonna
say import a P O ll o provider,
a P O ll o client, and in mem
ory, cache from at a P O ll o
slash client, like that, and
then we'll have to initialize
this so we can delete the morale
stuff. We'll initialize this
client by saying const client
equals new a P O LL. O client,
and we'll give it the parameters
here. And you can find this all
in the Apollo client
documentation will say there's
going to be a cache to help when
we do refreshes and stuff we'll
say new in
memory cache, and we'll say
comma URI, a que where we're
going to be connecting. And this
is where we're going to add the
API for our sub graph. So if we
go back to details, we can see
temporary query URL and this is
a rate limited temporary query,
because this is just a test net,
and we're going to copy this, go
back to our code. And we're just
going to paste it in here. So
whatever you have for temporary
query URL, and your sub graph
studio, that's where you're
gonna paste in here. Now, this
client tells our Graph QL, where
it should be making those
queries. And we're gonna make it
to here. Now, this starts with
HTTPS. So is this centralized?
Yes, because we are directly
calling the graph website.
However, all the data is still
gonna be stored in this
decentralized graph indexer. And
kind of similar to what we did
with IPFS, we're doing this kind
of as a gateway to make it a lot
easier for us to connect and
read the data from the graph
studio. However, in the future,
as more protocols and more
browsers adopt the graph, and
IPFS, this will become a lot
easier inside of our Morales
provider, but outside of our
notifications provider, we're
gonna say a P O ll o provider,
and then client equals client.
And then we're going to copy the
closing tag, and put it around
the notification provider and
press Save. Now I'm gonna save
our front end, now we're going
to try to run our front end. And
we're gonna have to change some
stuff in here because it's going
to freak out. So we're gonna run
yarn Dev, for new front end. So
we're gonna go to our localhost
3000. And it's going to totally
freak out, because we still have
some morale stuff in here. And
that's totally okay. We, of
course, we don't need a hard hat
Node running. Because we're on a
test net, we don't need to be
synched with Morales, we don't
need to be doing any of that
stuff. Because we're working
with a test net, right now, it's
actually not freaking out, which
is great. But it shows obviously
nothing for recently listed. So
what we're going to do now is
we're gonna do slash, graph
example, and hit enter. And we
can see Hi, show up. But if we
go to inspect, and we go to
console, a console here, we can
see an object here of active
items, which is returned from
the graph with buyer ID, NFT,
address price and all this stuff
in the air. This is fantastic.
So okay, okay. Okay. So all we
have to do now is we just have
to update. So let's go ahead,
we'll kill our server. For now,
all we have to do is update,
instead of use mirallas query,
we're going to delete this. And
we're just going to query from
Apollo query from our Graph QL.
And everything else stays the
same, right? Because our NFT
box, and all the rest of the
code that we worked with, will
still work exactly the same. So
first, we just got to get our
address. So we're gonna say
import, same as Sell, sell NFT,
import the network mapping, so
I'm actually just going to copy
it. So we're going to import
network mapping from constants,
network mapping dot JSON. And
now we can say const.
Marketplace, address equals, and
we're going to get the exact
same way we did this and sell
NFT to, so we're going to grab
this line getting the chain
string, we'll paste that in
here, which means we're going to
need to get chain ID from user
Morales. And then we're gonna
get the marketplace address like
this. So we're going to copy
that line, paste it in here.
Okay, great. Now we have the
marketplace address. So now
we're just going to do const.
Loading error data, which we can
do listed. And if T is again,
equals, use query, and we can do
that get active items. So what
I'm going to do is I'm going to
create a new file and constants,
we're going to pass that get
active items thing in their new
file, we're just going to call
it sub graph queries, dot j, s.
And then here, we're gonna say
import G QL. From at a Apollo
slash client. And we'll say
const, get active items, equals
g QL backtick. And exactly what
we did in that great, let's go
back to the graph example, we'll
just copy that whole line
actually pasted in here. And now
we'll just do export default,
get active items. And we'll
import this query from sub graph
queries into our index dot j s.
So we'll say import, get active
queries are skimming apt get
active items from dot dot slash
constants slash sub graph
queries. And now in our use
query will pass Get active
items, which should return are
listed NF Ts. So now, we'll
change this from fetching listed
NF Ts to loading, loading, or we
don't have listed NF Ts. So if
it's loading or we don't have
listen if TS then do loading,
otherwise, we're going to do
another mapping, but the return
of the Graph QL is going to be a
little bit different. So instead
of listing MTS dot map, it's
going to be listed NF T's dot AQ
two have items, dot map and f t,
and then we're going to get
price. And if the address token
ID, we're not going to get
marketplace address, but we'll
get seller from NFT. And it's
not going to be returned with
attributes. So we can just do
console dot log NFT instead. And
then we just pass all that stuff
normally to, to that NFT box
exactly the way that we did
before. So really, we're all
we're doing is we're swapping
out the query methodology here,
price is going to be from price
price is going to be from the
query, and ft address is going
to be from the query token ID
from the query marketplace
address, that's also gonna be
slightly different, we're going
to get that from our own config
seller is going to be from the
query, and then the key is going
to be from the query as well. So
now if we save that, if we
restart our website, with yarn
Dev, and we go back to our
homepage, we should see
everything exactly the same,
except for the images being
pulled from the graph, instead
of being pulled from her Alice.
Let's go back to our front end,
we'll give it a nice refresh,
close out the console. And we'll
go to our homepage. And I forgot
to do use query. So let's import
use query, import, use query
from at a Paulo slash client.
Let's save and let's go back and
give that a refresh. And oh, my
goodness, we now have updated to
get our events from a
decentralized data structure.
That's freaking awesome. Now
let's talk about hosting this
real quickly, we are using the
image tag in here in our NFT
box, we are using the image tag
in here from next Jas, which
comes with some pre processing.
So it's a little hard to use on
IPFS. So we would need to update
the way we do images in order to
host this on IPFS. But we still
can do that. Some other options
we have actually are Morales, we
can actually even host our apps
on Morales, if we want. We can
also use things like for cell or
Netlify, or etc, or really any
other traditional centralized
hosting service. Now, if you
want to, I challenge you to
update this code to make it be
able to be hosted on IPFS. So
that you'll have an end to end
decentralized. And if the
marketplace first wanted to make
a PR to this code, so that it
can be successfully hosted
completely end to end on IPFS
wins and empty for me. But wow.
And with that we are done with
less than 15. This is an
absolutely monstrous
accomplishment. And if you
finish this, if you've
understood everything, if you've
gotten through everything so
far, you should feel incredibly
proud of yourself. Because this
is our last full stack section,
our front end section and you're
a full stack monster at this
point. huge congratulations, you
should be super, super, super
proud. And definitely take a
break, go get a coffee, and get
ready for the final stretch of
lessons 1617 and 18. Those are
gonna go by a little bit
quicker. I'm very excited for
you take a break, and I'll see
you there.
Right, welcome to Lesson Six
tene, where we're going to be
going into even more low level
code here. The hard hat upgrades
of course, per usual, our entire
GitHub repository is located
here. And additionally, we have
an optional video that you can
watch. If you want to learn
more, we're actually going to
watch a slice of that video that
explains upgradable smart
contracts. So let's jump in. Now
I'm editing this video much
later after I filmed that, hence
why I have a beard so I'll be
jumping in from time to time
updating some of the sections.
When deploying your smart
contracts on chain. We all know
that those smart contracts are
immutable or unchangeable. But
what if I told you that they
were immutable?
Well, technically, that wouldn't
be correct. However, smart
contracts actually can change
all the time. When people
transfer tokens when people
stake in a contract or really do
any type of functionality. Those
smart contracts have to update
their balances and update their
mappings and update their
variables to reflect this. The
reason that they're immutable is
that the logic itself never
changes and will be on chain
like that forever. So
technically, yes, once they are
deployed, they are immutable.
And this is actually one of the
major benefits of smart
contracts in the first place
that nobody can tamper with or
screw with our smart contracts
once we deploy them. However,
this can be an issue if, for
example, we want to upgrade our
smart contract or protocol to do
more things, or want to fix some
glaring bug or issue that we
have. Now even though we can't
change the specific code that's
been deployed to an address, we
can actually do a lot more than
you think. And in this video,
we're going to explain the
different methodologies behind
upgrading your smart contracts.
And then we're going to show you
how to do it with hard hat and
open Zeppelin huge shout out to
a lot of open Zeppelin and
trilobites articles that helped
me put this video together and a
number of other sources as well
links in the description. So
let's get to it. Now at first
glance, you might be thinking,
if you can upgrade your smart
contracts, then they're not
really immutable that in a way
you'd be right. So when
explaining kind of the different
philosophies and patterns that
we can use here, we do need to
keep Behind the philosophies and
decentralization implications
that each one of these patterns
have, as they do all have
different advantages and
disadvantages. And yes, some of
the disadvantages here are going
to affect the centrality. So we
need to keep that in mind. And
this is why it's so important
that before you go ahead and
jump in and start deploying
upgradable smart contracts, you
understand the trade offs. So
we're going to talk about three
different ways to upgrade your
smart contracts. The first one
being the not really slash
Paramor ties way to upgrade your
smart contracts, the social
migration method, and then the
method that you probably have
heard about, which is proxies,
which have a ton of
subcategories, like metamorphic
contracts, transparent
upgradable, proxies, and
universal upgradable proxies. So
let's talk about the not really
upgrading method, or the
parameterization method, or
whatever you want to call it.
This is the simplest way to
think about upgrading your smart
contracts. And it really isn't
upgrading our smart contracts.
Because we can't really change
the logic of the smart contract,
whatever logic that we've
written, is there, we also can
add new storage or state
variables. So this is really not
really upgrading. But it is
something to think about
upgrades is just parameterizing,
everything, whatever logic that
we've deployed is there, and
that's what we're interacting
with this function means we just
have a whole bunch of setter
functions. And we can update
certain parameters. Like maybe
we have a reward parameter that
gives out a token at 1 percent, every
year or something like that.
Maybe we have a setter function
that says, hey, update that to
2 percent, or update that to 4 percent. It's
just a setter function that
changes some variable. Now, the
advantages here, obviously, this
is really simple to implement.
The disadvantage is that if you
didn't think of some logic or
some functionality, the first
time you deployed their smart
contract, that's too bad, you're
stuck with it, you can't update
the logic or really update
anything with the
parameterization, aka, not
really method. And the other
thing you have to think about is
who the admins are, who has
access to these setter functions
to these updating functions. If
it's a single person, guess
what, you have a centralized
smart contract. Now of course,
you can add a governance
contract to be the admin
contract of your protocol. And
that would be a decentralized
way of doing this. So just keep
that in mind, you can do this
method just need a governance
protocol to do so another
example of this might be a
contract registry. And this is
something actually that early
versions of ABA used before you
call a function, you actually
check some contract registry
that is updated as a parameter
by somebody and you get routed
to the contract, and you do your
call there. Again, this really
doesn't allow us to have the
full functionality of upgrades
here, you can argue that this
registry is a mix of one of the
later versions. But for all
intents and purposes, this
doesn't really give us that
flexibility that we want for
upgrades. But some people might
even think that upgrading your
smart contract is ruining the
decent reality. And one of the
things that makes smart
contracts so potent is that they
are immutable, and that this is
one of the benefits that they
have. So there are some people
who think that you shouldn't add
any customization or any
upgradability, you should deploy
your contract. And then that's
it. trilobites has actually
argued that if you deploy your
contract, knowing that it can't
be changed later, you take a
little bit extra time, making
sure you get everything right.
And there are often less
security vulnerabilities because
you're just setting it
forgetting it and not looking at
it again. Now, if I wanted to
upgrade a smart contract with
this philosophy in mind, the
philosophy that I do want to
keep my smart contracts
immutable, we can instead use
the social migration method,
which I previously called the
Eat method. And now I think it's
less funny. So we're just gonna
stick with social migration, the
social eating method, or the
migration method is just when
you deploy your new contract,
not connected to the old
contract in any way. And by
social convention, you tell
everybody, hey, hey, this new
contract, this new one that we
just deployed? Yeah, this is the
real one now. And it's just by
convention of people migrating
over into using this new one,
that the upgrade is done, hence
my slang name of social yeet.
Because you use the first one
out of the way and move to the
second one.
I think I'm funny. Yeah, this
has the advantage of truly
always saying, Hey, this is our
immutable smart contract. And
this is our new one. This is
really the truest definition of
immutable, because since you
give it no way of being upgraded
in place, than if somebody calls
that contract in 50,000 years in
the future, it will respond
exactly the same. Another huge
disadvantage here is that you
have to have a totally new
contract address. So if you're
an ERC 20 token, for example,
you have to go convince all the
exchanges to list your new
contract address as the actual
address. Keep in mind that when
we do this, we do have to move
the state of the first one over
to the second one. So for
example, if you're an ERC token
moving to a new version of that
ERC token, you do, you have to
have a way to take all those
mappings from the first contract
and move it to the second one.
Obviously, there are ways to do
this, since everything is on
chain. But if you have a million
transfer calls, I don't want to
have to write the script that
updates everyone's balance and
figures out what everyone's
balance is just so I can migrate
to my new version of the
contract. So there's a ton of
social convention work here to
do. trilobites has actually
written a fantastic blog on
upgrading from a v1 to v2 or
etc. With this eat methodology
and they give a lot of steps for
moving your storage and your
state variables over To the new
contract. So link in the
description if you want to read
that. Now let's get to our big
ticket item. So in order to have
a really robust upgrading
mentality or philosophy, we need
to have some type of methodology
or framework that can update our
state, keep our contract address
and allow us to update any type
of logic in our smart contracts
in a easy way, which leads us to
our big ticket item is the
proxies. What's our big ticket
item?
proxies, proxies. Proxies are
the truest form of upgrades,
since a user can keep
interacting with the protocols
through these proxies, and not
even notice that anything
changed or even got updated.
Now, these are also the places
where you can screw up the
easiest. Proxies use a lot of
low level functionality. And the
main one being the delegate call
functionality. Delegate call is
a low level function where the
code in the target contract is
executed in the context of the
calling contract. And message
dot sender and message dot value
also don't change. So you
understand what delegate call
means. Now, right? Great. And in
English, this means if I
delegate call a function in
contract B from contract a, I
will do contracts B's logic in
contract a. So if contract B has
a function that says hey, store
this value in a variable up top,
I'm going to store that variable
in contract a, this is the
powerhouse. And this combined
with the fallback function
allows us to delegate all calls
through a proxy contract address
to some other contract, this
means that I can have one proxy
contract that will have the same
address forever. And I can just
point and route people to the
correct implementation contract
that has the logic, whenever I
want to upgrade, I just deploy a
new implementation contract and
point my proxy to that new
implementation. Now, whenever a
user calls a function on the
proxy contract, I'm going to
delegate call it to the new
contract, I can just call an
admin only function on my proxy
contract, let's call it upgrade
or something and I make all the
contract calls go to this new
contract. When we're talking
about proxies, there are four
pieces of terminology that we
want to keep in mind. First is
the implementation contract. The
implementation contract has all
of our logic and all the pieces
of our protocol. Whenever we
upgrade, we actually launch a
brand new implementation
contract, the proxy contract
proxy points to which
implementation is the correct
one. And routes everyone's calls
to the correct implementation
contract, you can think the
proxy contracts sits on top of
the implementations the user,
the user is going to be making
contract and function calls
through the proxy contract. And
then some type of admin, the
admin is the one who's going to
decide when to upgrade and which
contract to point to. In this
scenario, the other cool thing
about the proxy and delegate
call is that all my storage
variables are going to be stored
in the proxy contract and not in
the implementation contract.
This way, when I upgrade to a
new logic contract, all of my
data will stay on the proxy
contract. So whenever I want to
update my logic, just point to a
new implementation contract, if
I want to add a new storage
variable or a new type of
storage, I just add it in my
logic contract and the proxy
contract will pick it up. Now,
using proxies has a couple of
gotchas. And we're gonna talk
about the gotchas. And then
we're going to talk about the
different proxy contract
methodologies, because yes,
there are many proxy contract
methodologies as well. And this
is why trilobites doesn't really
recommend using upgradable
proxies for your smart
contracts. Because they're
fraught with a lot of these
potential issues. Not to
mention, again, you do still
have some type of admin who's
going to be upgrading your smart
contracts. Now, if this is a
governance protocol, then great,
you're decentralized. But if
this is a single group or
entity, then we have a problem.
The two biggest gotchas are
storage, clashes, and function
selector clashes. Now, what does
this mean? When we use delegate
call, remember, we do the logic
of contract B inside contract a.
So if contract B says we need to
set value to two, we go ahead
and set value to what these
smart contracts are actually
kind of dumb, we actually set
the value of whatever is in the
same storage location on
contract as contract B. So if
our contract looks like this,
and we have two variables and
contract a, we're still going to
set the first storage spot on a
contract a to the new value.
This is really important to know
because this means we can only
append new storage variables and
new implementation contracts.
And we can't reorder or change
old ones. This is called storage
clashing. And in the
implementations we're going to
talk about, they all address
this issue. The next one is
called function select or
clashes. When we tell our
proxies to delegate call to one
of these implementations, it
uses what's called a function
selector to find a function. A
function selector is a four byte
hash of the function name and
the function signature. Don't
worry about the function
signature for now. Now, it's
possible that a function in the
implementation contract has the
same function selector as an
admin function in the proxy
contract, which may cause you to
do accidentally a whole bunch of
weird stuff. For example, in
this sample code in front of you
even though All these functions
are totally different, they
actually have the same function
selector. So yes, we can run
into an issue where some
harmless function like get price
has the same function selector
as upgrade proxy or destroy
proxy or something like that.
This leads to our first of the
three implementations of the
proxy contracts. This is called
the transparent proxy pattern.
And it's actually going to be
the pattern that we're gonna be
demoing to you today. In this
methodology, admins are only
allowed to call admin functions.
And they can't call any
functions in the implementation
contract. And users can only
call functions in the
implementation contract and not
any admin contracts. This way,
you can't ever accidentally have
one of the two swapping, and
having a function selector clash
and you running into a big issue
where you call a function, you
probably shouldn't have, if
you're an admin, you're calling
admin functions. If your user
you're calling implementation
functions. So if you're an
admin, and you build some crazy,
awesome defi protocol, you
better come up with a new wallet
address because you can't
participate. The second type of
proxy we're going to talk about
is the universal upgradeable
proxy, or the
op amps. This version of
upgradable contracts actually
puts all the logic of upgrading
in the implementation itself
this way, the solidity compiler
will actually kick out and say,
Hey, we got two functions in
here that have the same function
selector. This is also
advantageous because we have one
less read that we have to do, we
no longer have to check in the
proxy contract if someone is an
admin or not. This saves on gas,
of course, and the proxy is also
a little bit smaller. Because of
this, the issue is that if you
deploy an implementation
contract, without any
upgradeable functionality,
you're stuck. And it's back to
the Eat method with you. And the
last pattern or methodology that
we're going to talk about is the
diamond pattern, which does a
number of things. But one of the
biggest things that it does, it
actually allows for multiple
implementation contracts. This
addresses a couple of different
issues. For example, if your
contract is so big, and it
doesn't fit into the one
contract maximum size, you can
just have multiple contracts
through this multi
implementation method. It also
allows you to make more granular
upgrades, like you don't have to
always deploy and upgrade your
entire smart contract, you can
just upgrade little pieces of
it. If you've chunked them out.
All the proxies mentioned here
have some type of Aetherium
improvement proposal, and most
of them are in the draft phase.
And at the end of this
explainer, we will do a demo of
showing you how the delegate
call function works. And the end
of the demo is right now. So
let's look at delegate call.
Now, we're going to learn about
how to actually build these
proxies how to build these
upgradable smart contracts. And
to do this, we first need to
learn about this delegate call
function. And it's going to be
really similar to the call
function, which we learned much
earlier. If you haven't seen
that, be sure to go back to our
Harnett. And if T's we have a
sub lesson in there, about EVM,
opcodes, and coding and calling
and we'll give you all the
context for delegate call. Like
I said, in the explainer, it's
very similar to call however,
the way that I think about it is
one contract says Oh, I really
like your function, I'm going to
borrow it myself. And we're
going to be looking at solidity
by example. I'll leave a
description in the GitHub. And
all the code for this will be in
the GitHub associated with this
lesson as well. Now we have two
contracts, we have this contract
B that we're going to be
deploying on remix and it looks
like a real minimalistic real
simple contract. We have a
couple of storage variables
here. And then we have a
function that updates our
values, we have a function
called Set VARs and updates are
you into public num? Now as we
learned before, whenever we have
some type of contract with
storage variables they get
stored in, in this storage data
structure that's index starting
from zero, right now are you
into public num is that index
zero, or sender's at index one,
our values and index two etc.
Now we're going to deploy a
contract a and now this contract
is actually going to use the
delegates call function. Now a
contract a this is going to look
a little bit different, but it's
still going to have this set
bars functions, except it's
going to make a delegate call
function call to our contract B.
Now in our lesson 14 with NF TS
we learned about call API dot
encode with signature API dot
encode etc. So if you're
unfamiliar with function
selectors, if you're unfamiliar
with if you're unfamiliar with
this syntax, be sure to go back
to lesson 14 To understand ABI
dot encode with signature and
contract dot call. The
difference here is we're doing
contract dot delegate call. What
this call does is something very
similar to call. Normally, if we
did contract dot call on this
contract, we would just call
this, we would just be calling
this function set VARs, which
would update contracts B's
storage, but instead we're
saying Hey, call that set VARs
function, and then pass this as
an input parameter, but call it
in our contract, call it on
contract a, we're kind of
borrowing a function for our
contract. And so instead, what
we're going to do, is we're
going to borrow this set bars