and run the set bars function
over here. Now the difference is
instead of num equals num The
variables could be named
different than the variables on
contract a. So instead of num
equals num, our contract is
going to say, hey, whatever that
storage of zero have that equal
to whatever we pass as an input
parameter. And if that's a
little bit confusing, just stay
with me. Let's go ahead and
let's see this in remix. So I'm
going to copy paste this code
into remix here. So we can kind
of test and see what this looks
like. Again, there's a link to
this in the GitHub repo
associated with this course,
feel free to pause the video to
grab this link. It's solidity,
hyphen, by hyphen,
example.org/delegate call, or
you can just grab the code
directly from lesson 16 Hardhead
upgrades. So let's compile this
code. And let me show you what I
mean. So I'm going to compile
it, and we'll go to the Run tab.
And first let's deploy this
contract beam, we'll hit Deploy,
we now have a contract, num,
center and value are all blank,
we'll update the number to
something like 777, we'll hit
Set VARS. Set VARs will change
the storage variable num to 777.
And then we're changing the
sender and the value, sender,
and value is zero. Now let's
deploy contract a. So we'll
scroll back up contract a
deploy, of course, we're on the
JavaScript VM. Now we have this
contract a with num value in
Cinder are also all blank. But
when we call set VARs, it's
going to borrow this set VARs
function from contract B and run
it in contract a, you can almost
think of it as if we're copying,
set VARs and pasting it into our
contract a just for one run, and
then immediately deleting ADM,
that's what this delegate call
function does. So when I call
set VARs, we're going to pass it
this contract address as an
input parameter. So it knows to
call this contract said virus
function. When I pass it the
address, and I pass 987. Since
we're borrowing the function,
we're not going to update this
num. On contract B, we're going
to update the num on contract a.
So when I hit Set VARs, we see
num now has 19. Seven, we see
Senator and we see value still
being zero here, because again,
we're borrowing this function
and running it here. Now the way
that this works, is it actually
doesn't look at the names of our
stored variables, it looks at
the storage slots. So when we
borrow this function using
delegate call, so we could have
this these variables we named
anything instead of num, we
could call this first value.
Senator, we could call something
else. And then value we could
call foo, or whatever you want
here. And when we borrow this
function using delegate call,
instead of grabbing the actual
names of the variables, our
contract will swap out these
variable names with the storage
slot. So it says oh, okay, well,
in contract B, you're accessing
the num variable, which is,
which is at storage slot zero.
So when we borrow set bars and
contract a with Delegate call,
we'll say storage slot
zero is going to equal that
underscore num. Which are this
contract storage slot zero is
first value. So we'll say first
value equals underscore Now,
something else is going to be
stored slot two, so it's gonna
say okay, storage slot two,
we're gonna update storage slot
two to message that sender.
Okay? value here is storage slot
three. So whatever's in storage,
slot three, will update with
message dot value like this. So
that's essentially what's going
on behind the scenes. So let's
go ahead and let's delete those
and redeploy. redeploy them. So
we'll deploy contract be
deployed contract a, right now
in B, once again, if we do 1234,
set VARs, we have 123. And then
contract a. Now even though
these variables have different
names, we could grab contract
B's address, paste it in, do
654, hit Set VARS. And first
value is now six by four. So
delegate call allows us to
borrow functions, and then just
transposes whatever is in here
to the storage location
equivalents. And the other thing
that's interesting is even if
you don't have variables, it'll
still save to storage slots. So
in contract a, if we didn't have
any of those variable names,
storage slot, 01, and two would
still get updated. Now here's
where things can get really
interesting. Let's delete our
contract again. And let's change
the type of our contract A's
first value to from a UNT to a
Boolean. Let's save that. And
now let's deploy contract a. Now
when we call set VARs, on our
contract a, it's still going to
use the Set VARs function of
contract B, which takes a
Yewande and assigns the first
storage slot that number we pass
it, but our first storage slot
is now a Boolean was so what do
you think's going to happen now?
Well, let's try it out. Let's
copy contract B's address, paste
it in here. We'll pass we'll do
tu tu, tu as our input
parameter, we'll hit Set VARS.
Our transaction actually does go
through. And now when we look at
first value, it says true. Hmm,
that's really weird. What if we
change set VARs to zero, and hit
Set VARS. And now, first value
is false. In storage here, when
we add a number with set VARs,
it's going through because it's
just setting the storage slot of
the boolean to a number. And
when solidity reads it, it goes,
Oh, well, first value is a
Boolean. So if it's anything
other than zero, it's going to
be true. So this is how you can
actually get some really weird
results. If your typings are
different, or if your stored
variants are different. What if
we made this an address. So this
is where working with Delegate
call can get really weird and
really tricky, really fast.
All right. Now, with all this
being said, let's turn up the
heat. And let me show you a
small proxy, a minimal proxy
example, that shows how a
contract can be used as a
singular address, but the
underlying code can actually
change. And all the code we're
gonna be working with, once
again, in the hardhat upgrades,
FCC sub lesson, small proxy dot
Sol, and you can go ahead and
copy paste this code if you want
to follow along. So you don't
have to code along with me here.
But you absolutely can if we
want. Now, I will say this is
going to be one of the most, if
not the most advanced section of
the entire course. So feel free
to go ahead and skip over this
sub lesson. If you want to just
move on to learning how to
actually build these proxies,
without really understanding
what's going on behind the
scenes. However, it is still
really powerful if you do
understand what's going on
behind the scenes. So I have
this minimalistic starting
position right here. I have
small proxy is proxy. And I'm
importing this proxy dot sole
thing from up in Zeplin.
openzeppelin has this
minimalistic proxy contract that
we can use to actually start
working with this delegate call.
Now this contract uses a lot of
assembly or what's something
called you'll. And it's an
intermediate language that can
be compiled to bytecode for
different backends. It's a sort
of inline assembly inside
solidity and allows you to write
really, really low level code
close to the opcodes. Now we're
not going to go over you'll but
I'll leave some links to the
you'll documentation if you want
to learn more. Even if you're a
really advanced user, you really
want to try to use as little
EULA as possible. Because since
it is so much lower level, it is
much easier to screw things up.
However, like I said, for this
example, we are going to be
using a little bit of you'll now
in this proxy that we're going
to be doing, we have this
delegate function, which inside
this inline assembly, which is
you'll, it does a whole lot of
really low level stuff. But the
main thing that it does is it
goes ahead and it does this
delegate call functionality. If
we look here, we can see it's
using a fallback function and a
receive function. So whenever it
receives a function that doesn't
recognize it'll call fallback,
and fallback calls our delegate
function. So anytime a proxy
contract receives data for a
function it doesn't recognize it
sends it over to some
implementation to some
implementation contract where it
will call it with Delegate call.
In our minimalistic example
here, we have a function called
Set implementation, which will
change where those delegate
calls are going to be sending.
This can be equivalent to like
upgrading your smart contract.
And then we have implementation
here to read where that
implementation contract is. Now
to work with proxies, we really
don't want to have anything in
storage, because if we do
delegate call, and that delegate
call changes, some storage,
we're going to screw up our
contract storage. The one caveat
though to this, we do still need
to store that implementations
address somewhere, so we can
call it so ERP 1976. It's called
the standard proxy storage slot,
which is an Aetherium
improvement proposal for having
certain storage slots
specifically used for proxies.
And in our minimalistic example
here, we set bytes 32, private
constant implementation slot to
that location in storage. And
we'll say, okay, whatever is
that this storage slot is going
to be the location of the
implementation address. So the
way our proxy is going to work
is any contract that calls this
proxy contract. If it's not this
set implementation function,
it's going to pass it over to
whatever is inside the
implementation slot address.
That's what we're going to build
here. So we have the small proxy
is proxy. And we'll create a
real minimalistic contract. So
we'll say contract employee,
mentation A, and we'll just give
it a U and 256. public value and
then function set value, you add
256 new value, public will say
value equals new value So this
is going to be our
implementation. So now anytime
somebody calls small proxy, or
small proxy contract, it's going
to delegate, call it over to our
implementation, a, and then save
the storage in our small proxy
address. So we're going to call
our small proxy with the data to
use this set value function
selector. So let's make it a
little easier just to figure out
how to get that data by creating
a new helper function, do
function, get data to transact.
And we can get the data using
the API dot encode with
signature that we learned in an
earlier lesson. So function get
data to transact, we'll pass it
a un 256 number to update. So
we'll give this the number we
want to call a new value. We'll
have this be public pure, that's
going to return a bytes.
Memory. And we'll just say
return ABI dot ENCODE. With
signature set value, you went to
56, comma, number to update.
So you'll remember this from our
call anything section. And if
you don't remember how to do
that, remember to refer back to
our NFT section to learn how to
call anything and use ABI dot
encode ABI dot encode with a
signature and call anything with
its raw bytes bring and get the
data to transact. And we know
that when we call implementation
a, from our small proxy, we're
going to update our small
proxies storage. So we'll create
a little function in solidity
just to read our storage in
small proxy. We're gonna say
function, read storage. And this
will just be a public view, will
do returns, returns you into
256, value at storage slot,
zero. And we are going to use a
little bit of assembly here
since we are doing all this low
level stuff. And we're going to
call the s load up code to read
the value at storage slot zero,
we'll say value at storage slot
zero, and we're going to set it
and then in assembly, this is
how we set things, we're going
to set it equal to s load of
storage slot zero, and then it
will return this value here. So
we're reading directly from
storage. Oops, and then we need
a little parenthese here. Sorry.
So now, let's go ahead and
deploy our small proxy. And
let's deploy our implementation
A. Now our small proxy has a
function called Set
implementation. So we're saying,
okay, anytime we call this proxy
contract, we're going to
delegate call the functions over
to here. So we're going to grab
current implementations A's
address, paste it into set
implementation 77. So this is
the data of set value you in
256, with that number to update
encoded in it. So if we call our
small proxy, with this data, our
proxy contract is gonna go, oh,
okay, this is a function. I
don't I don't see that function
here. We're going to call our
fallback, right, which again, is
coming from open Zeplin. And our
Fallback is going to do this
delegate, which is this low
level stuff, but it's basically
just doing a delegate call,
we're gonna call our fallback
function, and then we're gonna
get the function in the
implementation A, we're gonna
borrow this function, and we're
gonna use it on our on
ourselves. So if I copy this,
the implementation has been set
to being this address down here.
So all the logic is going to be
done here. So when I go ahead,
and I grabbed this, and paste it
into call data, and I hit
transact looks like it went
successfully went through. If I
read storage, now, we see that
it is indeed 777, which is
incredibly exciting. Now, this
is incredibly beneficial,
because now let's say we want to
go and update our code, right?
We don't like contract
implementation anymore. So let's
go ahead copy contract
implementation A. And we'll make
a new one called implementation
B. Now, let's say whenever
somebody calls set value, we do
value equals new value, plus
one, or plus two. Let's go
ahead, let's save this. Let's
compile this. And let's deploy
implementation B, we'll grab
implementation B's contract
address, we'll call it onset
implementation in our proxy. And
essentially, we have now
upgraded from implementation a
to implementation B. Now, if we
use this same data here, we're
still going to call set value
was 777. But instead, we're now
delegate calling to
implementation B, instead of
implementation A. So if I call
if I put this data into the low
level call data, and I hit
transact, it looks like it went
through. Now I read storage and
now is 779 since doing value
equals new value plus two so
this is a minimalistic example
of how upgrading actually works.
Now, this is incredibly
beneficial, because we can
always just tell people, Hey,
make all your function calls to
small proxy, and you'll be good
to go. But like I said before,
this also means that the
developers of this protocol can
essentially change the
underlying logic at any time.
This is why it is so important
to be sure to read contracts and
check to see who has the
developer keys. And if a
contract can be updated, if a
contract can be updated, and a
single person can update it,
well guess what, you have a
single centralized point of
failure. And technically the
contract isn't even
decentralized. Now, something
else I was talking about in the
video is function clashes
function selector clashes. Right
now, whenever we call set
implementation, the proxy
function sedimentation gets
called because we don't trigger
the fallback because we can see
the function is here. However,
if I have a function called Set
implementation, in our
implementation, this one can
never be called, whenever we
send a function signature of set
implementation, it's always
going to call the one on the
proxy. This is where the
transparent proxy that we're
going to be working with can
help us out here and the
universal upgradable proxy can
help us to, and I'm not going to
go too much deeper into these
now. But we've left some links
in the GitHub repository to
teach you more about these
selector clashes. And how those
two proxy patterns that I just
mentioned, the transparent and
universal upgradable can get
around these, if you're confused
by anything in here, go into
this discussion thread and make
a new discussion about proxies
make a new discussion about the
Assembly about the you'll set
implementation, this is a great
time to connect with other
people taking the course and ask
questions here, because I know
that this is a really advanced
section, and requires you
haven't gone through a lot of
those sub lessons that we've
gone before. And if it takes you
a couple times of playing around
with solidity and playing around
with remix, I definitely
recommend you do so this is the
section we're seeing really is
believing. And I want you to
jump into remix. And I want you
to test this. And I want you to
play around with this and see
what you can break and fiddle
with. But with all that being
said, we finally have all the
knowledge that we need to build
our hardhat project that deals
with upgrades. So let's go ahead
and jump into it.
Your new terminal, we're going
to do MK dir, hard hat,
upgrades, FCC, CD, hard hat,
upgrades, FCC, and then code
period, or file, open folder,
this folder here, now I'm going
to grab that same yarn add we've
been grabbing from less than
nine, we're gonna paste it in,
we're going to add all of these
different parameters. And once
again, we're going to copy over
our hard hat config from
previous sections, we're going
to copy over prettier. And we're
just going to get our basic
default setup. At this point,
you might have a setup that
works best for you and that you
like better. And feel free to
grab that as well. So I'm going
to paste the prettier is in
here. And I'm going to paste the
hard hat.config.js that we've
been using, instead of running
yarn hard hat. And now we should
be good to go. So let's create a
new folder called contracts. And
in here, we're going to create a
new file called Box dot soul.
And then it's this contract,
that's going to be our
implementation or our logic
contract. So it will say pragma,
solidity carrot zero point 8.7
contract box will say you into
256 internal value will do event
value changed you into 256 new
value, do function store, you
went to 36 value, this will be a
public function will say value
equals new value. So this store
function is going to update our
variable at storage slot zero,
internal, and then we'll just
omit value changed that new
value. And then we'll just
create function retrieve, which
will be a public view returns a
UNT 256 We'll just do return
value. And then we're going to
create a new function called
version. And this will be a
public door. And that returns a
un 256. And we're just going to
have this return one. So our box
contract here is going to be
version one. Now we're going to
copy all this code, paste it
into a box v two dot soul and
rename it to contract box v two,
we're going to update the
version to version two here. And
we're going to create a new
function called increment. And
this will be a public function.
And we'll say value equals value
plus one. And then we will emit
a value changed event with
value. We're going to have one
contract address originally use
the logic in box and then we're
going to upgrade it to the logic
in box V two. And we're going to
learn how to use all the tools
that we've been working with
here to add this logic and
create this logic And let's just
make sure this works, we'll do
yarn, or that compile.
So let's make a readme.md, we'll
say, one, we're going to upgrade
box to box V two. So we're going
to make a proxy contract, that's
gonna point to box. And then
later on, we're going to update
it to point to box V two. Right,
so we're going to start it up
pointing to box, then we're
going to have it point to box V
two. And that's how we're going
to upgrade it, one of the first
things we're going to need to do
is deploy a proxy, we can deploy
a proxy manually ourselves, and
we can build the proxy contracts
and do all that stuff. That's
our first option. Hardhead
deploy also comes built in with
deploying and upgrading proxies
itself, where we can just
specify that we want to use a
proxy. And we could specify the
type of proxy that we want to
use. So number two is just
saying using hard hat deploys,
built in proxies. And then
number three is open Zeppelin
actually has an upgrades plugin,
which allows you to write some
really simple scripts that
allows you to have a really
simple API like upgrades dot
deploy proxy, and then upgrades
that upgrade proxy. Now for this
section, we're going to be doing
the hard hat deploys built in
proxies. However, in the GitHub
repo associated with this, if
you go to scripts, there's other
upgrade examples that will show
you how to use the opens up and
upgrades plugin. And we're not
going to do deploy a proxy
manually manually, because we
essentially just showed you how
to do that in our sub lesson. So
we're going to show you this,
we're going to show you the
Hardhead deploys built in
proxies, and if you want to use
the openzeppelin upgrades
plugin, that is available in the
GitHub repo as well. So let's go
ahead and do this. So we're
going to go ahead and we're
going to make a new folder, or
deploy folder. And first, we're
going to make a new file called
a one, deploy box dot j s. And
this is going to look really
similar to everything we've been
doing so far. So module dot
exports, equals async function,
we're going to get named
accounts and deployments. The
arrow function will say const
deploy COMM A log equals
deployments const deployer
equals await, get named.
Accounts, do a little logging,
like this, and then we'll say
const, box equals await, loi,
box, comma, we'll say from
Deployer, comma, args like this,
we'll say weight con formations
is going to be network dot
config dot block confirmations
for Masons. And yep, we got to
grab const from hard hat. And
then we can add the parameter in
here for proxies. And this is
where we can add a ton of
information. So like I said,
we're going to use the
transparent upgradable proxy
from open Zeppelin, which if we
want to use it, we're going to
have to add open Zeppelin. So
we'll do yarn, add dash dash dev
at open Zeppelin slash
contracts. And we can tell our
hard hat to deploy this box
contract behind a proxy will say
the proxy contract is going to
be the open Zeppelin transparent
proxy. And we're also going to
do a via admin contract. So
instead of having an admin
address, for the proxy contract,
we're going to have the proxy
contract owned by an admin
contract. And doing it this way
is considered a best practice
for a number of reasons. But
we'll name this admin contract,
box proxy admin and the artifact
for this box proxy admin. So
we'll need to create a box proxy
admin contract to be the admin
of our box. So in our contracts
folder, create a new folder
called proxy. And in here, a new
file called Box proxy admin that
saw and this is going to be the
admin contract we're going to
have for controlling the proxy
of our box so inbox proxy admin
dot Saul will do SP DX license.
I then to fire MIT pragma
solidity, carrot zero, point
8.7,
say contract, box proxy admin,
like this, right? And once
again, we're going to use one of
the open Zetland tools in the
transparent folder. They have a
proxy admin dot Saul, which is
going to be essentially what our
box proxy admin is going to be.
It has some functionality, it
has some functions in here like
change, proxy admin, upgrade,
upgrade and call for dealing
with upgrades. All contracts. So
we're going to import it will do
import at open Zeppelin slash
contracts slash proxy slash
transparent, slash proxy admin,
dot soul. And we'll say our
Brock's box proxy admin is proxy
admin, like this. And to have
this box proxy admin work with
the heart at deploy plugin, our
constructor needs to take an
address owner as an input
parameter, but we're just going
to leave that blank. And then,
and then we need to do the proxy
admin, which is just going to be
blank as well. And that's it.
That's all we're going to do box
proxy admin contract, which just
has all of the functionalities
to do upgrades and change proxy
admin and all this stuff. We're
going to deploy our box contract
behind a proxy and opens up and
transparent proxy that is owned
by our Brock's proxy admin
contract in the template
Aetherium contracts. GitHub repo
is actually an examples slash
opens up on proxies branch that
will show you how to work with
different types of proxies. And
there will be a link to this in
the GitHub repo associated with
this course. And then we'll do
our verification, say, chains
dot includes. And we'll go
ahead, I'm going to copy paste
our hard hat helper config from
our last project, which has
development chains, hard hat and
local host that we export, will
import this as well. const
development chains equals
require dot slash helper hard
hat config. If development
chains dot includes network dot
name, and process dot env dot
ether scan API key log,
verifying that the same as we've
done a way to verify last, we're
going to copy over our utils
folder. So just copy, paste, we
now have verify, which will
import it in here. So we'll do
const verify equals require dot
dot slash utils, slash verify,
await verify box dot address.
And then args is going to be
blank. So we'll just do blank
here, and boom. And that's going
to be it for our box deployment.
So we can test this out by
running yarn Hardhead deploy,
see if everything works here.
And that's it done. And then we
should do actually, we should
add log beach true as well.
Let's run this again, much
better. So you can see we
actually deploy a couple of
contracts. So we deploy our box
proxy admin, which is going to
be our admin contract, then we
deploy box implementation. So
hard hat deploy, went ahead and
took our box contract and
renamed it to box implementation
and then deployed it, then it
deployed our box proxy here. So
anytime we call this address, it
actually will point to the logic
of our box. Now what we can do
is we can write a deploy script
to deploy box, the box v2
implementation, and then upgrade
our box to box V to create a new
deploy script called Zero to
deploy box v2 dot j s or deploy
box two dot j s. And we'll do
something really similar here.
Right, so I'm just going to copy
pretty much of this, paste it in
here. Now we're going to do
const box v two equals await,
deploy. Box v two, comma, from
Deployer. Log True RMS blank,
weights confirmations, it's
going to be network dot config
dot lock.
Or masons, then I'm going to
copy the verification code, copy
this, paste it here, server,
this is going to be box v2 dot
address. Okay, great. So we now
have some code where we can
deploy box and box v2. Now let's
go ahead and write a script to
actually upgrade these. So we'll
do a new folder, scripts. New
File, and we'll call it upgrade
box dot j s. Now we're going to
do it the manual way here. And
the reason we're going to do it
the manual way is because I want
to show you exactly the
functions that we're calling to
do this upgrade process.
However, hard hat deploy also
comes with an API to make it
really easy to actually just
upgrade your box contracts. This
is gonna be script. So we'll
start off with async function
main. And then we'll copy paste
our traditional script, main dot
then process exit blah, blah,
blah, that whole thing. We're
first gonna get the box proxy
admin contract. We'll say box
const. Box, proxy admin equals
await ethers dot get contract,
box proxy admin and we got to
import you Here's from Hardhead,
then we're going to get the
actual proxy, which is our
transparent proxy. So we'll say
const transparent proxy equals
await ethers dot get contract,
box underscore proxy. Since hard
hat deploy, we'll just name the
proxy the name of the
implementation underscore proxy.
And then of course, we're going
to need our box V to contract.
So say const. Box v two equals
await ethers dot get contract,
box V two. Now we can say const,
upgrade TX equals a weight box
proxy admin, that upgrade. And
we're going to call the upgrade
function on our box proxy admin,
which calls it on our
transparent proxy, which will
change the implementation from
box one to box two. So box proxy
admin, that upgrade, we're going
to upgrade the transparent proxy
dot address to our box B to that
address, it will look in our box
proxy, a box proxy has an
upgrade function which calls
upgrade to on our transparent
upgradeable proxy will do a
weight upgrade TX dot wait one.
And now to work with the
functions on our box v two,
we're gonna say const proxy box
equals await ethers dot get
contract. At box v two, we're
going to get the box v two ABI
however, we're going to load it
at the transparent proxy
address. This way ethers knows
okay, we're going to call all of
our functions on the transparent
proxy address. But this proxy
box is going to have the ABI of
box v2, which is what we want.
Now we can say const version
equals await proxy box dot
version. And we'll say console
dot log version. And if we want
to compare this to its original
implementation, before we
upgrade, we can do the same
thing. We can say const proxy
box v1, let's actually call this
proxy box V to say cost proxy
box v one is going to be this
exact same thing
equals this call box here. And
we'll do const version equals
weight, right proxy box v1 dot
version, console dot log
version, or version v1, version
v1. We'll call this version v
two, version v two, and proxy
box V two. So we'll get our
version v one will upgrade. And
then we'll see at that same
address what the version
function now returns. So let's
open our terminal. If I run
yarn, our head node will spin up
a node will have deployed our
admin our implementation, our
proxy, and then our box V to
implementation. I'll make a new
terminal. And I'll run yarn,
hard hat run scripts upgrade box
that J S dash dash network,
local host. And we should see
that box actually update. And
that's exactly what we see. And
then let's do well, it's I
forgot to do.to string in here.
But it goes from version one to
version two on that exact same
address. And with that little
code, we have successfully
learned how to upgrade our smart
contracts programmatically. Now,
like I said, in the GitHub repo
associated with this lesson, you
can also check out the upgrades
plugin from open Zeppelin. So to
work with that, you would just
do upgrades dot deploy proxy
proxy to call the Prepare
upgrade function, and then
upgrade upgrade proxy just like
that. They also have an upgrade
tutorial, step by step for
hardhat that you can follow
along with as well. Now I know
this was an advanced section.
And I know we went a little bit
quick here. But honestly, if you
just finish this section, not
only have you completed all
these other sections that make
you a really powerful smart
contract developer. But you've
learned some really advanced
stuff here. We've gone into low
level code like delegate call,
we've gotten to assembly we've
gotten to you'll we've gotten to
these proxy patterns, which can
really make you a an incredible
stand out developer in the smart
contract space. So if you just
finished this section, you
should be so so proud of
yourself because we went really
fast and because there's a lot
of advanced information here.
Now, like I said, 100 percent, be sure
to go into the discussions tab
and ask questions and connect
and talk to other people in the
area. Maybe look at the already
running discussions and jump in
and start asking other students
and start asking other people
about what they've learned and
how their proxies are going. And
if they made anything really
cool. If you're just excited and
you want to go to the show and
tell section, make a show and
tell me like hey, here's my
GitHub repo for doing this
upgrade section. going here and
be excited with that being said
go and take that coffee break go
take that walk go to the gym go
get excited Go tell your friends
we are almost done we have two
lessons left and then you're
home free
All right, welcome back to
lesson 17 For hardhat. Douse,
you're almost done. Now for this
section, I've actually already
made a video on how to code a
dowel with TypeScript and
solidity in JavaScript. So we're
actually just going to play this
video for this section. The
reason we're going to display
this one is because I did a lot
of work to make this one look
really good. And it's still
incredibly up to date. So this
is going to be in TypeScript and
solidity. However, we're going
to have the JavaScript edition
of the code base in this code
from the video section. If you
want the most up to date version
of this delta template code, you
can use, you can select this up
to date code, which goes to this
doubt template repo. I'll be
updating this repo periodically
with new Dao examples and new
ways to create doubts or
decentralized autonomous
organizations. Now, before we
learn how to code a doubt, we
should learn what the DAO is.
And again, I've already made a
video that I've put a lot of
work into. So we're going to
watch what a Dow is from a high
level first, then we're going to
learn how to code a Dow. And
then our last section is going
to be security and auditing. And
we're going to finish this out.
So Bucklin, let's learn what a
Dow is. And then let's go ahead
and build a Dow, let's do it.
Now, daos for decentralized
autonomous organizations is a
bit of an overloaded term. But
it typically describes any group
that is governed by a
transparent set of rules found
on a blockchain or smart
contract. And I say overloaded
because some people say bitcoin
is down because the miners can
choose whether or not to upgrade
their software. Other people
think that Dows must use
transparent smart contracts,
which have the rules ingrained
right into them. And then other
people think Tao is just a
buzzword, so they just slap the
name relay on to any
organization so that they can
get some clout. And this makes
for sad, Patrick. And it's not
to be confused with the Dow,
which was an implementation of a
Dow back in 2016, which set the
record for the largest hack at
that time. So there's a lot of
different ways to think about
and the Dow term is used in a
lot of different ways. But in
essence, imagine if all of the
users of Google were given
voting power into what Google
should do next. And the rules of
the voting was immutable,
transparent, and decentralized.
This solves an age old problem
of trust, centrality and
transparency, and giving the
power to the users of different
protocols and applications
instead of everything happening
behind closed doors. And this
voting piece is a cornerstone of
how these operate this
Decentralized Governance, if you
will, and it can be summarized
by company or organization
operated exclusively through
code. And to really understand
all this, we're going to look
under the hood of the protocol
that's setting the precedent for
all other doubts and compound,
then once we look at compound,
we'll understand what goes into
building one of these and all
the trade offs, all the
different architectural choices
mean for your group. And then in
my next video, I'm gonna have a
full coat along tutorial for
developers looking to build one
of these themselves. But be
absolutely sure to watch the
rest of this video because it's
going to give you all the
architectural fundamentals. So
you can make intelligent
decisions when you get to that
section. And be sure that you
and your Dow friends smash the
like and subscribe button. So we
can keep giving you the best
engineer first content on the
planet when
it comes to smart contracts.
Let's get into it. So here we
have the compound protocol. It's
a borrowing and lending
application that allows users to
borrow and lend their assets.
And everything about this
application is built in smart
contracts. Now, oftentimes,
they're gonna want to do a lot
of new things, maybe they want
to add a new token to allow
borrowing and lending, maybe
they're gonna want to change
some of the API parameters,
maybe they're gonna want to
block certain coins, there's a
lot of different things that
they might want to do. So that's
where we're gonna go ahead to
governance, this is where you
can find a user interface for
list of all the proposals and
all the different ballots that
came to be. So here's a list of
some of the governance proposals
that this protocol has actually
been making to improve. And
let's look at one of these
proposals that's currently
actually in process. So if we
click on the proposal, we
actually see everything about
this proposal, who voted for who
voted against and the proposal
history here. Now, the first
thing to one of these proposals
is somebody has to actually
create the proposal in a
proposed transaction. And we
actually see that proposed
transaction right here. If we
click on this, and we scroll
down, we can actually see the
exact parameters they used to
make this proposal. Let's go
ahead and decode the input data.
And we can see this is exactly
what this proposal looks like.
The way that they're typically
divided is they have a list of
addresses and the list of
functions to call on those
addresses. And then obviously,
the parameters to pass those
addresses. So this proposal is
saying, Hey, I would like to
call Support Market on this
address, set reserve factor on
this address. Here are the
parameters we're going to pass.
They're obviously encoded with
bytes. And then here's the
description string of what this
is doing and why we're actually
doing this. The reason we have
to do this proposal governance
process is that these contracts
likely have access controls
where only the owner of these
contracts can actually call
these Do functions, and the
owner of these two contracts is
likely going to be this
governance style. And values.
Zero just means that we're not
going to send any eath along
with these transactions, once a
proposal has been created, after
a short delay to becomes active,
and this is when people can
actually start voting on them,
this delay between a proposal
and an act of vote can be
changed or modified, depending
on your doubt, then people have
some time to start voting on
them. And if it passes, which
this one overwhelmingly did, it
reaches succeeded, we click on
this transaction again, and we
go to the compound governance
contract. And we scroll down to
contract, right as proxy, we can
actually see the exact function
that the people call to vote,
namely cast by vote, cast, vote
by signature and cast vote with
reason. We'll talk a little bit
about the exact differences
between these in our next video.
But these are the functions that
they're actually calling. And if
you go to the compound app, and
we go over to vote, this is a
user interface you can actually
vote through to make it easier
if you're not as tech savvy. So
you can vote right through this
app dot compound at finance. Or
you can just send the
transaction yourself. Once all
those votes happen. It reaches
this queued stage. Now what is
queued mean? Well, before a
proposal actually becomes
active, there's a minimum delay
between a proposal passing and a
proposal being executed. So
somebody has to call this cute
function. And it only can be
called if a vote passes. And it
says, OK, that postal ID has
been cued, and we're going to
execute it soon. Now, if we go
to a different proposal, like
this one, for example, we can
see it has been executed, we can
see somebody called this
executed function. And they
executed Proposal A detail. So
this is going to be a full
example of the lifecycle of a
proposal going through this
process. Now there are a couple
that even failed, a whole bunch
of people voted against this.
And if you scroll down, you can
see it was created, it was
active, and the majority of
people voted against. So that's
where it stops. Now oftentimes,
just putting one of these
proposals through isn't enough
to really garner some votes for
it, you generally want a forum
or some type of discussion place
to talk about these proposals
and why you liked them or don't
like them. Oftentimes, a
discourse is one of the main
places that people are going to
argue for why something is good,
or why something is bad. So
people can vote on these
changes. And again, snapshot
might be one of these tools that
you use to figure out if your
community even wants something
before it even goes to vote, you
can join one of these, and with
your tokens actually vote on
things without them being
executed just to get the
sentiment or like I said before,
you could build your protocol in
a way that snapshot actually
helps you with the voting
process. All right, now you've
seen the protocol that has been
influencing all the other
details on how to vote. Now, you
know, now that we know what a
doubt looks like,
let's talk about the
architecture and tools that go
into building one of these and
additionally the trade offs that
they have. And the first thing
to talk about here is going to
be the voting mechanism. Now
voting in Decentralized
Governance is critical to these
days, because sometimes they do
need to update and change to
keep up with the times. Not all
protocols need to have a Dow,
but those that do need to have a
doubt need a way for the
participants to engage. This is
one of the most important
questions to ask him to tell
your communities. How do I
participate? How do I engage in
this doubt? How do I help make
decisions and you'll find this
is a bit of a tricky problem to
solve. Now, an easy approach to
this problem is going to be
using an ERC 20 or an NFT token
as voting power. Similar to what
we saw with compound use the
comp token to vote for different
proposals seems simple enough,
right? Boom, problem solved
gray. Now, this actually might
be the right approach for
certain doubts. But it also runs
the risk of actually being less
fair. Because when you tokenize
the voting power, you're
essentially auctioning off this
voting power to whoever's got
the deepest pockets, whoever has
the most money gets to pick the
changes. So if it's only the
rich people who get to vote,
then it's highly likely that all
the changes in the protocol are
going to benefit the rich, which
doesn't really seem like that
great of an improvement over our
current world. And if T's are
interesting, because they have
this non fungible component, but
yet, even they still run into
this issue. Additionally, if you
buy a whole bunch of votes, you
make a bad decision and then
sell all your votes. You as an
individual don't really get
punished, you just punish the
group as a whole. But you being
malicious, you can get away with
pretty scot free now again, this
voting mechanism is going to be
correct for some groups, but for
other groups, maybe not. It
really just depends on what your
down community setup is going to
look like. Now the next one
we're going to talk about is
skin in the game. Now metallic
has actually written a lot about
this and I highly recommend you
read his article, link in the
description to see that the skin
in the game method means that
whenever you make a decision,
your vote is recorded. And if
that decision leads to a bad
outcome, your tokens are axed.
You get punished for making evil
or bad decisions for your Dao
and your protocol. I like this
mentality because even if you
buy a ton of tokens and decide
to be ill with it, you can be
held accountable for your bad
decisions. Now, the hardest part
about this, though, is gonna be
how do we decide as a community?
What is bad outcome? How do we
actually punish these people?
And that's easy, because the
answer is, I'm not sure. Now,
the third method of this voting
mechanism is probably one of the
most interesting ones, but also
the hardest ones to implement.
And this is proof of personhood,
or participation. Imagine that
all users of the compound
protocol were given a single
vote simply because they use the
protocol. And even if they had
1000 wallets, they use the
protocol. One human being means
one vote, this would be amazing,
and a far more fair
implementation where votes
couldn't actually just be
bought. The issue, however,
comes in something known as
civil resistance, how can we be
sure that it's one vote equals
one participant and not one
participant pretending to be
1000s of different people, so
they get more votes. This method
hasn't really been solved yet.
But I'm willing to bet some very
clever engineer will do some
amazing chainlink integration,
because proof of personhood is
basically just off chain data
that can be delivered on chain.
And that's exactly where
channeling shines. Now, as you
can see all of these methods and
even more that you probably
think of aren't that far
fetched. And we actually see
these exact same methods
happening in the real world.
Proof of personhood or proof of
participation might just be the
exact same as kind of the
regular government voting that
we see every day. In the United
States, at least one person gets
to vote for one president, you
can't go around making a whole
bunch of fake people and voting
for president. But in companies
the ERC 20 voting standard kind
of applies, the more shares of a
company you have maybe the more
voting power you have in that
company. So we can draw
parallels between the real world
and how voting and governance is
going to work in our smart
contracts. And in fact, you
should draw parallels and look
for inspiration from the web to
space. Now when it comes to
implementation of the voting, I
put them into two categories on
chain voting and off chain
voting on chain voting is
exactly what we saw with
compound, the smart contract on
chain, your voter, you call some
function called vote with your
meta mask your ledger or
whatever, send a transaction and
vote, you voted Congrats, you
can wear your little sticker now
call that function and you send
a transaction, you send a
transaction, what are the
transactions use that are kind
of annoying and kind of costly?
Oh, that's right gas, I imagine
you have 10,000 people in your
community and it costs $100 To
vote per person, you're now
costing your community $1
million. Anytime you want to
change anything. This is
obviously insane, and not very
sustainable for your community
pro here is that the
architecture is really easy.
Everything's going to be
transparent, everything's going
to be on chain. And that's
really good. But yes, the con is
that you're going to break the
bank account for a lot of people
potentially. Now there are a lot
of variations of this to help
solve some of these problems,
especially the gas problem. One
of the ones that I'm incredibly
excited for is this one called
governor's seat, where they use
some random sampling to do some
quadratic voting to help reduce
costs while increasing civil
resistance. You want to learn
more about that one to be sure
to read about it in the
description. So on chain voting
is the simplest one here. But
let's talk about off chain
voting. To cast the vote off to
decentralized context, relax,
relax, you can vote off chain
and still have the 100%
decentralized, you can actually
sign a transaction and sign a
vote without actually sending to
a blockchain and therefore
without actually spending any
gas. Instead, what you can do is
send that signed transaction to
a decentralized database like
IPFS, count up all the votes in
IPFS. And then when time comes,
deliver the result of that data
through something like an Oracle
like chain link to the
blockchain all in a single
transaction. Alternatively, what
you could do is you could replay
all the same transactions in a
single transaction to save gas,
this can reduce the voting cost
by up to 99%. Right now, this is
an implementation and one of the
most popular ways to do this is
through snapshot. And I'm just
dying for someone to make a
chain link integration because
it's going to be so much safer,
more secure and better and blah,
blah, blah, die for it. This is
your call to action go build
this thing. This option. voting
mechanism obviously saves a ton
of gas to the community and can
be a more efficient way to store
these transactions anyways,
however, it needs to be
implemented very carefully. If
you run your entire Dow through
a centralized Oracle, you are
essentially reintroducing a
centralized intermediary and
ruining the decent quality of
your application. So don't do
that. And if you made it to this
point of the video, give
yourself a little pat on the
back. You're doing fantastic.
Fantastic. Like I said, I have a
video coming out after this one
it's going to show you end to
end how to build one of these
from scratch let's learn about
some of the tools that you can
use to help get you up to speed
quicker. Now there are a number
of no code solutions that can go
into building one of these
dowels Tao stack Aragon. Just
kidding, this is Aragon, colony
and Tao house are all
alternatives that can actually
help you with the upside of
running a Dao and building a
doubt. However, if you want more
granular control and you don't
want to have to pay any the fees
associated with these protocols,
you might want to Do it from
scratch. Now let's talk about
some of the more Cody solutions
that you can use snapshot is one
of the most popular tools out
there for both getting the
sentiment of a Dao. And actually
performing that execution, users
can vote through this protocol
with their actual tokens, those
transaction gets stored in IPFS.
But none of it actually gets
executed. Unless the doubt
chooses to, this can be a great
way to get a feel for what your
Dow wants to do. And Optionally,
you can send the transactions
and execute the votes as well
highly recommend checking out
Zodiac which is a suite of
database tools for you to
implement into your Dallas as
well tally is another one of
these UIs that allows people to
see and actually vote and
interact with these smart
contracts through user
interface. So those of you who
don't know about Gnosis safe,
you absolutely should know Safe
is a multi SIG wallet. And the
reason I put this on the list,
even though it's adds kind of
this centrality component is
that most dowels in the
beginning, are probably going to
start with some type of
centrality, it's much easier to
be fast when you don't have
1000s of people to wait for a
vote. And in the beginning, any
protocol is going to be
centralized to some degree
anyways, using a multisig, we're
voting happens through only a
few key members can be good in
the beginning for your dials,
and often emergencies as well.
But just keep in mind, when you
add one of these, you are adding
this level of centrality, and
then of course opens up and
contracts we love opens up and
contracts. These are the
contracts that we're going to be
basing our Dao code along.
Alright, so that's all the
tools. That's the architecture.
One more thing before I let you
go legality, the future of Dows
is interesting for all these
reasons we just talked about,
but especially on a legal front,
does it make sense for a doubt
to live by the same regulation
as another company? Why would
you even force it down to do
something, you'd have to enforce
them to all vote a certain way
if the government tells you to,
it's a little gray, it's hard to
nail down who to even keep
accountable for these days and
the United States at least you
can actually form your own Dow
and have it legally recognized
in the state of Wyoming. This is
something I want to do. So we'll
just have to see what happens
there. Oh, at this point, you
have been injected with all the
Dow knowledge you need to
succeed and thrive with this new
amazing technology and these new
amazing concepts. And I found
them kill baby. All right, well,
you heard him it's time to
build. Like we said, All the
code is going to be located in
less than 17 Here, let's jump
in.
In this video, we're going to
show you how to build your own
doubt inspired by compound now
this is going to be 100% on
chain voting and on chain
governance. We're going to show
you the easiest way to spin up
an NFT or ERC 20 voting type
down all using solidity and
hardhat. Now if you haven't
watched my last video going over
the architecture of Dows, what
goes into one of these be
absolutely sure to watch that
video first and then come to
this video. Because that video
explains all the philosophy
behind what we're doing here
we're going to be using opens up
and contracts and a hard hat
framework to build this all in
solidity. If you want to see a
brand new or Pythonic version of
doing this, check the link in
the description because we did a
video over at the chainlink
hackathon recently. And
additionally, additionally, we
know that because we're doing
this 100% on chain gas fees are
going to be expensive. So I'm
really looking forward to
somebody doing a chain link plus
IPFS plus snapshot integration
so that we can do all this off
chain. And once that exists, you
already know I'm gonna make a
tutorial on that. And if you
like this style of content, be
sure to smash that like button,
subscribe and leave a comment in
the comment section to let me
know what you want to see. Next,
let me know how you want to
supercharge your smart contract
developer experience. So let's
jump in. Right, so here's what
we're going to be building,
we're gonna have a very basic
smart contract here, right, it's
called box and all it can do is
store a value and then retrieve
a value. But the thing is, its
ownable. And only the owner of
this contract can call the store
function and guess who the owner
is going to be the owner is
going to be the doubt. So only
through a process of governance,
can anyone store a different
function here. And once we're
done, we're going to go through
the entire process of proposing
voting queueing and then
executing a transaction in a Dao
to update our Bach contract. And
that's one of the beautiful
things about these these Dao
setups is that they're
completely modular, right. And
so when I go through the whole
process, I'll do Hardhead tests
here, which my tests right now
are set up to just do
everything, we're going to see
every single step that this Dow
is going to take. So we see box
starting value is going to be
zero. And then all of this stuff
is going to the governance
process. These are just some
some notes. Basically people are
voting, queueing and executing.
And then at the end, we chained
the value of the box contract
through a voting process. And
that's exactly what we're gonna
show you how to do today. Now
remember all the code for what
we're going to be doing here is
in my doubt template GitHub repo
so if you ever get lost, feel
free to refer back to this to
get started. And additionally,
if you want to see the Pythonic
version of this, feel free to go
back to the downmix The main
thing is though that all the
contracts are going to be the
same no matter what brownie hard
hat, dab tools, foundry, it
doesn't matter. So the first
part of this section is gonna be
exactly the same. And here's our
agenda here. First, we're gonna
write the smart contract. So if
you're not familiar with
Hardhead, who cares, we're gonna
be doing the smart contracts
first, then we are going to
write deployment scripts. And
this is where your hard hat
knowledge is going to come into
play. We're going to be writing
our deployment scripts in
TypeScript here, because
TypeScript is phenomenal. If
you're unfamiliar with
TypeScript, I challenge you to
rewrite this in JavaScript and
make a JavaScript version. And
then finally, we're going to
write some scripts to interact
with our governance with our
deployed contracts. Now, a quick
note, this isn't how I
originally built this, I didn't
just read smart contracts, write
deployment scripts, write the
scripts, and then the tests and
boom, I was done, I had a back
and forth between tests, smart
contracts, deploy scripts, etc.
If you're thinking, Oh, my
goodness, that's so easy for him
to go through this. So
seamlessly. When I originally
wrote this code, it was a lot of
back and forth. And that's how
you should be developing, you're
going to be moving between tests
and smart contracts and stuff.
Additionally, in this tutorial,
we are going to show you some
sick Hardhead skills. So you are
not only gonna learn how to
build a Dow, but you're gonna
learn some really advanced
Hardhead skills. So let's jump
in. Let's do this. So the code
editor I'm using is Visual
Studio code. So make sure you
have a code editor up and ready
to go. And you'll need a couple
of prerequisites here. Again,
the prerequisites are in the
GitHub repository, we're going
to need Git, no J, s. And yarn,
if you want to just clone this
repo and follow the instructions
here to get started, you
absolutely 100% can and then you
don't even need to build this
from scratch. But we're going to
want to learn to build this from
scratch. So let's just start git
dash dash version. Great, we
have Git no dash dash version.
Great, we have node, and then
yarn dash dash version. Great,
we have yarn, we can get
started. So everything that
we're going to be installing
here for packages is going to be
a dev dependency. So the first
thing we need to do is do yarn,
add dash dash Dev, hard hat,
if you'd haven't already. And
now in our folder, we're gonna
have node modules package dot
JSON readme and a lock. Of
course, now that we have that we
can run yarn RDAP, we're gonna
get the hard hat CLI up. And
we're going to have all this
stuff in here, we're just going
to create an empty hardhat dot
config dot j s, and we're going
to turn it to TypeScript. The
advanced sample TypeScript
project has a bunch of stuff
that I don't like. So we're just
going to create an empty
hardhead.config.js. And perfect,
we've got a little hard
hat.config.js. Now let's go
ahead and create a folder, or
contracts folder. And this is
where we're going to add all of
our contracts. So the first
thing contract that we're going
to need is the contracts we want
to have govern, which in our
case is going to be box dot
soul. Now, I am actually just
going to copy paste my box, that
soul here, because it's not
particularly interesting. But
you could really code whatever
you want here. So feel free to
pause the video, copy paste from
my GitHub repo, create your own
governance contract that you
want to play with, or do
whatever you want here. But for
us, we just have a store
function, and retrieve function,
and an event, and then a private
value that we're going to be
storing and retrieving. And
that's it. So of course, we want
to fix this. We're importing
from openzeppelin contracts
opens up is amazing. We're gonna
want to add this we'll do yarn,
add dash dash Dev, at opens up
on contracts. And that should
get rid of the box. That's all.
let's reopen box. And boom,
looks like we did a detour to
that perfect. And for
extensions, I'm using the
solidity, the one Blonko, slit
extension. And that's what we
get this wonderful linting
things here. Great. So now we
want to check to see if this
compiles if using remix, you can
compile with remix hard hat,
you're gonna see how we compile
here. Or if you're using you
know, Browning, we just want to
see if this compiles correctly.
So run yarn had a hard hit
Compile. Looks like we ran into
some compilation errors, because
we need to update this, let's
use these 8.8 of solidity we'll
try to compile again. And
perfect looks like we're
compiling successfully. Look
here, we do indeed have our
contract in here. Okay, perfect,
easy part out of the way.
Already. That was so quick. Now
let's start creating the next
part. Let's create the
governance part. So what we're
going to be working with to
build this governance platform
is we're gonna be building it
off of the ERC. 20 standard, so
you're gonna get an ERC 20
token. And that's going to be
the token that you get to vote.
So let's create a new file
called governance token. That's
all governance token dot Sol.
And this is gonna be the code
for the token that we use to
actually vote. Now we're going
to create a normal ERC 20 token.
And then we're going to extend
it to make it governance a bowl
and you'll understand what I
mean in a second. So let's go
ahead and make this spdx license
identifier. It's going to be MIT
pragma solidity we'll do zero
point 8.8. And then we'll do
contract governance token, and
then we'll say is ERC 20 I'm
just gonna go ahead and import
openzeppelin Because open
Zeppelin has a package where
basically has everything we need
for an ERC 20 token. So we're
gonna say import at open
Zeppelin slash contracts slash
token slash ERC 20x We can go to
their github openzeppelin
contracts token, your C 20 And
we'll do ERC 20 Dotto, we'll do
this for now.