token, use your C 20 ditzel.
We're gonna change this, but
don't worry about that yet. Now
we're going to do a un 256
Public Storage Max supply, it's
the best practice, but it's
fine, we'll give this a max
supply this much was going to be
1-234-567-8910 12345678. So it's
gonna be 1 million, we're gonna
do 1 million of these tokens.
And then we're gonna create the
constructor construct or your C
20. Give it governance token as
a name, and then our symbol is
going to be GT. And for those
who who don't know, when you
inherit another contract in your
constructor, you can use that
inherited contracts constructor
as well. In fact, I think you
have to So governance token G
team, and then we'll even call
one of these ERC 20 functions
called mint. And we'll mint to
message dot sender, so whoever
deploys this ERC 20 contract
will just meant them everything,
the whole Max supply. Now
normally, if this was a normal
ERC 20 token, you'd be all done.
But this isn't a normal ERC 20
token. See, when we do votes, we
need to make sure that it's
fair, imagine this for a second,
someone knows a hot proposal is
coming up, they want to vote on.
So they just buy a ton of
tokens. And then they dump it
after the votes over. We want to
avoid this. We want to avoid
people just buying and selling
tokens to get in on governance.
So what we do is we actually
create a snapshot of how many
tokens people have at a certain
block snapshot of tokens people
have at a certain block. And we
want to make sure once a
proposal goes through, we
actually pick a snapshot from
the past that we want to use
this kind of incentivizes people
to not just jump in when it's a
proposal and jump out because
once a proposal hits, it uses a
block snapshot from the past. So
we're actually going to need to
change this a little bit. We're
gonna change this from ERC 20 to
an ERC 20 votes, and we can
actually see this in open
Zeppelin and the extensions
slash ERC 20 votes that soul
contract. If we go back to IRS
to their GitHub, we can see ERC
20 votes, they also have a
snapshot, which is pretty
similar. And some of the main
functions are it has these
checkpoints. So these
checkpoints are basically Hey,
what is the snapshot? There's a
number of checkpoints, you can
also delegate your tokens to
different people. So maybe
you're not going to be available
to actually vote. So you say,
Hey, I'm gonna give my tokens to
somebody else. You can get how
many votes somebody has passed,
votes get passed, or was apply
it has all these functions that
make this token, much better as
a voting tool. Right makes it
much much better. So we're gonna
say our contracts governance
token is ERC 20 votes and we
just have to add additional
constructor, this ERC 20 permit,
I'm sorry, I kind of copied
pasted that. So ERC 20 permit
governance token. And right now
we have a governance token that
is a little bit more capable of
doing actual voting, right,
because as the snapshot has this
delegating functionality, it has
these checkpoints, it's going to
be much better for doing votes
in a fair way. The only thing
that we need to do though, is we
need to add some overrides,
right. And we're just gonna say
the functions below our
overrides required by solidity.
And this part is a little bit
boring. So I'm just going to
copy paste it, feel free to copy
paste it from my GitHub. But
what we're doing is anytime we
do this after token transfer,
and the time we transfer a
token, we want to make sure that
we call the after token transfer
of the ERC 20 votes. And the
reason that we do this is
because we want to make sure
that the snapshots are updated,
right, we want to make sure that
we know how many people have how
many tokens at each block. Same
thing with the mint. Same thing
with burning, we want to make
sure we always know how many
tokens people have at different
blocks or can be at different
checkpoints I should say. And
that's the most important bit at
which checkpoint Are you going
to use for your token voting. So
cool. Feel free to copy that,
again, from a GitHub or if you
want you can even just try the
rest of the tutorial without
this and see how you fare. But
cool. So now we have a
governance token and ERC 20
token that we can use for
governance. So let's try to
compile it. Yarn Hardhead
compile. Great, looks like
things are compiling
successfully. Perfect. So our
governance token looks good. Our
box looks good. Let's actually
now start creating our
governance contracts. Now we're
actually going to make a folder
called governance standard
because this is going to be the
standard governance model. This
is going to be this on chain ERC
20 and I plan on updating this
in the future with no a
governance off chain or
something right. So for now,
we're calling a governance
standard because this is the
quote unquote standard way to do
governance, but in the air,
we're going to need two
contracts actually, we're gonna
need a government work, contract
that soul and then we're also
going to need a time lock that
soul and this will make sense in
a second. So our gov contract
dot soul, this is going to be
the contract that has all the
voting code, all the voting
logic that our governance token
is going to use, the Time Lock
is actually going to be an
additional contract that is
actually the owner. So the Time
Lock and the governor contract
are sort of one in the same, but
the difference is the Time Lock
is actually going to be the
owner of the box contract. And
this is important because
whenever we propose or cue
something to a proposal to go
through, we want to wait, right?
We want to wait for a new vote
to be executed. Now, why do we
want to do that, let's say some
proposal goes through, that's
bad. So like, let's say we have
a box contract. And then a
proposal goes through that says,
Everyone who holds the
governance token has to pay five
tokens, or something like that,
right, or whatever, or who
knows, right? Maybe that's
something that you don't really
want to be a part of. So all of
these governance contracts give
time to give time to users to
get out, if they don't like a
governance update. So we always
want to have some type of
timeline. So once a proposal
passes, it won't go in effect
right away, it'll have to wait
some duration, and then go in
effect. So that's what the
timeline is gonna be for.
Governor contract is going to
have all of our actual code. Now
we can cheat a little bit.
Actually, we can cheat a lot of
a little bit. So opens up one
has a thing called the contracts
wizard, and there'll be a link
to this in the description as
well. And this opens up when
wizard is a way for us to write
really basic boilerplate code
right in there wizard. So right,
so if we go to the wizard
contract here, we can see we can
make an ERC 20 and NFT 1155. And
then finally, this gov thing
here. So we can call it give it
a name, we're going to call Rs.
Gov contract, during explain
what all this means, and give it
a voting delay, which is the
delay since a proposal is
created until voting starts. So
once you create a proposal, you
gotta wait a little bit, the
voting period, how long votes
should go for. And the reason
that this audio is important is
because they actually do votes,
voting period in terms of
blocks. So it's an anti pattern
to actually do timed based
things in smart contracts, it's
much better to do block based
things. So we're saying one
week, but it's that's going to
be you know, if if the average
block time is 13.2 seconds,
we're gonna figure out the weak
proposal threshold is going to
be the minimum number of votes
and account must have to create
a proposal. So maybe you only
want people who have a lot of
your governance token to make
votes quorum percentage, it's
what percentage of people need
to vote it all. So we're saying
4% of all token holders need to
vote or we could say you know,
exactly 100 tokens need to vote
whatever we want to do here. We
also have some updatable
settings we have Bravo
compatible Bravo is the compound
type contract. So if you want to
make it integratable, with
compound you can do that. Votes
comp like or ERC 20 votes, we're
working with this ERC 20 votes,
we always want to do a time
lock, we're gonna do the open
Zeplin implementation of a time
lock, you could also do a
compound implementation, we
aren't going to do upgradability
here, however, I have a number
of fantastic resources on how to
actually do upgradability. And
if we did want to do
upgradability, it adds all this
other stuff. We're not going to
do that for now because it makes
it so much longer video, and
then you can add some stuff like
this, but Oh, so that's pretty
much it. And I know this feels
like you're cheating, or we're
just going to copy this whole
thing, right? Copy all that
stuff that we put in copy to
clipboard, and we're going to
paste it in. Don't worry, I'm
gonna explain what's going on
now. So we have our government
contract. And this is governor
Governor setting Governor
counting simple Governor votes,
Governor votes, quorum Franco,
all this stuff. All these are
just implementations to make it
easier to be governor, Governor
counting simple is a way of
counting votes, Governor votes
is a way of integrating with
that year's 20 contract. Quorum
fraction is is a way to
understand quorum time lock.
Obviously, it's time lock. This
is going to be the base
contract. That's gonna be some
settings. And we're gonna talk
about this in a minute. But
let's go over what are the
functions here so we have voting
delay. This is exactly the
voting delay, which we're gonna
do superdad voting gelei, we're
gonna get from this governor
settings contract that we're
going to set in a minute your
voting period that we're going
to set in our gov settings,
which is this one right here.
And again, if you want to like
look at all these contracts, you
absolutely can, right, if we go
to contracts, governance,
extensions, we have all these in
here, right? So if we look at
governance settings, we can see
it has voting delay voting
period, proposal threshold, and
those are right in its
constructor. And that's exactly
what we're setting, right. We're
setting voting delay voting
period, and then the proposal
threshold, and then we're also
going to make this customizable
as well. And the rest of these
that's exactly what doing
calling the quorum from the
super get votes. And then again,
the super is those inherited
contracts, get the state and
then we have some interesting
functions we have proposed. This
is what we're actually going to
do to propose new governance we
have proposal threshold, and
then we have execute which
executes a cued proposal. To
cancel, we have executor which
we're is going to be who can
actually execute stuff, we're
actually going to make it
anybody and then supports
interface, you can basically
ignore. But let's make this a
little bit more customizable. So
we have Iboats token, this is
going to be our governance
token, the timeline controller
timeline, this is going to be
the timeline controller that we
make an amended. And again, we
need this because we don't want
to let any proposal just go
through once it passes, we want
to give people time to get out.
But let's add the UN 256 voting
delay as a parameter here. And
for voting delay, we're going to
do this, we're going to set it
as our governor settings, we're
going to do a UNT 256 voting
period. And we're going to add
that right here. And this means
45,000 blocks is approximately
one week. And that's what that
means we're going to leave
proposal threshold to zero
because we don't really want to
change that we want to let
anyone make a proposal. And then
we're just going to add you in
256 underscore core
percentage to this. So Governor
votes quorum percentage
corporate senators. So now this
is completely customizable, for
voting, delay voting period,
core percentage for whatever you
want it to be. And believe it or
not, that's it. Now you have a
simple governance contract.
Thank you, openzeppelin, for
doing 99% of the work for us. So
that's it. So this contract,
it's going to have all these
functions that we're going to go
over for proposing for executing
and for queuing, different
proposals. Right. Now we got to
make a time lock contract here.
And this contract is actually
going to be a lot easier. So
we're just going to do it from
scratch. So we're going to spdx
license I then to fire, my team,
do pragma solidity and let's
just do this your point a point
zero, and then we're going to
import from open Zeppelin, a
contract called the Time Lock
controller. So if we look at the
governance here, if this time
lock controller dot soul
contract, and this has all this
functionality in here for
creating roles, who can actually
propose who can execute, who's
the Time Lock admin, but it also
has these execute stuff in here
as well. It's gonna work in
tandem with our governance
contract, right? This is the
contract that says that makes
sure our governance contract
doesn't just push stuff through
willy nilly. So we're gonna say
we're gonna first import that
import at open Zeppelin slash
contracts slash governance slash
Time Lock controller. That's all
and then we're gonna say
contract, I'm lock is Time Lock
controller like that. And we'll
create our little constructor
here, and truck door. And this
because this takes a couple
different parameters, we're
gonna take a un 256 Min delay,
which are min delay, Min delay
is going to be along you have to
wait before executing. So this
is Hey, once proposal passes,
great, we gotta wait this
minimum delay, then we're going
to do a list of proposers, an
address array memory of
proposers. And then the
proposers is the list of
addresses that can propose for
us, we're just gonna say
everyone's gonna be able to
propose. And then last, an
address array, memory of
executors who can execute
everything, and we're just gonna
say executors who can execute
when a probe posle passes. And
again, we're just gonna say
everybody, and the reason we
need these is because we need to
pass these to our time lock
controller, this constructor is
expecting three parameters. So
we'll just do Tama controller,
delay, pro posers, X EQ, tours.
And that's it. So this is going
to be what owns everything, it's
the timelog, that's going to be
owning our box. It's not the
government contract, the
government contracts is where
we're going to send our votes
and stuff. But at the time lock
that actually everything needs
to flow through in order for
governance to actually happen,
because we want to make sure we
have this min delay, we go
through the right process and
everything. And believe it or
not, that's everything. That is
all the code you're going to
need as far as the solidity
goes, to create a governance to
create a Dao. So even do your
own hard hat compile, make sure
everything's compiled. And tada,
we've done it, you've done most
of the hard work. Now we're
going to flip over to actually
writing the scripts to deploy
and to interact with everything
using TypeScript here. At this
point, if you're like, Oh, I
already learned everything that
I wanted, I don't use hard hat,
I use some other tools. This is
where I challenge you to go out
and I challenge you to try
something else. Now if you've
reached this point, I just want
to give you a huge congrats,
because you have taken the steps
to build your own doubt build
your own governance model.
That's all the solidity that you
really need. You can take that
deploy that and you're good to
go. But of course, we know that
there's more to being a smart
contract developer than just the
solidity you got to do the
tooling right to let's go ahead
and we'll jump into writing
those TypeScript scripts to
actually do this. And again, if
you want to see a Python version
of this, go check out a link up
description to see the Pythonic
version of this. And of course,
don't forget to smash that like
button, subscribe, leave a
comment on how you're doing so
far. And, of course, give
yourself a pat in the back.
Great job. You're doing amazing
getting this far. Congrats,
let's jump in.
Alright, so we're back here,
we've written our smart
contracts already, check wasn't
that easy, right, this was way
easier than I thought it would
be. Now we're just gonna write
our deployment scripts, and then
we're gonna write our scripts to
interact with them. Again, my
full repo also has tests, but
we're just gonna write some
scripts. And then feel free to
check out the tests yourself. So
let's write those deployment
scripts to we're actually going
to be using a package for
deployment called Hard Hat
deploy. It is absolutely
phenomenal for hard hat for
making your deployments much,
much easier. We're gonna scroll
down to installation, and we're
actually gonna go ahead and
install this. So typically, you
could install it like this.
Well, we're gonna use yarn, but
we're gonna do kind of the more
safe way which looks a little
wonky, but I'm explaining it
right. So instead of NPM
install, we're gonna do yarn,
add dash dash Dev, and then this
whole thing right here. So we're
gonna do yarn, add dash dash
Dev, and then just paste that in
here. So this is gonna be at
nomic, labs slash hard hat,
hyphen ethers at NPM, colon,
hard hat, deploy ethers. And
what this is doing is we're
basically saying hard hat deploy
ethers is going to be overriding
this hardened ether thing. And
we're also going to add ethers
as well. And then once we add
this in, check our package json,
we can see we have hard hats. We
have hard hat ethers, which is
being overwritten by this hard
hat, deploy ethers. And then
additionally, we're going to
want to add on a deploy. So do
yarn, add dash dash Dev, hard
hat hyphen, deploy. And what
this is going to allow us to do
is instead of having to write
scripts, and do all this stuff,
that kind of makes it hard to
save your deployments and
everything, we're going to just
create a deploy folder, where
we're going to add all of our
deploy scripts in here. So I
absolutely love this package.
It's makes deployment really,
really easy. So in here, we're
gonna create new file, it's
going to do oh one, we're gonna
go step by step deploying
everything, we're gonna call
this deploy, govern or token dot
TypeScript, that's gonna be the
first thing we're going to do.
Also, we're gonna change this to
TypeScript. Tada, we now have
TypeScript. Yay. Now the one
thing that is kind of nice about
doing kind of that advanced
TypeScript thing at the heart
had kind of gives it the
beginning, is you don't have to
install all the TypeScript stuff
yourself. But we do. So we're
going to do yarn, add TypeScript
type chain, vs node at type
chain slash ethers, V five, this
is a lot of stuff, don't worry
type chain slash hard hat, at
type slash Chai, at type slash
node. And then we'll make sure
this is all Dev, dash dash Dev,
I know there's a lot of stuff.
There's all this stuff to make
it TypeScript D.
You can absolutely do this in
JavaScript if you want. You just
have to do JS files and ignore
the typing. So But feel free to
do whatever you want to do.
Alright, cool. And we should be
okay here. Let's go into our
governor token here. And we'll
create a deploy script. So the
Hardhead deploy GitHub repo has
a little demo boilerplate code
for you actually do your deploy
script. So feel free to
reference here if you lost or
confused. So what we're going to
do is we're going to import the
hard hat runtime environments,
from our enhanced slash types.
And you'll see why we need this
in just a second. And then we're
also going to import deploy
function from Hardhead. Deploy
slash types. And these are the
two main things you need to
create a deploy function with
pothead deploy, we're going to
create our function, we're going
to call it const ploy governance
token, it's going to be of type
deploy function. So in order for
these to actually work, we just
create a whole bunch of deploy
functions that we run with heart
hub. And this is going to be an
async function. That's going to
take the hard hat runtime
environment as an input
parameter that we're going to
call HRV. So when we run hard
hat deploy, which you'll see in
a second, we're actually passing
our fake hard hat chain that
gets spun up in the background
for us, right, we can even do
like console dot log Hello. And
if we do yarn, hard hat deploy.
Actually, before we even do
that, if we do yarn, hard hat
dash dash help, you'll see,
since we imported hard hat
deploy up excuse me, we need to
add this to our config. First in
our config, we're gonna need to
do top imports, hard hat deploy
top Roscoe need to import at
nomic labs slash hard hat
ethers, we're also going to need
to import at type chain slash
hard hat. And then we'll leave
it there for now. We'll have to
import more stuff in a second
but literally like that. Now, if
we do yarn hard hat that should
help we should see a new task in
here. And we do we actually see
a ton of new tasks right? Filled
with tasks, check clean compile,
console deployed. And this is
the new task that we have that
actually deploys all of our
contracts, anything that's in
this deploy folder, our head
will go ahead and run right now
in our deploy folder. All we
have is this console dot log
Hello. So if we run yarn, or hit
Deploy, we should See, it just
prints out hello. It'll spin up
a new blockchain background,
while all of our projects and
everything, do some type type
chain stuff, and it says you'll
see this a lot deploy script dot
func is not a function. And
that's because we actually need
to export this now. So we'll do
export default, deploy
governance token. That's why
it's getting mad at us. Now
we'll run yarn had her hard hat
deploy. And boom, we say hello.
So this is how we can actually
deploy all of our scripts. And
we can run everything that's in
this deploy folder in one go,
which is really helpful. So
let's go ahead and deploy our
governance token first. And this
will get a lot faster as we go
along. Don't worry, so delete
this. And first we're gonna do
it, we're gonna say const. We
need an account to deploy this
first. So we'll say const, get
named accounts, deployments, and
network equals HRA. And this is
going to be a little bit more
advanced. This is hard stuff.
This is this is the slick stuff
we're doing here, we're getting
these from our hard hat runtime
environment, which is being
updated from hard hat deploy. So
get named accounts is way for us
to actually import accounts from
our hard hat config, right into
our deploy script. So we're
gonna go to our hard hat config.
And we're gonna create a new
config that's a little bit nicer
than this. So first, we need to
import the hard hat config type.
Since we're using type scripts,
we're going to import hard hat
user config from hard hat slash
config. And we're going to
create a config. So I'm just
gonna comment this out. For now
we're gonna say const. Config,
it's gonna be type hard hat user
config. Equals, and this is
where we can add a whole bunch
of stuff. So let's say our
default network is going to be
hard hat, which is kind of our
local fake blockchain. And then
we're gonna say solidity is
zero, point 8.8, then we're
going to do this thing called
named accounts, which is what we
came here in the first place
for. So this is just a list of
accounts that we can use. So for
accounts, we'll say Deployer,
this will be the name of our
account that does all the
deploying, and we'll just say,
default, is going to be zero. So
whenever we run an any chain,
our zero with account is going
to be named Deployer. What other
thing that we need to do is we
need to add our networks here.
And there's actually two
networks that we're going to
have, we're gonna have a hard
hat with a chain ID of 313337.
And we're also going to have
local hosts of chain ID 31337.
Now, these look like they're
pretty much the same. And I
understand that, but they're
not. And you'll understand why
in a second, but we need them
for now. Just to tell Hardhead
hey, here are the development
fake blockchains that we're
working with? Okay. So this is
kind of our basic setup here.
Okay. I know that was kind of a
lot. But now that we have get
named accounts, we have network,
right? Because anytime you
deploy something, it's going to
be on a network. And when we
deploy something, if you run
yarn, hard hat node, what hard
hat is going to do, it's going
to spin up a fake blockchain in
the background. Oh, it's gonna
be mad at me for a second. Oh,
I forgot to add export, default
config, right, we need to export
the config. Hell hard hat that
we're using this version of
sling. Now if you're on a hard
hat node, you'll see why we
added these two networks up here
hard hat on localhost, we
actually get spun up our own
fake blockchain, we get
accounts, we get private keys,
we get everything right. This is
a hard hat Node running in this
terminal, right? When you run
hard hat node, oddly enough,
it's actually the local host
network. It's not the Hard Hat
Network. When using hard hat
deploy, it's gonna be the local
host network. Or excuse me, when
you use hard hat node, it's
actually going to be the local
host network, not the Hard Hat
Network. The Hard Hat Network is
what it uses when it runs tests.
localhost is when you run this
hard hat node and have this kind
of fake blockchain running in
your terminal. So that's what
the localhost is. Cool. Well,
Ctrl C will kill that. Alright,
great. So now stuff is actually
working. So get them to count
deployments is going to be a
whole bunch of stuff from
deployments, you'll see in a
second and network is the
network that we're on. Okay,
great. So now we're gonna grab
const deploy log equals
deployments, this deployments
object comes with this deploy
function. And this log function,
this log function is kind of
nice for doing logging. And then
we're gonna grab const, employer
equals await, get named
accounts. So we're grabbing from
our config, this deployer
account, right? And it's always
going to be the zero with index.
So it's defaulted to the zero
index for whatever accounts that
were with. Great. So we now have
an account to deploy stuff from
we have a deploy function, we
have all this stuff, we're
looking pretty good. Cool. So
sometimes they'll do like a log,
flying governance token, dot,
and we'll say const governance
token equals await, deploy, and
then the name of the contract
which is governance token,
comma, and these are all the
parameters that we're going to
pass to it. So we're gonna say
from deployer doesn't take any
arguments. So args is just going
to be blank. We're going to do
log to be true so we'll get some
logs printed out for us. And
then I have this wait
confirmations attribute set in
GitHub repo. For now we're going
to ignore this. But if you
follow along with my repo and
you want to auto verify stuff,
this is something that you're
going to want to use. So you
need to wait some amount of
blocks for this contract to be
deployed before you can actually
go ahead and verify it, right.
Because if you're using ether
scan or something, you're gonna
need to wait like, yeah, you're
gonna need to wait a few
minutes. So check out my GitHub
repo for this wait confirmation
stuff, I'm just going to ignore
it for now. Additionally, in my
GitHub repo, I have this verify
function, where we check to see
if it's on a development chain.
And if it is, we don't verify
it. But if it's on like ether
scan or something, we go ahead
and verify it. So be sure to
check the GitHub repo to learn
how to just auto verify without
having to do anything. Now if we
just do this part. And then we
can even do Floyd, governance
token to address governance
token dot address. And we'll do
yarn hardhat. Deploy. Boom. So
we spin up on a fake Hard Hat
Network, we do deploy governance
token to address boom. And this
is how we deploy a fake has
deployed this to our own little
network here. Great. So this
tokens been deployed, we have
our deploy script. Yeah, zoom
out a little bit. Let's zoom out
a little bit. Great. That's the
whole thing. Now we're going to
add one more thing here, we're
going to add something called
delegate function. Now, when you
actually deploy this contract,
nobody has voting power yet. The
reason is, because nobody has
the token delegated to them, we
want to delegate this token to
our Deployer. Right, so we're
going to call this delegate
function. So we're going to
create a new function called
const. delegate. And it's going
to be an async function. It's
going to take a governance token
address as a string, it's going
to take a delegated account,
also as a string, so we're
racing and say, who do we want?
Delegate? Who do we want to be
able to vote with our token?
Okay, so we have created this
async function called delegate.
And how do we do this? Well, we
say Kant's over its token equals
token equals await ethers dot
get contract at.
And probably for two ethers for
us from hardheaded Otto did
that, which is great. That's
what we want. Once it's like
ethers. Thank you vs. Code away.
Ether is like a contract at. And
we're going to say we want our
governance token, which is at
contract, governance token
address. And I have auto format
unsaved, which is why it keeps
formatting like that. This
should be delegated account.
Okay, cool. We have our
governance token contract. Now
we can do const TX or
transaction equals await,
governance token dot delegate
delegate this delegated account
here. And then we can do a wait,
we'll wait for this transaction
to be confirmed by one block.
And then we'll just do console
dot log checkpoints, wait,
governance token dot num
checkpoints delegated account?
So what is this doing? So we
have this num checkpoints
function which we can go check
to see on that ERC 20 token what
this is actually doing. But
basically what this whole thing
is doing, we have this delegate
function that we haven't used
it. But when somebody calls us,
we're saying, Hey, you can use
my vote, take my votes and vote
however you want. And that's
what these this delegate does.
Now, if we look at this token,
here, see 20 extensions, your
see 20 votes, we look at number
checkpoints, we can see how many
checkpoints that account
actually has reason this is so
important is because once again,
like I was saying when people do
a vote, they do it based off
some checkpoints. And anytime
you transfer a token, or
delegate a token, basically call
this function move voting power,
which happens with the back end,
which writes the checkpoint and
says, Hey, at checkpoint x,
here's what everybody has for
voting powers. And that's what
these are so important. And I
know I said before, it's every
block, but it's actually just
every checkpoint, whenever these
checkpoints are updated, that's
gonna be a lot cheaper on gas
than if we just did every single
block, right? That'd be kind of
insane. So the checkpoint for
this governance checkpoint, and
we'll see what that actually is
in just a second. So we'll even
do a wait, delegate, governance
token dot address, and Deployer.
And we'll say log delegated.
Now, when we're on this
function, John Howard hit
Deploy. We have one checkpoint,
which makes sense, right?
Because this was just deployed,
it was just delegated. This
address has one checkpoint.
That's it. And the reason I
checked for this is because if
you see zero checkpoints here,
it means you haven't delegated
correctly. So be sure to check
for checkpoints. But that's it.
We have our deployed governance
token contract done. Bravo.
Let's move on to the next one.
So what do we want to do after
we deploy our governance token?
Well, let's deploy that timelock
or timelock.ts. And we're going
to copy a lot of this stuff over
from here, so I'm actually going
to Oh, and then sometimes you'll
get some weird linting errors
here. I just do det TS ignore
there. And sometimes you'll get
it here too. Oh, actually, we
don't even need network. Okay,
cool. Yeah, you don't even need
network loops. Sometimes we get
some weird linting errors.
Sometimes Vyas code has a hard
time telling understanding like
this, this overwrite thing that
we did. So just run that TS
ignore if if it gives you some,
some engineers, anyways, yes, we
have this Oh, to deploy time
lock here, we're going to deploy
our time lock contract. And
we're going to borrow a lot of
the things that we did from
here, so I'm just going to come
back here are actually going to
copy paste these two top bits.
Again, we're gonna do const
deploy timelock is going to be a
deploy function, it's going to
be an async function that takes
the heart at runtime environment
as a parameter, and cool, nearly
exactly the same sorry. And then
we're going to grab these first
three lines, or first four
lines, I guess, pesos, then
we're going to be getting those
exact same things here. And
we're going to be doing nearly
the exact same thing. So we'll
do log deploying. Time Lock,
point time lock, will do const.
Mark equals await, deploy,
unlock. We'll add some
parameters in here, we'll say
from Deployer. Now does this
take some arguments? It
absolutely does. Right, we can
take a look at the Time Lock,
Min delay proposers and
executors. So what do we want
our min delay to be? Well, this
is a value that we're actually
going to use a lot. So what I
usually like to do is I create a
new file called helper. hardhats
config.ts. And right at the top,
I'll say Export const min.
Delay, and I'll have this delay
be whatever I want it to be. So
let's just go ahead and do 3600,
which is going to be
approximately an hour, right,
you gotta wait this many
seconds, I think that's an hour.
Without the old calculator.
There's 60 seconds, in 60
minutes. Great. That's gonna be
one hour. So wait 30 minutes.
And we're gonna go ahead and
import that here. We'll say
import, Min delay. Wow,
autocomplete for being great.
From helper from, you know, it's
down directory, helper Hardhead
config. And that's gonna be our
first argument here. Our second
argument is going to be a list
of proposals. Now we're going to
leave it blank for now. And also
the list of executors we're also
going to leave it blank for now,
we're going to update this in a
minute. And you'll see why once
we get there, we'll do log true.
This also has a wait
confirmations thing in my
GitHub, but we're going to skip
that for now. It also has an
auto verify, we're also gonna
skip that for now. Then we just
need to export default, deploy
timelock. And boom, we should be
good. So let's try to run this
on hard hat deploying. So now
this should run both of these
great deployed governance token
deployed timelock.
Perfect, we are cruising now
what we want to deploy that
governance contract now. So
let's go ahead and do that.
We're gonna do Oh, three LOI.
Gov, nor contract.ts. And you
guessed it, this is going to
look pretty similar to what we
just did. Right. So in our
deployed time lock, let's go
ahead and just grab those top
two things. We'll paste it in
here. We'll do const deploy,
govern or contract, there's
going to be an apply function,
it's going to be an async
function, taking a part at
runtime environment, save and
close this for now. And we can
even go back and grab these
three lines from our Oh, to
deploy time lock, paste that
right in here, because we're
going to need to get the exact
same things. And additionally,
for this, we're going to need to
get the governance token and the
Time Lock contract. So we'll do
const governance, token equals
await. Get which actually, we
have this, this get function
that comes from these
deployments, which literally
just goes out and gets these
deployments. So we'll say get
Gover Nance token. And then we
also need to get the Time Lock.
So await, get m lock. And we
need these to pass as parameters
for our governor contract.
Right? Because if we open up the
governor contract that soul, we
look at the constructor, it
takes the token, the Time Lock
voting, delay voting period and
quorum percentage as input
parameters. So we'll do a quick
log deploying go burn nor ello.
And they will do const govern
nor contract equals await,
deploy, and will deploy the
govern nor contract I'm not sure
if I'm spelling this right
always, but that's fine. And
we'll do the parameters once
again. So it's gonna be from
Deployer. args are going to be
this list of args. What's the
first thing that it needs? It
needs the token first and the
Time Lock. So we'll do
governance token dot address,
then it's going to need the Time
Lock that address. And it's
going to need a vote on voting
delay voting period and quorum
percentage. So these are also
values that we're going to make
a lot. So let's open back up
that helper Hardhead config, and
let's create those as well. So
we'll say Export const just
voting period. And we'll say
this is going to be five blocks,
we'll do export const voting
delay, this is going to be just
one block, which I know is
really quick. And then we're
gonna need export const Orem
percentage, which we're gonna
say is four 4% of voters always
need to be voting. Excuse me, 4%
of voters need to have voted for
a vote to pass. Great. So we're
going to do voting delay voting
percentage quorum percentage. So
we'll import those so to import
voting delay voting period, or
quorum percentage from helper
Hardhead config. And now that we
have those delay period
percentage, we can just do kind
of a voting delay, voting
period, farm percentage, and
then we'll say log is true.
Again, this one as well. It has
a wait confirmations and auto
verification that we're going to
totally ignore. And then we'll
export default, blood Governor
contract. Oh, Carrie, we're
getting spicy. Let's just make
sure this works. Yarn hardhat
deploy. We should see three
contracts deployed here. I think
to compile governance, token
deployed timelock deployed
governance contract deployed.
Let's go. Alright. Now, we're
not done yet. We have two more
deploy scripts to do. The first
one, we're going to call setup
governance contracts. Okay. And
this one's really important. The
right now our time lock contract
has no proposers and no
executors. Right. So we want to
change that we want to only
allow for the proposer to be the
governor, the governor contract
should be the only one that
proposes things the Time Lock,
and then anybody should be able
to execute the way that this
works. We say the governance
contract proposes something to
the Time Lock once it's in the
Time Lock, and it waits that
period. Anybody can go ahead and
execute it. So Governor contract
everybody votes and everything.
Once a vote passes, Governor
says hey, Time Lock, can you
please propose this? Tom like
goes yeah, sure. But we got to
wait, this minimum delay, once
it's been in delay happens,
anybody can execute it. Now this
would be really cool to do an
integration with chain link
keepers, by the way, for the
chain link keepers to
automatically execute. And I
should build the next anyways.
So we have to set this up so
that these work as such, so
we're gonna create a new deploy
thing called Oh, four, setup,
governance contracts dot
TypeScript. And this is going to
be the code that does all the
setting up. And this is gonna
look really similar once again,
to all of our other deploy
functions. So we'll go head back
from oh three, we'll paste these
two top ones in here, of course,
we're gonna do const setup
contracts, is it going to be a
deploy function, going to be an
async function, it's going to
take HRV art at runtime
environment as parameters, and
then that's the winner right
there. Cool. And we're gonna be
grabbing those same three from
the top, as you can see, that
gets a little bit easier,
because it's kind of repetitive,
right, we're gonna grab that bit
right here. And now we're gonna
get those contracts so that we
can interact with them. And this
is another reason why a hard hat
deploy is so nice, because we
can just do const timelock
equals await ethers that get in
the next let's go ahead and
import ethers from hard hat
imports. Ethers
from Red Hat will even drop a
little TS ignore here. Ethers
dot get contract, we want that
time lock contract. And we say
we want to attach it to the
Deployer. So whenever we call a
function on it, it'll be the
deployer calling that function
and we want to do const Governor
equals await ethers dot get
contract, Governor contract,
this is all going to be attached
to the Deployer. Right. Now,
we're gonna do log setting up
roles. And we're going to set up
the roles right, again, we're
setting it up so that only the
governor can send things to this
time lock, because the Time Lock
is going to be you can almost
think of the Time Lock as like
the president. Right. So
everything goes to the Senate,
the House representative, which
is the governor and then the
President just says yeah, sure.
We just got to wait this minimum
delay, but the President will be
the one to actually execute
everything which I'm not
actually sure that's how it
really works in in politics, but
for for now, that's that's where
we're protecting the president
or the time like is the only one
that can actually do anything
here. So the way that this works
is we're actually going to get
the byte codes of different
roles, right? So if you look at
these time locks here, so we'll
do ones up on contracts. And we
go to the governance here. We go
to Tama controller has these
things called proposal roll,
executor roll time, like admin,
etc. And these are just hashes
of these strings here. But these
are these are bytes 32 saying,
Hey, anybody who has this this
byte 32 is a proposer, anybody
who has this byte 32 is an
executor. Anybody has this byte
there and soon as time like
admin, etc. Right now, our
Deployer account is the time
like admin, and that's bad. We
don't want that we don't want
anyone to be a time like admin,
right? We don't want anyone to
have power over this time lock.
We don't want any centralized
force here. So what we're going
to do is we're going to const
we're going to get those roles.
proposer, proposer role, it's
going to be a weight, unlock
that row pole sir role. And if
you're familiar with multi call,
this would be a great time to do
multi call and copy paste that
whole line x EQ tour role at x
EQ tour roll, we're gonna copy
this whole line admin role. And
this is going to be on lock
admin role. So these are these
three roles that we need to fix,
right, and let's go ahead and
fix them. So the first thing
we're gonna need to do is we're
gonna need to do const row poser
dx equals await Time Lock dot
grant roll, propose a roll to
our governor dot address. So
saying, okay, Governor, you're
the only one who can actually do
anything once you tell the Time
Lock to do something. We'll wait
for the Time Lock period to be
over. And then we'll be done.
And then we'll just do an await
posit TX dot wait one block just
to make sure. Now we're gonna do
the const executor, TX equals
await Time Lock dot grant roll
executor role to nobody, we're
going to execute this we're
gonna give this to nobody, we're
going to say address zero which
is going to be something that
we're going to want to add if we
go to our helper or head config
will say Export const address
zero equals zero by you can just
copy paste this if you want.
There's a couple other ways you
can do this with ethers as well.
We're just gonna do like this. I
like having my conflict this and
then we just import it say
import at zero from dot dot
slash helper Harnett config. So
we're giving the executor role
to nobody, which means
everybody. So once a proposers
thing has gone through, anybody
can execute it. So we'll say
executor, TX That wait one wait
a block. And then got one more
to do here, we need to revoke
role right now our Deployer
count owns that time lock
controller, right. And that's
how we can actually do these
transactions, we can actually
grant role because our Deployer
account owns it now that we've
given everybody access. And
given all the decentralized
access we need, we want to
revoke that role. So const
revoke TX equals await. I'm
locked up revoke role, admin
role from Deployer will do Rotex
that wait, now guess what
anything that's um, like, wants
to do has to go through
governance, and nobody owns the
time I controller, it's
currently after this runs, it's
impossible for anyone to do
anything with the Time Lock
without governance happening.
And then of course, when the
export default set of contracts,
great. And then the last step
that we need to do here is we
need to deploy the contract that
we actually want to govern over
write that box contract, that
real basic contract. So we're
gonna create a new 105, deploy
box.ts. And we're gonna do some
of the same exact stuff we've
done right, so we're gonna grab
these two, these two here, paste
it in, os deploy box is going to
be a deploy function equals
async function, Ah, sorry, hard
hat runtime environment,
we're gonna grab those first
three lines, the TS ignore, just
like that. And now we're going
to deploy this box. So log,
deploying bucks, and we're going
to do const box equals await,
deploy box, give us some values
from our Deployer. args does
this have any args so open a box
dot soul, I don't see a
constructor. And while this is
the easiest contract out of all
these though, no constructor,
and then we'll just say log,
it's going to be true. And
again, if you want to check out
my GitHub repo for that
confirmations, but feel free to
do so it's coming here. And
right now, our deployer has
actually deployed this right,
not our time lock. So we want to
give the boxes ownership over to
our governance process. So now
we're going to do say const
timelock, is going to be a
weight ethers dot get contract.
The same thing as before.
timelock. We're going to grab
ethers from hardhat import
ethers from hard hat. And we're
gonna do a little TLS ignore,
it's being finicky. And then
we're going to transfer the
ownership of our box to this
time lock, okay, and now so this
is actually what's known as a
box deployment. So before we do
that, we have to get the box
contract. So this is a box
deployment object, which doesn't
have contract functions we want
to get the box contract object
so we to box or const box
contract equals await ethers dot
get contract at box and then
we'll just do you know box that
address. You could also do get
contract. Actually both of these
pretty much if you have the
address, you can just do box
that address. You could also do
get contract here. Either one
works now that we have the box
contract, we do const transfer
owner, dx equals await by
contract dot transfer TX or
schema dot transfer ownership to
our timelock dot address, time
walk dot address, then we just
do a weight transfer ownership
TX dot weight one, do a log, you
done it. Those are export
default. Deploy box. Oh, let's
see if this works. So we just
did everything. We're deploying
the GOV token, deploying the
timelock, which owns the
governance process, we're
deployed the governance process,
we're setting up the governance
process so that it's totally
decentralized. And then we
deployed and set up our box so
that it only can be updated
through a governance process.
Let's see if it works. Yarn,
hard hat deploy. Let's see if it
works. Bada boom, you've done
it. So you've just set up a
script to set this entire
governance process up so you can
build your own doubt. Are you
still here? Well, hell yeah, you
are, congratulations on getting
this far, we have one more piece
to go, we just got to write
those scripts. So we can
actually interact with this, we
can actually do a governance, we
can actually see exactly what
the governance process looks
like. Now again, if you didn't
watch my last video on Dows, be
sure to watch that, because
that's going to give you all the
context for this part here. And
if you're still watching 100%,
smash the like button, hit the
subscribe, leave a comment in
the comment section below, it
really helps the channel out. So
proud of you for getting this
far. We're almost there, you're
getting now one more to go. And
then you are home free on
building your doubt. Let's get
back into it.
Alright, so now we're going to
make some scripts to actually
interact with propose Q and vote
on anything that happens in our
Dao. And these are the scripts,
these are kind of the things
that you would do on your front
end when you build this when you
build your doubt on the front
end. Or you could do an
integration with snapshot or
tally or something like that.
And again, if you want to see
come to full functionality on
the GitHub, I have this test
flow.ts It's not the greatest
test here. But you can also
check this out, because it also
does a soup to nuts
demonstration of going through
this exact process. So let's go
ahead and start making some
scripts. So we're gonna create a
new folder called scripts. And
this is where we're going to put
all of our scripts. Now the
process for this is going to be
we're first going to propose
something right? You know, maybe
we're going to propose that our
box contract stores the value
77, right? Because when it first
gets initialized, it's going to
start with zero. So maybe we'll
we'll propose it could start at
77. Once proposing is done, we
are voting on it. Right once
proposals it and we're going to
vote on whether or not we want
the proposal to go through right
yes or no. And then if it
passes, we go to queue and
execute, we queue first. And
then we execute, I'm just
putting them both in the same
script to make it easier. So
let's start with propose here,
because it's going to be the
first thing that we're going to
do. So let's create a new
function. We'll call it async
function, and then we'll
actually export it to export
async function propose. And
we're going to be in here for a
little bit. So let's clear
everything out. And okay, cool.
So this is where we're actually
going to propose on our governor
contract, right? So we're going
to propose a new governor
contract. So the first thing
we're gonna need, of course, is
gonna be the governor. So you
can't govern nor equals await
ethers dot get contract, govern
or contract, right? Since we're
doing ethers, we're gonna have
to do import ethers from heart
app. And then we're still
getting that fundamental thing.
We'll do a little AT Ts ignore
here. Cool. So we have the
governor contract here, we're
going to need the box contract,
we're gonna say hey, we want to
propose the box contract changes
the store value. So we'll do
const box equals await ethers
dot get this is a gift contract,
we want get contract, get
contracts at box. And those are
the two main ones that we're
going to need just to start.
Now, if we look at the proposed
function, right, if we go to
governance, we go to Governor,
and we look at that proposed.
This is what it looks like. Now,
I explained this proposed
function in my last video. So if
you haven't seen it, be sure to
go back and watch it right
because it'll give you
everything that you need to know
here are basically we pick a
list of targets, which our list
is just going to be just our box
contract. These are the targets
that we want to call functions
on, we do values like how much
needed ether we want to send,
which we're not going to send
anything, we have bytes, a array
called data. So this is going to
be our encoded parameters for
the function that we want to
call and then a description. So
that's exactly what we're going
to do here. So first, we need to
figure out what we're going to
do. So look at Box, we're going
to call this store function with
this new value here. So we need
to encode we need to encode this
socks here. And we also need to
encode what we want to upgrade
it to right so we have to code
all the function parameters. So
we'll do const encoded function
call equals box and the way we
can get this box that interface
that encode function data and
This is what actually turns it
to being this bytes call data,
right? So we're encoding
everything and this encoded
function, you can find this in
the ethers documentation, we
have to pass it the function to
call, and then the arguments we
want to pass, right, and this is
how we actually get that. So
let's get these arguments here.
So we're gonna say args, we're
going to make our proposed
function a little bit modular.
So we're gonna say args is going
to be an array of anything, and
then we're gonna say function to
call is just going to be a
string, right, and then right at
the bottom, we're actually gonna
call this, this proposed
function. So we're gonna say
propose, and let's say we want
to give it 77, the function is
going to be what it's going to
be store, store. And that's a
string. And this needs to be a
list. So we're going to do like
this. Now, we're actually going
to use this all over the place.
So since we're gonna be using
this all over the place, we want
to stick them in this part head
helper config. So what we're
going to do is we're gonna say,
export const, new store value
equals 77. And we're gonna do
export const funk equals store.
And I propose, we're just going
to import those. So we'll do
import, new store value, and
also funk from helper Hardhead
dot config, and it added it in
for us, which is great. So we'll
just put new store value in
here. And then we'll put funk in
here. And I know this might look
a little confusing, but
basically, the first thing we're
gonna do is we're gonna call
this proposed function which
calls you know, post function up
here. Now we're going to do some
fun little then process that
exit zero. And then we're going
to do a dot catch error, which
if there's an error, basically,
we'll just do console dot log
error, then process that makes
it. And this is pretty typical
setup for a really any script
you work with, and hardhat. So
great. So we have constant coded
function call, which has this
function to call an arc. So
we're basically combining these
into this bytes thing. And we
can even print this out, you can
see what this looks like. So you
do console dot log, you see that
this is like this, this crazy
bytes thing here. And the way we
can kind of test this, we'll do
yarn hardhat node, which will
spin up again, our fake
blockchain. But additionally,
with Hardhead deploy, it will
deploy all of our contracts
here, right, we can see timelog
governance, you know, everything
that we need for testing locally
has already been done. So once
we have that up, we can then do
yarn hardhat, run scripts,
propose that TS dash dash
network, local host, this is
important to do, again, because
when you're working with a node
that's running locally, you're
going to be working with local
host, we'll see what it prints
out here.
Contract named Governor
contracts, Governor contract.
Let's try that again. And cool,
you can see this is what that
encoded function call and
arguments looks like is this
really long byte string. But if
you were to decode this, using
the box interface, you would get
the function call and the
arguments, which is really
exciting. So cool, we've encoded
it to bytes. And now what we
want to do, we encourage the
bytes, and now we're going to
create that proposal
transaction. So we'll do console
dot log will say pro posing, and
say, function to call on box
that address with args. And then
we also need to pass a proposal
description. So we're gonna say
pro pose, all description, we
would do it on new line, why
not? Pro pulls all this option,
which we don't have yet.
Alright, we're gonna get it. So
we also need to pass a proposal
description, right, because we
have down here, description. So
let's add another parameter to
our propose here. So we'll say
proposal description, and this
will be also a string. Down at
the bottom, we're going to need
a proposal description as well.
So we'll create a proposal or
export const proposal
description, there's just going
to be some string. So we'll say
proposal number one, door 77 In
the box, that's the description
here, comma proposal
description. And then we import
this or a helper config. Okay,
perfect. So now we have the new
store value, the function the
proposal description, and we can
now call that propose that we
were just looking at so here's
what we're going to do const
propose TX equals await. gov dot
propose. And we need to pass
those lists. So first is going
to be a list of targets, which
for us is just a box that
address right only one target.
And again, these these little
brackets, make it a list of
values, which is just going to
be zero, a list of encoded
function calls or our bytes
data, basically, and then the
proposal description, and then
we're going to do propose, TX
dot wait one. Now, if you
remember, from compound, this is
going to be the exact same if we
go back to compound back to
governance, this transaction is
literally going to be the same
as this created thing here.
Right? And if we scroll down,
like more, we can see the code
input data, those exact same
things on a compound proposal,
right? We have targets values
signatures, well okay, this CES
is a little bit more, this a
little bit more advanced here,
using signatures, but it's got
the same thing called data and
then a description here, okay.
Now since we have a voting
delay, people actually can't
vote until the voting delay
passes. Now, with a local
blockchain, nobody's actually
processing blocks and time
doesn't really pass as quick as
we want. And so we're just going
to speed things up for our own
testing purposes. So the way I
normally do this is I create
this this variable, all
development, exports, on
development chains, and I'll add
hard hat and local host. Because
we can actually do things with
our own local blockchain, we can
actually speed up time, we can
speed up blocks, we can do all
this crazy stuff. So usually,
I'll actually import this in
here. And then we'll do a quick
F. And I'll say, if we're on a
development chain, let's just go
ahead and speed things up for
us. Right. So I'll say if
development chains that includes
network dot name, and then we
can import network from from
ethers, as well. And this is
what I was talking about those
super six skills that you're
gonna learn. If it includes
network dot name, then we're
gonna go ahead and move the
blocks forward, right, because
if we're not on development
chain, we can't actually move
blocks. So what we'll do here is
actually I'll create a new
folder called utilities, you
folder, you are utils. And in
here, I'll create a script
called Move blocks.ts. And we're
just going to create this little
function called move blocks,
which moves blocks for us. And
you'll see how we do this. So
we're going to import network
from heart app, because we want
to speed up that voting delay,
we'll do export async function,
we'll call it move blocks. And
it'll take an amount, which will
be a number, so how many blocks
that we actually want to move.
And then we'll just do console
dot log moving blocks. And we'll
say for let index equals zero,
index is less than amount. index
plus plus, or we're going to do
is we're going to do a weight
network DAP provider dot request
request. And we're going to
request method EVM. Mine. So
basically, we're mining for our
local blockchain, right, so you
can find these docks in the hard
hat docks in the ethers docks,
there's a couple different
places you can find these. But
this is kind of this really cool
hack that we can use to actually
move blocks forward on our local
chain. Now, obviously, this
won't work on an actual chain,
because you'd actually have to
do the mining but on our local
chains, we can absolutely do
this. So we've exported this
move blocks function, and we're
actually gonna grab that Mark
propose, we're going to import
move box from utils blocks. And
we're going to say down here, if
we're on this development chain,
and do a weight move blocks, and
then we'll move blocks by that
voting delay that we were
talking about, right? Because we
need to wait that voting delay
in order to move and it looks
like an auto import it for us
from our helper hardware config.
I told you, we were gonna use
that a couple of times, but
we're gonna move blocks by that
voting delay. Now, this proposed
transaction does some stuff that
we actually want, right? So one
of the big things that it wants
is, is it has this proposal ID.
And if we scroll down to the
event that it emits, it ends up
emitting this proposal ID, we