actually need the proposal ID
for later on when we actually go
to vote. So what we're going to
do is we're actually going to do
const propose receipt equals
proposed text dot weight. And
we're going to get those events
from this proposed receipt. So
we're gonna say const. Proposal,
id equals proposed receipt, that
events, the zero with event
because that first event is the
only one we care about that are
your stop proposal ID. This is
how we get this proposal ID from
this omit also created event. A
couple other ways to get
proposals to get events in
hardhat. And I got a video on it
on my YouTube, if you want to go
check that out. Something else
that we want to do is maybe we
want to see what the deadline is
with a snapshot, you can go
ahead and check my GitHub to
kind of see what the snapshot
looks like or the deadline,
basically, how long we have to
vote, you know what snapshot
you're working with, and all
these different things. But for
now, we're just gonna stick with
the proposal Id be sure to check
out the GitHub for more stuff.
Now we want to save this
proposal ID, we want to save it
somewhere so that our other
scripts so that our vote and our
queue and execute know what this
proposal ID is going to be when
we run those. So what we're
going to do is we're going to
create this file called
proposals dot JSON. And it's
going to store all of our
proposals. So we're gonna say
pro poll, souls dot JSON, it's
going to have all of our
proposals in here. So what we're
going to do and we're going to
add this to our helper Hardhead
config, and do export const,
proposals, file equals proposals
dot JSON. And we're going to
import this at the top as well
as proposals file. And then once
we get this proposal ID, we're
going to do is we're going to
read all the current proposals.
So we're gonna say let proposals
equals JSON dot parse, and we're
gonna do Fs dot read file sync
from this probe proposals file,
and we're going to pass it to
UTF eight. Now, this Fs we don't
have yet, so we're going to need
to import Fs. So we're going to
do yarn add Fs like that. If
we're looking at package dot
JSON. Oops, I should have saved
that as Dev, but I didn't Oh,
well, doesn't really matter. Now
that we have that we can
actually import this into our
TypeScript. So we're just going
to say, import star as Fs from
Fs. And now we can actually use
Fs F as a way to kind of read
from files. Now we can get this
list of proposals. So we got two
proposals that JSON right now
we're just making a blank JSON.
So the first time we run it,
it'll just be blank. But later
on, it'll have stuff in it. And
the way that we're going to save
these proposals is we're going
to say pro proposals of network
dot config dot chain ID, and
this little bank to say, yes,
there will be a chain id.to
string, we're going to store
them by their chain IDs, right.
So for each network that we have
a proposal to we'll we'll start
like that. And then we'll do dot
push proposal, id.to string, and
then we'll write it back. We'll
do Fs dot right, file sync,
proposals file. JSON does string
phi, proposals, and awesome. And
that's all we need to do. So
let's go ahead and actually run
this. And then I have some
console dot logs in here saying,
Hey, here's what the proposal
state is, is it open? Is it
voting is it canceled, you know,
etc. What the proposal snapshot
is, you know, again, check my
GitHub for that. But what we can
do, now this is done, we can do
yarn, Hardhead node, spin up our
little note here. And all the
contracts are deployed. And then
we'll do yarn, run scripts,
proposed that TS dash dash
network, local host scripts
proposed that TS is not found.
Pro pose, yarn, hard hat, run
scripts, pose IDs, oops, dash
dash network, local hosts. Try
this again. Now you found it.
Yay. Oh, I ran into an issue.
Although description Moviebox
Cannot read property zero of
undefined. Let's see where it
got mad at me. Poser sheet dot
event. It is events, not event
shots again, on the localhost.
There we go running ran into
another issue. Posle already
exists. Okay, so great. So the
proposal already exists, let's
go ahead and just like kill the
node, restart the node, so you
can't have two proposals that
are exactly the same, basically,
right. So we can't do that, we
would need to change the
description or something. So
we're just going to kill the
node and restart. Now we're
going to run this proposal
again. And hopefully this one
should work this time. Community
Property zero of undefined owes
receipt. This needs to be await
because it is a promise, kill
this one more time we run it
once all these get deployed. And
we're gonna go ahead and run
this. Now you can see how much
quicker this is than if you were
to actually send this to a test
net right to an event a lot of
waiting, which is no bueno. And
we run into one more Cannot read
property, push them undefined.
That makes a lot of sense, too.
Because proposals dot JSON as
nothing for chain IDs. So
231337. And we'll put a little
list in here. Right now it's an
empty list. Now we're going to
kill this one more time, kill
it.
And then once this goes, then
we're gonna go ahead and do
this. Perfect. Now we're going
to run this and now it should
save and everything should be
peachy hunky dory. Awesome.
proposal number one store in the
box, we move the blocks. And if
we look at proposal dot JSON, we
now see there's a list of
proposals. And this is the
proposal ID of that one we just
created. Oh, okay, we made a
proposal. Awesome. Nice work,
we'll leave that Node running.
And hopefully we'll just do
things right for the voting. So
let's create this vote script
now. Okay, so now we proposed
it's time to vote, let's do a
little voting. So this is going
to look pretty similar to that
script, we just we just created
right. So we're in New async
function, we'll call this main
proposal index number, and we're
calling this main because we're
going to have the vote function
be a little bit different.
You'll see why. And at the
bottom, of course, we're going
to do main index dot then
process dot exit zero, catch
error arrow function, console
dot error, error, and then
process that exit. One main
index, we're gonna say our index
zero cost index zero. We'll do
like this cost index is your
postal index. So we're gonna get
we're gonna get that bit zero
with index, right, the first
index in our proposals dot JSON.
So whatever is the first one in
this list is what we're gonna
use, right? And that's what we
want right now. There's only one
so it's easy. So we're gonna get
that first one in here. So first
thing we're gonna need to do is
we're gonna need to grab the
list of proposals. So we're
gonna do const proposals equals
JSON dot parse, FS dot read,
file sync proposals file, UTF,
eight. So of course, we're going
to need to import a bunch of
stuff. We're going to import
proposals file from that a slash
a Bernhard config. And then
we're going to do import star as
Fs from us. Great. We have Fs,
we can read stuff, and we can
get those boats. Okay, cool. So
we have a list of proposal IDs.
Now let's get our proposal idea
we'll do const probo. also ID
equals proposals of network dot
config. And then that's not what
we want. We want to actually
import network, import network
from hard hat, network dot
config, that chain ID,
exclamation mark of proposal
index, which for us is going to
be zero, right? We're getting
that first proposal in the list
of proposals. Now we're gonna
choose how we want to vote. So
zero equals against one equals
four, and then two is abstain. I
don't know why you'd ever
abstain abstaining costs gas,
you could just not vote, but
we're gonna say const vote way
and the way we're gonna vote
equals one. And we can also do a
reason. So if we go back to our
governor, there's a couple
different functions we get to do
to vote, there's cast vote,
where we just cast a vote, cast,
vote with reason, and cast vote
with signature where we actually
do a signature. And I asked this
question, Hey, what is cast vote
by sick do on the opens up on
forum, I was like, hey, what's
the what is the purpose of this?
My hunch was that anyone could
then execute this vote on behalf
of me if I didn't send the
transaction. And that's exactly
what it is. This method
implements a meta transaction
and allows a project to
subsidize voting fees, the
voters can generate a signature
for free, and the project can
submit those and pay for the
gas. So this is incredibly
powerful. And this is the
function that allows this, this,
this cast vote by signature is
what allows that snapshot chain
link integration that you know,
hopefully one of you build, but
for us for this, since we're not
implementing these meta
transactions, these off chain
stuff, we're just going to do
cast a vote with reason why
because we want to give it a
reason. That's really it. So
we're gonna say const boat TX
response equals await. Gov nor
dot cast, excuse me, we need to
get the government contract. So
we'll do const. Gov nor equals
await ethers dot get contract.
Gov contract. And then if we
don't have ethers, we should get
ethers. Great. Let's get ethers.
And we'll ignore that. But now
we have the contract. So we'll
do a weight gov dot cast vote
with reason spell this right?
With reason. And we'll say
proposal ID that way. And then
the reason which we don't have a
reason here, so let's make a
reason. Let's say the reason is
reason, equals I like do cha
cha, if you know that film, you
should definitely comment it in
the description. We have a
reason so we're voting for we're
saying yes, we want we do indeed
want you to change the box to
77. And the reason is because I
like a do the Cha Cha makes
perfect sense if you don't think
about and then we'll do a wait,
Kotex response that wait. So I
do some stuff, again, checking
the state of the proposal where
different numbers mean, hey,
it's in process, it's voting,
etc, we could check on that. But
we're gonna skip that for now.
All we're going to do now, now
that we voted, we're going to be
the ones to vote. So we're just
going to once again move the
blocks along. Why because we
want to just get to the end of
that voting period. So we're
gonna do again, if velopment
chains, that includes network
dot name, then we're gonna do a
weight move blocks, voting
period, plus one. So we need to
import a whole bunch of stuff in
here. poses file development,
looks like those got auto
imported, we need to import this
move blocks. So import move
blocks from utils blocks, and
that network is in here. And
then we need voting period from
our helper config. voting
period. Okay, cool. And then
we'll do console dot log, voted,
ready to go. Now the reason that
I checked the proposal state is
because there's this state
function in the governor
contract. So if we look up
state, what this does is it
tells us what the state of the
proposals in right if it's been
executed, return that's been
executed, if it's been canceled,
return has been canceled. You
have the deadline, check to see
if it's active, check to see if
quorum reached all this stuff,
right? And what you're usually
looking for is worm reached and
vote succeeded, right? If both
of these happen, the proposal
state DOT succeeded, right?
Otherwise, it's defeated or it's
not there yet. I believe this is
a one and this is a zero. So if
you were to call that function
and get the state right, now we
should get a zero. Or excuse me,
we should get a one for this
having passed. If you want to do
that as a little extra credit,
feel free to do so. So let's see
if we did this right. Well,
actually, I guess we got to
change this just to vote. But I
just wrapped everything up into
main. So let's see if this
works. Yarn, hard hat run
scripts vote network, local
host. So we should get a little
console dot log at the bottom
that says voted ready to go. So
now we're voting. We didn't just
go to the Arctic Council, we
could do yarn, hard hat console,
dash dash network, local host.
And in here, you can actually
just check the state right in
here. Why not? We'll copy this
line as governor because we
either get contract Governor
contract. Now we can do a wait,
Governor, that's state of go to
the proposals dot JSON, grab
this, paste it in here. And we
get a for the state of this
right now is for I forget what
four means. It's like a proposal
state. The proposal state is
actually in the eye governor so
the interface of the governor We
can see, zero is pending, one is
active, two cancelled, three
defeated, and four have
succeeded. So we are in a
succeeded state, which is really
good. That's exactly what we
want. So let's go ahead and quit
now. Excuse me Ctrl. C, our
proposal is now in a succeeded
state. And we've actually moved
the blocks along the voting
period. So voting is now over
because we cheated. So now let's
go ahead and queue and execute
this to the last bit here. So
this is gonna look real similar
to what we've done already.
Right? Let's minimize this,
export async, function, Q, and
execute. And then at the bottom,
we'll just call queue, and
execute. And I'm just going to
copy paste, but it's that same
syntax here, then process exec
catch, blah, blah, blah, you get
the drill. So in order to queue
and execute, go back to the
governor contract, not the
governor, let's go to the
governor. First thing we're
going to do is call this queue.
Now this Q function is actually
in the governor time lock, which
is in this extensions here. So
we can find the governor Time
Lock controller here, and it
does exactly the same as propose
we take everything that we did
in the proposal, and then we
just queue it like so. So we
pass the exact same values here.
And that's so cute. So what
we're going to do is we're gonna
need to first get those exact
same values, which I told you
we're going to use a few times.
So we're going to import bunk,
new store value, proposal
description of our article
thing, right now that we have
all that stuff, we'll say const
args equals a new store value,
we'll do const box equals await
ethers dot get contract, let's
get that box contract again,
we're gonna have to import
ethers from our hat. And this is
going to be from we're gonna do
TS ignore, then we're once again
code this function call to const
encoded function call equals
Boxtop interface, encode
function data. Once again, we're
gonna do funk is the function we
want to call and args this is
like real similar to the our
proposed bit that we did. And
then we're gonna do content
description hash equals ethers
dot utils that get GAC 256
ethers dot utils, that to you,
TF eight bytes, this will make
sense in a second. We're also
description. So what's our
propose, all we did was pass our
proposal description, however,
it actually gets hashed on
chain, and that's what our view
and execute is gonna be looking
for, it's gonna be looking for
the description hash, instead of
just the pure description,
right, and it's gonna be a
little bit cheaper gas wise,
which is good. So now that we
have the description hash, now
that we have all the same
functions that we did for the
suppose it's time to queue them.
So do cost gov equals await
ethers dot get contract. Gov
contract, console dot log will
say we're queuing and then we'll
do cos Q, dx equals gov dot q.
And we're going to pass the
exact same parameters we did
with the pose except for what
the hash instead of the actual
proposal, so box that address
zero for eath, and pass that
code at function call. And then
the description hash rate. And
then we're going to do oops, is
going to be a weight here. And
then we're gonna do a wait. You
text Oh, wait, one, wait a block
there. And great, then we're all
queued up. Now we still have to
wait that minimum delay, right?
Remember, on our timeline, it's
got this min delay thing. It
says, Hey, once something gets
queued up, you can't just
execute it right away. You gotta
give people time to get out. So
we're going to speed up time
again, we're going to say if
development chains develop l
meant chains that includes and
then it looks like it auto
imported for me development
chains. Yes, it did. Amazing.
That includes network dot name.
Let's just make sure we import
network from Hardhead. That
includes our name, then, of
course, we're going to move
blocks. But we also actually
have to move time here as the
minimum delay is looking for
some time. So let's create a new
util called Move time. Okay,
move time that Yes. And this
util is going to allow us to
move time so you're learning all
the cool stuff. So we'll quickly
write a script to do this
important network from hard hat
export async function move time,
how much time will be a number
of Mount console dot log, moving
time, and let's say await
network dot provider dot send
EVM increase time and then just
by the amount, then we'll just
say console dot log, move
forward, amount seconds, it goes
forward and seconds. Cool. So
now we have this move time
function. That was pretty quick,
right? So first, we're going to
move time and we're gonna move
time by that min delay first,
plus one just to be safe. And
then we're also going to move
blocks. We're gonna do a weight
move time, and then a weight
move blocks. And we'll just move
on block. So got it Import move
blocks from utils. It imports
move time from those utils as
well, time. And then we also
have to import this min delay,
which we get from our helper.
Hardhead config. Great. So we
moved all that stuff. Again, if
this were a real chain, you just
have to wait. But since we're
not a real chain, we can do
whatever we want. Yes, love
doing whatever I want. Now that
it's all cued up, the voters
passed, we're looking spicy.
Let's drive this home. Xe cuting
do a little console dot log
executing the const execute TX
equals await. gov dot execute.
We're going to pass this the
exact same set of things we did
for the Q TX so I'm literally
gonna copy this. paste it down
here. And then we're just going
to do a weight SQ TX dot weight.
We're going to wait one block.
And then the final hour we'll
see if the governance updated
our box contract const box new
value equals await box dot
retrieve. And that will do
console dot log. New box value.
Box new value.to string Oh, so
if we did this right, it's new
box value to be updated. Let's
see if we did it right yarn hard
hat run grips Q and execute now
work localhost. Did we do it
right? Are we successfully done
governance? We did. That's okay.
We're gonna figure out what we
did wrong. Did you mean could
check 256 I spelt some stuff
wrong. It needs to be spelt like
no CK. Just just k. Okay, let's
try again. It failed before it
actually did. I think that's
good. Queuing moving time
provider EVM and crit cuz I
spelt increased time wrong. Oh,
no EVM increase time to just
double check. Make sure I'm
spelling this right T is
actually capital. So I totally
messed up. So it's actually
already been queued. It's been
queued right now on our little
node EVM increased team. So we
can either delete and kind of
restart, or I can just go ahead
and I'm just going to comment
out a bunch of stuff, we're just
going to skip the cueing here.
We're gonna run this one more
time, because it's already been
queued. And now should just
execute, we're gonna move time
again. But that's fine. Oh, my
goodness, we did it. Right. And
then normally, you would just do
it in one script. But this queue
would fail because it was
already queued. Right, you can't
queue twice, move forward. In
time, we move blocks we executed
and we got a new box value
completely using our Dow
completely decentralized voting
completely on chain, no third
party trust going in on here.
There's no voting booth, there's
no you know, spending 1000s of
dollars on staff, everything we
just voted on happened right in
front of our faces. Now, again,
I highly recommend go to my
GitHub repo, you take a look and
you see what's going on here.
Again, if you want to see
JavaScript stuff, feel free to
do some JavaScript stuff. But
this goes over how to just get
clone and get started if you
want to do that as well. But if
you walked with me here, if you
walked through this with me, you
have learned in the absolute
Khan, thank you so much for
being here. And I'll see you
next time.
All right. Now, welcome to the
final section of our course, the
security and auditing section,
this one is going to be a little
bit less coding and a little bit
more explaining. And most of
what we're going to be learning
about here is in this Hardhead
security FCC section. Throughout
this course, we've given you a
couple of tips about different
security features. One, we
talked about reentrancy, we
talked a little bit about Oracle
Tax, and we're going to talk
about those more. And some of
the tools we can use to make our
code more efficient, to look out
for bugs, and to make our code
more secure. So we're gonna go
ahead, we're gonna go over this
hard hat security FCC code base,
and we're going to walk through
it a little bit. So one of the
first things that we're going to
talk about is, what is an audit?
Well, an audit is going to be a
security focused code review,
looking for issues with your
code. So for example, let's say
we have some code that looks
like this, this should be a
little bit familiar, because we
talked about this in one of our
earlier sections with
reentrancy, our code, withdraw,
goes and sends ether and then
updates the balances, this code
is clearly vulnerable to a
reentrancy attack here. And this
is something that an auditor
would catch. Since when we
deploy our code, that code is
immutable. And that code will
always be there, it's really
important to have these security
reviews done before we deploy
our code to a main net, and
before we go live, so if you're
going to deploy some crazy,
massive defy protocol, and
you're gonna have billions of
dollars of people's money locked
into your protocol, you probably
want to make sure that the money
is going to go to the correct
places. So audits are incredibly
important for the lifecycle of
our projects. And we want people
to peer review, we want people
to review our code to make sure
that everything looks good. Now,
when we send our code to audit,
though, we shouldn't just say
hey, here's our code. Can you
check them Make sure it's good.
That's not going to give an
auditor enough information, they
need to be able to very easily
know what your code does, how to
work with it, and what you're
looking for. Because auditors
aren't going to be kind of this,
this failsafe, where if your
code is terrible, they're going
to catch everything. Auditors
are human beings too. They can
miss things as well, auditors.
Also, don't make sure that your
code is bug free. Like I said,
audits are security focused peer
reviews for your codebase. And
when you do send your code to
audit, you want to make sure you
help out your auditors as much
as possible. There's an amazing
tweet thread from Tinto and
previously was an open Zeplin
auditor with a ton of tips and
tricks for working with
auditors, I highly recommend you
pause the video, you click this
link and you read through his
tweets because they are
fantastic. openzeppelin has a
readiness guide to try to help
you make sure that you're even
ready for an audit in the first
place. And we've got a link to
this readiness guide in the
GitHub repository. The summary
of them are to add comments to
your code, use natspec, which we
learned about to document your
functions, document your
functions, test, be ready to
talk to your auditors, and be
prepared to give them plenty of
time. They are literally pouring
themselves over your code for
weeks on end to make sure
there's nothing wrong. If you
rush your auditors, you're gonna
get a rushed audit, and they're
going to miss things. So let's
talk about the auditing process.
In auditing process is going to
look like this. First, they're
going to run your tests. That's
the first step in order is
always going to take and right
there, they're gonna find okay,
do they have enough code
coverage? Is everything passing?
What do the tests do? What is
the optimal functionality, after
an auditor runs tests, they're
going to read specs or run your
docs. And then they're going to
run some fast tools like
Slither, linters and static
analysis. And that's going to be
one of the first things we're
going to talk about slither and
static analysis. So static
analysis is the process of just
running some program to read
over all your code and look for
commonly known bugs. One of the
most popular static analysis
tools is going to be this tool
called Slither. And that's going
to be one of the first things
we're going to do here. So let's
go ahead and open up our VS code
now. And we'll make a new
directory called hardhats
security, FCC. We'll cd into it.
We'll do code period. And we'll
open this up. Now what I want
you to do, instead of starting a
new folder, and everything is
we're going to get clone, my
heart had security FCC. So we'll
do git clone, our net security
FCC space, and then put a period
to clone it into this directory.
And we'll get everything like
this. Now in here, this comes
with a couple of different
contracts for us already, that
each have a different
vulnerability, one of them is
going to be bad RNG. This is a
contract that picks a random
winner of a raffle using block
difficulty and message dot
sender. This isn't truly random,
as the miners can influence the
block dot difficulty, and people
can cancel transactions. And
there's a ton of ton of
different vulnerabilities with
creating randomness in this way.
We also have this liquid pool as
an Oracle, the two most common
types of attacks are reentrancy,
which we've learned about an
Oracle manipulation attacks,
which luckily for you, we've
taught you about decentralized
Oracle's and working with chain
link, which should make you a
lot safer. And especially for
this section, I'm going to harp
on these, please, please,
please, if you taking this
course, please do not make a
protocol that falls victim to
one of these, I will feel like I
have failed you. If you build a
protocol where you use some
centralized oracle that gets
manipulated, or you build a
protocol that has a reentrancy
attack. The tools that I'm going
to show you right here are going
to help you with reentrancy. And
everything I've taught you about
chain link should hopefully
teach you how to not get Oracle
manipulated. So in this contract
here, we're using a liquidity
pool as an Oracle and this is
kind of some advanced defy stuff
here. This is a minimalistic
decentralized exchange example
where people can buy and sell
and swap different assets. Now
using this singular exchange, to
get the swap price is a terrible
idea. Because this is a single
protocol for a single price. The
price from this protocol is a
single centralized location, and
we don't want to get our price
from a single centralized
exchange. We want to get it from
many exchanges. Getting the
price of any asset from a single
decentralized exchange is not
decentralized, is somebody
manipulates the market doing
some crazy advanced defy things
that will ruin the price of your
assets. So getting the price of
your assets from a centralized
location is a terrible idea. We
have a metamorphic proxy here.
The issue here is that it's
initialized double, and we don't
guarantee that the contract has
been initialized. We have a
classic reentrancy issue here.
And then we have and then we
have a vault here where some
password is stored on chain and
we're crossing our fingers that
nobody reads this password to
unlock it. So we're going to run
some static analysis on these
contracts, see if that static
analysis can spot some of the
bad things in here.
To get started, we're going to
use a tool like I said called
slither slither tool was created
by this Crytek team, aka the
trilobites team. Now, trilobites
is one of my absolute favorite
auditors in the space. And I
absolutely love all the tools
that this team puts out, they
put up open source security
tools for any of us to use such
as slitter. Now to get started
with Slither, we actually need
to install Python first. So you
can also run it with Docker. But
I'm going to show you how to how
to work with Python first. So if
you haven't worked with Python,
before, you can come to
python.org/downloads and
download Python right from the
website, you'll know you've done
it right. And you can run python
three dash dash version, like
this. Or if you have an older
version of Python, you can run
Python dash dash version. Once
you install Python, you should
also have this tool called PIP
three installed and you can
check by running PIP three dash
dash version, or PIP dash dash
version. And we also want to
install this sock select package
just in case we're using weird
versions of solidity to install.
So select, we run PIP three,
install sock select, like that.
And then we can do sock, select,
use. And then we can choose the
version of solidity or slither
to work with. Once you have
those tools, you can just run
PIP three install slither
analyzer like so. And you can
install slither into your Python
environment. I'm not going to
run it because already have. You
can also learn how to do this
all with Docker and we'll learn
how to do this with Docker in a
little bit. Now in our package
json, we actually have command
script in our package. JSON for
running Slither, you'll know
you've installed slither
correctly. If you can run
Slither, dash dash help you get
an output like this. Now we can
use slither to run it on our
contracts folder by running this
big command here. So we'll say
Slither. And we want to run it
on dot slash contracts, we need
to tell it that it has some
psaltery mappings, and every
time it sees open Zeppelin, it
should use Node module slash
open Zeppelin and every time it
sees chain link introduced node
modules slash chain link. And
I'm just going to read from our
package json. And we're
excluding a couple of functions
that it runs and excluding
builder ignore, but don't worry
too much about that. We've
actually just run that by first
running yarn to install all of
our packages.
And after we've installed all of
our packages, we can run yarn
Slither. Or you can copy paste
that slither command and run it
directly. Now we'll get this
massive output that looks like
this with some red and some
green. Let's go through what's
actually happening here, the way
that we can read Slither, it'll
list out a number of lines that
have an issue and then a
reference to that issue. And
each one of these is separated
by a new line. So that's a
section that's exception, etc.
So if we get a red here, that
means that there is a high
impact issue that we definitely
should address. And it even
comes with a reference link that
we can copy paste and put into
our browser and see what the
issue is and more information
from the slither tool about what
that issue is and how to correct
it. We can see it catches our
metamorphic contract issue. It
says metamorphic contract is
never initialized. It is used
here in metamorphic dot kill.
The reason that this is a
massive issue, if we go to our
metamorphic contract outsole is
that if we deploy this contract,
somebody else could initialize
this code, become the owner, and
then automatically kill it
before we even have a chance.
This is actually something that
has happened in the past and has
caused a ton of issues. So if we
see red in the terminal, this
means Hey, massive issue, we
should absolutely check it out.
Now there's gonna be a ton of
green in here. These are
detectors that are probably low
impact, and they're probably
okay. And in fact, we can see,
it's even just calling out some
opens up on stuff here, saying,
Hey, we see some inline
assembly. Inline assembly is
kind of scary, maybe don't use
that. So you can think of green
as kind of a warning that
there's a low likelihood that
this will impact anything, but
you might want to check it out,
we get this different versions
of solidity used, which is just
saying, hey, there's a couple
different versions of solidity
that might be something you want
to keep in mind, maybe you
should use the same versions of
solidity. We have this allow old
versions. And this is actually
why throughout this whole
course, we've been using zero
point 8.7 Because zero point 8.4
and zero point 8.7 are
considered more stable versions
of solidity. So if you're using
versions outside of there, so
there will say hey, maybe you
want to work with a different
version. We have some flags in
here about maybe Hey, you should
make a variable constant because
it never changes which is great.
Uses literal with too many
digits saying hey, this Just
kind of hard to read, maybe you
screwed up some of the zeros,
loud old versions. And what's
this reentrancy in ether store
dot withdraw. So just by running
this slither tool, we can catch
a reentrancy vulnerability in
one of our contracts, which is
fantastic. So running the static
analysis caught at least two
huge vulnerabilities in our
metamorphic contract. And in our
reentrancy contract, it didn't
catch the issues involved at
sole liquidity pool, or bad RNG,
though, which is why we don't
only want to rely on slither
because it's not going to catch
everything, but it will catch a
lot of major vulnerabilities. So
that's how we can use Slither,
at least from a middle middle
stack point to get started. So
great, we just learned how to
work with Slither. That's one of
the first tools that are really
fantastic in our audit process.
And that's going to be
considered a fast tool for
static analysis, running tests,
linters, etc, are also types of
static analysis.
After we run a tool like that,
we enter some manual analysis
where we walk through the code
ourselves manually, and maybe we
do it in tangent with running
some slower tools, like a kitna
Manta Corp, and other symbolic
execution tools. Symbolic
Execution is where we simulate
executing transactions on the
blockchain. And one of these
symbolic execution tools that
we're going to work with is this
a kidmin tool. Again, this is a
trail of bits tool for doing
something called fuzz testing.
Now in programming, fuzzing or
fuzz testing is an automated
software testing technique that
involves providing invalid
unexpected or random data as
inputs to a computer program. In
a lot of our code, oftentimes,
we're going to get people
interacting with them in ways
that we will never think about.
So we want to be able to provide
random data and random
information to our test to see
if something weird happens that
we weren't expecting. So we can
actually build our own fuzz
tests in our hard hat projects
and run these fuzz tests, I've
actually created a sample of
fuzz tests, we write our fuzz
tests in solidity, actually, as
opposed to writing our tests in
JavaScript. So let's say for
example, we've built this vault
contract. And we think that at
first glance, hey, nobody should
ever be able to know the
password, and no one should ever
be able to unlock this contract.
Which obviously, we know is
ridiculous, because we know that
anybody can read anything in a
storage variable. So we know
that this should fail, but it
might be hard to write a test.
To catch that this actually
would fail. A good approach to
testing this would be to just
send a ton of random bytes 32
objects to this unlock function
to see if we can unlock it. We
can write a fuzz test to do
exactly that. So in my vault,
fuzz test dot Sol, we're
importing vault outsole. And so
we're saying vault fuzz test is
vault and we have a password of
123, ASD 123. And now we have a
function called a kid and a test
find password, where it's going
to send a ton of random data
into vault to try to make s
locked equal false. So we just
say s locked equals true here,
and our first test will try to
make s locked equals false. Now
we could install just the kitna,
but at this point, it's a good
idea to bring up our the
security toolbox from trail of
bits. So trail of bits has a
package called the eath security
toolbox, which has all their
security tools in one single
container kitna, Ethan o Manta
core, slither, rattle, and not
so smart contracts, it has all
these in the same exact package.
Now to work with this toolbox.
We're gonna need Docker
installed. So we're gonna do a
little bit of installation here.
And again, sometimes this can be
the hardest part of the course
is just installing these
packages. So we've left a link
to Doc's dot docker.com, get
Docker to install Docker, to
actually work with these tools,
you're just going to come you're
going to click whichever one of
these is appropriate for you to
install Docker, once we have
Docker installed, we can run the
E security toolbox by pulling it
down from the Docker equivalent
of GitHub. And we're going to
use a whole bunch of Docker
commands that I'm not going to
explain here because this isn't
a Docker course, if you're
looking to get into the security
stuff, I would definitely
recommend reading up on all
these commands afterwards. And
we're going to leave a ton of
links for you to learn more. And
in the package that JSON
associated with this lesson. We
even have the command to get set
up right in here. So we can just
run yarn toolbox, which will run
our Docker command like this. So
I'm just going to run yarn
toolbox. And if you get
something like this saying
cannot connect to the Docker
daemon is the Docker daemon
running, because I need to have
my Docker daemon running. Since
I installed Docker desktop. I
need to have my Docker engine
started and running for it to
actually be working. Again to
work with this. There's a lot of
Docker setup and configuration
that needs to happen, which I'm
going to leave a ton of
instructions on how to get
started with Docker. Once we
have Docker setup. Now we can
run yarn toolbox, which will
stick us into a new shell to
work with any of these tools
that trilobites has Out of the
box. Now our vault fuzz test
comes with a config as well.
This is in a Yamo file with all
our arguments for running a
kidnap. So it has a test limit,
which is how many different
runs, we should do a time delay,
block delay. And then of course,
some re mappings in here. This
darker shell will already have
the security tools already
installed like the Kidner test.
So we'll run a kinah test on SRC
slash contracts slash test slash
fuzzing slash fault fuzz test
dot Sol dash dash contract will
be vault fuzz test, dash dash
config will be SRC slash
contracts slash test slash
buzzing slash config dot Yamo.
And we'll go ahead and we'll hit
enter here, and it'll say
analyzing contract, it'll give
us an output like this, it will
give us an output that looks
like this. What it's saying is
it found a use case where it
could make s locked equals
false. And the use case was 123,
ASD 123. So when what seemed
like almost seconds, it found
the password to unlock our
contract. And this is why
running a fuzz tester can be so
powerful, we thought our
contract was secure, but it
immediately found the password,
which means anybody else could
immediately find the password.
And this would be an indicator
that what we're doing there is
not a good setup. So we'll hit
CTRL C to escape. And to leave
our Docker setup here,
we'll just write exit. Now
again, I'm going to leave a ton
of links to work with a
kidnapper and work with this
fuzz tester in the GitHub repo
associated with this lesson, so
that you can go ahead and learn
more. Now, if you take anything
away from this whole section, it
should be this right here. The
two most common tasks are
reentrant. See, and Oracle
manipulation. So if you're not
going to be an auditor, and you
just want to deploy things to
main net, always, always before
you deploy anything, the
absolute minimum that you should
be doing is always running
Slither. And then looking
manually for Oracle manipulation
and reentrancy attacks. If you
see in your code that you're
getting pricing information.
Price is a piece of data that we
as humans have assigned to
something if you're getting
pricing information from a
centralized location, rethink
that scenario, rethink what
you're doing there. If you're
getting a random number, if
you're doing any type of
automation from a centralized
location, rethink it and change
your strategy. The chain link
Oracle network has been created
for a reason to prevent getting
hacked like this. So please keep
these in mind before you deploy
anything to main that with any
type of security guarantees.
Okay, great. So we've learned
about the fast tools, we've
learned about some of the slow
tools. We didn't look into Manta
Corp or Mythix. But these are
also tools that you can use
Manta Corp is going to be
another tool from the trilobites
team. And Mythix is actually a
smart contract security service
from the consensus team, you
basically send a bot that they
have running in the cloud your
contracts and will do some
automated process to check for
security vulnerabilities. This
is a paid service. But if you're
going to be deploying a protocol
that's worth millions of
dollars, spending a few $1,000.
Spending a few $1,000 to make
sure it actually does. What it
says is going to do correctly is
definitely something that you
want to invest in. After you run
through this whole process. You
the smart contract developers
and the auditors should discuss
their findings. And if there's
any issues, repeat the steps,
repeat all the steps again after
changes are made. So this audit
process and making sure your
contracts are secure is a long
process. And then afterwards, an
auditor will finally write your
report with all security
vulnerabilities and everything
that they found in your
contracts. Typically, you'll
organize reports in a chart
that'll look something like
this, you'll label issues that
have a high chance of happening
and have a high impact as
critical things that have a high
impact, but a low likelihood as
medium, and etc. I'm also going
to leave some examples two
audits that have been done in
the past so that you can take a
look at them. And you can see
what a full audit looks like on
certain code. We'll be looking
at openzeppelin sigma prime, and
trilobites, because these are
three of what I think are some
of the best auditors in the
space. Now in the GitHub repo.
We also have a ton of other
tools that you can use Mythix,
mithril ethers play and
consensus security tools. If you
want to learn more about
security and auditing, I highly
recommend that after this course
you play the Ethernet game and
damn vulnerable Defy. These are
two games that will teach you a
ton about security. And we'll
test the chops and we'll test
everything that you've learned
in this course. There's also a
couple of security focused blogs
that I really like. One of them
in particular is wrecked dot
news. They keep a running list
of some of the largest hacks
that have ever happened in the
space and then retrospectives on
why those actually happened. And
they usually make it very
entertaining as well. We have
some articles in here as well.
One of the best places to look
at is this known attacks section
where they talk Talk about
reentrancy, Oracle manipulation,
front running and a ton of other
attacks that you should
absolutely be aware of when
writing your smart contracts,
we're not going to go over them
here because they do a great job
in these resources explaining
them, you should also check out
this article because I helped
write it. So definitely check
that out. And then we've got a
list to even more sections. So
this is going to be a living
section here. So please feel
free. If you find more things in
the future, please feel free to
make pull requests and update
this repository so that other
people can learn and know more
about security and auditing and
have contract examples on what
bad code looks like and how to
actually catch them. Even though
this was one of our quickest
sections. From a video
standpoint, this actually is
going to be one of the longest
sections of your career.
Security is something that is
always going to be on your mind.
And there's always going to be
new tools to help with security.
new things to think about. So
even though we went through this
very quickly, I would 100% want
you to pause this video, and
work with and try out some of
the tools we tried here. And
then maybe even try coming up
with your own vulnerabilities as
well. And with that being said,
you have just finished the last
section of this massive master
course on learning smart
contracts, solidity, web three
and blockchain development,
you should be incredibly proud
of yourself. Congratulations, I
and the web three community as a
whole want to congratulate you
for completing this absolutely
monstrosity of a tutorial, you
have done an amazing job to get
this far. And to watch me
talking to you right now. And if
you haven't finished the course,
go back and finish it before
coming here. We have learned so
much on this journey. And I can
say from the bottom of my soul
that I am so glad to have you in
the web three space, smart
contract space, the blockchain
space, the cryptocurrency space,
we are so excited that you're
here. I'm really looking forward
to seeing you in the web three
in the blockchain community. Now
a lot of people ask, Well, where
do I go? Now, I didn't have all
this newfound knowledge. I'm
armed with the intelligence of
the web three developer space.
Well, I've left some links in
the GitHub repository to lead
you to those next steps. But the
biggest thing that you can do
for yourself right now is go
take what you've learned, and
apply it somewhere. This is
going to be probably the most
thorough course you will ever go
through in this space. And you
can go tutorial to tutorial and
boot camp to bootcamp all you
want. But at some point, you
have to make that leap, and you
have to dive in. And that's
where the majority of the growth
is going to be anyways. So if
you're here, wondering where to
go next, go join a hackathon. Go
start jumping into issues on
GitHub repos, go start applying
for grants, go start applying
for jobs and say, I took
Patrick's massive course. Here's
my GitHub repo, work on a
personal project, work on
somebody else's project. Take
this knowledge and apply it, the
challenges that you'll run into
and the challenges that you'll
face. Really trying to do
something without me hand
holding you is where you're
going to learn 10 times as much
as what you've learned here.
I've walked through as deep down
this rabbit hole as I can take
you. Now it's up to you to go
out and do something with it. So
thank you, everybody who helped
me create this course. Thank you
for taking this course. And I'm
so excited to see you in the
community and see what you build
and see what we can create with
this technology.