If you're interested in learning
about blockchain, this is the
course for you. Patrick Collins
is a veteran software engineer
and longtime finance industry
developer. Be sure to leave a
comment with something you
learned from this course.
Welcome to the ultimate solidity
smart contract and blockchain
Developer course, JavaScript
addition, we recently did a
version of this video in Python
that has over 2 million views
right now making it the most
watched smart contract tutorial
on the planet. We've learned a
ton from doing that first
course. And if you love the
Python language, definitely be
sure to check that one out.
We've taken all the learnings
we've got from making that first
course, wrapped it up and put it
into this JavaScript video for
you. If you're looking to get
started in web three blockchain
smart contracts or any of these
terms, this is the course for
you. And it's for anybody and
everybody, no matter your
experience level in programming
or in blockchain. Ideally, you
know, a little bit of JavaScript
before starting this. But if you
don't, no worries, we will help
you along the way. And in case
you do want to learn a little
bit of JavaScript before
starting here, there are some
fantastic courses on Free Code
Camp to learn more, but you
absolutely don't have to. And
really, any experience with any
object oriented programming
language will work, right. So if
you're brand new to coding, or
if you're brand new to
blockchain, this is exactly
where you should be. And if you
already know a lot about
blockchain or coding, this
course will give you even more
deep fundamentals on the space.
So welcome to the edge of the
rabbit hole. So for those of you
who don't know, my name is
Patrick Collins. I'm a smart
contract engineer, developer
advocate on the chain link
protocol. And I live in breed
smart contracts. I also make
YouTube videos on my own
channel, medium Twitter threads
and more. teaching people about
smart contracts about coding and
about this new technology. I
love helping developers learn,
grow and learn about this new
Advent. That's blockchain and
smart contracts. And I'll be
taking you on your journey to
becoming a blockchain expert and
Wizard of the smart contract
developing world. And even if
you don't want to become a
developer, the first section our
blockchain basics, will give you
a lot of fundamental knowledge
about how blockchain and smart
contracts, even work. I am so
excited for you to be here. And
I hope you enjoy the journey.
This is a data dump, passion
educational project of
everything I've learned working
in this space. And I am 100%
certain that if you follow
along, you'll come out the other
side of this, armed with the
knowledge to be a positive force
in this incredible industry,
solidity and smart contract
developers are massively in
demand with an average salary of
being around $145,000 a year,
there is massive economic
opportunity from learning this
course. And this technology has
the ability to revolutionize
everything that we interact
with, and you can be one of the
pioneers ushering in this new
age. In our courses. We already
have a track record of giving
people these educational needs
and sending them into their
careers in the blockchain and
smart contract space. And we are
going to give you all of the
cutting edge tools and how to
use them including working with
things like D phi NF TS Dows,
ERC 20s upgradable, smart
contracts and more. We're going
to teach you the skills
necessary to build defy
applications like Ave synthetics
and compound, billion dollar
decentralized applications, or
massively successful NFT
projects like crypto punks, or
board apes. Dow is like maker
Dow or developer, Dow and any of
the amazing things you've seen
in the cryptocurrency world. In
learning these skills, you will
have all these economic
opportunities at your fingertips
and the ability to be a pioneer
in completely changing the way
we interact with each other. In
a fundamental way. Building
decentralized smart contract
applications is building a world
that's more accountable a world
with unbreakable promises, a
faster, more efficient,
financially free world, a
collaborative community,
combining the prowess of
philosophy and technology into a
new system. We'll learn more
about the purpose and the value
of smart contracts and
decentralized applications in
lesson one of this course, and
why they're so exciting. Finish
this course. And you'll be
ready. So again, I want to give
a major thank you and a major
kudos to you because you've
taken the first step to enter
this realm. So welcome to Web
three. Welcome to the
blockchain. Welcome to smart
contracts. And I'll see you at
the bottom of the rabbit hole.
So let's jump into some best
practices for this course so
that you can learn most
effectively and learn with this
course as best you can.
You do not want to skip
this part. It'll help you solve
80% of your issue. Now, while
going through this course be
100% certain to follow along
with a GitHub repository
associated with this course we
have a link in the description
of this video for you to
absolutely click on follow along
have open in a tab as you're
doing this because it has all
the code Sam polls, timestamps a
community to interact with and
more, it is going to be your
Bible for watching this course.
And yes, we have a Discussions
tab. This Discussions tab is a
place where you can ask
questions, engage with other
developers who are going through
this course as well. Get some
help, and etc. Be sure to say
hello and meet other like minded
individuals like yourselves.
Now, blockchain and smart
contracts move really quickly.
And things are constantly being
updated. So to make sure you're
always up to date with the
latest, when I open up some
documentation, try to open up
the documentation for yourself
as well. And maybe even have the
code sample next to you. And as
you're writing code, be sure to
refer back to make sure that you
are keeping pace, and then you
have the most up to date
samples, sometimes technology
might change, and there might be
a way to do something a little
bit better. So we have this file
called chronological updates, be
sure that this is the first
place to check when you run into
an issue to see if maybe
something was updated that you
missed, it'll be chronologically
ordered. So it's easier to find
updates. Basically, this is to
say, always refer back to the
GitHub repo first. And if you do
to find a mistake, or something
isn't working the way you
expected, jump into the
conversation, leave a
discussion, leave an issue, ask
questions here, take breaks, I
cannot tell you how many people
tried rushing through our entire
first course in one setting and
didn't retain as much
information, your brain
remembers information much
better if you take breaks. So
every 25 minutes or half an
hour, maybe take a five minute
walk. And then every two hours
take a much longer break. And if
you really want to make sure
something drills in, try to go
back and reflect on what you did
for the lesson prior before
continuing to the next lesson.
And at the same time, though,
learn at your own speed. There
is no right speed for this
course. If it takes you a day, a
week, a month or even a year, it
doesn't matter. Learn at the
pace that's right for you, you
can change the speed at which I
talked using the little gear
icon in the YouTube video. If
I'm talking way too fast for
you, you can slow me down. And
at the same time, if I'm talking
too slow, you can speed me up,
you also don't even have to go
in order. You can bounce around
topic to topic, if you don't
want to learn full stack, you
can skip the full stack stuff.
If you don't want to learn
coding, we can skip the coding
stuff. If you only want to go to
the advanced stuff, go to the
advanced stuff. You are highly
encouraged to pause, come back
and ask questions. The
blockchain and smart contract
world is incredibly
collaborative. So be sure to use
tools like the discussions tab
of our GitHub repository, asking
questions on Stack Overflow and
Aetherium Stack Exchange and
tagging relative technologies,
making issues on different
GitHub repositories that you're
working with jumping into
discord, Reddit, Twitter, and
any other place that these
communities and technologies are
congregating. And the reason I'm
putting so much emphasis on
these community aspects is that
becoming a solidity and
blockchain engineer is so much
more than just the solidity
part. Being comfortable with all
the tools in this space,
including the ones to get help
and to give help are essential
to being successful here.
Networking is massive, and it
makes it a ton of fun. As you
continue your journey and you
get more advanced and you're
looking for places to meet other
developers. Hackathons are one
of the best places to connect
with other engineers, the
chainlink hackathons eath,
global hackathons, and Dev folio
hackathons are three great
hackathon suites to connect. And
no matter where you are in your
journey, they're great places to
flex what you've learned.
Alright, so those are some of
the best practices for this
course. You're standing at the
edge of the rabbit hole, looking
down, peering into the world of
web three and smart contracts
and blockchain. If you're like
me want to jump in, you want to
keep going further. Let's begin
our journey into the world of
smart contracts. And it all
starts with the blockchain
basics.
Now, I know you're excited
to get coding. But before we
jump in, we want to learn some
of the fundamentals of
blockchains and smart contracts.
Understanding these ideologies
and these basics are so
important, because it'll dictate
how you architect your
decentralized applications,
learning the basics of
blockchain and solidity is
critical. But if you already
know the basics of a blockchain,
feel free to jump into lesson
two.
Now, since you're here,
you've probably heard of Bitcoin
before. Bitcoin was one of the
first protocols to use this
revolutionary technology called
blockchain. The Bitcoin white
paper was created by the pseudo
anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto, and
outlined how Bitcoin can make
peer to peer transactions. In a
decentralized network. This
network was powered by
cryptography, decent Tality, and
allowed people to engage in
censorship resistant finance, in
a decentralized manner due to
its features, which we'll talk
about in a little bit. People
took to this as a superior
digital store of value, a better
store of value over something
like gold, for example, and
that's why you'll also hear
people commonly refer to it as a
digital gold similar to gold.
There's a scarce amount or a set
amount of bitcoin available on
the planet, only so much that
you can buy and sell. You can
read more about the original
vision in the white A paper
we've linked to the white paper
in the GitHub repo associated
with this course. Now, this was
an insane breakthrough in a
little bit, we're going to learn
exactly how this is all possible
and how this actually works
under the hood. Some people
though, saw this technology and
wanted to take it a little bit
farther, and do even more with
this blockchain technology. And
a few years later, a man named
Vitalik Buterin, released a
white paper for a new protocol
named Aetherium, which use this
same blockchain infrastructure
with an additional feature. And
in 2015, him and a number of
other co founders released the
project Aetherium, where people
could not only make
decentralized transactions, but
decentralized agreements,
decentralized organizations, and
all these other ways to interact
with each other without a
centralized intermediary or
centralized governing force.
Basically, their idea was to
take this thing that made
Bitcoin so great, and add
decentralized agreements to it,
or smart contracts. And in fact,
technically, these smart
contracts weren't even really a
new idea. Back in 1994, a man
named Nick Zabo, had actually
originally come up with the idea
smart contracts are a set of
instructions executed in a
decentralized autonomous way,
without the need for a third
party or centralized body to run
them. And they come to life on
these blockchains, or these
smart contract platforms, like
Aetherium. And it's the smart
contracts that are going to be
the core thing that we're going
to be working on in this course,
and that we're going to be
developing, you can think of
smart contracts in the same way
you think of traditional
contracts or traditional
agreements. They're just a set
of instructions between parties,
except instead of written on pen
and paper or typed up in
Microsoft Word, they are written
in code and embodied on these
decentralized blockchain
platforms. And that's also where
they're executed. Instead of
being executed by the two
parties, or three parties, or
however many parties that are
involved. This removes this
centralized issue that we'll
talk about more in a bit. This
is one of the main
differentiators between the
Etherium protocol and the
Bitcoin protocol. It's these
smart contracts. Now,
technically, bitcoin does have
smart contracts, but they're
intentionally Turing incomplete,
which means they don't have all
the functionality that a
programming language would give
them. This was an intentional
move by Bitcoin developers.
Bitcoin developers viewed
Bitcoin as a store of value
versus Aetherium, developers
viewed Aetherium as both a store
of value and a utility to
facilitate these decentralized
agreements. Now, the smart
contracts on blockchains alone
are absolutely incredible.
However, they do come with a
huge issue. If we want these
digital agreements to replace
the agreements in our everyday
lives, they probably are going
to need data from the real world
blockchains by themselves
actually can't interact with and
can't read or listen to data
from the real world. This is
what's known as the Oracle
problem. These blockchains are
deterministic systems and
they're deterministic on
purpose. And we'll learn about
more about how that works in the
sessions to come. So everything
that happens with them happens
in their little world. But if
they're going to be these
agreements, they need external
data and they need external
computation. And this is where
Oracle's come into play.
Oracle's are any device that
delivers data to these
decentralized blockchain or runs
external computation. However,
if we want our applications to
stay truly decentralized, we
can't work with a single Oracle
or a single data provider or a
single source that's running
these external computations. So
we need a decentralized Oracle
network. Similar to our
decentralized blockchain
network, you're on chain logic
will be decentralized, but you
also need your off chain data
and computation be
decentralized, combining this on
chain decentralized logic. With
this off chain, decentralized
data and decentralized
computation gives rise to
something called hybrid smart
contracts. And most of the
biggest protocols that we
interact with today are some
type of hybrid smart contract or
interact with hybrid smart
contracts. To some extent, this
is where the protocol chaining
comes into play. It is a
modular, decentralized Oracle
network that can both bring
external data and external
computation into our smart
contracts to make sure they're
decentralized end to end, while
giving them the feature richness
that we need for our agreements.
chainlink allows for us to get
data to upkeeps, get random
numbers or really customize our
smart contracts in any
meaningful way. Now, throughout
the course, we're going to use
the terminology smart contract.
However, whenever we say smart
contract, we're often using it a
little interchangeably with
hybrid smart contracts, but just
know that when we say hybrid
smart contract, we're talking
specifically about smart
contracts that have some type of
off chain component. Now since
the theorems release, a number
of different block chains or
smart contract platforms have
come to light such as avalanche
polygon, Phantom harmony, and
more. For the majority of this
course, we're going to be
assuming that we're going to be
deploying to the Ethereum
network. However, everything
that we learned here is going to
be applicable to the vast
majority of the blockchains out
there like polygon, avalanche,
Phantom harmony, etc, and
understanding everything from a
theory and funding mentals will
give you the skills that you
need to switch chains very
easily with literally one line
of code. So don't worry about
learning a specific tool or with
a specific chain because most of
them work together seamlessly.
Now, there are a couple of smart
contract platforms that don't
use solidity. But still learning
the fundamentals here will make
you much better at those as
well. And the Etherium by far
has the most value locked and is
the most used blockchain and
smart contract platform out
there. You'll also hear those
two terms used a little bit
interchangeably as well.
Sometimes they'll say smart
contract platform, sometimes
they'll say blockchain, they
kind of mean the same thing.
Obviously, blockchains could
mean store of value and smart
contract platform, but you get
the idea. Similarly, chainlink
is the most popular and powerful
decentralized Oracle network is
the one that we're going to be
focusing on for this course as
well. chainlink is also
blockchain agnostic. So to work
on Aetherium, avalanche, Polygon
Solana Terra, or really any
other blockchain out there. Now,
throughout this course, you'll
hear the term DAP or
decentralized Protocol, or smart
contract Protocol, or
decentralized application. And
they all kind of mean the same
thing. A decentralized
application is usually the
combination of many smart
contracts. And when we get into
solidity, you'll see what a
singular smart contract really
looks like. And like I said,
learning all these core
fundamentals will make you a
better solidity and a better
smart contract developer, you'll
also hear the term web three a
lot in this video. And in the
industry, web three is the idea
that blockchain and smart
contracts are the next iteration
of the web web one being this
permissionless open source world
with static content, web two
being the permissioned web with
dynamic content, but all the
agreements and logic runs off of
centralized servers where they
control your information. And
then web three comes back to the
permissionless web. But once
again, with dynamic content, and
instead of centralized servers,
running your logic,
decentralized networks, run the
logic creating these censorship
resistant agreements, that the
smart contracts enable is also
generally accompanied by the
idea that the users own the
protocols that they work with,
and it's an ownership economy.
You'll see what I mean later in
this course. And we've talked a
lot about the history and about
the high level of these
protocols and of the smart
contracts and what they can do.
But what do these smart
contracts really mean? What is
it when I say trust, minimize
agreements or unbreakable
promises? What is the real value
add of these smart contracts?
Before we look under the hood,
take a peek at how this all
works. From a technical
standpoint. Let's learn what all
the value of this is. What is
the purpose of us building all
these technologies? Have you
taken this course? What problem
does this technology solve? In
my mind, a technology is really
only as good as the problem that
it solves. If it doesn't solve a
problem, then why bother Mark
contracts, Blockchain web three
cryptocurrencies, those are all
just different words that
encapsulate the idea of what
we're doing in such a unique
paradigm. I think the easiest
way to sum up what these smart
contracts do is that they create
trust minimized agreements. And
if you might be scratching your
head to that. A much easier way
to think about it is just that
give rise to unbreakable
promises. Yes, you heard that
right. Unbreakable agreements
and promises. Additionally, they
give rise to speed, efficiency
and transparency, and a number
of other things. I made a video
pretty recently about exactly
this. So let's dive in and take
a listen to the purpose the
undeniable value
of smart contracts
cryptocurrencies, fundamentally
re landscape markets and
agreements as we know them.
Unfortunately, you've probably
only been bombarded with people
screaming about empties and
money. Now, some of the memes
are fun, but let's forget the
bullet and get down to the
essence of the space. If you're
already in web three. This is
the video to send to your
friends to explain why you're so
excited about this space and
explain why we're here. And then
if you're not into crypto,
you've come to the right place.
And yes, there are fun memes and
markets and there's some money
stuff in there all these things.
But outside of all that the
purpose of blockchains relates
to the age old elementary school
unbreakable, promise the pinky
swear, let's get Froggy. Nearly
everything you do in life is the
result of an agreement or a
contract. Your chair was the
result of an agreement to buy
and sell lumber to assemble and
sell the chair to a real tailor
on Amazon. Then you made an
agreement to buy the chair for
$40. The lights in your house
are powered by electricity,
which is an agreement from you
and the electric company you
agree to pay them in return
they'll keep the lights on the
electricity they generate it's
agreements between them and
engineers who built turbines to
generate the electricity with
insurance you agree to pay some
amount of money to them every
month, and in return, they will
do nothing or I mean, they'll
cover your medical bills, almost
everything you do and everything
you interact with is the result
of some form of agreement or
contract in some aspect. Now,
agreements and contracts can
feel kind of abstract and boring
to really grasp on to simplify,
we can also refer to them as
promises. When you get an oil
change. They're promising that
they will faithfully change your
oil In exchange for money, when
you put money in the bank, they
promise to keep it safe in
exchange for them to use your
money to give out loans. When
you buy a lottery ticket, the
lottery promises to give you a
fair chance at winning a ton of
money in exchange for you buying
the ticket. Whenever you make
one of these agreements. In a
way, you're asking them to pinky
swear to not screw you over and
to treat you fairly. But this
doesn't always happen. Let's
look at a real world example of
someone breaking the Pinkie
swear back in the 80s and 90s,
McDonald's ran a promotion for
people to win money by
collecting McDonald's Monopoly
game cards. The idea was simple.
You buy McDonald's in return,
you get a chance to win $1
million. You can imagine
McDonald's literally going Hey,
everybody, I promise you if you
buy our MC food and McNuggets,
we'll give you a fair chance of
winning this money, we ended up
breaking this promise, instead
of having a fair chance of
winning your chance was in fact,
zero in the mid 90s. Between 13
and $24 million went into the
pockets of not people playing
the game, honestly. But a group
of corrupt insiders who had
rigged the game, meaning that
when you played the McDonald's
Monopoly game, you were buying
into a set of lies and promises
that were 100% always going to
be broken. And the thing is, it
doesn't really matter if this
was McDonald's fault or not.
They were the ones making the
promises that they ultimately
could not keep. Another way you
could think about it is that
that's $24 million that they
essentially stole from you and I
now if this system was deployed
on a blockchain was something
called a smart contract, it
would have been impossible to
defraud this $24 million due to
smart contracts being immutable,
decentralized and transparent.
But I'll get back to that in a
minute. In all the agreements
and contracts we make, imagine
making a pinky swear with a 10
year old and imagining how that
agreement would hold up. Hey,
buddy, Could you could you
please keep my money safe? You
can play with it if you like,
but just please have it when I
come back. Immediately. You
might get that worrying feeling
in your chest, something might
go wrong. This 10 year old might
lose your money. You might be
thinking, how could I trust
them? Will they break their
promise and this feeling of I
can't breathe because of
untrustworthy situations
happens? Once all the time. Can
I trust this used car
salesperson to give me a good
car? Can I trust this tag that
says machine washable? Or will
it make my shirt shrink? Will my
insurance provider break their
promise of covering my medical
bills want to get hit by a bus?
I'm Patrick promises he'll go on
a hike with me. Well, he
actually I actually will. But
the issue with our current
agreements and contracts is we
have to trust the people. We're
making them to do the right
thing. However often they're
actually incentivized to not do
the right thing. insurance
doesn't want to pay out money.
Sometimes salespeople just want
to get the shit off the shelves
and with my girlfriend, I
promised to go on a hike. But I
need hikes. Where else is has
happened. Now you might be
thinking okay, Patrick, this
seems cool. But like Where has
this actually affected me? Well,
the McDonald's lottery that we
just spoke about above during
the Great Depression with the
run of the banks banks promised
to keep our money safe and that
when we went back to go get it
they would actually have the
money there. And well and behold
there were times that they
didn't have the money they're
just last year Robin Hood
painted this amazing picture. On
user application we will give
you access to the markets we
promise we will give you a
retail investor a fair chance of
interacting with the world the
finance
side, but not this asset. This
asset, this asset or this asset,
the 2008 financial crisis
remember that shady deals behind
closed doors combined with lies
about financial product brought
the world to its economic knees,
how are you? hyperinflation in
Zimbabwe hyperinflation in
Brazil, fair enough. US history
is a relentless lesson of
trustworthy entities being
notorious promised breakers and
we finally have a way to fix it
with smart contracts. Now,
before I jump into smart
contracts, a lot of people might
be thinking, hey, cool in all,
however, we have systems in
place to protect against a lot
of these things, which is true,
and which is great. And that is
a very helpful step forward. But
these systems often breaks ones
in 2008 Definitely didn't work.
The ones with the Robin Hood
crisis definitely didn't work.
And even if these systems apply,
and you go to court to try to
work them out, maybe you're in
court for years before you
actually see a resolution and by
that time, what you needed the
money for is longer. So what is
this technology? What is this
tool that can fix this
fundamental problem in our
agreements today, this tool is
smart contracts and this tool is
what the blockchain was built
for. Now, I'm gonna give you a
quick overview of what a smart
contract is. However, I'm
leaving some links in the
description for more in depth
explanations, but the basics of
them is a smart contract is an
agreement contract or a set of
instructions deployed on a
decentralized blockchain. And
once the contract or set of
instructions is deployed, it
cannot be altered, it
automatically executes and
everyone can see the terms of
the agreement. Real basics of it
is that the code is executed by
decentralized collective like a
group of people but a group of
people running a certain
software. This means that no one
person or entity can actually
alter any of these agreements or
change the terms of the
arrangement in these traditional
agreements. Whoever owns the
contract, whoever owns the
execution of the contract can
flip a switch and say, We're not
going to do that anymore. In
smart contracts and web three in
blockchain, you no longer can do
that. Typically, these smart
contracts are on a decentralized
blockchain, and used in
combination with a decentralized
Oracle network to get the real
world assets and information.
And if these words sound like
I'm conjuring up a magic spell,
well, again, check the links in
the description. If you want to
learn more about the technical
implications. If you're not a
technical person, then you're
not interested in getting into
the nitty gritty, you can kind
of think of it like HTTPS, I bet
the vast majority of you don't
even know what HTTPS stands for.
And yet you use it every single
day whenever you log on to the
internet. So how does this fix
the McDonald's Monopoly issue?
In its traditional form, the
lottery was executed behind
closed doors, somebody operated
and owned the code and the
contracts and the agreements
that ran the lottery, and they
had the power to alter it. And
nobody other than the people
internal on the lottery could
audit this altering happening.
Now if the code for this lottery
was deployed onto a blockchain,
every time a hacker attempted to
alter it, everyone would be
notified. Not only that, but you
couldn't even alter it, because
the terms of a smart contract
cannot be altered. Once
deployed, combine that smart
contract with a chain link VRF
Oracle to get a verifiably
random number. And presto, you
now have a perfectly
decentralized, unalterable
agreement that is impossible to
hack commit fraud or manipulate
we have just saved the public
between 13,000,020 $4 million
just by fixing the issue of
trust. How does this fix Robin
Hood? Well, the problem with
Robin Hood is already fixed.
Right? Again, the problem is
that there's a centralized body
that can flip a switch at any
time and say you can't access
these markets anymore. We're
breaking our promise of actually
giving you access to the
markets. This is already fixed
with something called
decentralized exchanges. And
these exist today, one of these
exchanges is one called uniswap.
You can swap ERC 20 tokens,
which are kind of the equivalent
of stocks, but some are some
are, it's a little confusing. I
won't get into that here either.
But it doesn't have that
centralized body that can flip a
switch and ruin access to the
markets. And had these investors
been on a decentralized
exchange, it would have saved
them hundreds of millions of
dollars, and it would have
prevented fraudulent market
manipulation. How does it fix
run of the banks with
transparency built in an
automated solvency checks, you
can build a bank like smart
contract that has insolvency
checks built in that make it
impossible to get there and
solve it means brokers any
agreement or any history lesson,
where there was a trust
assumption that was broken,
smart contracts can be applied
to and should be applied to,
especially in a time where big
money runs, owns and controls
everything, we desperately need
to move to a world where some
self interested centralized
entity can't flip a switch and
ruin people's access to the
services that they need. We can
move away from a world that is
brand based to a world that is
math based. Right now, if you
interact with a service that you
don't like, or that they break
their promise, the only thing
you can do is walk down the
street to the next service
that's going to make the same
set of promises. And you have to
hope and pray that they're
actually going to keep it we can
move from that to a world where
we can just look at the map and
say, oh, okay, one plus one
equals two. This is what this
agreement is going to do for me
every single time guaranteed,
because it's a decentralized
autonomous agent has no
incentive to be evil, and
everything is transparent and
out in the open of a big
company. And if it was better
for me for one plus one to equal
three, maybe I would go behind
some closed doors and flood some
numbers and come back and be
like, hey, one plus one equals
three with smart contracts.
That's impossible. Doing the
right thing is infrastructural
now, given the choice between
two agreements, one where you
have to trust a single
centralized entity that they're
going to do the right thing for
you, versus a decentralized
untampered double collective,
which one you're gonna choose.
I'm picking the one that can't
screw me over every single time.
For every agreement I can apply
it to now this technology is
relatively new, but we have
already seen it relandscaping
entire markets and continue to
do so the traditional financial
world is already getting its
lunch eaten by defy or
decentralized finance. There's
already over $200 billion of
people's money in these
protocols to help have a more
fair, more accountable, more
transparent financial system.
This defy movement is one of the
main reasons I got into this
space because we desperately
need to move away from where we
are right now. And and people's
chances for wealth being sucked
up by some group that's bending
the rules in their favor and
smart contracts are our ticket
to that better world. More and
more industries are also coming
over to smart contracts and
blockchain because of all the
innovations and because of all
the advantages that it has as we
grow and as we get better as we
get closer to this vision of
having this concept fulfilled,
trust minimized agreements.
These smart contracts are
minimizing the trust that we
need to give other people in
order for these agreements to be
executed. If trust minimized
agreements is too confusing for
you just say unbreakable
promises. Now I gotta be honest
with you guys. blockchains and
smart contracts and
cryptocurrencies can actually do
more than just trust, minimize
agreements. They have security
benefits, uptime benefits,
execution, speed benefits, and a
whole lot more. But it's a lot
easier to just learn about one
and learn the other ones later,
right. It's kind of like
sprinkles on top. So this is why
we are here. This is why we're
building this future and this is
why we are so excited about it.
Even in just this introduction
part, we've learned a ton. So
let's do a quick summary of what
we've learned so far. Bitcoin
was the first protocol to take
this blockchain technology into
the limelight and take these
cryptocurrencies into the
mainstream Bitcoin is a sort of
digital gold or a store of value
able to make transactions
between users in a decentralized
manner. Aetherium and other
smart contract platforms take
this blockchain technology one
step further, enabling people to
make smart contracts and
decentralized trust minimized
agreements, the smart contracts
and decentralized applications
can access and interact with the
real world using something
called decentralized Oracle
networks. chain link is a
decentralized network that
allows us to build these hybrid
smart contracts, which combines
our on chain logic with our off
chain, decentralized data, and
decentralized computation,
giving rise to our logic being
completely decentralized, and
our data and external
computation being completely
decentralized, giving us all the
features that traditional
agreements and traditional
contracts have. Now these
digital currencies like
Aetherium, and Bitcoin have
value. Even without the smart
contract part, having a
censorship resistant,
decentralized store of value is
naturally powerful in its own
right, we have some links in the
GitHub repository that will
teach you how this decentralized
store of value flips traditional
finance on its head. And it's
another one of the great reasons
for building smart contracts.
But again, the easiest way to
boil it down is trust minimized
agreements, or unbreakable
promises. But let's also go into
some of these other features
that smart contracts have over
our traditional environment. The
first feature, of course, is
that they are decentralized. And
they have no centralized
intermediary, the different
individuals that run one of
these blockchains are known as
node operators. And it's the
combination of all these 1000s
of node operators running the
same software running these
algorithms running these smart
contracts that make the network
decentralized. We'll dive deeper
into how that works later. The
next feature is transparency and
flexibility in these
decentralized networks. Since
all these individual node
operators run the software,
everybody can see everything
that's happening on chain,
meaning there's no shady deals,
there's no weird things
happening. Anything that's going
to be unfair, people will be
able to see and just not use,
everybody has perfect
information and has to play by
the same rules. Now
additionally, this doesn't mean
that there's no privacy, the
blockchain is pseudo anonymous,
meaning that you aren't
necessarily tied to an identity
in real life, they also have the
feature of speed and efficiency.
For those of you who have ever
tried to do a bank transfer or
send money across seas, you
know, it sometimes can take two
to three weeks, when in fact,
all these banks are really doing
is basic math. They're
subtracting money from your
balance and adding it to some
other balance. Why does it take
so long, in the blockchain, all
of these transactions happen
instantly. Another instance for
those in the financial world
today know that clearing houses
and settlement days can take a
long time. In the blockchain,
there's no need for any of that,
because they happen instantly.
This obviously is much quicker,
but it also makes for much more
efficient interactions with each
other security and immutability.
Again, immutable means that it
can't be changed. Once a smart
contract is deployed, that's it,
whatever is in the code is going
to be in the code forever, they
cannot be altered or tampered
with in any way. This means that
the security is much easier.
Whereas in a centralized world,
somebody can hack into the
server, jump into the database
and change some numbers. You
can't do that in the blockchain
world. And since it's
decentralized, in order to hack
the blockchain, you'd have to
take over half of the nodes as
opposed to in the centralized
world, where you only have to
take over one in the regular
world. If your computer and your
backup computer go down, all of
your data is gone. In the
blockchain world, if your
computer and your backup
computer go down, all your data
is safe, because it's being run
on all these other decentralized
nodes. And even if a few 100
nodes or a few 1000 nodes go
down. It doesn't matter because
as long as one node has a copy
of the blockchain, you're good
to go hacking a blockchain is
nearly impossible, and leaps and
bounds more difficult than
hacking a centralized server.
Not only that, but this is safer
in the asset sense as well. All
you need to access your
credentials and your information
in your assets is your private
key. Which is basically your
password for all of this. And as
we've discussed in the video,
the smart contracts remove this
counterparty risk, remove this
centralized intermediary, remove
these trust gateways that we
have to do in web two. When we
engage with users and
individuals, they don't always
have our best interests at heart
smart contracts, remove this
counterparty risk, because once
one of these contracts is
created, they can't go in and
they can't alter it. And they
can't let greed or ego or
anything else, get the better of
them and alter the terms of the
deal. And as we said, this gives
rise to these trust minimized
agreements or these programmatic
unbreakable promises. We move
away from brand based agreements
to math based agreements, where
we can look at the cryptography
we can look right at the code
and see exactly what something
is going to do and how it's
going to execute, versus having
to rely on a human being doing
the right thing with smart
contracts and decentralized
hybrid smart contracts. Doing
the right thing is
infrastructural all these pieces
boil down to us having the
freedom to interact the way we
want to interact without having
to be afraid that interacting
like that is going to screw us
over this trust minimized piece,
these unbreakable promises, make
interactions so much better. In
a purely web two world, we're
constantly bombarded with
messages of projects and
protocols pushing us to move or
act in the direction that makes
them more profitable. Versus in
the smart contract space,
we can see everything
transparently. And we can even
engage in interact and be
partially owners of the
protocols and the interactions
that we decide that we want to
be a part
of. So smart contracts have
been around for a few years now.
And what did they generate for
what industries have come about
due to these smart contract
platforms being around? Well,
you've probably heard of some of
these and some of these we've
already mentioned, but let's
give you a quick refresher, d
phi d phi stands for
decentralized finance. And it
gives users the ability to
engage with finance and markets
without having to go through a
centralized intermediary. For
example, like we said, with
Robin Hood, you no longer have
to trust that Robin Hood would
continue to give you access to
the markets, you instead would
be able to see in the smart
contract. Yes, I have access to
the markets or in the 2008
financial crisis. You never have
to trust that these groups and
institutions are giving you the
correct things on the back end.
You can see everything
transparently right on the
blockchain, you can engage with
things like money markets and
sophisticated financial products
easy effectively and securely at
the time of recording. defi has
around $200 billion in assets
under management and is quickly
growing. If you're really
excited about defy we have a ton
of defy examples showing you how
to build and interact with these
protocols. In coming lessons.
Dows or decentralized.
autonomous organizations are
another group that we've already
mentioned. Dows are groups that
are governed completely
decentralized by a set of
instructions or smart contracts
on chain. There are some massive
benefits here where engagement
is much easier. The rules are
black and white. And you can see
everything directly on chain
voting and governance
technologies completely
decentralized in the blockchain
space is one of the big ones
pushing how we can evolve
politics and how we can evolve
governance to make it more
efficient, fair and reasonable.
And you better know it, we have
some examples of how to build
Dows and how to work with Dows
incoming lessons. So be sure to
watch those NF T's Stanford non
fungible tokens and can really
be kind of described as digital
art or just a unique asset, they
can do so much more, but we'll
keep it high level for now.
Projects like board apes and
crypto punks have revolutionized
the way that people get paid for
their work, show off their
creativity, status, and so much
more. And yes, of course, we
have lessons showing you how to
create and interact with NF T's
as well, so many other groups
and so many other industries are
being created as a result of
this insane technology. And
maybe after finishing the
journey with us here, you go out
and you'd be the one to pioneer
the next industry or the next
billion dollar idea you've
learned so much already. But now
that we've learned a lot of this
high level information, let's
finally jump in, and let's make
your first transaction and let's
get you set up to interact with
this new world. In this next
section, we're going to get you
a wallet and we're going to show
you exactly what a transaction
looks like and feels like. Let's
dive in. This is the Aetherium
website aetherium.org We are
going to make a transaction on a
test Aetherium blockchain I'll
explain what that means in a
little bit. This is going to be
our first transaction that's
made on the blockchain. Now
again, this process that we're
going to follow is going to work
the exact same with polygon,
avalanche Phantom and all these
other EVM compatible
blockchains. I'll explain what
that means in a bit too. For
now, just follow along and have
fun in order to make a
transaction on any of these
blockchains. The first thing
that we need to do is we need to
set up a wallet. So I'm gonna go
ahead and go to meta mask
because it's one of the most
popular wallets and one of the
easiest to Use, we're going to
go ahead and download it. I'm
using the brave browser, but it
works for Chrome, Firefox or
really any other browsers. And
it's just going to be a little
extension in the top right hand
of your browser. This way, we
can really easily see it any
times what we have in our
wallet, will still are all of
our Aetherium based currencies.
So I'm gonna go ahead and
install meta mask for brave,
add to brave, add extension. And
now we can go ahead and get
started with working with Brave,
this is the first step you
absolutely need to take when
starting your journey and one of
the easiest steps to take. So
we're gonna go ahead and get
started. And we're going to
create a brand new wallet. So
we're gonna go ahead and hit
create wallet. If you already
have a wallet, you can actually
import it via I have a seed
phrase, and we'll talk about the
seed phrase or secret phrase in
a little bit. So let's go ahead
and create a new wallet. And
sure, we'll agree to help out
Metamask now we will create our
password make sure that this is
really secure. For the purpose
of this demo, my passwords are
just gonna be password. But
please don't have that be your
password. You may also get a
video like this teaching you
about your secret recovery
phrase. This is the same thing
as your pneumonic. But see your
recovery phrase is a lot more
clear as to what it is. And
again, to give us a ton of
different tips on how to
actually store it and keep it
safe. The main takeaway from
this is never shared this
absolutely never shared this. So
we're going to go ahead and
click reveal secret words. I'm
showing you guys here because
this is just a demo and I don't
really care. However, if you
show this secret phrase to
anybody else, they will have
access to all the funds in your
application. So everything that
we're going to do in this
tutorial, we're going to use
fake money, we're going to use
not real money, so it doesn't
matter. Now for the purposes of
testing and developing, I always
recommend using a completely
separate meta mask, a completely
separate Wallet. So for going
throughout this entire course,
if you already have a wallet, or
if you already have a meta mask,
please just set up a new one,
create a new profile, create a
new meta mask, and this will be
your wallet that you use for the
duration of this course.
However, if you're going to
actually put money in here, you
absolutely need to have this
written down. Because if you
lose access to this, and all
your private keys, which we'll
talk about in a little bit, you
will lose access to your wallet,
and you will lose access to all
your funds. So they give some
tips like store this phrase and
a password manager like one
password, write this phrase down
on a piece of paper, put it in a
secure location, memorize it,
whatever you want to do, just
make sure you have this backed
up somewhere, I'm just gonna go
ahead and hit download this for
now, it's not best practice to
save to your computer, it is
much better to use a password
manager or write it down on a
piece of paper or something. So
we're gonna go ahead and hit
next. And it's going to ask us
to verify that we actually have
it written down. And we're gonna
go ahead and hit confirm, and
great and gives us a couple
other tips. Remember, definitely
take these tips very seriously,
especially if you're gonna use
this for real money. Like I
said, For this demo, we're just
going to use test money. So it's
not as big of a deal. But if you
put real money in, you
absolutely need to backup this
seed phrase or secret phrase or
we're going to refer to it as
our pneumonic phrase. Awesome.
Now we can see the interface of
our wallet here full screen. And
depending on your browser, you
can actually come up and pin it
to your browser so that you can
just click it up in the top
right, and it'll drop down and
you can see the same interface
here our pneumonic phrase that
secret phrase, those that secret
12 words that they gave us have
given us access to a new
account, the address of our
account is located right here.
In fact, if we click it and copy
it to our clipboard, and go to a
tool called a block explorer
called ether scan, we can
actually paste our address in
here and see details about our
account. Ether scan, like I
said, is what's known as a block
Explorer. And it's a way to view
different addresses transactions
and other happenings that happen
with a blockchain. If we look at
this address that we just
created on ether scan for
Etherium main net, we can see no
transactions have happened.
There's really no analytics,
there's no comments, there's no
balance, there's no value,
because it's a brand new wallet,
and this address that we just
punched into ether scan
represents our unique address
our unique wallet only
identifiable for us. We'll talk
about ether scan a little bit
more in a bit because it's a
tool that we're going to use
quite often in wallets like meta
mask, you can actually even
click right here and create even
more accounts. So let's go ahead
and create a new account. We'll
call this
account two.
As you can see, this one has a
different address. So if we
click this one, we go back to
ether scan. We paste the address
in here. We hit Enter. We can
see another address again that's
uniquely identifiable to us,
right here. It is zero balance,
no value, no transactions now If
we go back to our Metamask, and
we click the little button, we
can see we have two different
accounts in here, it's the same.
If we hit the extension in the
top right, click the button, we
have two different accounts. The
12 word secret recovery phrase
allows us to create multiple
accounts, all with the same
secret recovery phrase. So that
secret recovery phrase will give
us access to both account one
and account two and any other
accounts that we create by
hitting this Create Account
button, because it gives you
access to all the accounts in
your meta mask. Now, these
addresses of both of our
accounts are the public unique
identifiers, but they also have
a private unique identifier only
identifiable to us. Similar to
the pneumonic, these are private
identifiers we never want to
share and we never want to give
out their private This is known
as your accounts private key. So
the mnemonic will give you
access over many of these
accounts, the private key will
give you access to just one of
these accounts, we can see it by
hitting these little three dots,
going to account details and
export private key, you'll just
have to punch in your password
here. And you'll be able to see
your private key. This is going
to be your private key for your
account, you can think of your
private key as a password for
your account that lets you
create transactions. Now the
reason that I'm showing mine on
screen is because I'm not going
to put any real money in here.
And this is just going to be a
burner account for this
tutorial. And I highly recommend
once again, you use a burner
account, you use accounts that
you never put any real money
into. And along the way, I'll
show you how to make sure that
you don't do that. But normally,
it's not a good idea to show or
share your private keys or your
secret recovery phrase, if
somebody gets a hold of this
private key, they will have
access to my account one.
However, they won't have access
to my account to if they get a
hold of my 12 word recovery
phrase or pneumonic they'll have
access to both accounts. And
this is why when people say keep
your private keys safe, your
keys, your Bitcoin, your keys,
your Aetherium, they're talking
about both your mnemonics or
your secret recovery phrases.
And your private keys keep those
private, your public addresses
are totally public. And anybody
can view your accounts on
something like ether scan, or
any other explore. And it's
totally okay for people to share
their public addresses. If you
lose your private key, you lose
access to one of your accounts.
If you lose your mnemonic, you
could potentially lose access to
all your accounts. Basically,
what I'm trying to say is back
these up and keep them in safe
places for this course it's okay
if you lose one, since we're not
putting any real money in them.
But in the real world, be sure
to do this. And great. Those are
some of the main security
considerations here. Now, if you
look up in the top right, right
next to that account button that
we've been clicking, you also
see this thing saying Etherium
main net, this is our networks
tab. And if we click it, we can
see a list of all the different
networks that we currently have
access to a Etherium main net is
the main network of Aetherium.
And this is where real money is
spent and used for transactions.
For this course, we're not going
to be working with the Etherium
main net, we're instead going to
be working with something called
a test net. Since we're
engineers, oftentimes, we're
going to want to test and see
what our code is actually going
to do and how to interact with
it. We're going to use a
combination of local networks
and test networks to actually do
this to actually test our smart
contracts. We're mainly going to
use local networks. But we'll
get to that in a little bit to
see some of the test networks
that come default with meta
mask, we hit show slash hide
test networks, this will bring
us into the settings page. And
we just hit select this to show
test networks in the list. And
we just hit on Now if we scroll
back up, we'll close out of the
settings, we hit the network's
tab again. Now we can see all of
these other networks here like
ropsten, Koven, Rinkeby, and
Garelli. These test networks or
networks that resemble
Aetherium, or polygon, or
Avalanche or phantom or any of
these other blockchains. And we
can actually switch our accounts
to one of these other test
networks. Let's click rink B,
for example, we can see that on
the Rinkeby test network. We
also have zero Aetherium we have
no money or nothing in here, we
have a blank Rinkeby wallet.
These test nets work nearly
identical to how Aetherium main
networks except for they run
with not real money. They run
with fake money as a way for us
to learn and interact and see
how these different smart
contracts actually work together
at the time of filming. rink B
is one of the most popular test
networks along with COVID. So
we're going to work a lot with
Rigby In this tutorial, however,
be absolutely sure to check our
GitHub repository to make sure
that you're always up to date
with the best test network for
following along with the
tutorial here since their test
networks people are running them
out of the goodness of their
hearts. And sometimes the best
ones actually change so, so be
sure to follow along with the
GitHub repository. We might also
use COVID From time to time or
maybe even Grilli. So we're
going to show you how to use a
couple of these different test
nets. In fact, if we go to the
GitHub repo associated with this
course, we can see recommended
test net is indeed currently
ranking. So that's what we're
going to work with should this
change, you should be able to
follow along with another test.
And we'll leave notes as to how
to continue. Now what we can do
actually is we can go to Rigby
ether scan, we can go to,
you can look up Rinku ether
scan, and it looks like it's the
first thing that shows up
Rinkeby dot ether scan.io, we
can punch in this same address,
copy and paste it. And we can
see some of the details of this
address on the Rinkeby ether
scan. Like I said, right now,
it's totally blank. This
networks interface later on is
also how we're going to be able
to work with polygon, avalanche,
etc, we'll just have to add
networks. But we'll get to that
in a bit. And just to reiterate,
test nets are free and for
testing our smart contracts and
main net networks cost money and
are considered live. Now I also
do want to put a caveat here
that we do want to keep in mind
that these test nets are being
run at the goodness of people's
hearts. So we don't want to
abuse them, we want to use them
to learn and then move on. So
try not to send a billion
transactions on one of these
test nets. In fact, what we're
going to do right now is we're
going to send a transaction on
the Rinkeby test net. And this
will show us exactly what it
would look like on a main
network. In order for us to
simulate one of these
transactions, we're going to go
to what's called a faucet. And
if you go to the GitHub
repository associated with this
course, right underneath the
recommended test net is going to
be a test net faucets, which is
going to show us where the most
up to date faucet location is
for us getting test net
Aetherium. So here we are at
faucets dot chain dot link,
which again is the recommended
faucet, and what we can do is we
can actually put our wallet
address in and get some test net
link or test net Aetherium. Now
what we are gonna have to do is
we are gonna have to connect our
wallet to the Rinkeby network.
So we're going to come down,
we're going to switch from COVID
to Etherium. Rigby, and then
we're going to make sure our
meta mask is on the Rinkeby test
network here. Once both of those
are set up, we're gonna go ahead
and hit Connect wallet. And
we're going to choose meta mask.
Once we do that, our meta mask
is actually going to pop up and
say would you like to connect to
this website, connecting to a
website is how we give these
websites in interface to
interact with our wallets and
interact with our meta masks.
Don't worry, we're not sending
any transactions like this,
we'll get to that in a bit. So
we just we can pick an account
we want to connect. Let's choose
our account one, we'll hit Next.
And then we'll go ahead and
connect. Now that we're
connected, we can actually see
our account connected up here.
And that little warning is now
gone. And our wallet address is
automatically placed into here,
we're going to make our first
test transaction. And for now,
we don't need test link. So
we're going to leave that off.
But later on, we're going to
come back and get that test
link. For now we're just going
to need 0.1 test Aetherium.
So let's go ahead and complete
the security by choosing the
traffic lights. And we're going
to hit Send Request. What this
is going to do is we're asking
this faucet to send us 0.1 test
Aetherium test net faucets are
ways for us to get money into
our wallets on a test net. And
this is why this test and
Aetherium isn't worth any actual
money. Since we can get it for
free. These don't exist on Main
net, you can't get real
Aetherium or real money for free
on a main network. So we're on
Rinkeby we're getting fake
Rinckey Aetherium. And we're
gonna go ahead and hit send
request. Once we hit Send
Request, this transaction hash
is going to pop up here, and it
says transactions have been
initiated waiting for
confirmation. This means that
some other wallet is actually
going to send us 0.1 test eath.
And this is the transaction that
it's doing to do that now we
just have to wait for our
transaction to finish verifying
and finish going through. Now if
this doesn't work right away, I
would recommend Wait a minute
and then just try it again. But
what we can do is we can click
this transaction hash. If that
transaction doesn't show up, we
can also just close this. And we
can copy our address here. And
actually we already see 0.1 eath
in our wallets here. But we can